- Hello and welcome to Chapter 2.
Now we're gonna just
continue to talk about
the building blocks of
Python, variables, constants,
statements, expressions, et cetera.
The first thing we have to
talk about is constants.
These are just things
we call 'em constants
'cause they don't change.
There are numbers, strings, et cetera,
and we use them to
sorta start calculations
or, you know, if something
is greater than 40 hours
we're gonna do something,
so 40 is the constant in that situation.
So, we have 123, we have
98.6, we have 'Hello World',
which is a string by
enclosing it in quotes,
we pass each of these things
to the print function,
and a side effect of the print function
is that we see the output.
So print(123), prints out 123,
print(98.6), prints it out.
So these are just really
the syntax of constants
and without constants we
can't write really much
of anything.
The other sort of foundational notion
of any programming language
are the reserved words,
and like I said before, reserved words
are these special words where
Python is listening for them
and there is very special meanings,
so when Python sees if, it's
not just any other word,
it means how Python implements
conditional execution.
Variables are the third building block,
and that is a way that you can ask Python
to allocate a piece of memory
and then give it a name,
and you can put stuff in that.
Sometimes you just put one value.
Later we'll see,
we do collections in
chapters eight and nine.
We will see that more than one value
can be put into a variable.
And the variable, how
we control the variable,
is through the assignment statement,
and as I said before,
it's important to think of
the assignment statement
as having an arrow to it.
So this is not saying x for
all time is the same as 12.2,
what it's saying is
take 12.2, find a place,
find some memory in your
computer there Mr. Python,
give it a label x, we get to choose the x,
that's the variable
part, we chose it, right,
and then stick 12 in it, and
then the same is true for 14,
go find another spot, name it
y, and then put a 14 in there.
So, think of this as an
arrow every time you see
that equality, the assignment,
in an assignment statement.
Now, these variables hold one value.
So now if we have these
three statements, these two,
and then the third one executes,
it says put 100 into x, but
that wipes out the old value
of 12.2 and it rewrites it with 100,
and so we can change the variables;
that's another reason that
we call them a variable.
There are some names,
now insert some rules
for making variable names.
You can start with a
letter or an underscore.
We tend not to as normal
programmers use underscore,
we tend to reserve those for variables
that we use to communicate
with Python itself,
so when we're making up a variable,
we tend not to use underscores
as a first character.
You can have letters and
numbers and underscores
after the first character
and they're case sensitive
but it's really a bad idea
to use case as the only differentiator.
So, in this case, spam,
eggs, spam23, and _speed,
are all totally legit.
We would probably not use this one
unless we were actually doing it
because Python told us
to use that variable.
23spam starts with a
number, #sign is starts
and dot is not a legitimate
variable character.
And spam, Spam, and SPAM are different,
but this is not something that you want
to sort of depend on too much,
so that's just the rule names.
We tend to start them with a letter
and then use letters,
numbers, and underscores.
Underscores other than the first character
are generally pretty common and
you'll see those used a lot.
Now, when we're choosing variable names,
one of things about variables,
is we get to choose the name;
we get to choose the name
x, choose the name y,
And so sometimes we like 'em short
but sometimes we want them descriptive,
and the notion that of
making variables descriptive
is often confusing to beginning students.
Sometimes it's really helpful to,
if you're gonna have a line of text
and you name the variable
line, that's great,
because the next person
reading your program says,
oh that must be the line of text.
Whereas, it also can become
misleading, that line,
the name of a variable,
somehow has meaning.
So sometimes we'll have
even singular variables
and plural variables,
like friend and friends,
you know like is plural?
Does Python know about
singular and plural?
And the answer is no.
So sometimes we pick
variables that make no sense,
sometimes we pick variables
that make a lot of sense.
This is just something that
you as a beginning programmer
are going to have to understand
that we can pick anything we want.
And so, you'll see I'll try
to call attention to this
in the first few lectures
as we go through.
So here's a bit a code with
an assignment statement,
two assignment statements,
a multiplication,
and a print statement,
and you can say what is this doing?
Now, Python is perfectly
happy with this code
'cause it assigns it in there,
you have said please go
give me this as a label,
and then we assign two variables
and then we're carefully pulling
these two variables back out,
multiplying them together,
and sticking them into
yet another variable
and then printing that variable out.
That seems like, you know, how
we can figure out what it is,
you just have to look really careful,
and a single character mistake,
and Python is gonna be,
you know, pretty unhappy, okay?
So that's one way to write this program.
It's hard though, because
any of those characters
are long variable and
they're random stuff,
it's not very friendly
to anyone who might read your program.
Now this looks a little friendlier.
It's the same program,
because Python just
wants a correspondence.
You pick a, you pick b, and you pick c,
and it's really much easier
for us to see what's going on,
and so this is, in a way
going from here to here,
is much friendlier,
but, we can being even friendlier
if we pick mnemonic variable names.
So this is, this is not mnemonic,
this is short and convenient,
this is long and inconvenient.
Python is happy with any of these.
Here on the other hand, is another version
of the exact same program,
and now you think to yourself,
oh yeah, now I get it.
35 is the number of
hours, 12.50 is the rate,
and then we're gonna multiply
the hours and the rate
and come up with the pay,
and we're printing out the pay.
Now whoever wrote this program
is helping us greatly
understand what's going on,
and that's good.
Choosing variable names, Python again,
all three of these are the same to Python.
Choosing variable names in
a way that help your reader
understand what's going
on, is a great thing.
The problem is, the danger
is, if you read this
and you think that somehow
Python understands payroll;
that if you name a variable hours
that Python knows what hours means.
The answer is, Python, really doesn't care
what you name the variable,
as long as what you name
it you use it, right,
and so you gotta be careful.
And so you'll see, when I write my code
in these first few weeks,
first few lectures,
I will sometimes write it with gibberish,
I'll sometimes write
it with extremely short
but meaningless variable names
and sometimes I'll use
meaningful variable names
and I'll call your attention
to it and it will get you.
You'll start, when you
look at this third kind
it has meaningful variables
or mnemonic variable names,
you'll just instinctively want
to give Python more intelligence
than it sort of deserves.
I guess that's probably
the best way to say that.
So, we've talked about constants,
we've talked about reserved words,
we talked about variables.
And so, here we have a sentence,
like we've already done
some of these things,
where we said x = 2, we
retrieve the old value of x
and add 2 to it, so that becomes
4, and then we print 4 out.
Print is a function that's built-in
and we pass in whatever
we want to print out,
so this parenthesis is
part of a function call.
Okay, so an assignment statement,
you have to really get
your head around the notion
that it has this arrow nature,
and that it valuates this
entire right-hand side
before we change the left-hand side,
and so you can think of this
sort of as at time step 1
it does this and then at
time step 2 it does the copy,
and that's how you can
have something like x
on both sides of an assignment statement.
And so, if for example we
have x, and x has 0.6 in it,
x has 0.6 in it, what happens is, is that,
it first it sort of ignores
this part right here
and evaluates the expression.
So it pulls the 0.6, everywhere
x appears, it pulls 0.6 out,
then it starts running these calculations,
and then it has the new value.
After all the calculations are done,
then and only then is it
going to put that back into x.
And so it sort of takes that
and puts it back into x,
and then wipes out the old value.
At this point, this
has all been taken care
and it's been reduced down to this 0.93,
and so that is what's
put in as the new value.
So, up next, we'll talk
a little bit more about
making more complex expressions.
(classical music)