- [Instructor] Hello, and
welcome to Python for Everyone.
I'm gonna do some coding.
It's related to the dictionaries
chapter, chapter nine.
And we're gonna do some wordcount
that's basically right out of the slides.
But I'm gonna just write
the code in front of you
rather than have you
look at it in the book.
So what we're gonna do is, I've
got my text editor up here.
And let me start by making a new folder,
New Folder,
for my chapter nine exercise.
And then I'm gonna go
and make an untitled file
that will assume the previous one,
and I'll do what I always do,
print
hello, and save it.
And save it here, into exercise 09,
and ex 09 dot py.
So now I have a folder
that's in my py4e folder
and that happens to be in my Desktop,
py4e is my folder on my Desktop,
and now I have all of these sub-folders,
cd ex 08,
ls is dir on Windows,
ls, oops,
I gotta go up one,
ex 09 ls.
So I've got that file right there.
Now I'm gonna wanna read some files
and so I'm gonna bring some files down,
couple of files,
Python for Everybody code 3 intro dot txt,
so I've got this URL
and I'm gonna save it,
Save Page As,
and it's really important that I save it
in the same folder as
I'm gonna write my code,
just so that when I open this file,
it knows where it's at.
So I've saved that one,
and I'm gonna also take this clown text.
I'll use this to make my life simple
so I have a real short thing
that I can show you how it works.
And so now if I go back to my terminal,
I see I've got exercise
09 python intro dot txt
and clown dot txt.
Okay?
So let's go back to my text
editor and get started.
I will prompt for the file name,
input Enter File
colon space.
Now I'm gonna do something,
if the length
of the fname that I just read
is less than one, I'm gonna say
fname equals
clown txt.
I do this so that I can just hit enter
and it defaults to clown dot txt,
if I wanna give it a
different name, I can.
So if I just hit enter at this prompt,
then this will give me a
string that's zero lengths,
so if it's less than one,
I'll just assume that.
So let me open that.
Handle equals open
fname,
and let's read through it,
for line
in handle,
we'll strip it,
line equals line.rstrip
to take the white space
off the right-hand side,
and then we're gonna say, print line.
Again, I'm not just doing this,
I really, when I write
code, I just saved it,
when I write code, I do this kind of stuff
all the time, just for
my own sanity-checking.
And so now I'm gonna run python3
ex 09.py, just to test that.
I'm gonna hit enter now
and it's gonna assume,
hopefully, clown dot txt
if it all goes well, and
yep, it read one line.
Okay?
So that part's working,
I'll just leave that print statement in.
The next thing I wanna do is
a classic thing where we're gonna go read
a bunch of lines and then go horizontally
across those lines and words,
so I'm gonna split that,
wds equals line
dot split,
and print wds.
So I'll print that,
and I'm gonna save it and test it.
I really love to test
things over and over,
there's the actual line,
this file clown dot txt only has one line
and it breaks it into words
and so I have those words.
Let's just run it again
with intro dot txt,
so this will have a lot of lines,
line, line, line, line, line,
lots of lines.
Every line has, it prints out the line
and prints out the words
that we split it into.
So now I, one of the things that I do here
is I wanna believe, now I can believe
everything from here up, like oh,
it's gonna open the file, it's
gonna read through the lines
and gonna split 'em into words.
And so then I'll just, behind it,
I'll just say, okay, I'll
just comment that out.
Now, I need another for loop,
for
w in wds.
Now words is a Python list,
it has some number of words in it,
zero or twelve or
whatever was on the line.
And now I'm gonna print out
the word.
And so now it will go
through that horizontally
and now I'll just do clown dot txt
so that you see I'm not
printing the line out,
that's the words that
have been parsed from,
split from the line.
And now we got this loop.
Now, one other thing that's interesting
is just to make sure
that you're going through
all the words, and I like
a print statement here,
to know that w is going
to successfully take on,
literally, all the words of this file.
So if I comment this print statement out
and I run it again,
clown dot txt,
that for loop, starting from here,
is every word in that file,
which happens to only be one line.
But now if I do the same
thing for intro dot txt,
it's just gonna go through the words,
and in a sense, by
nesting these two loops,
we're gonna hit all the lines
and that's a lot of stuff
but it hit all of the
lines, all the words,
and away we go.
Okay, so here's where
our dictionary comes in.
I'm gonna make a variable
called di for dictionary
and I'm gonna say, give me a dictionary.
Now, the ict is not
something you can choose,
that's defining the type of dictionary.
Di's the variable that I chose.
Okay, so the key thing to this dictionary
is we're gonna make a counter,
and we're gonna use w, the word,
absorb, elegant, whatever,
and we're gonna use that as the index.
So the simple thing to do is to say,
if w is in
di,
then we can say w, I mean the dictionary,
sub the word which is our key
and the key value store of the dictionary,
is equal to the value that we had before
in that area, d sub w plus one.
And if it's not in there,
else
di sub w
equals one.
And I'm gonna print,
print
new,
so every time we see a new word,
it's gonna say new,
and I'm going to also then print w
and the current value of the counter for w
as it's going through.
Now notice how far in I'm indented.
This is all part of this inner loop,
so this is the loop that's gonna run
every single word.
Okay?
And I'm gonna run this first with clown
so it runs slowly, so
we saw the was new, and the count is one,
clown is new, count is one,
ran is new, the count is one,
after is new, the count is one.
Now we saw the again, but
now we made the count be two.
Let's print here.
I'll say, existing.
So you can kind of see it.
Now in the print, I'm printing this,
let's make it even a little more verbose.
Print w.
And then I will make it so
it prints the word before
and the count after and then
whether it's existing or new.
So we're gonna put a lot
of print statements in.
Print statements are cheap.
So now, we see the word the,
it's the first time we see
it and we set it to one.
You see the clown?
It's the first time we
see it, we set it to one.
We see ran, new, one.
Later on, we see the, it's already in,
so existing means it was
already in the dictionary.
W, as a key, was already
in the dictionary.
And so that's why we added one to it,
so the old value was one
and then we added di sub the
equals di sub,
di sub the equals di sub the plus one.
W is the string, the, T-H-E,
that's what that string is.
And so we've made it all the way through
and you see the in this one line
occurred, ultimately, seven times.
So now I want to print out the
contents of this dictionary
at the very end of both loops.
So I gotta d indent twice,
and so that will give us the counts.
And so this is what we get
when it's all said and done.
The happens seven times.
But it just worked its way through.
Okay? So you got that.
Now, this is a pretty
verbose way of doing this,
but I did it the slow way to show
that there are two situations,
if it's already there, you increment it,
and if it's not there, you set it to one,
effectively inserting it, right?
So you insert it and set it to one
with this di sub the equals one.
But let's get a little less verbose here,
get rid of some of these print statements
cuz we covered all that.
Get rid of this line,
and go back to printing
w and di w at the end,
we'll leave that one in.
So what I wanna do,
is I wanna look at this
bit of code right here,
this if w in di else.
We do this so much with dictionaries
that there is an easy mechanism
to do this, that combines these four lines
into a single contraction.
And so I'm gonna do this,
I'm gonna print
let's put two stars out,
then the word, and
di dot get of the word
comma negative 99.
Okay, and so
this di dot get of the
word is the important part.
The way it is is, this is a dictionary,
dot get says, in its first parameters,
the key to look up which is word like the
or fell or clown or whatever,
and 99 is the default value that we get
if the key doesn't exist.
So this is an effect, an if then else.
This little di dot get w
negative 99 is,
if it's in there, do one thing,
if it's not in there, do something else.
So let me show you how this works,
and you'll see that the 99 will happen
when,
okay.
So, the first time we see the,
get returns 99.
So let's move it over here.
So the first time we see the,
the is not in the dictionary,
so this di dot get of the
word the in the dictionary
gives us back the negative 99.
And this still is working
and so the is one,
clown is whatever, but away we go.
Now let's do it this way.
Let me count this out,
let me count this one out
and run it again so it's a
little clearer what's going on.
Okay.
So the first time we see the,
the is not in the dictionary,
the first time we see clown,
and we know it's negative 99,
but here, we ask for it and the is one
because we've seen it before.
And so that's just this get mechanism
allows us
to get a new value, or get a value out
if the key exists and specified
a
default if it's not there.
So I'm gonna go oldcount
equals
di dot get
w comma zero.
So instead of using 99 here,
I'm gonna just get rid of all this.
(gunshots)
Is what I'm saying is,
look up in this dictionary,
get is a function that's
part of all dictionaries,
look up using the key w, which is the,
and if I don't get it,
give me back zero.
And so, I'm gonna say print,
word comma
old comma
oldcount.
And now what I can say,
whatever the oldcount is.
It's either the value
that was in there or zero,
and now I can say,
newcount equals oldcount.
And now, let's see, newcount,
and now I can say, dictionary sub word
is equal to newcount.
So I'm gonna get rid of
this if then else then.
This is basically saying, look
up the oldcount that we have,
if you don't find one, use a zero.
We'll print that out
and then I'm gonna say, afterwards,
I'll print the newcount.
And so,
so I'll print the oldcount,
here are some of these blanks,
print the oldcount.
And you can see the oldcount was the
because the doesn't exist,
was zero, the new one's one.
Clown's old is zero, new is one.
Clown's old, ran old zero,
but now we get to the,
its oldcount was was one
and now its newcount is two.
Okay?
So by using this get and
saying, if we don't find it,
we'll assume the count is zero,
that makes a lot of sense, right?
You know.
If not there, the count
is zero.
If the key
is not there,
the count is zero.
So that's what this line does.
Get the value under the key,
(mumbles) where the key,
or give me zero back.
And then I can take that old number
and just add one to it
and then stick it back in.
Now this is ultimately not
how we tend to do it, okay?
We tend to blend this all
into one big, long statement.
Di sub w equals
this part
plus one.
So that says, get the
old value from this key,
or zero, and then add one to it,
cuz that really combines
all of these lines
into a single line, okay?
So I'm gonna delete 'em now.
And now we've combined this all into one,
what effectively is, an idiom.
Retrieve,
create,
update
counter,
all in one line.
I'll still print out, in this case,
I'll just say di sub w,
and then we'll see the counter, okay?
And so now I'll run this.
We have a new, but now we
see the second time it's two,
and so we see car the first time,
we've seen that the
second time, we see car,
I mean the third time,
we see car the second time,
and away we go, okay?
And so that's pretty straightforward,
and so it really,
T-R,
got a typo there.
So let's just get rid of that
and
run it with the clown stuff
and we get the right data there.
And let's run it with intro dot txt.
And there we go, okay?
And so it's tearing out a bunch of words
and giving us a dictionary.
So, that was a lot of work
to get to this line 16
that has the dictionary in it.
Now we wanna find the,
the most common word.
So we're gonna loop
through this dictionary,
and part of it is like,
once we printed this dictionary out
and we verified that it's right,
don't worry too much about
the code up here, right?
Matter of fact, I can take out
some of these print statements,
and we can trust all this.
So now we're gonna work on this.
Okay, now we wanna find
the most common word.
Now this is like a maximum loop,
so if you recall,
we have a whole set of key value pairs,
communicate is to two,
skills is three,
so we have these key value pairs,
and we're gonna loop through
and look for the maximum.
Now, in a dictionary,
we can loop through the key value pairs
with the following syntax:
for
I would call these variables
k and v for key and value,
but yeah, in the dictionary's name
dot items.
And items is a method
inside of all dictionaries
that says, give me the key value pairs,
and we need two iteration variables.
So this is like an assignment
statement for k and v.
K and v take on the successive values
for the key and the value.
Okay?
So if I just now print
k comma v,
and I'll take this print statement out
and then run the code,
on, whoops,
what I forgot, oh, I fell
back into my Python 2 days.
Need parentheses for my print.
So there's clown, and
it just prints it out.
And it's the same thing,
except it's pretty where we're
putting each one on a line.
So the v is the value, so we're looking
for the largest value, oops.
So the thing is, we know that the values
are always numbers that
are greater than one,
so I'm gonna do
a quickie maximum loop.
Largest equals negative one.
Now in previous times, we've seen that
this is a bad assumption,
because we know these are
counters that are always positive,
it turns out this is not a bad idea.
And so I can say, if the value
is greater than the
largest we've seen so far,
largest equals the value.
Okay?
And when that loop is all
done, we can print the largest.
Okay?
And so this is just a max loop
and we're using this value,
that's the number, the
value is the second thing.
Oops.
Ah, can't type python.
Oh, it's a typo.
Yeah, I'm not using value, I'm using v.
So largest equals v, let's try it again.
Okay, so we're all done with seven,
so these were the things
that we were looking for,
and it was looking for the maximum
and it just dutifully found
seven was the largest,
but we also wanna know what the word is.
And so what we can say here is,
we can say the word is none,
meaning it's like, we don't
know what the word is,
and then whenever we catch
this new largest number,
we say, theword equals w.
So I like to think of this as
capture remember
the word that was largest.
Right? That's what I'm doing.
R, remem, E-M,
R-E-M-E-M,
remember.
Right, that's, R-E-M-E-M-B-E-R.
There we go.
So this trick here is,
not only knowing what
the largest number was,
but the word that was associated
with the largest number.
So now I can print out at the end,
theword and the largest,
and that's the count.
Okay, and so now we know that,
oops, did we make a mistake here?
Okay, that does not look good,
cuz it says car and seven.
If v is greater than the largest,
oh, it's not w.
(laughs)
I used a really bad variable.
See that's the whole value there.
There we go.
It's k, which is the key.
Key (laughs).
I was gonna say, that was quite the bug.
See what happened there?
I had this as w and it
just happened to be,
it was the last word on the file.
Car, the last word on the file,
because I used the wrong variable.
Right?
Little mistakes, little mistakes.
The and seven.
Okay, so let's get rid
of this print statement
cuz we know what's going on here.
And away we go, and this
should now work if we run it.
We can even get rid of the word done here.
There we go, the, seven.
Now, the cool thing about this is,
this code runs just as
easily with one line of code
or the intro of the book, intro dot txt,
and not surprisingly, the is
still the most common word
in the introduction dot txt,
I seem to like that word,
and it's 226 times.
Okay, and so that is the basic pattern
of reading some, this is just a word loop.
Now sometimes there would be some
checking to see if the line is
the one you're interested in,
maybe tearing apart the line,
but at the end of the day,
this idiom of starting a dictionary.
Now it's a common problem to know
where to start the dictionary.
You want to accumulate the
numbers for the whole file,
so you don't want to put it
in between line six and line seven.
Okay?
So I hope that particular
thing helps a little bit,
helps you understand dictionaries.