so Jason was the world's best loved data
interchange format it I discovered it in
2001 I don't claim to have invented it
because it already existed in nature I
just saw it and recognized the value of
it gave it a name in a description and
showed its benefits but I did not invent
it I don't claim to be the first person
to have discovered it there were other
people who I later found out had come
along the same idea in 2000 the earliest
instance I found of JavaScript being
used as a data interchange format was at
Netscape in 1996 so it's an idea that's
been around for a while and if you look
at other data representations like the
property lists that were used at next
and then reader at Apple except for a
couple of cosmetic changes it's the JSON
notation as well so it seems like it's
an inevitable sort of representation for
data at least data that is intended to
be consumed by programming languages and
ultimately that's all data I started
with JavaScript but my first application
was facilitating communication between
programs written in JavaScript and
servers written in Java so I recognized
that even though it was born out of
JavaScript it could be and should be
language independent so I simplified it
as much as possible to as much out tried
to make the simplest possible
specification for how to structure data
and put it on the wire and that
ultimately became called Jason
in 2001 I was at a company that started
called state software and we developed a
platform for doing applications which
could be delivered through unmodified
web browsers what today is called Ajax
but in 2001 that was kind of a radical
idea and not many people would believe
that was the impossible were that were
that it was a good idea but we produce
some brilliant demonstrations and we
were starting to make some progress in
trying to convince potential customers
that they should adopt the style of
application development and as part of
the description we'd say and then we use
this JSON idea for communicating the
stuff back and forth they say Jason
what's that so it's this thing we found
in JavaScript it's really great and I
said oh we can't use that we just
committed to XML so that we can't visit
but XML is wrong for all of these
reasons it's it's hugely expensive it's
much harder to use all that well we
can't use that thing you did because
it's not a standard I said it is a
standard it's a proper subset of equi -
6 - which is a standard they signal that
that's not standard so I decided if I
want to be able to use this thing I need
to make it a standard so I bought JSON
org and put up a web page and sort of
declare it it's a standard that's it
that's all I did I didn't go around
trying to convince industry in
government and and everybody that this
is what they should do I just put up a
website basically one page website and
over the years people discovered it and
then realized oh yeah this is so much
easier I'm just going to do that
the thing I never understood about XML
for data interchange
okay so basic generally the pattern is
you've got a query you send it to the
server
it gives it to the database and you get
back this XML thing and then you have to
send queries to that in order to get the
data out of it
yes it's why can't you just give it to
me in a form where I know what it is and
I can use it immediately and so that was
the the main benefit of Jason I think
wasn't that curly braces are so much
better than angle brackets I mean
ultimately that none of that matters the
thing that mattered was that the data
structures that Jason likes to represent
are exactly the same data structures
that programming languages represent you
know when Ajax was formulated the X and
Ajax was supposed to be for XML and the
smart kids right away realized well this
is too hard we don't want to be doing
XML here and some of them discovered hey
you can use Jason here instead and it is
so much easier so much faster um so they
start doing that and for a while there
was a debate and we're some people were
arguing Jesse James Garrett said the X
stands for XML so you can't use anything
but XML that didn't last very long there
were a number of other alternatives to
XML that were being considered around
those times but Jason was the only one
that was designed specifically for Ajax
probably the boldest design decision I
made in designing Jason was to not put a
version number on it so there is no
mechanism for revising it so Jason were
stuck with it but whatever it is in its
current form that's it and that turns
out to be its best feature because it's
it wants to be a low-level thing I mean
it's it's basic infrastructure it's the
thing that you pile everything else on
you know it's sort of the equivalent of
alphabet you know language you know we
might make up lots of words and lots of
ways of having sentences but it's very
uncommon to make up new letters and
that's sort of the place where Jason
lives so it's good that it's not going
to change
I expect maybe someday
we'll find that there are really
important things that Jason doesn't do
like cyclical structures graphs are not
easily represented in Jason they can be
but it requires a level of indirection a
little bit more work someday we might
decide we don't want to do that work and
then we replace Jason with something
else we will not extend Jason to do that
we'll replace Jason and even after we do
that replacement everything that was
ever developed that still uses Jason
will still work because Jason will never
change