(light piano music)
- [Instructor] In this video,
we're going to actually
download and install
Python 3 from Python.org on a Macintosh.
Your Macintosh, for years,
has wonderfully come with Python 2.
So, if I type python minus minus version.
Then, I type that, I see
that I've got Python 2.0.
What we want to do is, in
addition, install Python 3.
One of these days, Macintosh might upgrade
their distributed version of Python 3,
but there's so many things inside Mac
that depend on Python 2.
I'm going to expect that it
will always be named Python 3,
which is what we're gonna call it.
In a second.
So, here I am at the Python.org downloads
and I'm gonna download Python 3.
You click here, and I've
actually got it sitting here
in downloads already
cause I always do that.
And so, so I'm gonna install this.
There is the installer.
And say continue, continue, continue,
of course I agree I read
all that really fast.
And now I'm going to install it.
(light piano music)
Okay, so now that means
if I run a terminal,
so this is of course
is start run terminal.
So Python 2 is still there,
but Python 3 is also now there.
So we should have Python 3 installed,
so we installed Python 3.6.
And so there we go,
and that's all it takes
to install Python 3 on the Macintosh.
So let's write our first
little Python program.
I'm going to, I like Atom.
And so I've got this Atom
editor, it's Atom.io.
Right here, Atom.io, download
and install the Atom editor.
I like it because Atom works the same
on both Windows, Max, and Linux,
and it has syntax highlighting
and so I really like things like that.
So I'm gonna make myself
a simple Python program.
Hello world, like we always do.
Now you'll notice that it's
not syntax highlighting yet,
but I'm gonna do a file, save.
Oopsie daisy. File, save as.
And I'm gonna go onto my desktop,
and I want to make a folder called py4e.
I'm just gonna call this hello.py.
Oh crud, gotta rename it.
Rename it.
I ended up with two dots,
hello.py there we are.
And so now I'm here, and
I'm in my home folder.
I can go in my desktop
and I can go into that new folder I made,
Python for everybody,
and I can see the files.
Now, there are ways to run this,
and I really want you
to learn the terminal,
so that you really know what you're doing.
And so here we are, we are in
the folder that has the Python
and then all we do to run it
is we say python3 hello.py.
And there we go, and of
course this is Python 3
cause I'm using parentheses there.
So, instead of double quotes.
But Python 2 is still there
and of course if you
just run python hello.py,
it'll be a syntax error or not.
It must be they added something.
(laughs)
Yeah, cause Python is still version 2,
but apparently they allowed print in
of the latest version of Python 2.
So, away we go, okay.
So again thanks for watching.
I hope this was helpful to you
to get Python 3 installed
on your Macintosh.
(light jazz music)