hello and welcome to
the graduation ceremony for my mooc i'm
of course dr charles severance uh
and i'm your instructor and i'll be
awarding you your certificate
when the time comes i really appreciate
the fact that you've
stuck with the class long enough to get
a to get a certificate
um but as is traditional with
graduations we have a graduation speaker
and he's
my good friend and colleague kurt bonk
from indiana university
and so before we do the graduation
ceremony i would like to
have our graduation speaker talk briefly
kurt
this is going to be a pc talk
there you go what does that mean well
politically correct for one thing i got
my red indiana glasses and my
blue michigan go blue shirt on
it's partly about what i'll call not
personal computers another pc word
but possible courses meaning possible
paths not next courses you're going to
take with dr choc
necessarily but i'm going to walk you
through four p words
four c words for your possible courses
in life
this course this mooc was about
your passion your interests what you
decided to do
you moved into an area maybe a new area
that's within
your comfort zone or maybe a bit beyond
it
but you're trying to find your element
in life as sir ken robinson says we're
all looking for our personal element
right
so number one passion you have to be
passionate about
your course interests and what you
explore as part of passion you can't
just be passionate
and expect to succeed in life you need a
purpose you need a goal you need to be
moving towards something
as this professor at stanford talks
about the highest goal
maybe this course you took wasn't your
highest goal but it was
a goal nonetheless and we're all moving
towards that so we want to have
purpose you want to have passion but the
only way you're going to get through a
mooc
is to have persistence or grit you
push your way through it persevere in
that class
find that extra energy inside and i want
to congratulate all of you for finding
that
you've got your passion right you found
your purpose hopefully even just a
course related purpose
and persistence perseverance grit
that's the number one word today in
psychology number four
of course you're in this class so you
have to have a little bit of
playfulness along the way you know i got
into mooking stents when i did my mooc
every weekend take a look at it online
but i have a little playfulness in my
mooc
four p words keep those in mind as you
proceed
another p word into life and your
possible courses in your life
c words of course you chose
to get involved choice it's your c word
you got autonomy
it's your personal decision to get into
this class and complete
that class another c word but commitment
the second c word i want to focus on you
not only
decided or chose you committed to it
to completing this course and that
when you come when you did that all your
peers were watching you
and talking to you and sharing with you
and next word
connections a c mooc a connectivist mooc
and
any class online is about connections in
relationships
hopefully you didn't just finish this
class you form
new bridges new relationships new
possible
pathways possible courses in your life
and so those connections you have might
help you
down the road anywhere not just for the
content
here but maybe it'll help you get a new
job somewhere or find out about a new
interest
right and then what is this about some
of you
will want the certificate you're going
to want this
some of you want your million dollars
well
maybe you won't make a million from this
taking this class or all your classes
but
what you will do is maybe like steve
jobs become innovative the book i'm
listening to now in my car
and i just finished defining your
element
you have completed a course you might
get a certificate another c word
so those are the four p words passion
persistence purpose and playfulness
and the four c words we move through
choice
right you want to have some choice in
your life commitment
to things that you do choose to to
pursue
and relationships or connections and
finally completion
a course a certificate and you move on
in life
if you can keep those eight principles
in mind as
you proceed into other courses i think
maybe you'll find some
future successes i hope you do i hope
you follow your heart
into additional courses with dr chuck or
with other people
so i congratulate all of you on not only
signing up
but on completing as many of the modules
and maybe all of them
so you can get your certificate not just
here but your life certificate as a
open learner and informal now formal
learning thank you very much
outstanding outstanding um so i really
want to thank curt for coming
here to ann arbor he came all the way up
from bloomington um
and so kurt and i have done a number of
things together just to be here with
chuck you know
no that wasn't yeah he had another
reason to be here so we figured we would
tape this
so it is now time for you to sort of
walk in front of your computer and uh
receive
your fake graduation certificate i mean
there's
a little known fact that when you
actually graduate from college they
don't actually give you
the real certificate they give you a
carefully rolled up piece of paper with
a little bow on it
and then you get to your seat and you
open it up and it's blank but that's
what we're going to do again and you you
can print your own certificate
or badge depending on the course that
you've taken and so it is time for you
to get up and sort of walk in front of
your television or your laptop and i
will
hand you your certificate i have my uh
harry potter uh slytherin severus snape
juan to poof you know make you educated
and so here you go uh i congratulate you
and uh you can reach up and uh grab your
certificate and uh there you go
shock your hands shake your hand we'll
shake your hand we'll both shake your
hand and uh
and uh and as kurt said uh this is
hopefully just the beginning of uh
of a number of wonderful courses and so
again thank you for your time
thank you for your persistence thank you
for your commitment and
uh hopefully you'll see both of us on
the net and on the web teaching
internet classes so thank you very much
you