- Hello and welcome to
our chapter on databases.
We're gonna learn a lot in this chapter.
Learn a whole new
programming language, SQL
and learn how to use that.
So you're gonna need a
new piece of software
to run all of the
exercises that I'm gonna do
called SQLite browser.
We're using a database called SQLite.
Go ahead and download this,
you might have to pause
and come back if you like.
Go to sqlitebrowser.org and
download it and install.
While you're doing that,
we'll talk a little bit about the history.
In the old days, 1960s 1970s
I started doing computing in 1975.
We didn't have a lot of storage.
I mean this is 16 gigabytes right here
and we didn't even have megabytes.
The computer I had had a
few megabytes of stuff.
We also we didn't have
a lot of disk drives
and so permanent storage
was often sequential.
These tapes, these tape drives that we had
tapes and tape drives were
the scale part of storage
'cause you could just make more tapes
and you could rack them
up and so that was our way
of greatly increasing the
storage of the computer.
The problem they had was
is they were sequential.
You read it, it advances,
read it, advance,
read and advance.
Now interestingly we've been
writing programs that do this
that everything we've written so far
pretty much reads the whole file,
reads the whole web page, reads this.
Everything we read it.
We read either a loop
or read the whole thing
and that's 'cause we have plenty of memory
but we're still reading sequentially.
And so the way you would do this
when you didn't have
enough spinning storage
or online storage is
you used offline storage
but the trick would be
that you would sort it.
So let's imagine that you're a bank
and you have a bunch of accounts
only a few of which are active on any day
and you have a tape that
has in account number
order from low to high,
the prior balance, last night's balance
of every one of your bank accounts
and then you do all the transactions
and you record how much
money was taken in or out
for each account number
and then you sort those transactions.
And then what you do
is what we call a
sequential master update.
And that is, you would write a program
that would read the first
transaction and hold on to it.
So okay this is account 45.
Then it would read the
first count like one
and it would copy one then it'd read two
and read like seven, eight, 42, 43.
Then it would read like 44.
Now it would read 45 but
now it would change that
and write the new 45
and read the next thing
and so this might be 60.
And then it would read a bunch of stuff
and copy a bunch of stuff
and then it would finally
get to 60 and it would merge
the add or subtract and so
the old balance ended up here
and the new balance did here.
And you had to only make
one pass through the data
so it was super efficient.
So we had all these mechanisms to sort.
We used to do punch cards and have sorters
and all these things
and then these things would run for hours.
And if you watch old TV shows
these tapes are spinning
and these things are
running back and forth.
These are simply reading and writing tapes
and that's how we did a
lot of data processing
because we could store
far more on a tape drive
than we could on a disk and
with racks of tape drives
we could scale the storage
that our computers had.
So that's the way we did data processing
but it meant that the only way you knew
what the old balance was
was it was the balance as of this morning
before you bank started.
You don't know what the
balance was for the day
and that led to things like
you can never withdraw
more than $100 a day
or something like that
because you don't know
what the old balance was
or you might go withdraw a $100
at a couple of different branches
and so they weren't able to
look your stuff upright away.
Now it didn't take long
until the disk drives
got better and better and better
and you could store the entire accounts,
all the accounts and the
current balances on computers.
And the problem becomes is
what happens if in the
middle of the afternoon
you want to update a balance.
Well, do you want to read all your data
and then write a brand new one
and say that takes like 10 minutes.
That means for that 10
minutes only one person
can be updating their bank balance.
And because we could
randomly access this data,
we didn't have to read
it all sequentially.
The trick was, how do
you spread the data out
and then how do you make it
so you can change a balance?
This is of course second nature today
but how do you make it so
you change a balance here
without changing the balance there
and you can have multiple people
going simultaneously through these things?
And make sure that you can't say
withdraw money at two different
locations simultaneously
and somehow have your bank
balance get corrupted by that.
So there's a lot of
debate on how to do that.
And early days we just did
sequential master update.
But increasingly we
wanted to make better use
of the random nature of our
computers and our storage.
And so that's what led to databases.
Databases are the science
of how you make use of
rotating random access
data, permanent data,
in a way that allows you to read, modify
and update that simultaneously
from many different locations
and yet keep the data
completely consistent.
And so this led to a study
of a thing called relational databases.
Relational databases are
not the only databases
that happened.
We had many other kinds of databases.
And there was a debate and I
remember in the 70s and 80s
there was folks that said oh no no there,
you could do index sequential,
that's the was to do it.
And relational databases
weren't all that popular.
The first time that I saw them,
I didn't like relational databases.
Relational databases had
an inherent advantage
because they were based on some
really powerful mathematics.
The interesting thing is, is early on
the relational databases were slower
but eventually they figured out
how to sort of bring all
the cleverness to bear
to make relational databases fast.
And so relational databases
are a pretty advanced
technology and there're
companies like Oracle
that are very very wealthy
and their primary product
for many many years was nothing more than
a clever database product.
A clever piece of software
that was really good
at solving this problem.
And that's how important this
problem was to computing.
If you read about databases,
you're going to see two
sets of terminology.
One set of terminology comes from
the mathematical background.
And it has to do with the underlying math,
things like relations,
tuples, and attributes.
That's kind of like the
fancy math version of it
and programmers kind of think of them as
rows and columns inside of a table.
And so if you look at
sort of fancy theory,
you'll see words that look like this,
and they're just full of
this and the connection.
Now all this is important and true,
and if you really want to get good
you sort of begin to
understand the nature that
we model data at connections rather than
at sort of intersection points
rather than just modeling data
as a flat file the way we do.
But for now we're going to as programmers
think of this as just like,
oh, it's like a super fast spreadsheet.
The super fast part is the math,
for us the rows, columns
and tables are spreadsheets.
So it thinks of thinking
a spreadsheet of sheets.
Sheet, sheet, sheet.
And that's like a table, a named thing
like tracks or albums, artists or genres.
And then there is rows, and each row
has a different kind of data.
And then there's columns,
and we sort of specialized
the first column in many spreadsheets
to say what's in there.
This is not really the
data, this is like metadata.
It's like the titles in this first column,
that's not really the data
and the data starts here.
And we have different kinds of data
like strings and numbers,
et cetera, et cetera,
for each of the rows.
And literally you can get away with this
as sort of about 80% of databases
is just a really super cool spreadsheet.
But under the covers, it is
far more powerful than that.
So one of the early
arguments that happened was
again what the programming
model for this was.
And a lot of folks wanted
a programming model
that reflected how the
data was actually stored.
The notion of Structured
Query Language came about
in a way to express what
you wanted to happen
and allow that to be sort of
a very abstract expression.
Select all records that meet this criteria
not read read read read read read.
And so Structured Query Language is
not a procedural language.
It is a imperative language,
where you're simply saying what you want
and then somebody writes the loop.
The database actually does loop
but it's a way for you to avoid
actually writing the loop.
Now that turns out to be
the power of databases
'cause the cleverness
on how to write the loop
is a way that you would
probably never figure out
how to be most supremely optimal
when it comes to writing the loop.
As you'll see toward the
end of joining many tables
together and selecting and throwing array
and getting down a count or whatever,
someone has figured out how
to do that really really well.
So the idea was you would express,
we're going to create some data,
we're going to retrieve some data,
we're going to insert and delete it.
Create, read,
crud, C-R-U-D.
Create, read, update, and delete, crud.
And so that's what this does,
it's a language that
does this very simply.
Now the applications that
we're going to use this for,
are more of a data analysis application.
We've been doing data analysis
through the whole course.
And the kinds of things
that we'll see in the
remaining chapters is we'll
take some raw data file,
these might actually
come across the network,
and well write some Python
programs to play with
that data, parse it, clean
it up, make sense of it,
and then write it into a database.
And this might be a slow processor,
this might be really nasty
and this might be a way
to have very clean data.
And then we'll write
another Python program
to sort of read this, read through it,
and it's all efficient and pretty.
And then we can produce files
and maybe we'll visualize it
or do further analysis in our Excel
or a JavaScript visualization framework.
And so in this situation
you will be the person
who is both sort of writing the programs,
database administrator and
you can, using SQLite Browser,
play and look at database
kind of in a raw way.
And the first part of this, we are mostly
going to be using SQLite Browser
just to talk straight to a database.
Later we'll write Python
programs that read and write data
and visualize the data.
So this is what we're going to do first
and then second we're going
to do this part right here,
that's the second thing we're going to do.
Now another really common
use of applications
and something that if you
continue learning more
about programming, is that
you will want to write
an online application
like Amazon or a company
or Twitter, that's got a website
and it stores dynamic data in databases.
And so the picture for that
is similar but different
than the picture we're
going to start out with.
And so the way this usually
works is that you, the end user,
uses a web browser,
talks to the application,
and the developer writes
the application software,
and that application
software stores its data
in a database and inside that database,
we talk to the database using SQL,
and all the data is actually stored here
and the magic happens,
the data server is that
database software that's
so precious and valuable.
And then there's another
person often called
the database administrator
who has access to the
direct access to the data.
And these roles in
medium and large projects
are kept separate mostly because
the production, while
it's running and live,
the developer leaves the data alone
and works on let's say the
next version of the software.
And then the developer
has a tester version
of the application that
they run on their computer
where they're doing all that stuff.
And so this database
administrator is a role
in a large project where
we have to run production
and keep production careful,
keep production in good shape.
So a database administrator
has this responsibility
for the production aspects of the data.
And you may be working
in a situation where that
you're not actually controlling the data,
the database server's
on different computers.
You have little special access
and you write programs
to sort of read the data.
And so the database
administrator is the person
who is asked by the organization
to administer that data.
The data that we develop,
and we'll do this in a second
part of these lectures,
conforms to a data model,
that's the metadata.
Is this an integer, is this a string,
how many columns is this?
And the data model turns out
to be very very important
and there's a lot of science
to building an effective
data model that leads to
really good performance.
And it's a collaborative activity between
the application developers
and the database administrator
to make it so it's efficient,
runs in production,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
There's a lot of products out
there that you may encounter.
But we're going to be using SQLite.
SQLite's a little tiny database server
and it's built into so many things
and that's why we like it.
But if you're going to work
in a large organization
you could easily run into Oracle
which is the number
one commercial product.
Microsoft has a thing called SqlServer
which is a commercial product
and it's also very popular
and very effective.
The more popular open source,
there's things called Postgres,
there's MySql, and MySql
recently was sort of bought
by Oracle, and there's a
copy of that called MariaDB
that doesn't belong to Oracle, MariaDB.
Most of the SQL that we're gonna learn
is common across these database systems
because SQL's a standard,
but then there are parts
that weren't part of the original standard
where each database
avender has done things
a little bit different.
But there is a core common
subset that just does
the basic create, read,
update, and delete operations.
So SQLite is a very popular.
You probably have it in your
cellphone, 10, 12 times.
Your web browser has a
database engine in it.
Your car has a few databases in it.
And so SQLite is what's called
an embedded database system.
Python comes built in with it,
you just import SQLite3 and away you go.
And so it's a very very
popular because it's free,
it's open source and it's
such a tiny little piece
of software that you
just include it in other
pieces of software and use it
to solve the data management
problems of those pieces of software.
Like you browser might use
SQLite to store your bookmarks.
Now you think, oh there's
only how many bookmarks
can you have.
But what if there you need it to be fast,
and what if there's like people
that have 10,000 bookmarks?
There probably are.
Do you still want it fast?
Do you want to be able to search?
And so you get all that by
using a database like SQLite.
And so again we're going to
encourage you to download
the SQLite browser so
you can follow along with
what we're going to do coming up next.
And so here is the SQLite browser.
Here's what it looks like,
and it's just a desktop application.
And coming up next
we'll start playing with
this desktop application
and see how it works.
("Fire Breather" by Silent Partners)