- So welcome back,
we're now going to talk about expressions.
Expressions are a little
more complex calculations
that we can sorta do
on the right hand side
of an assignment statement.
So one of the things about
expressions is operators,
and then operators in
computer programming are often
very much the same as the
mathematical operators.
But we don't have all the fancy characters
that we have in mathematics,
and so we have to choose
what's on the keyboard.
And then we really go back
to the 1960s and 1970s
and then we use what was on the keyboard
in the 1960s and the 1970s
to make these operators.
So plus is addition, minus is subtraction,
we don't have a times sign
or a dot in the middle,
so we use the asterisk as multiplication,
division, we can't put two
things over the top of each other
so we use slash for division,
raising to the power,
because they didn't have
little characters back then
is star star, which is
raising to the power,
and then remainder, remainder is the,
when you do integer division,
it's also called the modulo
operator, it's the remainder,
not the quotient and I've got
a picture of that coming up.
So here's a whole series
of little examples of this,
right, so we've already
seen, you know, the plus,
x equals x plus 1,
keep remembering that these
assignments are arrows,
basically, arrow, arrow
the other direction.
Multiplication, 440 times 12.
Dividing this by that's division,
over 1000, 5.28.
Here we're gonna put 23 into jj
and then we'll do modulo.
So that says take 23 divided
by five and give me back
the remainder and put it in kk.
So this is the expression
that evaluates like this.
Take 23 divide five into
23, four remainder three.
The three is what comes
back up here, okay?
And so that is the remainder,
it's also called the modulo operator.
It turns out for things
like, picking a random number
and then taking the modulo of 52,
is a way to pick a card randomly.
So this modulo operator is actually
a specialty in games and
other things, super useful.
So that's the various operators.
It's important to know which
of these operators goes first.
It's called operator precedence.
Now normally we put parentheses in.
Like you know, so if I put
the parentheses in here,
I'd say this goes first parentheses,
then this goes first,
actually not that one.
Whoops, got that one wrong.
This happens first, this
happens, then this happens.
Okay?
But it's important for
us to be able to know
if there were not parentheses
the order in which
these things will happen.
So the way things work, in
terms of operator precedence,
is parentheses are the
most important thing,
followed by raising to the
power, all those being equal,
multiplication and
division, are both equal,
and then addition,
and then within it's adding left to right.
So let's see an example of how this works.
And so if we take one plus
two, raised to the three power,
divided by four, times five.
And we print out what comes out of this.
So, the way I did this
when I was taking exams
back many, many years ago when I was first
in computer science, is
I'd write it all down
and I'd look for the
highest precedence thing.
Now parentheses would make this easy.
But exponentiation is the first one,
so that means we're gonna take this,
and that's gonna be eight.
Two to the third power,
two times two times two.
Two cubed is eight.
Then what I would do is,
I would rewrite the whole
thing with the eight there,
and I'd look across, and I'm
looking for multiplications.
Because the powers been done,
the multiplication's what
I'm looking for next.
And then there is both
multiplication and division.
They are equal, they're at the same level.
And so what happens is,
they're done left to right.
Eight divided by four happens
before four times five.
And so the fact that
it's not four times five,
but instead eight times four,
is because of the left to right rule.
So then this gets rewritten to be two.
One plus two times five.
And this one, multiplication
is the top one,
so that does this next.
Two times five becomes ten.
I rewrite it again.
And then one plus 10,
addition is the lowest thing.
And that's how we end up with 11.
And so that's how I
would do these problems
if I ever saw the problem on an exam.
And it's a fun problem to put on exams
because there is one and only one answer,
and every programming
class has usually at least
one slide about this stuff.
So like I said, the
rules go top to bottom,
parentheses, power,
multiplication, addition,
and then left to right within it.
So, we talked about variables
and computing values
to put inside variables,
but the one thing you kind of also,
maybe you noticed today as we go by,
is we have different kinds of data.
We call it type.
Is this of type integer?
Is this of type floating point number?
Is it of type string?
What is going on here?
And Python is pretty
smart about various kinds
of types of data.
And so, you know, we're
adding one plus four here,
and Python knows as it looks at this
that that's an integer
and that's an integer.
And will add it together
and make it an integer.
So that thing is an integer.
We can also use this plus
to get get need to strings.
This is hello blank plus there.
And plus looks here and
says, oh that's a string
and that's a string, so I
know what to do with strings.
I will concatenate those
two things together
so it become another
string that gets assigned
into eee and it's hello space there.
The plus doesn't add the
space, I added the space
by putting it right there.
And so these operators are kind of smart,
in that they kind of know
what they're dealing with
and sometimes they will
do one thing or another,
depending on the kinds of
values, variables, or constants
that they're working with.
And so, sometimes type
can get us in trouble.
So here we have eee, which is hello there,
because we concatenated
these two strings together,
and now we're adding one.
And the problem now, is that
it looks on one side and says,
that's a string and
that's a number and says,
I don't know how to do that.
This is another one of
those annoying errors
that you think that somehow
Python doesn't like you,
but it just is confused.
If you look at these things,
trace back, trace back
always means I quit.
Means I stopped, I ran, I'm
quitting now because I don't
want to go any farther
because I've become confused.
So your program stops running and you say,
here's where I stopped running.
Because we're typing
interactively, it's always
line one here.
Type it, but you read carefully
and you don't get too stuck
on too much stuff, line one
that tells us something.
In module>TypeError:
Can't covert 'int' object
to str implicitly.
So that's an integer right
there, and that's a string,
and that's what it's complaining about.
That little bit right there.
If Python is so grumpy about types,
then we should be able
to ask it about a type.
So there turns out that
there is, inside Python,
a built in function called type, t y p e.
So we can pass into type.
So this syntax is calling a
built in function name type,
parentheses is the parameter
that we're passing to it.
We're saying, hey, hello,
tell me something about
the type of the variable eee.
And so this is a function,
the parentheses are part
of the function call.
And it says, oh that
would be of class string.
And then we can pass in
a constant that says,
hey what about hello?
The string hello.
It's like, oh that's a string too.
What about a one?
Well that's an integer.
And so we're asking Python
through the type function,
what the type of either a
variable or a constant is.
And there are even
several types of numbers
and we'll even see
Booleans and others later.
Like one with no decimal,
that's an integer number.
98.6 with a decimal, that's
a floating point number.
And so, you know, constants and,
constants can be both
integer and floating point.
And I'm just asking over
and over and over again,
what is the type of, what's in xxx,
what's the type of what's in temp,
and what's the type of the constant one?
And what's the type of 1.0?
You can also use a set
of built in functions
like float and int to
convert from one to another.
And so this basically
says, I wanna convert,
oops, let's go back.
I wanna convert 99 to a
floating point number.
So this is a function
and it's participating
in this plus, but before
it can finish the plus,
it turns this into a 99.0.
The difference between
99 as an integer and 99.0
is that it's a floating point number.
And that actually turns this computation,
as it looks to the left
and looks to the right.
It says, oh I've got a floating
point number on one side,
and an integer on the other side.
And so I'm gonna make my
calculation overall be
a floating point calculation.
I can also pass into the float function.
I can say take this
variable i, which has a 42,
also an integer, and then
give me back a floating point.
So that'll be 42.0 pass that into f,
we print it out and it is
indeed 42.0, and it's a float.
And so it knows the type
and value in any variable.
This is an integer, a value 42.
This is a float, a value 42.0.
Integer division in Python
2 was kind of weird.
And it was actually one of
the big things they changed
between Python 2 and Python 3.
This is a Python 3 course,
so we're not worried
about that too much.
What's nice about integer
division in Python 3
is it always produces a
floating point result.
And that means that Python 3's
division is more predictable
and it works more like a calculator.
So in this case, I mean
you can go back and look
at my Python 2 lectures
and see how crazy it was
in Python 2.
10 divided by two is 5.0,
and the weird thing here is
these are both integers,
but the division forces the
result of a calculation to
be a floating point number.
And this, you know, ten
over 2 could be five,
but nine over two is 4.5.
And so that is accurate.
In old Python 2, it
would give us back four,
which is completely
unpredictable and weird.
The same with 99 over
100, as you would expect,
if this were a calculator you'd get 0.99.
Actually what you get in Python 2 is 0.
Because it would round it down,
it doesn't round at it all truncates it.
So 99 over 100 is 0.99 and
then it truncates it to zero.
That's Python 2, we're not
talking about Python 2.
There's a good reason we're
not talking about Python 2.
Welcome to Python 3.
Of course if there are a
floating point on either side,
the result is still a floating
point, floating point,
and the result is still a floating point.
So, integer division
produces a floating result
in Python 3.0.
Not in Python 2.0.
That is an improvement in Python 3.0.
And that's why we're
recording these lectures.
I have a whole great set
of lectures about Python 2,
and now I'm gonna have
a great set of lectures
about Python 3.
Welcome to Python 3.
Okay, so we've been
talking about converting
from integer to floating point,
but you can also convert
from sting to integer
or string to floating point.
And so here we start out
with a little string value,
now it only works for strings
that are made of digits.
So "123" is not an integer,
it is a three character string
that has one, two, three
as the characters in that string.
Which is very different than 123.
We say what is the type of this?
It's a string.
We say let's add one to it.
And it says can't convert "int" to string.
So that blows up, right?
Cause this is a string.
It looks to both sides,
string plus an integer,
not good, okay?
But, we can convert this.
We can call the int function,
which is like the float
function, and pass a string in.
So it says, hey, take this
and turn it into an integer.
So take the input of s val,
which is the string "123"
and give me back an integer
representation of that.
Which is going to be 123.
So we say what kind of
thing did we get back?
Well we got back an integer,
we can now add one to it and get 124.
And so, you have to
manage the type of things.
And you can convert from
one type to another.
Now, it is not magic.
If you send something into
it, a string that doesn't
consist of digits,
then you're gonna end
up with another error.
Invalid literal for for
integer with base 10,
blah blah blah blah blah.
So it's really complaining.
It says, I want these to be number here,
and you just gave me letters.
So that's going to cause this to fail.
Another thing that we're
going to do with variables is,
just like the print
function takes something,
a list of things, in this case
a string comma a variable,
and then prints some
output in the program,
the opposite of that is input.
Actually input generally
happens before output.
Input is a built in function.
And we pass to it a prompt.
A string of text that's going
to be printed out for the user
and then it stops and waits.
So it says, who are you?
And then right here it just sits.
Waiting for us to type something.
So we type, blah blah blah blah,
and then hit the enter key.
Right, we hit the enter key,
and then this text ends
up in this variable.
So this is an assignment
statement that Chuck
is the result of the input call,
gets copied into the nam variable.
So let's do that again.
It's evaluating an assignment statement.
Remember it's kind of this
way, or you can think of it as
do this right side first.
It writes this out.
Writes that out.
Then it waits.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Until we hit the enter.
And takes this Chuck, and
that becomes the result
of this input.
Which is then assigned into nam.
Now then we go sequentially
to the next line,
it prints out Welcome, and any
contents of the variable nam.
Now this one, this
comma here actually does
put the space in here automatically.
So it says Welcome space Chuck.
So there's no space in
Chuck, just c h u c k,
and so print can take more than one thing,
separated by commas.
As a matter of fact print
can have a whole bunch of.
Oops come back come back.
Print can have comma,
comma, comma parentheses,
as many as you like.
Everything you've seen up
to now is kind of one thing
in the print, but that
doesn't mean that print
only can do one thing.
So I've talked about variables,
we've talked about constants,
we've talked about input,
we've talked about output,
and now it is time to write
our first meaningful program.
And so this program has
to do with those of you
who have traveled internationally.
If you've traveled to the United States
and you've traveled
outside the United States,
you notice that there is
an elevator convention
that is different inside
the United States.
The United States, the
walk in the ground floor
and the elevator that's one.
If you want in a ground floor in Europe,
or many other places in the world,
and the elevator is zero.
So we have written a small app,
that we're gonna put on the app store
and get wealthy with,
called Elevator Floor Conversion App.
And it's gonna ask us, we're
in Europe and we're lost,
and you say, well what
floor would this be if I was
in the United States of America?
And so here's we have to
read the floor that we are at
in Europe, and then we're
going to convert it to
a U.S. floor, and then
we're gonna print it out.
This is very silly,
but it is a pure essential
program that has input,
does some kind of task on that input,
and the produces some output.
Which is useful, for some
value of useful, okay?
So let's take a look at
how we combine everything
that we've learned in this lecture
input, processing, and output.
It's a three line
program, but it's sort of
the beginning of something
that programs do.
Okay, you're gonna do lots
of programs that do this.
So, here we go.
Program starts.
We do the input side effect,
it prints out this and then waits.
We type in zero.
That comes back here.
And the zero, which is a string.
Input gives you back a string,
it doesn't give you back a number.
It's a little different in Python 2,
but in Python 3 input gives you a string.
So "0" which is what we typed here.
We didn't type the quotes, it's a string.
Gets stored in the inp variable.
Then we move to the next statement.
And on this right hand
side we convert that
string variable to an integer.
So that become the integer zero.
We add one to it and
then that becomes one.
And then we assign that into usf.
I've named this variable
United States Floor.
Right?
So inp is the input and usf.
That's mnemonic, it doesn't
know anything about elevators.
It's just I picked a variable
that was quite friendly.
And so at this point, usf
has the United States floor
that's equivalent the the European floor
and then I just fall down
and I do a print statement.
Print out US floor, US floor comma,
that's this space right here,
and then whatever the contents
of the US floor variable is.
And you could see that I
could write this on four,
and it would say three.
I could write this in say seven,
and it would say six.
This is an amazing program.
It converts floors in a
European numbering scheme.
Wait, actually no, I got that wrong.
Hang on, let me clear this.
I wasn't thinking clearly.
I could type in four and
it would give me back five.
I could type in six and it
would give me back seven.
See I'm confused.
Haven't been in Europe
in a couple of months
and so I forgot all about the floors.
But that's the idea.
Now, this is a super,
super, super simple program.
Not super useful, but you get the idea
that we're gonna pull some data in,
we're gonna do some intelligent thing.
Soon this will be
hundreds of lines of code
instead of one line of code.
And then we go ahead
and present the results
to our user.
Now, another element of
most any programing language
is what's called a comment.
Comment is a way for you
to put in a program file
some text that's to be
ignored by Python or SEER,
what ever language we happen to be using.
In Python comments
start with a pound sign.
So what you could do is put a
pound sign anywhere in a line,
and then after the pound sign
Python ignores everything
after that pound sign.
It can be the first character.
So here's our recurring concept that we
talk a lot about.
We're not gonna cover this.
Remember what this does.
This is counting how many letters.
There's 16 thes.
And in that file there were
six tos, or whatever it was.
This is that code.
We'll get back to this code.
But what we've done here,
is I've added some
comments that are really
for human consumption.
So this first paragraph is
get the name of the file
and open it.
The second paragraph is
count the word frequency.
You know maybe I should
have said histogram here.
Count the word frequency
and assemble a histogram.
And then here I'm putting
this pound sign in,
find the most common word.
And when I'm all done
I print this stuff out.
All right?
And so all I'm saying is
comments are for people
to read, your next
programmer, or the person
who's gonna change your program
after you're done with it.
And they're nice.
And you don't have to use
any particularly weird syntax
or variable name conventions.
You put a pound sign in and
you can write anything you want
from that point forward.
Okay, so we've talked a
little bit about variables,
and types, and mnemonics,
and how we would choose
variable names, and how expressions work,
and the various operators,
converting between different byte types,
printing, input, output, and comments.
So that just kind of gets us sentences.
Coming up next we'll talk
about conditional execution.
Where we're really starting
to move up to paragraphs.
So see ya in a bit.
(soft music)