- Okay, so we've taken a look at loops
and now we're going to just take a little
bit of a look at some of the operations
that you can do with loops.
- Um, Python has this,
as we'll soon learn,
object orient approach to its operators.
And, the plus can add strings
and it can add numbers,
it can add floating-point numbers,
integer numbers, strings, etc.
And, so the plus similarly
works this way with lists.
The plus looks to its left
and looks to its right
and says, what am I adding?
And in the case that I'm adding the list
one, two, three and the
list four, five, six.
It concatenates them together
and in this way it sort of
functions like a string.
And so, we get one, two,
three, four, five, six.
It just concatenates lists,
this list to another list.
And, it doesn't change a or b,
just like in any kind
of assignment statement
Its calculations on the right side
don't change the variables and
then produce a new variable
and then assign that into c.
You can also use list slicing.
It's easy to remember,
if you remember how strings work,
lists work exactly the same way.
So, of course, it's a little tricky,
the first number's the starting position.
They start at zero.
So, one is right there,
so it's the zero position, one position,
start at one, right, but go
up to but not including three.
There's one, two, three.
So, this goes up to but
not including three.
And, that's why we get
forty-one, twelve out of that.
So, up to but not including,
I'll just say that over
and over and over again.
If we do, you can leave
the first part out,
you can leave the first part out here
and you can say up to
but not including four.
So, that starts at the
beginning goes up to
but not including four,
and so that's how we get
that piece right there.
We can say, um,
start at the position three,
zero, one, two, three.
Start at position three and go to the end.
Now, the fact the number three is in here,
is sort of irrelevant.
Um, three to the end
is those three numbers.
And, then you can do the whole
list with slicing as well.
Again, these are pretty
much the exact same examples
I used when I was doing strings,
they're pretty much the same.
There's a number of different methods
and you can look up all the
documentation in the list.
I often just use the dir command
to remind myself of them,
append we'll look at,
count looks for certain
values in the list,
extend adds things to the end of the list,
index looks things up in the list,
insert allows them,
the list to sort of be
expanded in the middle,
pop pulls things off the top,
remove removes an item in the middle,
reverse flips the order of them,
and sort puts them sort of
into order based on the values.
So, let's look at a couple of these.
Um, so if we build a list from scratch,
we have a way to ask for an empty list.
There are a couple of different ways
to ask for an empty list.
We could use just two square
brackets next to each other.
But, this is a form we
call a constructor form
where we say, hey Python, make a list.
And, in this case the word list
is like a reserved word to Python,
it's really reserve class, but, um.
Say list, list parenthesis
says makes me an empty list
and then, assign that list into stuff.
So, stuff is now a list object,
it's a type list but it has nothing in it.
And, then we can call the append methods,
stuff out of append and stick book in.
And then, we say oh,
and that knows how long,
and the stuff knows how long it is,
where the end is and how
to add something to it,
then add a ninety-nine to
it and we print it out.
And, we got book and ninety-nine,
reminding ourselves that lists,
while they're often the
same types of variables,
same types of values, in the
various positions in the list,
it doesn't always have to be that way.
Then we say, oh, we'll
stuff append cookie,
you can keep on going
and then we end up with
three things and the cookie.
We have an in operator,
it works pretty much like
the in operator in a string.
Uh, is nine in my list?
And, that's pretty simple and
the answer of course is yes,
nine is in my list.
Is fifteen in my list?
Looking through, no it's not,
fifteen is not in my list.
And then, there's the not in operator,
you can think of that as
kind of like one operator.
Is twenty not in the list?
And the answer, since
it's not there, is true.
And, so that's a way to just, you know,
it's kind of like starts
with or end for strings.
Same kind of stuff.
Lists are in order and they're sortable,
and so this is something
we take good advantage of.
A lot of what computers
want to do is sort stuff,
you know look all these things up,
append them and then get them sorted.
And so, there is this
method inside of list
that's just the sort method.
So, here we you know put three values
in zero, one, two positions.
Zero, one, and two,
Joseph, Glenn, and Sally.
And, then we tell the list to sort itself
and then we print it out.
Now, this is actually
sorting the list in place
which is different like
than upper and lower,
because if you remember
strings are not mutable,
but lists are mutable and so you say,
hey, just sort yourself.
Okay, and so just sort
yourself and then it sorts it.
And then, it's in alphabetical order,
Glenn, Joseph, and Sally.
I happen to be clever, I
only put strings in there
and I put my uppercase and lowercase
in a very consistent pattern.
But, the list has changed,
and if I look at list sub one
that is the second item, which is Joseph,
that prints out right down there.
There's a whole bunch
of built in functions
to help manipulate lists,
the other things I was
showing was method sort
is a method that's part of lists
but there are other functions
that take lists as their arguments.
Um, we already talked
about the len function,
it tells you how many items there are.
There is, pretty obvious, max,
it says go through and find the largest.
Min, go through and find the smallest.
Sum, goes through adds them all up.
And, we can say, let's do average
by taking the sum of all of them
and dividing it by the length.
And you might think to yourself, oh wow,
I wish we'd had known
this a few chapters back
when we were having to
write all those loops
to do max, min, sum,
largest, smallest, etc.
You can kind of think in
your mind that inside each
one of these functions
is a loop that does,
pretty much, what you
did in those chapters.
Part of the reason we did that back then,
was even though these things were here,
was they're kind of easy
loops to understand.
And so, those are there and
basically there allows two different ways
of building loops to do
the maximum and minimum.
Now, it's not necessarily
all that much easier to
do something using these
because you either can do them the old way
or you can make a list
and use these functions.
So, let's take a look, and
I'll just say that these
two bits of code are doing
the exact same thing,
and what they are is
implementing a program,
that's going to repeatedly ask for numbers
until we type the word done,
and then it's going to compute the average
and tell us what they are.
And, so using sort of the
stuff from the loop chapter,
we start with a total
variable and a count variable,
set them to zero and
then we read a number,
check for done to break out,
but then we convert it
to a floating-point value
and then we say total
equals total plus value
and count equals count plus one.
So, this is gonna run over
and over and over again,
how ever many times
we're going to do this.
And then, it's going to
pop out and when it's done,
it's going to have this value of total,
the running total will
become the overall total
divided by count and then it'll
print the average out, okay.
So, that, that's kind of
how we would have done this
before we knew how to do this with lists.
Now, let's take a look at the other one.
And, the other one, we say
lets make an empty list,
remember this is that constructive syntax
that says to Python, make me an empty list
and assign the empty list.
It has nothing in it. Right.
But it is a list.
Has nothing in it, into
the variable numlist.
Now, we're going to write another loop,
we're going to, this
part here is the same.
These three lines.
Read the number, if it's done,
quit and convert to value.
But instead of doing the
actual calculation right now,
all we're going to do is
just append it to the list.
So, the list will start out empty,
then the three will be in the list,
then the nine will be in the list,
then the five will be in the list.
So, we're appending each
time through the loop
we're appending into the list.
So, we're just growing the list
every time I read it value.
Instead of actually computing something
with the value that we've got,
so in either case we get value
and in one case we append it to the list.
And then finally, it
finishes, the break happens
and then we just say, oh hey Python,
sum up everything in the list,
add these three numbers together,
and then take the, divide it by the length
of all those things and
you'll have the average.
And, so these two things give
us exactly the same output.
Now, there is one difference,
if there was like one million
or one billion numbers,
they actually all have to be stored
in the memory simultaneously.
Where as here, it's actually
doing the calculation
of the billion numbers and
not using up so much memory.
For most of the things
you're going to be doing,
the difference in memory, there
is a difference in memory,
this uses, this one here uses more memory,
but I can't draw very well.
More memory, um, it uses more memory,
but it doesn't really matter
by the time it's all said and done.
And so, for you, the
difference between these things
is not all that significant,
but it's important to
understand that they're just two
techniques to accomplish
the same thing with lists.
(classical music)