- So now we're going to
move from merely matching
to matching and extracting
so we're going to say hey,
I would like to not only
have you take this template,
this little pattern, this string pattern,
regular expression pattern,
run it across the line.
I want you to give me
all the ones that match,
and I want a list of those,
and that's what we're
going to use the find all,
so search gives a true/false,
find all gives a list of
all the strings that match.
So if there's four of them,
you'll get four things in the list.
If there's nothing that matches,
you'll get an empty list.
So, let's take a look at
what we got going here.
So, instead of calling
search, we'd call find all,
we still pass in the string
that we're looking through,
and then we have our
little template pattern,
and this is a new bit
of regular expression.
Any little bracket
operation, square bracket
is one character, that's just a character,
but then in between here is
a set of allowed characters.
So zero dash nine means a single digit,
zero, one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight or nine.
But that's really one character.
And then we have, so that's one character.
And then when the plus applies to that,
which means if we look
at this whole thing,
this whole thing says one or more digits,
that's the code we write
in a regular expression,
that says one or more digits.
And we're just gonna use that
in our regular expression by itself,
so we're going to look for any string
that's one or more
digits, and pull it out,
and give it back to me.
So it's gonna look, so
that's my little template,
stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp, opp, got it.
Stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp,
stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp, oop got it.
Stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp, got it.
So what we get back after we ask find all
to find all of the one
or more digit strings,
is two, nine, and 42, so
it actually parsed it,
it split it, it found
all these things and said
I found them all for
you, and here they are.
Two, 19, and 42, so it's
a list of three strings,
'cause that's how many you found.
Now it might've found none,
and we've got an empty list at that point.
But it found some.
Okay, so just as an example,
you know we did this thing,
we get two, 19, and
42, but if I said this,
that basically is a upper-case
vowel a, e, i, o, or u,
so that's one letter,
and that's one or more.
So it's saying you know, something like a,
a would match, e, i would
match, o, o would match.
But if you look now,
it's saying okay that's,
I'm looking for one or
more, minimum one or more
upper-case a, e, i, o, u
is a set of characters,
one or more upper-case letters,
and so it says like look, you find,
oop there's an upper case, but it's an M,
no, no, no, no, upper-case,
no upper-case, no upper-case,
no upper-case, found nothing,
did not find anything,
and so it gives us back an empty list,
and so it's like find all
the things that match this,
and the answer is, none match,
here's your list of nothing okay?
And so that's, and so you have to check,
that's how you have to check,
even if you've got something,
'cause it's not gonna return you false,
it returns you a list with no items in it.
Now, the way it works,
like I said it sort of
is taking this template and
stamping it across the line,
scamping across the characters.
Now, there might, there's a behavior
that might not be intuitive you,
intuitive to you at the very beginning,
but the notion of what
we call greedy matching,
and that is, when it can match
more than one possible string,
overlapping string, it chooses the largest
of the overlapping strings,
and so the easiest way to
show this with an example,
and we're saying I want
something that starts with an F,
with one or more characters,
and ends with a colon.
So that's there, that's my little stamp,
that's my template.
So it starts with an F, good, that's good.
One or more characters,
duh, duh, duh, duh, duh,
have a colon, that's, so
that could be from colon.
That would match.
But look, I've got another colon here,
and this is just continuing on
with one or more characters and this,
so the question is do we get this,
or do we get this part right?
And the answer is with greedy matching,
is we get the larger of the two, okay?
And so what you get back is
somewhat counter-intuitive.
You get the whole thing
is the match from colon
using the, we could've got from colon,
but the reason it picks
this, is this one's longer,
so any time it has a choice,
it picks the longer one, and
that's what greedy is meaning,
it'd probably be better
described as larger
or tending toward the longest
string or something like that.
So you can of course, suppress
this behavior like everything
in programming regular expressions.
You simply add another character,
and so now it's going to
say I would like to start
with the letter F, that's any character
one or more times and
then this question mark.
This is still one, you know,
one little thing non-greedy okay?
And so that just says do it not greedy,
which just means that it prefers
the shorter of the strings,
and so now it could still match
this string or this string,
but because its been
told to not be greedy,
it chooses this string instead,
and that's the string that we get,
and so that's the not greedy,
and you just add the question
mark after the asterisk,
so it's usually an asterisk question mark,
or a plus question mark.
That's a two-thing, that's
zero or more characters,
non-greedy, and that's one or
more characters non-greedy.
Actually most of the time the,
it seems to me that
the non-greedy would be
the more reasonable default,
but that's not how it is.
Greedy is the default, and
non-greedy is optional.
Now, we can play some
more with this stuff okay?
And so, let's take a look
at this little example,
where we have a non-blank
character as back-slash capital S,
one or more of those non-blank characters,
followed by an at sign,
and then again one or more
non-blank characters.
So this is looking for
strings that have an at sign
with non-blank characters on both sides.
This is an example of where
it sort of comes to this at,
and it goes this way, and it
does it in a greedy manner.
If you told it to not be
greedy, it would give you this,
these three characters, but
we're telling it to go greedy,
so it goes all the way to
here and stops at this blank,
and then stops at this blank.
And so that's a nice little thing,
find the at signs, go to
the first blank, blank,
and pull that stuff out, and so that,
with one little match,
you've pulled this thing out.
Now of course we've done that
before with other techniques.
So that's just another
way to pull stuff out.
Now if we, we get this whole thing,
but what if that's not
exactly what we wanted,
and we can tell, we can,
we can give it a matching
string that's different
than the extracting string
by adding parentheses,
and so here's another example
where we basically say
this is our string we wanna
match from at the beginning,
followed by a space, followed by,
ignore the parentheses for the minute,
one or more non-blank characters,
followed by an at sign,
followed by one or more
non-blank characters.
So this is also going
to, if there's no from,
it's not gonna be looking for that right?
So it demands the from is
here, so it matches that,
and the spaces demand it as well.
And then it says oh,
non-blank characters great,
I got an at sign, great,
now blank characters,
oops stop there, and so
this is what's gonna match.
Now the key is that we
don't actually want that
back in our extraction.
What we really want back in our extraction
is this part right here.
So what we do is we put parentheses in.
Parentheses don't, our code, their code,
in the regular expression world,
parentheses say start your extraction
and end your extraction.
And so when you do this
with a parenthesis,
when you do it you know,
without a parenthesis,
you get, you get the whole from right?
Without a parenthesis,
oh wait no, okay that
doesn't have a from in it so,
but if you do that with a parenthesis,
you match the from, but
you only get this bit
to come out as well,
so you can add this to make
the matching part more precise,
but without changing
what you get returned,
and you specify what
you wanna get returned
with the parentheses.
So next I wanna show you just
a couple of different ways
to use these new-found skills.
(rock music)