- So, now we have a socket.
We are going to talk
about what we're going
to do with it, right.
So, the socket basically
functions at this level:
your application is
saying, "Make me a socket,"
which is sort of this end point,
and then the connect actually
connects to an application
on the far side and
there's a port involved,
so that might be port 80.
And, this is the far host
and that could be
www.py4e.org or data.py4e.org,
okay, and so the socket is solving this
and the question, then, is
what are we gonna send
and what are we gonna expect to get back?
And, that's what we call
the application protocol.
So, we know that these
two have made a phone call
and it's no different
than making the phone call
and saying, you know, "Hello," right?
And, everyone knows that
when the phone rings
and you pick it up, you're
supposed to say, "Hello,"
and that's part of our protocols.
So, who talks first, right?
So, the dominant protocol
that we use on this,
in this section, is the HTTP protocol.
That's, the key is a
Hypertext Transfer Protocol.
It's dominant.
It's really easy to use,
that's why I used it as an example,
but realize that there are many others
like mail and file
transfer and remote login
and all kinds of other protocols;
each is a different application protocol.
They all use, sort of,
sockets at their lower level,
but then on top of that, they
layer the rules of the road
for retrieving HyperText web pages
and we have used these for
all kinds of other things.
So, the protocol, like I said,
it's like who answers the phone first.
What do they say,
what happens if the person
doesn't answer right,
can you hear me now?
Those kind of things, and
it's a real simple thing,
and all you really need to do is,
so that both sides can agree,
you have to just write a thing
that's like the rules in the middle
and say, "Okay, everybody,
"as long as we all do
this, we'll be fine."
It's as simple as picking
on which side of the road
the cars can drive on.
It works fine no matter which side,
but if each car randomly picked,
it would be, really, kind of a mess.
So, if you look at the typical URL
and this is one of the things
that the Web innovators
in 1980 really invented
that was wonderful and it
seems second nature, today,
but in 1990, it was rather revolutionary
in that these Uniform Resource Locators
encrypted and included
in themselves a protocol,
the host to connect to and
the document to retrieve.
So, this is one of the
clever, clever ideas
that the Web came up with
because we used to have to pick
a program, like FTP or
Telnet or whatever, SMTP,
and then we had to go to the right host
and then we had to talk to
that host a certain way.
So, in HTTP, it's a really simple protocol
invented in 1989 and 1990
by Tim Berners-Lee and
Robert Cailliau at CERN
and they created a protocol
that we have grown to know and love
and used for way more
than retrieving documents,
as we'll see in the upcoming chapters.
So, we're gonna talk a
little bit about what happens
when you click on a page that has a link.
Now, there's all kind of
fancy stuff that can go on,
but this is the basics.
And, so, lets just imagine for the moment
you just are sitting looking at a webpage,
Dr-Chuck.com/page1 and inside
that there is a hyperlink.
It is a indication that says,
"When you click on this page,
go to a different page,"
and, in that, you see the name of the page
that you're supposed to go to.
So, we click on this link
and that is a browser.
This is an application, this is a process,
or an app
(computer keys clicking)
that's running on your computer;
this is the browser, okay?
And, when the browser sees the
click inside your computer,
then the browser make
a connection to port 80
on the web server, Dr-Chuck.com
and sends the request.
This request that it sends
is precisely specified
by a standard, which we
will see in a second.
Then, the web server some magic work,
oops, let's go back,
then, the web server does
some magic work in here,
reads some files, runs
some code, does whatever,
constructs an answer to our
phone call and sends it back
and it sends, in this case, back a webpage
in the format of HTML, the
Hypertext Markup Language,
which is different than HTTP,
which is the protocol
that we're exchanging.
HTML is the format of the
document we're getting back
and, in this, has an anchor tag,
href in then end of anchor
tag and some highlighted text,
and now your browser gets this back
and then renders it according
to the rules of HTML and CSS
and Javascript, et cetera, parses it
and then makes a pretty webpage
and this web page happens to have
a link back to the first
page and if you click there,
it will do this over
and over and over again.
And, that is the request-response cycle
and that's governed by a
series of Internet standards.
These are standards that were built
and from the '60s, '70s, '80s and '90s
and continue to this day, by a group
called the Internet
Engineering Task Force or IETF.
The documents they produce are called RFCs
which stands for Request For Comments.
The RFC, the word RFC is kind of like,
a sort of joke, as it were.
It's, they're trying to kind of funny
in that, ah, funny is not the right word,
they're, it's ironic in
that they're trying say,
even some of the protocols of the Internet
that we've used for several decades,
they're always interested in improvements
and that's what the RFC stands for
and they're all named RFC dash whatever.
And, if we were gonna cruise around,
we could find some various RFCs
and this is RFC 2616.
It might have been revised since then,
but this is like a document and
this is what they look like,
Hypertext Transfer Protocol, version one.
And so, you're reading this document,
you're gonna write a
browser and you want to talk
to the application protocol that is HTTP,
this is one of many documents
that helps define what HTTP is.
So, if you look and you
looked down and said,
"Oh, here's what a request looks like.
"This is how I'm gonna get
a document from the server,"
and you keep reading and
you keep reading and it says
you're supposed to have the
request method with a space,
with a request URL, the
with a URI with a space, the HTTP version
and the carriage return and a line feed,
that's what it's saying.
And so, it looks kind of like this, right?
We say get the document,
followed by a space.
They've got to be one
space; you do two spaces
and it's going to be
quite frustrating, okay.
And so, this is an
example that you can run
on a number of,
on Linux operating systems
and Macintosh operating
systems with no changes.
If you installed Telnet
on your Windows box,
you should be able to run
something like this, as well.
So, Telnet is a program that
we used in the old days.
It used to be how we logged into servers,
but because it doesn't encrypt
your data back and forth,
we don't use it anymore.
But, it basically is a program
that can open a socket to a host on a port
and I'm saying Telnet
to this host on port 80
and at this point, I am connected
and whatever I type on my
keyboard is gonna be sent
to that server.
Now, if you're doing
this, you probably want
to cut and paste this really fast
because if you take too long,
most web servers will be, like,
"You're a human, I don't
want to talk to humans;
"I want to talk to programs."
So, remember to type this fast enough
and then you have to hit Enter, twice,
so you have to have a blank line, here.
Just type this exactly as it's shown
and then you will get back,
a server, if you do it right,
the server, and the server's
properly configured,
the server will give you back some headers
and this is metadata about the
document you're going to get.
For example, it's saying
it's got text/html
which means that the
remaining stuff is gonna be
in HTML, Hypertext Markup Language.
It has a blank line and
then the actual document
and then the connection is closed.
And so, if you do this, you
can set this up in a way
that you can run this on your own computer
and, in effect, hack through
the back door, a web server.
Now, you can't hack the secure
web servers and mail servers.
They used to be easy to hack,
but they're harder to hack, now,
because they challenge
you for information,
but part of the reason I'm so
obsessed with the command line
is this is how real hackers work
and they know how
to talk some of these
protocols, more directly.
And so, we think of this beautiful,
sophisticated application
talking to some other thing
and it's all pretty and we
got wonderful clicky buttons
and nice usability, but the reality is,
like in The Matrix Reloaded,
here, the kinds of things
that really talented hackers
are doing use command lines
and they really know what's going on
and that's how they do it.
They understand what's going
on better than the developers
of the computers that are trying
to be resistant to hacking.
So, I come from a long line
of using the command line
and that's why I encourage
you to use the command line
in this course.
So, the next thing we're going to do is
we're going to go up into
the application layer
and instead of typing
those commands by hand,
we're going to actually
send them from Python
and write a very simple
Python web browser.
(sultry jazz piano music)