- Hello and welcome to Chapter 8.
We're gonna talk about
lists in this chapter.
Up to now, we've been
talking about algorithms.
Algorithms are the concept
in computer science
of using the programming language
to express the steps that
you want the computer
to go through to solve the problem.
Read some data, convert it
to a floating point number,
check to see if it's greater than 40,
do one thing if it's great than 40,
do another thing if it's not,
then print out the result.
Or, open a file, read everything,
and if the first line starts
with something, do something,
if not skip it, and then
add all the things up.
Those are steps, those
are a series of steps,
and hopefully by now
you're getting to the point
where you have a good
understanding of steps.
But there's a whole other
side of computer programming
called data structures.
And data structures is
not the steps but instead
clever ways that you lay out the data
and clever ways that you make sure
that the data does what you want it to do.
And so that's what we're going
to start talking about now.
Lists are the first and
simplest data structure.
Strings are kinda like data structures
but lists are probably our
first real data structure
that we're gonna think about and design
and make use of effectively.
But before we talk about
what is a collection,
we should talk about
what is not a collection.
So we're familiar with what a variable is.
We know that a variable is
a little piece of memory
that's got a label on it.
And then an assignment statement, ya know,
sticks a 2 into x and then 2
is in this little cupboard.
And then it goes to the next
line and then 4 goes into x
and so the 2 goes away and the 4 is there.
A key thing is you can't
have more than one variable
at any given moment, right.
And more than one value in a variable.
So when we move to collections,
collections are more like suitcases.
We can put lots of things in them.
We have ways of organizing them,
and as we go through lists
and dictionaries and tuples,
we'll see how there are
different ways to organize them.
And, as a matter of fact,
we've been talking about lists for awhile.
Every time we use one of
these square bracket syntaxes,
in earlier programs, we've
been working with lists.
And so this is technically
a three item list
with three strings, got commas here.
Joseph is one string, Glenn
and Sally are another string.
And here's another one
that is another thing,
and the list is basically,
it's a list constant
and it's being assigned into a variable.
So this friends variable
has three things in it,
so that's different than
what we've been talking about before.
So these brackets, bracket structures,
with square brackets are those lists.
And so the print is just the print
with parentheses to get the print to work,
but 1, 24, 76 is the
three item integer list.
Red, yellow, and blue is
a three item string list.
But it doesn't all have
to be integers or strings.
Python can handle different things
and different kinds of data
in different positions in the list.
So, red, 24, 98.6. a three
item list with a string,
an integer, and a floating point number.
And, while we're not gonna
use this too much for now,
this outer list is a three item list,
and the second item is another list.
So this is kind of alluding toward
what we'll do when we start
talking about data structures.
And that is, we have a structure
and then we have another
structure inside of it
and sometimes this can get quite complex.
And, we're doing this for a reason.
This here has no reason,
just to show you that it's possible,
that lists can be made
up of lots of things,
including other lists.
And of course there is also
the notion of the empty list.
And like I've said,
I have had to be able to tell
you about lists all along.
We use them in for loops.
We can put lots of things here,
we can put file handle here.
We can go through the file.
we can put a string there,
we can go through the
characters in the string
and in a list, and the iteration variable
then goes through the
successive elements of the list.
And that's why this
prints off 5, 4, 3, 2, 1,
and then the loop is done
and it prints out blastoff!
So we've been using them and
we've been actually iterating
through lists with for
statements all along.
So the for each, I mean
the for statement, ya know,
has been something we use with lists.
And when you just need to
go iterate through the list
and go through every item in order,
the for is a great way to do that.
So friend is our iteration variable.
Friends is our list variable,
and so that says friend
is gonna successfully
take on the value Joseph, Glenn, and Sally
and print out Happy New Year,
Joseph, Glenn, and Sally.
It runs three times, once
for each of the values,
and the iteration variable advances.
Now, I do want to make
it really clear that
the choice of friends-uh and
friend-uh, singular and plural,
is arbitrary and capricious.
It happens to be convenient and intuitive
that the iteration variable is one
and the list variable is more than one,
but Python has no idea
about singulars and plurals.
Matter of fact, Python wouldn't care,
it would be totally equivalent for Python
to do the same thing, to
have the list variable be z
and the iteration variable be x.
X will take on the success
values of these three things.
Now, am I being nice to you
by calling this list friends
and this iteration variable friend?
I am, but I also don't
want it to confuse you
if you're just a beginning developer.
So, just like strings, we can
sort of look within lists.
Part of the thing is when
you put more than one thing
in a data structure, you
need to get them out.
And so lists have positions,
they maintain order.
And so the first thing in the list is
the sub zero position, sub one, sub two.
Just like strings, they're zero based.
Just like European elevators,
they're zero based.
So if we take a look and
we say oh, friends sub 1,
that's how I read that the
little square brackets,
when you take a variable here,
and you say friends sub 1.
Remember, singular plural don't matter.
Friends sub 1 means Glenn
cause this is the zero
and that's the one and
then Sally's the sub 2,
so that's what prints Glenn
out in this particular thing.
Now, lists are mutable.
Mutable is another word for
changeable, they can be changed.
Meaning a list has three things,
you can change this thing right
in the middle if you want.
To take a look at what's not mutable,
strings are not mutable.
So, if I take a look at
assigning banana into fruit.
Well fruit sub zero is a capital letter B.
Could we imagine for a
moment that we could change
fruit sub zero to lowercase b?
Well this syntax would be
how you would do it if you could do it,
but it turns out that
strings are not mutable,
meaning they're not changeable
once you create them.
And that's why when we do things
like lowercase or uppercase,
we take a look at the fruit and we say
give me a lowercase copy of that,
and then we take the
return value from this
and we store that in x.
And that's how x becomes lowercase banana.
But fruit is still the original one,
so fruit has not changed.
Compare and contrast
that with a list, though.
Here we have a five item
list, 2, 14, 26, 41.
And we're gonna do the sub 2 position,
and the sub 2 is 0, 1, 2 so
it's that one right there,
and we're going to assign a 28 into it.
So that 28 is going in here.
I'm gonna wipe that out and put 28 in.
So we can do item assignment
in lists by putting
a bracket syntax on the
left hand side to say
don't just put it in the variable,
put it within this position
within the variable,
so that's what that's doing.
And when you print that out, the 28,
everything else is unchanged,
meaning the whole list is there.
There could be a thousand
items in the list,
and then you're changing the second one.
We have a function called len,
we've been using this
len function all along
to take a look at how strings are.
It counts the number of
characters in the string,
so that's a 9 character string.
If we have items in a list,
len tell us how many items there are.
It's not like how many
characters there are,
it's the number of things.
And each thing, doesn't
have to be a number,
it could be a number, a
string, or even another list,
and len is the way to say, hey
how many things are in there?
There's a function that
returns a list of numbers,
and we use it, as we'll see in a second,
to construct specialized
loops to go through lists.
So let's take a look
at this range function
just for a minute.
So, range takes as its parameter
the number of numbers
that you want returned.
So I would like a four item
list with the numbers 0
up to but not including 4.
And so it just turns out
that that is really useful
for constructing for loops
that are counted for loops,
that go to zero to the one to the two,
as compared to the definite
loops that go through each one.
And so it's a common thing to say okay,
we know how many things are in this list.
There are three friends.
And if I put, combine range and len,
so I take len friends which is 3
and then I take range
sub 3, I get 0, 1, and 2.
And so the interesting thing is
this zero corresponds to the first one,
1 corresponds to the second one,
and 2 corresponds to the third one, okay?
And so, we'll use this to construct loops.
Especially when we need to go through,
we need to go through an array
and remember what position we're at.
And so here's just an example
of two different loops.
This is a for loop that's just gonna go
through whatever's in this list.
So friend is just gonna take
on the successive values.
And so it's gonna print
out these three things,
just as you would expect.
And if you don't need to,
while you're going through
the loop, know the position,
your relative position
from the top in the loop,
that's okay.
But sometimes you want a
little more sophisticated loop.
And instead, you want to be able to
loop through where you know the position.
And so what we do instead is,
instead of looping
through that list itself,
we do range len friends,
which gives us 0, 1, 2.
And then i takes on the
successive value 0, 1, and then 2.
So this loop is gonna run four times
and i is 0 the first time.
And we might even just look up the value
inside that sub zero value.
So we get Joseph the first time,
so prints out Happy New Year, Joseph.
Goes and i becomes 1 now,
so gives us Glenn and that
prints out, away you go.
So if you look at these two loops,
if you look at these two loops,
they really do the exact same thing.
The only difference is
this we allowed the for
to find it's way with the
iteration variable through,
and here we created our
own i variable that went
through the positions,
and they're dense,
there's no gaps in here.
So it's zero through two
that it goes through.
So these two are equivalent.
There'll be times when you'll
want to use one and the other.
I tend to prefer the first
one because it's prettier
as long as it works for me.
So that gets us started with loops,
we'll be back in just a bit.
(light piano music)