- So now we're going to make a database,
we're going to use SQLite Browser,
hopefully you've downloaded
it so you can follow along.
And I've got this handout,
this basic database handout
that saves you from having
to type all these things
so bring that up in your web browser.
And so that gives you all of the commands
that I'm going to type, now, and so
you could pull 'em out of
the, either the web page, the,
you could pull 'em out of the slides
or you could pull 'em out of that.
So.
I'm gonna bring up the
database browser here.
Database browser.
Now the thing that's gonna happen,
you'll see this has
happened on my desktop,
I'm gonna make a new database,
and you have to store it somewhere
and so I'm gonna put it on my desktop
and I'm gonna call it py4efun.
And so we should see a
new file on my database.
Right there, py4efun.
Now that's a file that
you don't wanna edit
with a text editor or
anything like that, this is,
a database that, this
is a file that's to be
read by SQLite Browser and nothing else.
Okay, so we're gonna CREATE a table
and I'm gonna make a table called Users
with a column called name that's a text
and a column called email, so I'm gonna,
it's already asking me to make a table,
I'm gonna call this Users.
And I'm gonna add a field,
that is called name.
And I'm gonna add a text.
And I'm gonna add another
field called email.
And I'm gonna make that be text.
Now the key thing here is we are in effect
making columns and rendering an opinion
as to exactly what that column
is supposed to be used for
and we're not allowed to
violate that, it's not like
oh we'll do whatever you want, because,
the database is optimizing its storage
based on our contract that we're,
we're effectively making
the contract ourselves,
we can make these columns
anything we wanted, but,
we're just going to, we have to,
we're in a contract with ourselves.
And you can see it's kind of small here,
you can see there's a CREATE
TABLE and that's on the slide.
And that's the SQL way of doing that.
This user interface is
just helping us write SQL.
So now I'm just gonna say OK.
And if you take a look,
you can see,
that I now have a table Users.
And I can look at my database
structure, table Users,
and away we go.
So now that is creating
it, and like I said,
here in the slides is
the CREATE statement,
or on the webpage there's
the CREATE statement
that could've done it.
Now,
we can insert some data.
Let's add a new record
to this database Users.
And we'll call this guy...
Name.
Charles.
Csev@umich.edu.
So now we have a record.
So it's kinda like a
database, spreadsheet.
Now that's not the SQL way to do it.
There's SQL sorta going
on in the background.
But if we really wanna do this using SQL,
we're going to use the INSERT statement.
And the INSERT statement looks like this.
The SQL syntax sometimes has extra words.
INSERT INTO is actually two SQL keywords.
The name of a table.
The columns.
And then the word VALUES
and then one to one correspondence between
the values and in parentheses
so it looks kinda like a,
a tuple in Python, but we're
nowhere near Python right now.
Okay and so, that's what we're gonna do.
And so I'm gonna grab this.
Kristin.
And I'm going to go over
here to my SQLite Browser
and say Execute SQL.
So now I can say paste that in,
and then hit this little run button.
And that's going to
submit the SQL to SQLite
and then update that file and it says,
query executed successfully,
and away we go.
So if I got back now
and I look at the data,
I see that there's two things in here.
And now I can actually
insert all the rest of these,
let's go back to my
little bit of stuff here,
let's put all these other rows in.
It turns out that...
If I go into the SQL and
I wanna do more than one,
more than one command at a time,
I can put a semicolon at the
end of each one of these things
and then I can run them all four,
all at the same time, I mean
one after another actually
is what's going on here.
So, boom boom boom.
And now I take a look at
the data and look I've got
all those things in there.
Now.
Eventually the thing that's gonna generate
that SQL is a program, not us.
This is, we're being the
database administrators
so we're sorta doing things manually.
Once things get going you write programs
to do that insert over and
over and over again in Python,
or a web language like PHP
or something like that.
And so that is the INSERT.
Now, we can get rid of data.
And so I'm gonna say DELETE
FROM, that's the keyword,
Users is the name of a table,
WHERE is a WHERE clause,
we'll have lots of WHERE
clauses in SQL, which is,
it's not like an IF, in
effect the delete is going
towards the whole table
and being turned on and off
by this WHERE clause.
So DELETE FROM Users if you
didn't put the WHERE clause on
will actually delete all the rows.
But where email equals ted@umich.edu,
well, that one is going to make it
so it only applies to those,
to the rows where that is true.
So I'm gonna go over here in SQL.
And I say DELETE FROM Users
where email equals ted@umich.edu
and then I'm gonna run it.
'Cause it's only one I
don't need a semicolon
at the end of it, and now
if I go back and I look
at the data, Ted is gone.
Okay?
UPDATE.
So the UPDATE says...
UPDATE's keyword, Users
is the name of the table,
SET is a keyword, and then
this is column equals new value
and then a WHERE clause.
Again this UPDATE, if we
didn't have a WHERE clause,
would change every row in the table.
And so WHERE email equals csev@umich.edu.
Oh I gotta change that, 'cause I
already got the name to be Charles.
So you see the name is already Charles,
so I'll just execute here.
Make this be Chuck so we see it.
And then I run it.
And then you take a look at
the data, and it's changed.
That's it.
That's an UPDATE statement.
You're doing great, you're doing great.
And so, um.
The next thing we're going to do
is we're gonna take a look
at how we retrieve data.
Now this is the SELECT statement.
SELECT *, you have a list of columns,
and * means all columns,
FROM is a keyword,
and then the name of a table.
So this SELECT * FROM
Users is the kinda thing
you type all the time, as
a matter of fact it's what
SQLite browser is doing
internally to cause this to happen
but we can do it by hand, by saying,
SELECT * FROM Users and then run it.
And so then we get a little record set
that is those four records
that are sitting there.
We can also throw a WHERE
clause on the end of it,
so we'd say SELECT * FROM
Users where email equals
csev@umich.edu and that,
again the SELECT * FROM
Users goes at the whole table
and the WHERE clause
goes at the whole table
and then filters out all of
the things except one record.
So the WHERE clause is,
send it to the table
but then filter based
on whatever and so it,
it only shows us that.
Okay.
We're cruising right along here.
You can also put an
ORDER BY clause on there.
So we can say SELECT *
FROM Users ORDER BY email.
So that's a column.
SELECT * FROM Users ORDER BY email.
And so that orders by email.
Or we can change it to name
and we can say descending.
So that's the name in a descending order.
Sorting and selecting are good things
the databases are really good at.
So this is the summary
of what I've told you.
I said the databases do CREATE,
READ, UPDATE and DELETE, CRUD.
And we've done all those
things, except we did
CREATE, DELETE, UPDATE,
READ, that's what we did.
That's the summary of SQL.
And so...
You might be saying why did I take so long
to learn such a simple
and elegant and beautiful
language 'cause it's not really exciting.
It's a extremely simple
language that's very predictable
and you're like, that's pretty easy
and it turns out that some of you
may have been using SQL in situations,
maybe with Microsoft Access or something,
or actually type in the stuff
and you just kinda typed it
and you never realized that you were
learning a programming language.
That's why I like SQL and that's
a very declarative language
and it's very straightforward,
it's much harder to learn,
I mean it's much easier
to learn SQL than it is
to learn Python 'cause
in Python you have to
figure out how loops work and
how iteration variables work
and you'll notice there's none of that.
And so, the, but the key
is, is we've only started
to understand the power.
That's the simple ability to move around
and update data and read data randomly
using these simple sets of commands,
but up next we're going to
look at how you do this with
data models and relationships
and really, multiple tables.
(heavy rock music)