- Hello and welcome to
Chapter 13, Web Services.
So what we've been doing so far is
we've been using the
request-response cycle,
we've learned about sockets,
we learned about urllib,
and we've actually
learned how to pull HTML,
and even flat text off the internet,
but what we're gonna talk about now is
using that same request-response cycle
to retrieve information that is
specifically designed for
programmatic consumption,
so that, you know, we had
to have this beautiful soup
which sort of did a hack job or hard,
solve the hard problem of parsing HTML,
but why not produce data in a format
that makes good sense to a program,
because programs wanna talk to each other.
If you recall, the whole idea of a socket
is to have one application process
sending data to another
application process,
and so if we think
about this for a moment,
and we realize that we
have all these programs,
they can be written in
different programming languages
and they're all connected and so
they might wanna send data back and forth
through the network.
PHP programs, JavaScript
programs, Java programs,
and so we have to decide on a protocol
that is independent of
any programming language
and then we call that the wire protocol,
because if you were to sort
of take some connection
and watch the exact characters
that go back and forth,
that's what you would see
if you were monitoring
the wire, so that's why we
call that the wire protocol,
and so the idea is is that we have to
agree on a format that is
gonna represent the data,
and we can't a Python=specific format,
or a Java format, and
when we take the data
from the internal representation,
maybe a Python dictionary,
so send it to the wire, we
call that act serialization,
and that's going from sort of
the internal representation
to the serial representation,
or the wire representation,
and then, here is an example of person
with a name and phone number
with using less thans and greater thans,
this is an XML example,
and then in a far end
in a different programming language,
it receives this and then deserializes it
and then turns it into
some useful structure
inside that programming language,
and so this is an example of wire protocol
that's using XML, and that's one of the
formats we're going to talk about.
Another format that we're gonna talk about
is a format called JSON,
JavaScript Object Notation,
and it is simpler and easier,
but it's not as precise
and descriptive as XML is,
and so, while you'll find
that most of the things
you run into, especially
if you're talking to
APIs of one form or another,
you'll find that JSON is very common.
XML still holds sway in
places like documents.
So if you look at docx at the end of a
Microsoft Word document, docx means that
it's an XML version of the representation
of a word processing document.
So the first thing
we'll talk about is XML.