- So now, we're going to
dig into strings a bit,
and we've already looked
at how you can pull out
a single character in a string,
and now we're going to look
at what we call slicing,
and that is pulling
chunks of a string out.
And again, we're gonna use
the square bracket operator
and so, the way I say it is sub.
S sub zero through four.
That's how I read this.
S sub zero through four,
so I look at the colon as through,
I look at the brackets as sub.
And so, S sub zero through four says
start at position zero,
and then go up through,
but not including four, right,
so we don't include four.
So that's probably the
hardest part of this.
Up to, but not including.
This seems counterintuitive, kind of like
starting at zero seems counterintuitive,
but after a while, you'll
kinda get used to it,
and there'll be situations
where you're writing code like,
oh, that's why that works better.
But just for now remember it.
Up to, but not including.
It's just kind of a little thing
we'll come back to when
that is useful for us.
Six through seven, well, that
ends up being starting at six,
up to, but not including seven,
so that's why we only get the P out.
Now, one thing that Python
is pretty nice about
is it's not going to give you a traceback.
We might expect that six through 20, well,
there's no 20 characters,
but it's like, eh,
that's okay, we'll just
let you stop at the end,
and we'll start at six and
go all the way to the end.
Oh, no traceback.
It's almost disappointing
sometimes when Python
doesn't track back, when you think, ah,
you know, if you're so
obsessed about everything,
I would have traced
back in that situation,
but, hey, I guess if you're
allowed, you're allowed,
and so there we go.
Now, you can eliminate or
omit the first or last.
If you eliminate the first,
it assumes the beginning of string.
If you eliminate the second,
it assumes the end of the string, and ...
Why you would do this I don't know,
but that's from beginning to
end, so it's the whole string.
So, whole string, eight
through the end is thon,
and up to but not
including two is mo, right?
So you get that.
So just ...
That's pretty simple.
Once you've got the rest of
slicing and the rest of string
indexing, the notion of
eliminating the first or the last
of the colon expression,
the first or second of
the colon expression,
I think is actually pretty
intuitive, pretty nice.
We've already been
concatenating strings together.
We overload the plus operator,
and there is no space added.
Remember, when you're doing print ...
X, Y, this comma does turn into a space,
but that's not what's happening here.
There is no automatic space being added,
and so we see Hello and There,
and it just is HelloThere with no space,
and so if we want, we just have to
concatenate the space explicitly
if we wanna put spaces into strings.
The problem is if you ...
You might think it's more
convenient to add a space
with concatenation, but
then you have to think,
well, what about if I
wanna concatenate things
and not put the space in.
Then I'd need a different operator.
So that's kinda why it works that way.
We can use in differently
as a logical operator,
so we're using it as an
iteration structure in for loops,
but we can also use it
as a logical operator in if statements,
so it's kinda like the,
you know, double equals,
or not equals, or less than or equals,
or something like that.
It's like those guys.
And so, it returns a true or a false.
Is n in fruit?
So that's a question,
and the answer is True.
Is m in fruit, no, that's
the answer to a question.
Is nan in fruit?
Doesn't have to be a single character,
can be more than one character,
and the answer is true.
And then you say something like, you know,
if a in fruit, and so
this is the logical value
that returns a true or a false,
and yes, we found it.
So that becomes true
in this particular case
so it runs the little indented bit.
So, in is an operator in
this particular situation.
In a for loop, in means
something different,
and we'll use in for
other things as operators,
as logical operators coming up in a bit.
You can compare strings,
and this has to do with
the character set of your computer,
the character set that
Python is, but in general,
you know, it is
lexicographically less than
and lexicographically greater than.
Upper case and lower
case are a little weird.
I think when we used the
max function earlier,
the way my computer was set up,
uppercase was less than lowercase, but ...
In general, uppercase
is less than lowercase.
But in general, it's bad to assume case,
but there is a deterministic
way to sort strings.
You can, you know, have something equal to
or less than or greater than,
and all those operations work naturally.
The less than and greater than
you have to kinda be aware of
uppercase, lowercase things like where ...
You know, punctuation sorts
less than or greater than letters.
That's kind of unpredictable,
and it depends on
the character set of your computer,
and something you just
play with and figure out.
If you're doing sorting stuff
by first name and last name,
as long as the case is kinda
the same, you know, if ...
If you were sorting Chuck
with an uppercase and Glenn,
the fact that these
uppercases, they'd sort right,
and these lowercases would sort right,
but if you were to do
instead, lowercase chuck
and uppercase Glenn, then
that would sort weird.
As a matter of fact, the
G would come before that,
and so case can mess
this up, but in general,
other than case and special characters
and other things, it technically works.
It's just hard to kinda predict it.
A lot of what we do is
use the string library,
and so the strings are objects,
and we'll talk later about
what that really means.
And objects have these
things we call methods.
So a string object has
some built-in capabilities,
and one of the built-in capabilities
that the string object has
is, here is a string object,
and because greet is a string object,
if we said type, we'd
see that it was an str.
Dot lower says hey, dear string,
make a lowercase version of yourself.
It's like calling this function
lower and passing greet
into it, and then giving that back to me.
Now, it doesn't actually change greet.
It gives me a lowercase copy.
So here I have Hello Bob,
with an H and a B uppercase,
and what I get back in zap
is hello bob, all lowercase,
and note that greet is unchanged.
So Hello Bob is still there,
and you can even call
these methods on constants,
so this is a string object,
quote, Hi There, quote,
dot lower, that says ...
Call lower on this bit of string,
and give me back a
lowercase version of it,
and so it prints out as
the residual return value.
This is like a function call.
A method call is a kind of
special form of a function call.
It's a function call where you say
the thing, dot, the function name,
rather than function name
passed in as a parameter.
Like len, for example,
is non object-oriented.
You know, len of X, that's
not object-oriented.
Object-oriented would be X
dot something, parenthesis.
So constants are objects as
well, and taking the lower
gives us back lowercase, hi there.
And so that's just one of
the things that you can do
in the string library.
These are built into string
variables and constants.
They're just always there.
As soon as you make a
string, they're part of it.
And when you do type and
it says it's class str ...
We'll get to object-oriented, don't worry.
We'll get to object-oriented.
And so you can do things
like use the type.
This used to say, type 'str,'
but it's class 'str,'
kind of this is more of an OO ...
The word class is an
object-oriented concept,
but it is a string, and
you can use the dir,
and of course there's extra stuff up here,
and this is showing all
the different methods ...
Or capabilities, things
we can do to strings.
So, you know, X dot
something, parenthesis.
Well, what can we do there?
This is all of those things
that we can do to X's
that are built in and come with X's,
I mean come with strings,
when we build them.
And Python, of course, has
great documentation online
for all of these string
methods and what they do
and how they work, and why
they work the way they do.
And so here's some of
that Python documentation.
We'll look at a few of these.
But, you know, don't hesitate to say,
Python string uppercase, and
I'm like, oh, yeah, yeah,
that is upper, right?
And so, here's a few
things that we can ...
Do and use, some of the ones I use a lot,
and we'll look at each
one of these things.
So, the find() operation
says find me a substring
within a string, right,
find me a substring within a string,
so find me the first na, and
give me back the position.
So that gives me back two,
and then I can say, go find a z in there.
Well, there's no z, and so
it returns me negative one.
So that's what the find does.
So we're gonna do a lot ...
We're gonna use this kind of stuff a lot,
and we do a lot of looking in strings.
Converting things to upper or lowercase,
there is an upper method
and a lower method,
so greet, greet.upper and
that means the uppercase
nnn is HELLO BOB.
Greet.lower, that means
the www is the lowercase
hello world, and greet is unchanged.
Greet is still hello bob
with upper and lower,
because each of these
methods basically say
I'm going to give you
back a uppercase copy
or a lowercase copy of the original thing
without changing the original thing.
Search and replace is super useful,
super duper useful, and it's pretty clean.
Here, we have a string, and
we use the replace method.
In this case, we're passing
in the old and the new.
Bob, replace all Bob's with Jane's,
and so that takes this Hello Bob
and turns it to Hello Jane.
Again, greet is unchanged.
Greet is unchanged.
And it does more than one
thing, so this says, go find ...
No, let's clear that.
This says go find all the
o's, and replace all the o's
with X's, and so it goes
and finds two of 'em,
and then out come two X's,
and so that really is a ...
It replaces, not just
replace the first one,
but replace all of them.
White space, as we'll see, is a big deal.
And white space is not just blanks,
although the most common thing,
but it's also certain
non-printing characters like tabs
and new lines and other
kinds of things, and so
we have a number of different
ways to strip white space.
So here we've got some
spaces at the beginning
and spaces at the end,
and we print out, we do an L strip,
and that throws away the
spaces at the beginning,
that's the left, so it's a left strip ...
If there's nothing there,
it doesn't harm it.
R strip means throw away all
the blanks on the far end,
and then strip says go take ...
Take both sides, both sides for strip,
and so that pulls out all
the spaces on both sides.
This will be useful, 'cause
sometimes when you're tearing
stuff apart, you'll find
yourself getting extra spaces,
sometimes at the beginning,
sometimes at the end,
and it can be tab or new line.
It's sort of white space,
space that is kind of
not visible, clear.
That's what white space is.
It's like if you were on a piece of paper,
it's the white space.
It's like, X.
Well, that's not white space,
but right here, oh, that's white space.
It's any character that doesn't
cause printing to happen,
if that makes any sense.
It's any character where
nothing would be printed,
and there are characters like that.
There's like even bell characters,
but we don't use them very much.
We can ask very conveniently.
We can say, hey,
does this line start
with a particular string?
And so, you know, line ...
This is a question, gonna
return a true or false.
Does this line start with 'Please'?
And the answer is, True, it
does start with 'Please.'
Does this line start with a lowercase p?
No, it does not, and
so again, you use this
in the context of if something,
colon, some block of text.
Some block of code.
So, we can combine these
things to tear stuff out,
and so let's assume that
what we wanna do in this case
is we wanna take a from line,
this is from an email form,
email format from a mailbox.
And this has got the from with a space,
and the person's email, and then at sign
and the school they're
from, and a space, and then
the rest of the stuff, like
when this mail was sent.
And this is a real mail
message from this guy Stephen
from the University of Cape
Town in South Africa, and
it's really Stephen, and
this really is the first line
of a file that you'll
get to know pretty well
by the rest of this course.
Hi, Stephen!
We like you.
You're the example in my class,
and have been for a long time.
People actually who know
Stephen have taken this class,
and they're like, Stephen, I
saw your picture in the class.
So if you're ever in Cape Town
at the University of Cape
Town, say hi to Stephen
and tell him that you saw
him in the class, but okay.
That's neither here nor there.
What I really wanna do is I wanna extract
his school from this email line.
Okay.
So.
Now eventually, we will do things like ...
The data will come from files,
but this is still chapter six.
So this is the data we're
gonna search through,
and so we can say, hey,
let's go find the at sign.
Search up to this position
and find the at sign.
So data dot find at sign, and
give me back where that's at.
That's in position 21.
It's position zero.
Then, what we're gonna do
is we're gonna look for
the next space after the at sign.
So we're gonna start at the at sign,
and tell find to start
here and look forward
until it finds a space.
So data dot find, look for a space,
starting at the position of the at sign,
and then that'll be in position 31,
so 31 is what we get
in the space position.
So now what we have is we
have, in two variables,
we have the position of the at sign
and the position of the
space after the at sign.
Now, what we really want
is this bit right here.
So we have to go one beyond the at sign,
and we don't want the space, so we say,
we're gonna use slicing here,
data sub at position plus
one, up to but not including
the space, ooh!
Smiley face, 'cause we didn't
have to say space minus one,
because that is up to but not including.
And so we get that little bit right there.
So we don't have to say minus one there,
because this is not actually included.
The thing that's at the
position of the space
is not included.
So that's already a little
benefit for the up to
but not including, and so when
we print this variable out,
host, we get exactly just the
school that Stephen works at,
and probably went to, as a matter of fact.
I don't know if he went there or not.
So, this is just kind of a note
for non-Latin character sets.
You know, all programming
languages from the 60s on
tended to work in what we
call the Latin character set,
which is United States,
and England, and Europe,
and lots of places uses
this ABC character set
and the special characters,
but it's really common
to want to use different characters,
and so if you're going
from Python 2 to Python 3,
and we'll talk about this a little later
when it matters more ...
Luckily we're in Python 3,
and so, one of the big things
about Python 3 is that all the
internal strings are Unicode.
In Python 2, there was sort
of some confusion as you
went between strings, and this
is just a little bit of code,
and so I'm putting in here ...
You know, some Asian characters.
This is Korean, actually.
Asian characters into x,
and then I say what
kind of a thing this is,
and that is a string,
and then there's this Unicode,
and this comes from Python 2.
If it's a Unicode operation,
it's still a string,
whereas in Python 2, if you put
any international characters
into x, then it was a
string, and then there was
a separate kind of constant
called a Unicode constant,
and it was a different type.
And there was ways that
you had to mess with these
Unicode variables as you did things like
read them from files and
put them back into files
and did other things, so it
was much more difficult ...
In Python 2, but we're doing in Python 3,
and in Python 3, it natively
understands non-Latin
character sets, international,
Asian characters sets,
Spanish, French character sets,
and so, this is a good thing for Python 3,
and this is one of the real
benefits of using Python 3,
and as we start doing stuff
where we're exchanging data
with the outside world,
this will come into play
and I'll have to show you how to use it.
There was weird things that you had to do.
It just makes a lot
more sense in Python 3.
Okay?
So, we've talked strings,
we learned about the string,
we're converting it,
we've done a whole bunch of stuff,
and this is, again, you know,
we're not yet doing anything super useful.
We're learning sort of how
to like slice and dice,
even though we're sort of
not making the meal yet.
Up next, we're gonna talk about files,
we're gonna read some
data, and we're gonna
slice and dice and use all the things
in the next chapter that we've learned
up to this point, so see you in a bit.
(jazzy instrumental music)