- Welcome to Networked Programs.
This is Chapter 12.
Now we're going to learn a little bit
about how we talk to
resources on the network
using Python.
Now, this is a really quick introduction
into how the network really works.
I have a whole book that I wrote.
It's also translated into Spanish,
on how the network works.
Starting at the very lowest layer,
packets and everything,
right on up,
and it's actually really easy to read.
I wrote it for a high school audience.
It's a short book and pretty easy to read.
So if you read that book
you will understand that there is this
layered architecture,
the TCP architecture that
sort of runs our network.
At the lowest layer,
on one side here this is your computer
and this is server computer
and if you start on a web page,
goes across the network,
does this like 15 or 20 times,
that goes up into the server,
reads the data
and then the data comes back
15, 20 tops for the packets,
and then it's shown to
you as what you see.
And so that's how it works
and there's these layers
that we're not going to
talk about in this section
but I talk about in that book.
The layers of the link layer
which talk about how to get over one hop,
the internet layer
which talks about how to construct,
say 15 or so hops
to get packets back and forth.
That's the sort of lower level bits.
We're gonna start at what we call
the transport layer
and that's the layer where your computer
sort of assumes that it
can make a phone call
to another computer.
Another process
running on a program on this computer
talks to a program on this computer
and then it kind of comes back.
Okay and so we're gonna leave this alone,
we're going to ignore it.
We're going to assume that there's this
nice reliable pipe that's going from
point A to point B
and what are we gonna do with the pipe?
But if you're interested,
take a look at the book.
So we're just gonna start with the pipe.
Some kind of connection.
We have two processes,
process, process
and we have some kind of a connection
between them
and it is a connection
that we can both use
to talk and to listen.
In nerd terms we call these things sockets
and that is one process
running on one computer
another process running
on a second computer,
connected through the internet somehow
and one computer speaks into that socket
and it comes out
and the other computer returns
something and it comes.
And so this is a bi-directional protocol
of data which is a series of an effect
data phone calls between applications.
So the application might be on your side,
this might be your browser.
Chrome, Firefox, Internet Explorer.
On the other side this is a web server.
It might be Internet IIS,
Internet something
something from Microsoft
or Apache or Java Tomcat.
There's another program
and you are making phone calls
between these programs.
Now in general these servers here
stay up all the time
and you sort of just can
make a request when you feel like it
in your program.
But that's what we're going to do
and this is what we call a socket.
So that little connection,
that phone call,
that data phone call is
what we call a socket.
Now, you have to decide
which of the systems you're gonna talk to
and then which of the services
on those systems or which process.
And so we have this
concept called port numbers
and they're best thought of
like extensions on phones.
So one organization has one phone number
and it says, "please enter the extension
of the party you'd like to talk to".
Well that's kind of what ports are.
They're like, "I'm a server
and I'm connected to the internet,
please enter the extension of the process
that you would like to talk to."
And so for example,
there might be processes
running on various computers
and so the email's known to hang out
on cross port 25
or extension 25.
Login, insecure login,
lives on port 23,
and secure web lives on 80
and secure web lives on 443
and there's a couple
of different protocols,
say if you have your mail stored on Gmail
and you have a local mail client,
say like Thunderbird or Apple mail
that talks a protocol
to pull that mail across
and those live on various ports.
So, these ports are those extensions
and by convention
we have standards that tell us
what to roughly expect at those ports.
So when you're talking to port 80,
you expect to talk to a web server
or a http server.
If you're talking on port 23,
you expect to talk to a Telnet server
and on and on and on and on
and so these are the extensions,
the typical, commonly
used default extensions
for various network application processes
that are serving us data.
Now sometimes you'll go to a URL
and you'll see in that URL
there's a colon and a number,
that means that it's a web server
that's running on a port other than
the official 80 or 443 port.
Now, in Python we can
talk to these sockets,
right, we can just talk to them
and it's really easy,
surprisingly easy.
We have to import socket
'cause that's a library,
it comes with Python
but you can't use it in your program
until you say it.
And then you, basically
in the socket library
you call socket function,
that's what that syntax is saying.
You're making a socket.
Now the key to a socket
is sort of like an unopened file handle,
it's half of a file handle
it's an outward looking thing
that's not yet connected.
These parameters,
you're just gonna type them in.
This says we're gonna make a socket
that goes across the internet
and it's a stream socket
which means that it's
a series of characters
that come one after another
rather than a series of blocks of text.
There's another kind
that's harder to deal with
but we're gonna do this.
So this, don't worry about this line,
just know that this creates a socket
but does not associate it.
The very next line,
we get back a socket object
that I'm storing in the variable mysock.
And then when you wanna make a connection
across the internet,
to the far end,
you say, "oh, hey, dear socket,
extend yourself across the internet,
make the phone call to this host,
data.pr4e.org
and on that port 80."
So that's making the phone call.
This is like a phone number
and this is like the phone extension.
So we haven't sent any data yet,
we have simply run the phone
of a process,
hopefully living on port 80.
If it's there, great.
This might blow up.
This one here won't blow up.
But this line here
we could blow up
if there's nothing
sitting on that process.
It would come back and say,
"Oh, you tried to call?
You got no answer."
That's a legitimate thing to happen.
Maybe you don't have a network connection
or maybe that service
is down on that server
or the whole server's down.
But...
So I just, it's kind of amazing
that we're sitting here in Python
and in three lines we have
probably half a million engineers
have built this thing called the internet,
all these protocols and all this software.
And we just made use of it
in three lines of Python.
And I guess this is one of the reasons
that people absolutely love Python.
Absolutely love Python.
So, now that we have a socket
we have to ask ourselves
what kind of data are we going to send
and then what kind of data
are we going to expect to receive
across that socket.