- So now we're going
to talk about the other
serialization format,
JavaScript Object Notation.
Chances are good as you go out there,
you will very likely encounter
more JSON than you will XML.
Not that XML is bad,
XML is better for rich
and hierarchical documents.
Where as JSON is best
for just pulling data
out of a system and moving
it between two systems
with a minimum of fuss.
This is Douglas Crockford.
I have a great interview from him
and he's a funny guy, very very smart.
He claims he didn't invent
JSON, he discovered it,
because it really is based on
the literal notation for JavaScript.
And it actually looks
a lot like the Python
literal notation for
objects and for lists.
Now Douglas Crockford is
a quite a sense of humor.
He wrote this book called
JavaScript the Good Parts.
That's the little one right there.
And then JavaScript
the Comprehensive Guide
and the sense of humor
is all the stuff that's
in JavaScript that's not too useful.
And while this is sort
of a tongue in cheek
it also is trying to say that JavaScript,
what Crockford is really saying here is
JavaScript is a great
language as long as you
avoid the tricky bits and sort of keep it
very very simple.
And JavaScript is indeed a great language
but JSON comes from JavaScript.
You can read about JSON at json.org
JSON is not a international
standard, it's not like an RFC.
It really is, Douglas
Crockford decided to register
json.org and typed in some
pages and people started
reading it and people started using it.
And partly that was because
it was truly derived from
the JavaScript literal syntax.
So we're all ready to code.
Here is some Python that's
gonna process some JSON.
Keep it straight, Python process JSON.
So again I'm using the
triple quoted string here.
Now you'll notice the
syntax that we are using is
not angle brackets, but
instead curly braces.
And so the curly brace, and
then within the curly brace
you have key value pairs, "name" : "Chuck"
in the key colon value and
both sides have quotes.
You can also have objects within objects.
Curly brace, key value
pairs, key value, key value.
Looks a lot like Python.
And then you can do this.
So this is a structure
that has one key value pair
that's a string.
Another key value pair that's an object.
And then these are key values within
those contained objects.
So this is a string.
That again probably was
retrieved across the network
from some other place.
And we're gonna pass that string into
the JSON library loads, loads
stands for load from string.
So it reads this, parses it,
looks at all the white space.
White space again doesn't
matter too much here
unless it's between double quotes.
The white space doesn't matter.
And so it parses it and then
returns us a dictionary.
So the thing that's different about JSON
is that it's structure in our presentation
are simpler than XML.
So in Python everything
either comes back as a
dictionary or list, or a
dictionary within a dictionary,
or a list within a dictionary.
But it's all dictionaries,
it's not a separate structure
that you have to do gets and
finds and find alls and lookups
so it's right there.
So when we get this back
because this is a curly
brace, info is a dictionary.
And so we can just use the
standard syntax of Python,
info sub-name.
Well that will bring,
let's clear this.
So info sub-name will go find Chuck.
So if you can pair that with the XML
that's just a lot easier.
Now when we have info sub-email
that's this thing, so info
sub-email is that thing,
and then sub-hide is this.
So that's what comes out here.
'Kay so it's really a nested
dictionaries and lists,
we haven't seen a list yet,
but this is a set of nested
dictionaries that it parses.
And it's equally simple in
other programming languages.
This is a little more complex version
where the outer element is
a square bracket, which means
it's going to be a list.
And so we have a list of
one comma, two things.
So this is a list of two dictionaries.
So there's two dictionaries
inside that list.
So again we take this
string and we load it into,
use the JSON parser to read
the string and give us back.
In this case, info is a
list, it's got two items.
If we printout info it'll give us two,
and we're going to iterate through.
And so if we're going to iterate through
item is going to first be this
and then it's going to iterate to this.
And it's going to printout item some name,
which is going to printout Chuck.
Item sub-id which is
going to printout 001.
Now you'll notice that
there is no attributes
and that's 'cause JSON is simpler.
But we can have the X
just as another item.
So we say item sub-x and that's
going to print the two out.
And then it will iterate to the next one
and it'll printout the
same thing for those guys.
And so, JSON is simpler because
you can't represent as
complex a data structure
or you have to compromise and map it
into simpler data structure
but then it is lists and dictionaries.
And so once you've got it parsed
it is easier to understand
and to make use of.
So that was quick.
So that's part of why
everyone likes JSON better,
is once you have come up
with a format that you're
going to send it back and forth,
it's easy to make it and
it's easy to read it.
Now what we're gonna talk about is
sort of moving up a level.
If you've got all these data
formats and URLs that you
can hit to pull all
those data formats down,
what approach do you do as you start to
construct applications
that increasingly go from
a single application to
a network application.
("Soul and Mind" by E's Jammy Jams)