- In this section, we're
gonna write a web browser
using Python.
So we've already got a socket,
we know how to write a socket.
In the previous section we played with
the protocol and used
Tellnet to do it by hand,
and now we're gonna do it in Python.
And what you're gonna find
is it's not that hard.
So here we go.
So the first three lines of
this program, import socket,
make the socket.
Remember, the socket isn't really
got the connection, so you
make the socket, again,
we're gonna make a stream-based socket,
and it's suitable for
going across the internet.
The connection that's
like ring, phone call,
connect to data dot P R
four E dot org and port 80.
So that basically says
send the socket across
and connect to a web server,
and so there's gotta be a
piece of software running
and this will blow up if the
software is not running, okay?
So then, now we've got a phone.
We've made a phone call.
Now whether or not the
remote side says hello or not
is up to the application protocol,
and in this case, the
web servers say nothing,
and they wait for you to talk first,
so we're the web browser in this case,
and so we're gonna talk first,
and we know what, because
we read the documentation,
we know that we're gonna
send get blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah blah blah blah.
Space blah blah blah blah blah H D one,
and then two new lines.
Return, return, remember you
had to have a blank line?
We'll talk a little
bit about this end code
It's preparing the data
to go across the internet,
and then we say send it.
And so this basically
takes that little string
and sends it across the network,
and then this piece of
software is waiting for it
and then the software
goes and reads the file
or does some other stuff and
then it starts sending us
data back, which we can
then choose to receive.
So now I write a real simple loop.
We're gonna receive the
first, we're gonna receive
these things 512 characters at a time,
so we're gonna loop through
receiving 512 each time,
and if we get zero
characters, that means it's
end of the stream, the stream is closed.
And if you look at the little example
from the previous one,
you saw connection closed.
When the connection is
closed, we get an indication
that it is because we ask for some data
and we get zero data.
Otherwise if there might
be more data, this'll wait.
If the network is slow, you'll see
if you do print statement in here,
you will see that this will
pause from time to time
on a really slow network.
If your network is fast,
it'll just go blank,
and it'll be so fast it won't matter.
But this is how we go.
So this is basically
until the entire socket,
until the socket is closed,
we are going to read this data,
and because this data's
coming from the outside world
we have to decode it before we print it,
and then when we're all
done we break out of here
and we close the socket.
So literally that is an entire web browser
written in 10 lines of Python.
And again, this is why
everybody loves Python.
So this is what this program
will show if you run.
The get is sent.
It looks exactly like doing it by hand.
You get some headers.
Again, this is metadata.
It tells you something about the file.
In this case, one of the important things
is what kind of thing is coming next.
There's always a blank line between,
as a break between the
headers and the actual data,
the metadata and the data,
and then here is the actual
text of that romeo dot
txt file, and then it's
just gonna run this,
print data dot decode.
All this is coming from
the print statement.
If you were gonna parse
this, you have to know
that you're gonna read the headers
up to a little blank line.
The blank line is your indication
as a software developer
that the headers have stopped,
and the actual text begins,
and you know the syntax.
This actually could be a jpeg or a png
or some kind of image, right?
And this data right here
would like like blech.
So if you type this and
you change that code
to actually talk, go retrieve a jpeg url,
gibberish will come out, okay?
And so that's exactly what you will see.
And so now you have built
a very simple web browser.
Next I wanna talk a little bit about
what happens when characters transition
from outside your computer,
I mean from inside
the computer in strings,
out across the sockets
to servers and then back.
(metal music)