- So we're gonna find that
there's a number of different
ways that we can read through
the file, but the most common
way that we're gonna read
through the file is to treat it
as a sequence of lines,
and we're gonna use the
determinant loop, the for loop to do this.
And, so what happens here
is we get back this handle
that opens the file and
gives us back the handle.
That handle xfile is the
variable I named called
I just named it xfile.
That's not the data, but it is a
sequence, it is that file
handle represents to Python
a sequence that we can
potentially walk through and then
get all the lines.
And it's the simplest, most
beautiful, elegant way to read
all the lines in the file.
We use the for loop and we
have an iteration variable,
this is going to take, when
we talk about the file,
cheese is gonna be the first
line, then the second line,
then the third line, then the fourth line.
So it's like going through a
string but you're going through
a file now and you're
getting it line by line,
so that's each line.
I just picked a variable named cheese
so you didn't get confused.
Later I'll call this line, but
Python doesn't know
anything special by naming
that variable line.
Okay?
And so this is, it's the
for and the n, and so
I read this as for each line,
in the file, the file handle xfile.
So run this loop one time
for every line, and then
print it out.
So it's actually really
quite simple, 'kay?
Other languages like C or
C++ or other languages,
they have to write while loops
with end of file conditions,
and all kinds of things that
make this very difficult,
but this is one of the prettiest
things that Python has.
It's a very, very pretty thing.
Okay, so let's talk
about what we might do.
And we're going kinda
back to iterations now.
What if we wanted to count
the number of lines in a file?
Well this is a basic
loop counting pattern.
So we open the file and then,
like in all these loops,
we do something to sort of prime
the loop to get it started.
Set a variable count to zero,
and I'm gonna use the variable
line that's gonna go through
each of the lines in the file,
for line in fhand,
down the file.
And it's gonna run this loop
once for each line in the file
and the variable line is gonna change.
But all I'm gonna do is add
count equals count plus one,
so that's just, like from
counters, that's just how you
detect, so every time we see
a line, we're just gonna add
one to the counter.
We're not printing the line,
we're not even lookin' at its
data at this point.
And then when the line is
done, however many times it has
to go, out it comes, and
we print out line count
equals count.
And so if we open mbox.txt,
this is gonna do all this work,
and then print this line
out, and say line count is
132,045, so this is a little
five-line program that shows
you how to count the lines
in a text file using Python.
Again, simple and elegant and
not too much syntax for you
to have to learn.
Now it's also possible to
read the file as a series of
characters all in one go.
Read the whole file, and
now you gotta be careful,
depending on the size of the
file, this is gonna lead to a
string variable with a lot of data in it.
Now if it's, you know, 100,000
characters, that's actually
kind of a small thing, but if
it was, you know, 10 million
lines, that would probably not be good.
You'd wanna read it one line at a time
and process each line,
and then do something.
But, mbox-short.txt is
a small little file.
So we open it, and we
get back a file object,
file handle object, and
we call the read method,
and that says nope, go
through and read all the text
and give it back in one
big block, one big string,
and I'll put it in inp.
And so that's where you
have a line, a new line,
a line, a new line, a line,
a new line, so it really
lines, it's just a sequence of characters,
with new lines in there to punctuate them.
And now you can split that
later, we'll see how to split
that into separate lines if you want.
Now I picked a file that was short and so
this inp variable now has a string in it,
and I can use the len function,
pass a string into the len
function, says oh, 94,626 characters.
That's kind of a small
a small little file.
And perfectly okay to
read it all in one go.
And so now I say just print
the first 20 characters.
That's, you know, beginning
to up to but not including 20,
and so it shows the first 20
characters of that little file
is a from line, 'cause
this is a mailbox file.
Now, let's say we're
going to do a searching,
and we did this loop where
you're looking for something.
And so we're gonna search
for lines that have a prefix
of from.
Okay?
That's what we're gonna do,
and we're gonna print those
lines out, so there's lots
of lines in this file,
you know, line, line, line, line from.
Line, line, line, line from, alright?
On and on and on.
And we only wanna show these lines,
the ones that match, right?
That's what we wanna do.
And so (clears throat)
we are going to write an
open statement, and then
we're gonna loop through,
and we're gonna ask the question.
If the line starts with from, print it.
So sometimes it's gonna
skip, skip, skip, skip
and that's gonna run it.
And skip, skip, skip, skip, skip.
That's gonna run it.
Skip, skip, skip, and then
it's gonna run it, okay?
So, that's the basic idea.
And that'll finish when it's
all said and done, and so
this is like a criteria,
this is like a search.
We're looking for lines
that match the string
that have the string from as their prefix.
Now, when we look at
the output of this, it's
kinda weird.
We see kind of these little
blank lines that show up.
Blank, blank, blank,
blank, blank, blank, blank.
What's going on here?
(mumbled hum)
What's going on?
So let's take a quick look.
The problem is is new lines.
Well I mentioned that the file has
new lines in them.
And so when you do the for
loop, it doesn't throw the
new lines away, as you might
expect, it would be kind of
nice if it did, but it doesn't.
It actually shows you, when
you read, it reads that first
line up to and including the new line
and gives you that back as
the variable, so that is the
first new line, so that
means it's gonna go down.
And then the print statement
actually adds another new line.
So that's the second line of
the file has a new line at
the end of it, and the
print statement adds another
new line.
So if we take a look at the code,
there is
a new line, oops, come back.
If we take a look at the code,
this variable line has a new
line in it.
Oops, where am I at?
I'm on the wrong slide, there we go.
Yeah.
This is what I wanna do.
If we look at the code,
there's a new line in here
and then the print adds another new line.
So the print adds a separate new line.
And that's how we get two new lines.
The print statement's new
line, and the little line
from the file.
Here's how we fix it, and
you're gonna write this code
a lot because when you're
reading text files, you end up
with a new line, and often
you don't want the new line.
But thankfully, (clears throat)
as we saw in the previous
chapter, there is a nice
little function in Python
for strings called strip,
that allows you to throw
away white space.
And to review, remember white space
is anything that doesn't print.
And this new line is not
a non-printing character,
so rstrip gets rid of it,
so it's a way to get rid of
white space, and rstrip
does it from the right end,
so it's the right end of the string.
And so, if we just are gonna
loop through all the lines in
the file, we say line equals
line rstrip and then this
variable no longer has the
new line at the end of it.
We have our little if
statement and if we print it,
then this line, the data has
no thing, and then the print
the data has no new line in
it so the print only goes
down one, so now we have
single-spaced output.
And so you're gonna be doing that a lot.
It's really common to read
through a file and then just
strip the new line or any
trailing space off the end
of that.
Now there's a couple of
ways to do a loop like this.
And let's just think of this as
we're looking for a line, a
file with lots of different
lines in it, and we wanna
ignore all the lines except
some say good lines, and we
wanna do something with those
"good lines", or the
lines we're looking for.
Needle in a haystack, this is
like searching for a needle
in the haystack.
So if you look at this code at
high level, we're gonna loop
through everything and then
we're sort of picking which
lines are, and these are
the good lines down here.
Now often, we have a bunch
more code that we wanna do,
and we're not just printing them,
but we're gonna do a lot of code.
So sometimes you actually
structure the loop a little
bit differently.
And so the way to do it, and
this is gonna do the exact
same thing, it's just
a little different way
of thinking about
this loop, so the top part is the same.
We're stripping it.
And what we're doing here is
everything's the same here,
except we add this not.
If the line does not
start with from, that's
the translation that, if the
line does not start with from,
continue.
So basically, we have a skipping pattern.
So the lines we're not
interested in, we skip,
so we come down, we, you
know, skip a lot of lines.
(swooshing noises)
And then we find a line
that's good and then
we fall through.
So this is the good code, and
then we have all the other
good code that we wanna do to that line.
We have that showing up down here.
So this is just two patterns
that, two ways to do the
exact same thing.
So another way to select the
lines that we're interested
in, just use the in operator,
so we talked before about
the in operator and how that works.
So we're basically, gonna wanna use
the continue skipping method,
so we're gonna read all the
lines, these first few lines,
if uct.ac.za is not in the line,
skip it.
And so this is gonna
print out all the lines
that have the string uct.ac.za in them.
And so you see this is
the output of the program,
dot, dot, dot, dot, dot.
Sometimes you'll have
programs that want to
read different files.
Often I give assignments
where I say, "Show me how this
"program runs on the short
file and then show me again
"how it runs on the long
file, just like this."
And so the way we do that,
to input the file name,
instead of making the file
name be a constant to the open
call, we make the file name BA input.
So we just run an input statement,
which gives us a prompt,
and then we type mbox.txt and
then that shows up in this
variable f name, it's a
corsa string all the time,
and we pass that into
open and then we open it,
and then we do, you know,
the count operation.
So if we enter inbox.txt it counts 1797
subject lines in inbox, and
if we give it mbox short,
it says there are 27
subject lines in mbox.
And again, this is another
one of those ifs and it's just
counting, but only counting
lines that match a particular
a particular
pattern.
Okay, so now the user can
also type bad file names,
and we need to be able to
deal with that as well.
And so we're taking a small change
to the code.
The dangerous code is
this line right here,
this line right here is
gonna trace back if that file
doesn't exist.
So what do we do?
Well, we're gonna just expand
that, the rest of this program
is exactly the same, the
only thing's different is
we've got this line, we've
took out insurance on it,
and we know that it
might blow up and so we,
we have it in a try and except block.
So here's how the code runs.
So, you know, the input runs,
we type in a good file name,
it comes in here.
This works and so it skips
the except and so it runs the
code and prints out the count.
So that's the good pattern.
The bad pattern is
here.
We type in a bad file name,
it comes in the try except,
this file name is na na boo
boo and it's gonna blow up so
(imitates explosion)
this line blows up, so it
jumps down at the except code,
prints out file cannot be opened.
So it print this out, now
this quit is really important.
Because if we don't put this
quit in here, it's gonna
continue down here and it's
gonna blow up here because
the file handle is not defined
properly at this point.
And so what we have is
we have this quit op.
Quit is a special
function where it comes in
and never returns.
So this is a way to terminate
the entire Python program
silently with no trace back, alright?
So we put in our own error message,
so we look like we're
professionals, say could not open
this file, and then we stop.
If you don't, it's gonna
come down here and it's gonna
trace back, trace back right there,
it's gonna blow up, so the quit is useful
when you want to stop executing
because you've detected
some kind of an error.
So that's a quick zoom through
opening and reading files
and doing some patterns.
Most of the rest of the programs
in this course are going to
say open,
for,
rstrip,
deuce look for, and then
do something interesting.
That's going to be our
loop that we're gonna do
over and over and over again.
And now we see how this
looping and if and iteration
and variables are
are starting to come together
and you can actually sort of
do a program that does something useful.
But before we get to too
many more programs, we gotta
switch a little bit, switch
gears and talk up next
about data structures and
that is the shape of data.
And how we can use more
intricate and complex variables
to help solve our problems.
(jazzy piano music)