- Now we're going to look
at some more patterns
of the different things we
can do at the top of the loop,
in the middle of the loop,
and at the bottom of the loop.
And the first one we're
going to do is counting.
We're going to take a look
at the number of something,
the number of things in our list.
We could just inspect it and see six,
but you'll have four
loops like you're reading
through a file or scanning
through some data,
so the notion of counting,
you have to assume
that you don't really know
.... that there's going
to be a lot more than just six.
But for now we're just going
to do six, and we're going
to count how many things
that we see in this loop.
And the pattern is simple,
you set a variable,
zork to zero at the beginning.
We often call this variable
count, in mnemonic.
Now we're going to run
this loop six times.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
And each time through we're
just going to add one to zork.
So zorks start at zero, then it goes one,
two, three, four, five, six.
And we're going to print it out.
We see the nine, and zork is one.
Two, 41, zork is two.
Zork of 16 when we see a 15, four stops,
and we print out
afterwards, and six is then
the ultimate count that we got.
That's very, very simple, the pattern is
that set it to zero at the beginning,
add one to it, and if you
run that enough times,
then this is how many times that happened.
In a sense, it's how
many times this line ran.
Sometimes we put this in an if statement,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
We can do the same thing to get a total.
The way the total works is
you compute a running total
of the items that you've
seen far, and at the end
the running total in
effect becomes the total.
A better variable name
for this would be sum
or total or something, but
zork, I'll use zork again.
So you set zork to zero, and it starts out
the total you've seen
so far is indeed zero.
And then we're going to
run this one, two, three,
four, five, six times and thing is going
to be the iteration variable,
it's going to take on
the successive values, and
each time through we're just
going to take our running
total and add to it
the thing we've seen.
So we see nine, and the
running total is nine.
We see 41, and that
running total becomes 50.
We see 12, the running total becomes 62.
We get a three, it becomes 65, we get 74,
running total's 139.
How many more are we going to see?
We don't know, could be
a million, could be one.
Oh, it's only one, we get a 15,
our running total is 154, and what's true
at any moment here is the
running total is right
of what we've seen so far.
Now, when we're done,
before loop quits for us,
and afterwards, 154 is indeed the total.
So the running total
while we're in the loop
at the end of the loop,
after the end of the loop
we have the actual total.
So it's not very difficult to
convert this to the average,
because we've calculated the
count and we've calculated
the running total, and now
we're going to have the average
by simply dividing those.
Now this time I've use mnemonic variables.
Don't get confused by this,
mnemonic variables are just
friendly names I chose for
you to read the code easier.
I am not communicating
to Python in any way
by naming this count and sum,
but count and sum is nice.
So I set count to zero and sum to zero.
Go back up, I set count
to zero and sum to zero
at the beginning, and the count
is zero and the sum is zero.
And then I'm going to
run this loop six times.
One, two, three, four,
five, six, and each time
value is the iteration variable.
Every time I run the loop I
count equals count plus one,
sum equals sum plus value,
so I have a running count
and a running total,
and they show up here.
One, two, three, four, five, six,
and then the running total.
And then at some point the
for loop, we do the last one
and the for loop jumps
out, and it divides,
654 is the count in the running total,
and then it divides the
average sum over count.
So that's just a pattern of
something in the beginning,
something in the middle,
something in the end.
Another kind of thing
we tend to do in loops
is we look for things, we hunt for things.
This is where we have an if
statement inside of a loop,
and of course I've created
a silly simple thing.
In this code I am looking for large values
that are greater than 20.
Again, don't think of
this as just six numbers,
but I'm looking for all
the values and I want
to print them out.
It says before, it's
going to run this nine,
if nine's greater than 20,
it's false, so it goes back up.
41, true, so it prints
out 41 and goes back up.
12, false, it goes back up.
Three, false, goes back up.
74, true, so it runs this, so out comes
that little print statement, goes back up.
And then 15 is the last
one, and that's false.
It goes back up and the
for says we're done.
And then we do afterwards.
This is just the notion
of having an if statement
inside of a for loop, where we're sort of
picking or choosing or selecting
or looking for something
in a large set of things
that we're looping through.
We can also say I want to know
if a particular value is there.
We're going to use a Boolean variable.
We've talked about integer
variables like one, 42,
and then floating point
variables like 98.6,
and then string variables like Hello world
that have quotes in them.
This is a forth type
type, a kind of variable.
It's called a Boolean variable,
and it only has two values.
It has true and false.
As a matter of fact, these if statements,
they return Boolean values,
value equal equal three,
that is returning a
true or a false based on
the value of value.
There's a mnemonic confusion
there, but I'm using it.
I'm going to make a variable called found,
and that's a decent name for a variable,
so don't get hung up
on that, and I'm going
to initially say found is
going to indicate to me
whether or not I found a three in my list.
And I'm going to start
before the loop starts
and say false, because we
haven't found anything yet.
So found equals false.
So at the beginning of
the loop, found is false,
before the loop starts, found is false.
And now we're going to run
this loop a bunch of times.
Nine, is that true, no, skip.
41, is that true, skip.
12, skip.
Nine, 41, 12, and found has remained false
because we haven't done anything to it.
But now in comes a three,
and this becomes true,
so it runs this code, found becomes true,
and then we print it and you'll notice
that when we see a three we get true.
And then it runs again, we
get 74, it's still false.
15, it's still false, run, run, run, quit.
And the residual afterwards is true.
In fact, if you didn't know any of this,
print that out, all you know is that
afterwards we looped
through all those things
and we know that there
was a three in there.
That's what we're doing.
We searched all of them,
we checked for threes,
when we found a three,
and you can see basically
that the found remains false
until it flips to true,
but then there's nothing
to set it back to false.
There's nothing in this loop that's going
to set it back to false,
so once it sort of
catches the three, then it remains true
for the rest of the loop and
then it just finds its way out.
If you want to think about it for moment,
ask yourself, how might we
make this loop more efficient
by putting a statement right in here?
Think about a way, once
you've found it and it's true,
there is sort of no
reason to keep on going.
What would you put there
to perhaps make this loop
to look for threes just
to tell you whether or not
there was at least one three in there,
how to make that more efficient,
just think about that.
Now let's look back at the largest value
that we started out with.
If you think about this,
let's kind of give it
sort of a rough, rough look here.
Largest so far is our, kind
of like a running total,
but it's our hypothesis
is the best large number.
And we have this if statement that says
if the number we just
see right now is greater
than the largest so far, then capture it.
Take whatever number
we saw and capture it.
When we see nine, it's
better, we capture it.
We see a 41, it's better, we capture it.
We don't capture this,
we don't capture this,
we capture the 74, and
we don't capture the 15.
And that's how we do it.
You could think of this as better.
When the number we're
looking at is greater
than our working
hypothesis of the largest,
we grab it because it's better.
This line right here is
the grab line, grab it.
So then the question is, how
would you modify this code
to teach it to find the smallest value
in this list of numbers?
Think of it as, you
have a starting number,
you have a what's better
and this grabbing notion.
How could you do that?
Take a look.
Okay, so let's take a look.
Let's do a couple things.
If you look at this if
statement that's better,
it's better now if the
number is less than,
but then we should probably change this
to be smallest so far, smallest so far,
smallest so far, smallest so far,
smallest so far, smallest so far.
Matter of fact, that's what this is.
We've changed the word largest so far
to smallest so far, and we've
changed the greater than
to a less than, is that going to fix it?
I'll give you a second to
look at it, pause if you need.
Is that going to fix it, is that going
to find our smallest number?
The answer is, of course, no, it's not.
If we run this code, we've
set the smallest so far
to negative one and it
starts out negative one,
we run it, and it's nine.
Is nine less than negative one?
No, it's not.
After we see a nine, the
smallest so far is negative one.
Now we're going to run 41.
Is 41 less than negative one?
No, it is not.
So is the smallest so far
is still negative one?
As a matter of fact, it isn't
the smallest so far anymore.
Just because we named it
smallest so far doesn't mean
it is the smallest far.
That didn't work out so well.
None of these, because they're
never less than negative one,
do anything, and we claim that afterwards
the smallest we've seen
so far is negative one.
And that is because, of
course, negative one is smaller
than any of the numbers that we saw.
So how could we fix this?
Well, if we started the smallest
so far with some arbitrary
big number, then it'd be better.
So if we made this a
hundred, whoops, come back,
if we made this be like a
hundred, that'd be good,
because the first time
through the nine would
be less than a hundred so
we would capture the nine
and then the rest of the
loop would work just fine.
But then what if we didn't know
how big these numbers were?
As a matter of fact, the largest
so far wouldn't have worked
if all the numbers were
negative, think about that.
We just assumed they were
positive and so we kind of
wrote lazy code that assumed
all numbers were positive.
That might not be a good
assumption depending
on the numbers that you're dealing with.
So maybe a hundred's a
good number to start with.
Or maybe like a thousand, or 10,000,
or like some number with
lots of zeros in it.
How big should we make this?
And the answer is, we're
kind of solving this problem
the wrong way.
The thing we really want to
do to solve the problem is
to just accept the fact
that if we're looking
for the smallest number so far,
that the right hypothesis
is the first number.
And if we just knew what that
first number was, the nine,
that would, because it's the first number,
we know it's both the largest
so far and the smallest so far
as soon as you see the first
number, but we don't know
here before the loop starts
what that first number is.
I mean, you can look at it,
but assume this is just data
that's coming from somewhere
else and we don't know it
until we start reading it.
So you have to construct a
loop that deals with the fact
that we want to capture the
first value as our hypothesis
for smallest so far, so how do we do that?
Let's take a look.
What we do is, we use yet another type.
So we have integer,
floating point, string,
Boolean, and now we have a
thing called the none type.
None type is a special marker
in that is only has one value.
Boolean has true and false.
Floating point has an
infinite number of values
and integer has an
infinite number of values,
but none type has one value, none.
None is a constant,
capital none is a constant.
The difference is that we can check to see
if we have stored none.
None is often used to indicate emptiness,
not non-existence, because
smallest doesn't exist
until we assign it, but
we're going to assign it
to a mark, a flag, a
marker, someway to say
this is not even a number, it's nothing.
And you can do this, so
let's make a variable
called smallest and in it put none.
It sticks it right in,
it's not a string none,
it's like a special type.
So that actually captures the notion that
before the loop starts,
the smallest number
that we've seen so far is none.
We haven't seen any numbers.
Then we come in and we
have an if statement.
And we have a new operator called is.
Is is stronger than equal sign.
So if smallest is none, that becomes true,
it runs this case, and
so then what it does is
it copies this first value,
which is nine, into smallest.
We see a nine and the
smallest so far is nine,
which is the first value.
Again, we're assuming we don't
know what the first value is
before the loop starts, so
we use the first iteration
through the loop as the
moment where we capture that.
Smallest is the value,
and then we print it,
we go back up, and now
it runs again with 41.
41 is not none, there's
only one thing that's none.
So it is not equal to none,
smallest is not equal to none,
or is not none, so this is
false, so it skips over here.
Then it asks the question, is
the value we're looking at,
41, less than smallest?
Well, smallest is nine in
this case, and this is 41,
so that's false, so it
skips that and goes on.
We see 41, we don't take
it, and then you can see
that this will never become true again.
This is pretty much false for the rest
of the iterations of the loop.
That's false for the rest of
the iterations for the loop.
So it just is going to run down
here and ask this question.
And at some point we see a
three, and we run this code,
we capture it, we see
74, we don't capture it.
We see 15, we don't capture it.
Then the for loop skips out,
at the end we have the smallest.
Actually, this would be a good technique
for the largest as well,
because it really is
just a technique to put
a marker in this variable
so that we snag that first
number, or first whatever,
as we read and parse through them.
So the is and is not operators
are very useful in Python.
You can think of them as
like the double equal sign.
They're asking a question.
They're asking a question, the returnature
of the blank is blank,
returns a true or a false.
It is stronger, double equal says,
are these things equal in type and value?
Just as an example, if I were to say
is zero equal to 0.0?
It would say yeah, that's true.
But then if I say zero is
0.0, that would be false.
That's because these two
are the same value wise,
these two are not the same type wise.
So is is stronger than equals,
meaning that it demands
equality in both the type of the variable
and the value of the variable.
And no conversion is done.
That's just a very
strong, don't overuse is,
if you're dealing with
numbers or even strings,
use double equals, don't use is,
because sometimes it
gets a little confusing.
Use is sparingly, I tend
to only use is on Booleans
and on none types, I
don't use is on integers
and I don't use is on floats,
and I don't use is on strings,
just none or true false.
And also is not is also an operator.
So you just say blah,
blah, blah is not none,
or blah, blah, blah is not false.
We've been looping around
and doing loops and loops
of loops, we looked at
the indefinite loops,
the wild loops that
kind of run for a while,
and we looked at break
and continue as a way
to either escape completely from the loop
or go back up and discard the
current iteration of the loop.
We looked at none, we
looked at Boolean variables,
with for loops, definite
loops where you've got
some kind of a set or a list
or some kind of sequence
that you're looping through.
And then the concept of loop
idioms where you do something
at the top, something to each item,
and then you get a benefit at the bottom.
So that gets us through iterations.
(light jazz music)