- So, now we're going to wrap up
and talk a little bit about
how strings and lists are related.
They're sort of related
in that they both have
zero based things and we used the
square bracket operator
to do various things.
But there's a lot of situations
where we're looking at our data
and we're combing the
use of lists and strings.
So, let me show you the first thing.
Probably the coolest thing,
we're going to use it a
lot, the rest of the class
and that is the split function.
So, let's take a string, we got abc here.
It's with three words.
But we're interested in the fact
that there is spaces in this word.
And was split does, it says,
you know I'm gonna look
through this thing, I'm gonna find this
and I'm gonna break this into pieces
and I'm going to return you a list
of the separate individual pieces.
So, look for blanks and break it in pieces
and give me back the pieces.
So, I'll print these out
and now you'll see that it's a list
with three items, with three words.
The spaces are gone but
it's given it to us.
So, it's like split this into words please
and give me the individual words.
Give me a list of individual words,
rather than a big long string
with spaces in the middle of it.
And that is a quick way to go from a line
and it's really common.
A lot of things are going,
like go get the second thing
or the third thing or whatever.
So, the split's really nice
'cause then you can just grab stuff.
So you say, oh, how many things did I get?
Well I got three, the LEN
function tells us that
and I can print the first word I got,
which is with the sub zero
and that'll be like with.
With will be the first word,
'cause that's the sub zero position.
So I read something, I split it,
I can say there's three things
and I can look at stuff,
the first word basically.
Without really knowing much.
Now, if you remember earlier,
we'll see this, we used find and slicing
to do a similar kind of thing,
but people tend to prefer the split.
Oops, go back.
You can also then
look through them, you
can split these things
into stuff as a word
and go through the with W
and then it's gonna go through,
W is gonna take the
successive with three words.
So, you can make a loop
by reading through data,
splitting it, then writing a for loop
and then it's effectively
going through the words
to that line of data.
And so that's a really powerful concept
that we'll use in a lot of programs
that we're going to write.
Just a couple of bits about this
and how it works.
Split with no parameters here,
it looks for spaces.
But it also treats a bunch
of spaces as a single space.
So it's pretty smart about that
and so even though this
has a lot of spaces
between lot and of,
you only see lot, of,
all the spaces are gone.
It does something special about spaces.
It's really white space.
So tabs, new lines, or other characters
would also qualify in split, basically.
Now, you don't always have
to split based on spaces
and a lot of data that
you're going to run into,
you're going to want to
split on something else.
So, here's some data that looks like
we're using colons to separate
the first, second, and third piece.
Now, if you just call split,
split's looking for space
and so split gives you back a list
of the things broken apart with spaces
but there's not a single
space in that line
and so we get a list, see it's a list,
but there's only one item
and the semi colons are sitting there.
Split doesn't go like,
whoa this looks like
it should be semi colons.
Split's job is to use spaces
and split the string based on spaces.
But, given that this is
something we like to do,
you can split what
character you'd actually
like to split on.
Now, it's not quite as clever
when splitting something
other than spaces.
It doesn't understand that
if there's a bunch of
semi colons in a row,
it still thinks of those
as points to split.
But in this particular case
when there's no spaces,
it's going to split that.
So it says split this
based on the semi colon
instead of being based on the space.
And so, if you take a look
at what comes out of this,
we split on semi colon,
now we have a three item list
and we get first, second, and third.
And a lot of your data comes
out of some logging system
or some router, status updates,
who knows what you're looking at.
But the delimiters off in
something other than space
and you can do that with split.
So, this is a useful
thing when parsing things
like our email address.
We want it to get things
like the email address,
this second piece off of the line
and so we can use split
to take advantage of this.
So, here's a little loop
that's just going to print out,
not the email addresses but instead
the day of the week.
We'll print the day of the
week out for all these things.
How do we do that?
Well, we can observe, really quickly,
that if we split based on spaces,
it's the zero, one, two,
it's the two positions.
So we can quickly write a bit of code
that opens the file,
then loops through the lines.
We do this all the time now.
Our strip takes off the
end of the new lines.
We can check to see if it
starts with from space.
From space is our key.
So, we're ignoring all of the lines
that don't start with from space,
but then we find a line
that starts with from space
and we split and we just
print out the second word.
And so we get the second word of the lines
that start with from
and that's how this thing works.
Now, sometimes we're going
to dig into it deeper
and we will take something, split it,
and then split another piece of it again,
with a different delimiter.
So let's just say the
thing we want to achieve
is getting the part after the
@ sign for email addresses.
We did this with again, find
and pose and stuff like that,
but you can use split to do this as well.
So the first thing we're going to do,
we're going to take this line,
we're going to split it based on spaces.
Chop, chop, chop, chop
and the fact that there's
an extra space there.
Doesn't matter, split happily
just like zooms through that
and then words sub one,
zero, one, two,
words sub one is this email address,
so we'll put that in a
variable called email
and so email will be a
string that's just this.
So in two lines,
we've pulled out the second
address into a variable.
Then what we're going to do,
is we're going to resplit that.
We're going to take this string we got
and split it based on @ sign,
'cause we know it's an email address.
So we get a new set of pieces,
the first part is the persons name
and the second part is the host name
their email is hosted on.
And what we can do then
is we just happen to know that
this is the zero item
and this is the one item.
So we can get at that.
So the interesting thing of going here,
if you think back to
how we did this before
with find and pose and all that stuff,
it's really a lot cleaner.
For me, I can look at this,
after you understand it
and it's easy for me to
understand that it's correct,
where as that pose stuff,
you gotta add one
and start the second find after,
just remember that and
this is a lot cleaner way.
This is a more typical way of pulling
this kind of information out of a line.
So, in this chapter we talked about lists,
we talked about the concept of collections
at their first data structures,
not just doing algorithms.
We kind of know algorithms now.
But now we're going to do data structures.
This chapter and the next two chapters
are foundational data structures
and then we'll, like everything,
we'll make more complex data structures
by composing those data
structures together.
We've looked at how strings
and lists connect together
and how split works
and these are all really powerful tools,
that we're going to use going forward.
(piano jazz music)