- Okay so now that we've
gotten through the definitions,
let's work into some sample code.
But hey, look at this, we've got ourselves
our cookie cutter and some cookies.
So remember that a class is a template,
it's not the actual thing.
An object is an instance of a class.
So you have to take the class
and do something to make the object.
And actually you can see
here some other classes,
there's clearly sort of a snowflake class
and a gingerbread man class.
That's an object, object, object.
Somewhere out here there
is a snowflake class
and a gingerbread class,
but we got a snowman object
and a snowman object and a snowman class.
So class is the template,
object is the instance.
So here's a better python code.
So let's take a look at what we got here.
Classes is in the reserved
word, kind of like def.
We have the name the class,
that is a name that we choose.
That's the name by which we'll refer
to this class for the
rest of this program.
And it has a colon at the end of it,
in which it starts an indented block.
Which ends when we de-indent.
Inside the class, there
are generally two things.
There is some data and
this just looks like
an assignment statement in the class.
X equals zero.
And then there is a def.
This looks just like a function,
in that it starts with a
def, has a colon, indents.
So that function finishes right there.
The difference is that this is a method,
because it lives inside of a class.
And so there is no function called party.
There's a function called party
within party animal class.
And we'll talk in a second
about this self thing.
It is the way that inside this code
we refer back to that variable.
So this is not actually
executing any code.
It's sort of remembering the template,
defining the class party animal.
This is what we call constructing.
Using the party animal template or class,
we are making a party animal.
And then once we make that, we
stick it in the variable an.
And then we're going to
call this party method
three times, one, two, three.
Now this self thing, and
we'll take a look at the self.
The self ends up being an alias of an.
And so you can look at this syntax,
it's just kind of an
equivalent of this syntax.
It's calling the party method
within the party animal class,
and passing the instance
in as the first parameter.
And so self ends up being an alias of an
each time these are called.
Now if we make a different variable
and a second object,
which we will eventually,
you will see that that works
a little bit differently.
And so, this syntax is a
short version of that syntax.
So if we watch how this
executes, it's oops.
It starts up here.
It just defines it.
And then we construct it.
And that's what basically constructing it,
we know how to construct it
because we look at the class,
and we make a variable x,
we make some code party.
And then we construct that, that's what
the party animal does.
And then we assign that into an.
And so, an is now pointing at that.
Then when we call the party method,
that basically takes
this an and passes it in
as the first parameter,
which is used as self.
And so, self.x, which is what we're doing
in this line right here.
Self.x is a variable.
X starts out as zero.
X starts out as zero because
when it was constructed
it was set to zero.
So we're in here, an is an alias of self
and now it looks up self.x, which is zero,
adds one to it so this becomes one.
And then we print so far, so far one.
And then the code returns and it goes down
and does it again.
And x becomes two.
Prints out so far two, comes back down
and does the last time, calls it again.
Self.x is two, add one to
it and stick it back in.
So this becomes three
and we print out three.
And then the program finishes.
And so you can think
of this as constructing
the object and then associating
it with this an variable.
Now we've created this object,
we can play around with things
we've playing around before
with dir and type.
We use dir and type to inspect variables
and types and objects.
So we've been using objects all along.
This code here says, hey
make me an empty list.
Well it turns out that what we're saying
is that there's already a list class
inside a python and we're constructing
an empty list and when we get back
this empty list, we're
assigning that into x.
So x in a sense, contains
or points to an empty list.
So then we say, hey what is in x?
What kind of thing is x?
Well it's a list.
This is a thing, it's a list type.
Lists have list of things in them.
And use a pen and all the things
we've been doing before,
they're just objects.
And then the dir, if you remember the dir,
the dir is the capabilities.
And there's all these
internal capabilities
that do things like implement
the bracket operator et cetera.
There's double underscore ones.
We can ignore them.
Although you can even look them up
and figure out what they
mean, if you feel like it.
But the methods that we tend
to call are in this class.
And so things like x.sort.
I've always told you,
that is the sort method
within the x thing.
And the dot operator is the operator
that we use to look something
up within an object.
So you've been using
this syntax all along.
X.sort, dictionary.items, all of those
are methods within the
corresponding class.
If we take a look at this line of code
that we've been doing for a
very long time, which says,
oh stick hello there into y.
If I reword that, is more
OO or object orientated,
what this single quote does,
says make me a string object,
and put some text in it and then when
that is done being
constructed, stick that into y.
And so y now points to a string object
that's been pre initialized
to the string, hello there.
Now that's a long way of saying
hello there ends up in y.
But in OO terms, we can talk about that.
If we do a dir of that,
we see a whole bunch
of internal methods, which
have double underscores
and then we see all kinds of
methods that we've been using.
We've been using methods like upper.
We've been using methods like find.
We've been using methods
like rstrip, right?
We've been using these methods.
So we gonna like y.rstrip().
Again that's a method, that's an object,
not a class, it's an object.
And that is the object look up operator.
Now if we do the same thing
to code that we've built
or a class that we've built.
So now we have a party animal class.
Remember this up to
here is just definition.
Now we construct it and we store it in an.
So an is a variable that contains
an object of type party animal.
We asked it what type it
is and it prints out here.
It says, this is a class.
And it's main_partyanimal
in this whole thing here
is the _main, it's scoped _main.
But you can see that you
have made a new type.
You built a type by
using this class keyword.
And then we use the dir,
remember dir looks for capabilities.
And again, you'll see a whole
bunch of underscore things.
They have meaning, you can look them up.
But eventually you'll see the two things
that you've put in it.
One is the method party and the other
is the attribute or field x.
And again, these are the things
that you can say an.x or an.party.
Because this dot is the object operator,
the object lookup
operator that says look up
in the object an the thing x.
Or look up in the object
an the thing party.
Okay?
So up next we'll talk a little bit about
how objects are created and destroyed.
We also call that, object life cycle.