- Hello, and welcome to chapter six.
In this chapter, we're
gonna talk about strings,
and chapter seven is the payoff chapter,
so we, you know, up to this point
we're still learning, sort of,
basic building blocks and actually,
we're gonna write a real
program in chapter seven.
So, just learn this, and the
payoff's in chapter seven.
So we actually have been using strings
from the very first lecture,
'cause if you print "Hello,
world," well, that's a string.
And so, we've been doing things
this, this little, this
slide here is all review.
We use plus to concatenate strings,
we use print to print them out,
print's just a function
it takes as a parameter,
something strings, integers, et cetera.
We can put digits in strings,
but we can't add to them.
By now you've figured this out.
But you can use things like
ints to convert the strings
to integers and then print things out.
So, you know, we've been
doing this for a while,
and we've been talking
about strings all along.
Now today, what we're gonna do is going to
just get into strings in more detail,
we've reading, we input data
with the input function,
input returns us a string...
and, if we want to input a number
we have to run some kind of conversion,
like we have to do an int
before we take this data
that we read from input, you know,
and so there's things that we've gotta do,
and we've been doing all these
things in programs so far.
But if we look in a little
more detail inside strings,
we can index within
strings each character.
So each character has a separate
position and a separate index.
And they basically, the
letters, are, have positions.
And the positions start at zero,
and the best way to, I explain
this, to remember this,
is the elevators as we
used in one of our examples
a long time ago, elevators
in Europe start at zero,
and so strings start at zero as well.
Turns out, in the old days,
there's some efficiency
with the notion of lists
of things starting at zero.
These days, the efficiency
isn't the issue,
but there's a certain
elegance starting at zero,
even though intellectually,
you might think that one
would be the, the first
character in the string
might make most sense to be sub one,
but it's not, it's sub zero.
But just remember that, and
so we have this operator
called the index operator,
and it's square brackets.
So, you know, fruit is a variable
that contains the string
banana, and then fruit sub one
is the character that's in position one.
Now that actually is the second character,
I'll keep reminding you until
I get tired of reminding you.
So, that assigns A, the letter A,
into I mean, the letter A
into the variable letter.
Of course, that's a badly choice,
it's either a well chosen variable name
or a badly chosen variable name.
And the thing that goes
inside this can either be
a constant or it can be an expression,
so this is x equals three
and then fruits of x minus 1,
well that means two,
which is position two,
which is an N, and so that gives us an N.
So the index is an operator,
and you can add this
bracket syntax to the
end of a string variable.
You can't index beyond
the length of the string,
so if I say zots of five,
well there are only three characters,
which means zero, one, two,
but so five doesn't work.
And of course, we get a
happy little traceback.
Hmm.
So you have to be careful
when you're starting
to pull stuff out of strings.
Although some of the things allow it,
some of them don't and then
you'll kinda get used to that.
We can ask how long a string is.
And so we use the len function.
We pass the string variable,
and we pass it into len as parameter,
and len gives us back
the length of the string.
Not the position, so it's
zero through len minus one.
So it's zero through length minus one.
So you, length is just
another function that,
we've been doing
functions now for a while,
you pass in a parameter,
and then len does some work,
and out comes six, and
that goes back into x,
'cause the function has a residual value.
It just happens to be a built-in function.
And so, you know, somewhere
deep inside Python,
there is code that takes this,
and somebody wrote a
loop or look something up
and then returned a
return value and sent back
a six to go into our x variable.
And so a function is
there, and like I said,
we've been using this for a while.
Another thing we tend to do
is to look through strings
and look at strings and
dig data out of strings.
Python is excellent for doing, sort of,
these kinds of look-ups.
And so, we can write a simple loop.
We can write a for loop that
creates some kind of a iteration variable,
like index, and given that
we know that these positions
are zero through five, we
can set this to be zero,
and then write a while loop:
while the iteration variable
is less than the length
of fruit, and remember,
this is six, so it's gonna
be zero through five.
Zero through five are the
values we wanna generate,
and then we can look up one at a time,
pull out fruits of
index, so fruits of zero,
fruits of one, two, three, four, five,
and then print out the
position and the letter.
Index, and then add one
to index and it runs,
this'll run six times, zero through five,
and out we go to produce
this output right here.
And so that's one way of
looping through strings.
That is a basic indeterminate loop,
but we construct carefully
an iteration value.
Construct an iteration value
and work our way through that loop data.
The other way is to use a
determinant loop, a for loop.
And generally, when we're able to use
a while loop or a for
loop, all else being equal,
we generally prefer a for loop.
And so here we have the
for key word and fruit,
and it's an in, and so
for letter in fruit,
well that just says letter
is our iteration variable
and it's gonna take on
the successive values
of each of the characters,
so this loop is gonna run six times,
and letters gonna be B-A-N-A-N-A, banana.
I'm always terrified
when I make these slides
that I'm gonna misspell banana,
because somehow I always think
that there are two N's somewhere,
I don't know, it's not one of
my favorite words to spell.
I actually didn't choose
banana as the constant,
the author who I borrowed
the textbook from,
Allen Downey and Jeff Elkner,
they used banana and so
I'm still using banana.
So some of the jokes in the book
aren't my book, aren't my jokes,
they are the jokes of Jeff and Allen.
So here are just two equivalent, you know,
so you can have the while loop,
they sort of both do the same thing,
they both just print the
letters out one time through,
each of these loops runs five times,
but you can see how the determinant loop,
the for loop, is a prettier loop.
Unless you truly somehow
need to know this number
as you're going through the loop.
But if all you're doing is going through,
and you wanna touch, in order,
each of the characters of the string,
you then simply write a for
loop, 'cause it's more elegant.
The less code you write,
the less code you write,
the less chance there is
for you to make a mistake.
And so, the fact that
these are equivalent,
this is three lines,
well, two lines of a loop
and this is four lines of a loop,
that's twice as many places
as you could make a mistake.
'Cause you might, you know,
misspell index or something.
I mean, why even make
an iteration variable
if you don't need to make
an iteration variable.
And so, we can do things that hearken back
to our iterations and loops chapter,
where anything that you
can do in those things,
like look for the largest letter,
look for the smallest letter,
search to see if a letter exists,
or say, count the number
of A's in the word banana.
And so, that's what this is doing.
And so, we, so we have a counter,
so again we do something
at the top of the loop,
we're gonna do something
in the middle loop,
and then we're gonna print
it out at the bottom.
So we start our counter at zero,
we're gonna loop through
B-A, all the letters,
and then if the letter is A,
then count equals count plus one.
And this is kinda a pattern
in a loop where we're
noticing something and instead of like,
we did it earlier, where
we said found equals true,
well, we're gonna count them this time.
So if we have one, we'll get one,
if we have zero, we get zero,
and how many ever there are,
but there should be three,
because it's gonna run
three times and there's
three A's in banana.
And so, this is, you know, a
conditional within a count.
We've seen counts, we've
seen conditionals in loop,
in prior chapters.
And so, again, I love
the in keyword in Python.
It again reminds me of a
set notation in algebra.
If you're a math whiz, if you're
not, don't worry about it,
or maybe you will be a
math whiz and you'll say,
"Woah, this set notation reminds me a lot
"of the, the in, keyword in Python."
So, (coughs) again, it's for
iteration variable letter,
again, don't get stuck with letter,
I just happen to be
using it here, in banana.
And that's for each character
in the string banana,
run this loop once changing
the variable letter
to be the particular character
that we're pointing at.
And so, it's taking care,
for is taking care of a lot for us, right?
And so this is sort of
this really smart for loop.
The for loop is, you know,
both deciding how many times
to run the loop, in this case six,
and it's advancing the letter.
So, advance, print, you know,
decide whether you're done,
advance, print, decide
whether you're done,
I am now done, because I (beeps
and makes wooshing sound),
you know we're done with
that particular string.
And so, you can think
of the for as, you know,
magically doing all of this for you.
Of both deciding how long to run the loop,
when you're done or not, and moving down
through all the successive
letters in the loop.
So, up next, we'll do, talk a little bit
about additional things
that we can do with strings.
(light jazz)