- So, now we're going to take a look at
how we deal with more than
one table, multiple tables,
because the real power of SQL
and the power of database performance
has to do with when you start
connecting tables together.
If you go back to that
original mathematics,
it models data at the intersections
between the row and the columns,
and these intersections
are the magical bits.
Breaking an application
to use multiple tables
is an art form, it takes a while.
There are some simple basic
things that you can learn,
and we'll teach you here.
It's not to hard to learn the basics,
but then it's much more complex
to be super skilled at it.
In general, advanced
databases, in my mind,
it's hard to teach advanced databases
because they're always
so contextually grounded.
Something like a Twitter or Google,
the databases are so specialized.
Everyone can do
small-to-medium sized databases
using the basic techniques,
but at some point,
once you escape medium sized databases,
you end up in these sort-of narrow things,
and optimize each
database very separately.
I just tell people, learn the
basics really, really well,
write programs, and then go do real work.
But, database design is
the act of figuring out
the data that your application
is going to want to store,
and spreading that across multiple tables.
But, we don't just do it randomly,
we do it very much cleverly.
If you look at a data model,
this is what it looks like.
What we're showing here
in this data model,
is we are showing five tables,
and this is a calendar system.
We're seeing the columns that
are in each of the tables,
and then we're seeing the
relationships between the tables.
And, even in these relationships,
there's a little bit of code,
and when you have an arrow
that looks like that,
there's many of those to one,
and this is a many-to-one relationship.
Many-to-one relationship.
We'll talk all about that stuff, but--
If you go into an organization,
and you have a really large
and complex data application,
they might have something
printed out on the wall
that looks about like this,
which shows the database tables
and the connections, etc.
And, they might say,
"Oh, you're job is to go
down into this little corner
"and add one column field
there, and then do this,
"and then connect it with
this thing over there,
"and then make a screen
that shows all these things
"that pulls from this table,
this table, and that table,"
and that's your job if you're a programmer
on a large software development project.
These database models
become the core backbone
of the knowledge that applications
are managing and using.
So, the idea is that you
take your application,
we're gonna start really simple.
We're going to take your application,
and you have to draw a
picture, and the basic rule--
And, literally, you could
spend course upon course
learning about database normalization,
but I'm going to distill
it into one basic rule,
and that is, never put the
same string data in twice.
So, my name, Charles Severance,
if I build a database well,
you should go into that
database, and you'd say,
"Okay, the words Charles Severance,
"which is the name of a
person, me, in that database,
"only shows up once."
And, what we do instead is
we connect things together
and model my name as
connection to the record
that has my actual name in it,
rather than putting my name
all these other places.
So, the idea is to pull
duplicate data out,
and make only one copy of it.
So, there is the users, and
in there is the user's name,
and the username shows up only here,
and everything else points
to the particular user entry.
So, that's the idea.
Here's our first application.
We are working as a start-up,
we just quit all of our jobs,
and we are going to build a
music management application.
I mean, what a great idea.
Don't you think that
will be quite successful?
And, so we have mocked up,
and we have figured out that this
is what our music management application--
We wanna track people's
tracks, know something about
what artists and albums
and genre they are,
we're going to have ratings,
and how many times we've played
them, and how long they are.
That's the data that our
application needs to represent.
And, we've done testing
on this, and wire-frames,
and everyone loves this,
a great user interface.
And, so this is how it's gotta look.
But, we're going to have
billions and billions of tracks
in these things, and so
we want to come up with
an efficient database to handle this.
We're going to take a look at this,
and look at each of the columns
and we're going to ask ourselves,
"Is this column part of one
of our existing objects,
"our existing tables, or is this object--
"have to create a new table."
And then, once we've defined
those different objects,
we connect the tables together
and model the connections.
Now, a little trick to make it
a little easier on ourselves,
is we can look in these columns
and look in the columns that have
duplicate information vertically
that's string information.
So, rating is just a number like 0-5,
so we don't worry too much
about integers and numbers,
and that kind of stuff,
but we do look for strings.
And the problem here, is these
strings occur many times.
And so, these are the problems,
and so we have to put these things
where there is replication of string data
in the vertical dimension.
We have to put those in different tables.
We'll start out.
Now, the first question that
you have to ask yourself
when you're going to draw this picture
of how this data is in multiple tables
and connected together,
is what is the first one that
you're going to write down.
And, this is an interesting debate,
and often people are sitting
in a conference room,
and people who have experience
kinda know what to do.
Usually, if it's a multi-user system,
like a learning management system,
the users might be central concept.
Perhaps the courses might
be the central concept.
This is a single-user
system, and so you can think,
"Well, what is really
this application about."
It's not about people, it's one person.
But it is about tracks.
And so, we can say,
"Okay, we'll take the track is probably
"the most foundational
notion of this application."
And then, we can take and say,
"Okay, now that we've decided
"that tracks are the foundational notion,
"which of these columns are simply
"an attribute of the track."
The cheapie, the cheating
way, the easy way
in this particular one
is like these numbers.
All these numbers, like this
number and these numbers,
not that one (laughs) --
they just go along with track,
and so we'll put that in.
We've got the track title,
rating, length, and count,
and we put that in.
And then, the question is, we've got--
The remaining things are,
we've got the artist,
we've got the album,
and we've got the genre,
and so, we can say,
"Okay, we've got some
vertical duplication,"
so we're going to say,
"Okay, this track probably
belongs to an album,
"so let's pull out the
album into its own table."
Pull the album out into its own table.
And, so, that pulls that
out, and then you say,
"Okay, what would be the next thing
"that we're going to pull out."
So, we've pulled out the track,
we've got this taken care of,
this taken care of, that taken--
Now, we've got the album.
Well, albums belong to artists,
so let's take out the artist.
And then, we'll pick
where the genre belongs,
and we'll just say that the
genre belongs to the track,
because there might be albums
with more than one different genre.
So, each album is not
necessarily a rock album,
it could have a rock track,
and a country track, etc.
Now, what we've got is,
we've got four tables, right?
We've got a track table,
we've got an album table,
an artist table, and a genre table,
and if we double-check, all of the columns
that had vertical duplication in them
now have their own little table.
So, we can eliminate,
the next thing we'll do
is to show how we're going to eliminate
this vertical data replication
by showing how you represent
these relationships
that we just created
inside of the database.