- Hello and welcome to Python Objects
I'm Charles Severance
and we're well on our
way to getting through
all this material in the Python.
So this lecture is in a weird place
I even debated where
to put it in the book.
I don't really wanna
teach you how to write
a lot of object running programming
but we're gonna start using objects
and I wanna be able to
use the terminology.
So as much as anything,
this lecture is about terminology
and understanding the words.
Things like methods and method signatures,
and variables and inheritance.
And so think of this as
a terminology lecture,
rather than a learn how to program
or learn how to use this.
It's not something you're
gonna figure out right away,
and there'll come a time
when you as a programmer
really want to start
object runner programming,
it's really a powerful
and wonderful technique.
But I think it's too early
as a beginning programmer
to really say oh let's
write a bunch of objects.
So just relax and enjoy
and learn this material
and think of it as sort
of a theoretical thing
rather than a how to program thing.
And so part of this is we're gonna start
reading data structures.
And data on how to use all
these libraries etcetera.
And we're gonna see the word objects right
And then we're gonna start hearing them.
And I want you to be
able to read the Python
documentation so that you
understand what's going on
and the word objects
should make sense to you.
Even though you're not gonna write
a lot of object running programming.
And so page upon page upon page
database stuff which we're
gonna talk about soon.
Is a ...
Uses objects all over the place.
And the beautiful soup uses objects.
We kinda been using them
and I've been waving my hands.
And I use the word method
without defining it.
But now it's really time to
define it and go to it.
So.
I want to review
from the very beginning
what we think of as a program.
So the classic program
my favorite little minimum program
is our little elevator floor converter.
Which converts from
European elevator floors
to United States elevator floors.
And the key to this is that
it's input processing and output
and this is a good way to model
any program.
And in that process
we've got variables
and we've got logic we got algorithms.
We got loops that we write.
We got all kinds of things.
And we construct a series of steps
to achieve some goal.
In Object Oriented
and frankly you've been
using Object Oriented
all along.
The program has lots of objects.
And we're sort of putting
stuff into these objects
taking stuff out of one object
and putting it into another object.
And you've actually been
doing this all along.
As soon as you're looking
at dictionaries and lists.
You're doing objects.
And so it's
an object is quite a little thing.
It's sort of its own little space
inside of a program.
That contains code and data.
And so we're working together
all these objects are
now working together.
It's a bit of self
contained code and data.
And it is one way to take
a very complex problem.
And make it easier
by breaking it into separate things
that can be engineered
and developed separately.
And so you've been using string objects
or maybe you'd use
beautiful soup or something.
These are powerful capabilities.
And if you had to look at all of them.
It's just hey here's a thing
use this object
it will do these things for you
and there's lots of details inside of it.
Just don't look at it
don't worry about it.
And so there's boundaries that
things that you can use.
Things that you can look at.
And things that really you
don't bother looking at
you go read the documentation and use it.
And away it goes.
But then someone had to write that
and so they built an object.
So what we're going to
do is look a little bit
under the covers
of what it takes to build
some of these objects.
And so if we think of this program
that originally just
sort of did processing.
We can think of it as having
some kind of an input.
Right.
Coming into our program.
And we have a string object.
A dictionary object.
Maybe eventually some objects
like a database object.
Or an object that we eventually define.
And you can think of us
we're receiving data.
It comes in an object.
Which is a string object.
We start putting the
strings in dictionaries.
And do whatever we pull
out a list of them.
And so you can think of data
as moving between these objects.
And like I say
even strings in the first week
first lecture the first
week the first everything.
We were using objects
and we've been using them all along.
And so you can think of every string
and every dictionary
as a little program all by itself
that has a bit of code
and a bit of data.
And so a string has the data
which includes all the characters
that make up the string.
But then there is a method called
upper that does upper case.
Or R strip that strips off
the white space from the right.
And so it's like
they're almost little programs
that have inputs and outputs themselves
and we can make lots of them.
There's lots of cooperating objects
that make up an application.
And one of the nice things about
the object oriented pattern
is that
they form boundaries.
And within the boundary
if you're inside the object.
You can say look
I'm gonna build you a string object
or a database object.
Or a beautiful soup object.
And I'm gonna build this capability
and I'm gonna give it to you
in the form of an interface.
And I'm not really gonna
care how you use it.
And so we have this sort of
visibility wall where
I'm gonna make an object
and I'm gonna let you use it.
And the maker of the object
doesn't necessarily have to know
every single thing
about the use of that object.
But so just like
inside the object
they don't have to worry about
what you're doing with the object
outside of it.
When you're outside the object
you don't have to worry about
what's going on inside of it.
We as the user of the object.
We talk to its interface
and we get things from it
and give things to it
and use functionality within that object.
But we don't have to look inside of this.
We can just say
oh it's a nice little magical thing.
Read the documentation.
We read a web page
and it told us to do this this and this.
And away you go.
And so it is a
it is sort of this isolation boundary
that works both for the
programmer who's writing the object.
And the programmer who's using the object.
And so it's a
it's a very nice pattern.
So you'll see how
we're gonna build code
and we're gonna group it together.
And then we're gonna be using it
sort of as a big
blob of stuff.
So.
Some definitions in this space.
Words that I want you to understand.
When we're gonna create
one of these things.
One of these objects.
Instances.
That has some data in it
and some code in it.
We have to be able to define
the shape of this object.
What code will each object have in it.
And what data will each object have in it.
And that's called a class.
The key to a class.
And this little picture
that I've got up here in all these slides.
Is a key.
The class is a template.
It's not the thing itself.
So it's a cookie cutter.
It knows a lot about how cookies are made.
And if you have cookie dough
and you hit the thing
then you make as many cookies as you want.
And so this nice little cookie picture
is a great you know
mental model of how it works.
The class
the class oops.
The class is the template
and then the object
are all of the cookies
that are made from that template.
But the template defines
the shape and the nature of the class.
So the code that we write
of each of the objects.
The code we write
is the class code.
And then later we say
oh lets take that template
and make ourselves an object
or an instance.
Now as we're defining a class.
We have two basic things
that we put in the class.
And there's a couple of
different terminologies for this.
One is method which is code.
It's like a function that
lives inside of a class.
Not a function that lives
inside your program.
But one that lives inside of a class.
And so this is a scoping thing.
A method is really just a function.
But its lived
it lives inside the class.
And then fields or attributes
are data items that are in the class.
And so they're variables that
are defined in the class.
You can define variables outside the class
that you use in your program.
You've been doing that all along.
But if you're saying
I'm gonna build this capability
and its gonna have data inside of it
and code inside of it.
The code is the method or message.
And field or attribute.
And.
They're just ...
There are just two
two different sets of terminology.
Method is what I'll probably use.
If you look in some
object oriented patterns
like small talk or
apple.
They often don't call these messages.
So you can either like
access a method inside of a class
or an object.
Or you can send a message to the object.
The same is true for field and attribute.
There's just a chunk of data
that's in the object that
you may or may not have
the right to access.
So like I said
a class is a template
it defines the characteristics
of the objects that we're gonna
use to make it.
It is the cookie cutter.
So dog is sort of the exemplar.
Lassie is a particular dog.
And so dog has fur
and dog barks
and dogs do all these things.
And so we know something about dogs
but it doesn't mean we have a dog.
Right we ...
In the class is a more abstract concept
that when it's time to get a dog
we know certain things about dogs.
Instances or objects
are once we say
oh time to make a cookie
from the template.
Time to get a dog.
We know something about dogs.
That's the creation of an object.
And that we call them instances.
Instance of a class.
So the class is a ...
Doesn't exist.
But we say make me a new
object using this class as its template.
Oh and now make me another one.
And so we can have many many objects
from one class.
So just like
many cookies from one cookie cutter.
Method is a bit of code
that lives inside of an object.
It's like a function
but it's scoped to within the object.
Or within the class.
Okay so that kind of gets us started
on some of the terminology.
And we'll come back
and we'll take a look at
how we write code
that's object oriented.
(jazz music)