- So now that we know what a primary key,
logical key, and a foreign key are,
we're going to actually start putting
these together and creating tables
that have these kinds of values in them.
So, when we were done,
we drew this picture
that was sort of a logical model
of how our data would be spread across
four tables and how those
tables are connected.
Now we have to take this
and we have to map it
in a way that leads to the columns
and the needed columns in each
of our database tables.
So here's what we do.
We basically have to take,
and for each of these,
when we're gonna build a track table,
and we're gonna build a track table,
we add a primary key.
So we just added an id field
to every one of these things,
and that's so we have a place to store
the sequence number of
this particular row.
We have logical keys,
we've just marked those.
Those are strings, and
then we have things like
rating, length, and count, they just kinda
go in here, and now we have
to model a relationship.
In the table, the
relationship starts from,
we put one more column
in, and this is the one
I will name "album id" and that just is
an integer column that's going to record
the album id, so this might be 16,
and then 16 goes in here.
So there's one of these columns
that's a foreign key that points to this.
And that's why it's foreign,
this is a key that's
not in the track table.
This is a key in the album table
that we're pointing to, so
there's the foreign key.
That's what we have to do, and we just
do that over and over and over again
and we quickly convert that picture
that was a logical picture,
to having every table has a primary key,
and every time we have a starting point,
we have a foreign key, foreign key,
and then foreign key.
And then we mark these
things as logical key,
logical key, logical key,
and we'll see how we do that.
And so that's the picture.
Now we have a picture of exactly how
we're gonna lay these tables out,
and the fields that we
need in these tables.
So, we're going to do a
create table statement.
And I've got this create
table statement sitting there.
And so this one's going to
be a little bit different.
We're gonna say create table "artist"
and the id field is integer,
and we're gonna add all of this stuff.
This is adding to the column
to tell it additional stuff.
It's a primary key, which means we're
gonna use it to look up a lot.
It's automatically
incremented, which means
the database is actually gonna provide
this number for us as we insert records.
It's not allowed to be null,
it's not allowed to be empty,
and it's supposed to be unique.
And then the artist is
gonna have a name column,
a name column that's just text.
So let's do that.
We already have our users.
Now we're gonna do a
create table in this SQL,
and you can do that, that's
okay, that's totally fine.
And we have to get this
right, and we say away we go.
And so now if I take a
look at database structure,
I've got a users table, that users table
we were playing with before,
and this artist table.
Let me go ahead and
delete this users table
just to say goodbye.
So now we have the artist table,
and we take a look and it's got an id,
and it knows all about this stuff, 'kay?
So, that created the table.
We're going to keep doing this.
The next thing that
we're going to show here
is we're going to show
the foreign key, right,
so artist id is just an integer.
In some database languages,
like MySQL and Oracle,
you would put more stuff here to say
this is a foreign key, blah blah blah,
but in SQLite, we keep it simple
and just say that is an integer column,
that's a foreign key, the album table
has a primary key and a foreign key,
and then the title.
So we'll go back and we'll grab that text
out of my little page, this create table.
Go back to Execute SQL, and then run that.
And we'll continue, the
genre table has an id on it.
Just copy and paste
these, that whole thing,
you do that over and over and over again,
so we'll go in here and run that one.
And so the last one we're going to do
is the track table, and the only thing
that's kinda weird about the track table
is it's got two foreign keys, right.
It's got album id and genre id.
Once you draw the
picture, you just sort of
literally translate these things.
It's got two foreign
keys and a primary key
that's pretty much just like
all those other primary keys.
Integer counts and integer lengths and
integer all that stuff,
and now we've got it.
We take a look at our database structure,
we're gonna see that our
album, genre, and track
are all set up, and these are new columns
that we just made with those
create statements, kay?
So now let's insert some data.
This first insert statement is
kind of important to take a look at.
So insert into, by the way the keywords
can be upper or lower
case, table name, columns.
Now, this table has two
columns, it has id and name,
but we told the database that id
was auto-increment, so it's gonna actually
give us the number, it's
gonna assign the number
rather than make us assign.
We could make it be one two three,
but we say, "Hey, database, you're good
"at this, why don't you
make it one two three?"
And so there is going to be a record
that it adds Led Zeppelin,
so let's take a look at that.
We'll insert Led Zeppelin, oops,
over to SQL, insert Led
Zeppelin and run it.
So now if I look at database structure,
let's look at browse data, and look
at the artist database, you will see
that I put Led Zeppelin
in, but this id field
here was auto-incremented, and so
it was put there by the database.
Now when we do the next insert,
which is AC/DC,
and we take a look at the data,
we'll see that AC/DC is 2.
Now, if you're writing this in a program,
if you're gonna write this in a program,
you can get these numbers back
from the database in your program,
but I'm not writing this in a program
so I have to remember that 1 is Zeppelin
and 2 is AC/DC.
I'm gonna keep myself a
little cheat sheet here
to remember that, because everywhere else
in the program that we
wanna say Led Zeppelin,
I gotta say 1 now, because the artist id
of 1 means Led Zeppelin in those rows.
Now we're going to go back and we're
gonna take a look at the next one.
Now we're gonna put the genre in.
If you think about it, we're working
from the leaves out, the track will
be the last table that we'll update
because we'll have to define the keys
for things like rock and metal
and Led Zeppelin and
all those other things.
And again, even though the genre table
has two columns, id and name,
we're only gonna specify the name
and let the database assign the value.
So I'm gonna insert both of these
and use the semicolon trick.
Put a semicolon here
and a semicolon there,
and run that.
So if I take a look at my browse data
and I look at the genre, it's assigned
1 to rock and 2 to metal.
I'm gonna write that down.
1 rock, 2 metal.
I shoulda done something
like rock and country
'cause I can't even tell the difference
between rock and metal, but whatever.
My musical skill is not
what's at issue in this class.
So now, we're going to put an album in.
The album is the first thing
that has a foreign key,
so if you remember,
album points to artist,
and so that means it has a
foreign key of artist id.
We have to explicitly say this
'cause the system doesn't know
which artist Who Made Who is,
but we know that Who Made
Who is AC/DC and that's 2,
and so we know to put artist id in,
so we'll say insert into
album, title, artist id,
and so we have to know
what this 2 number is.
And of course, because we have our
handy little cheat sheet.
We can go over to execute and run that,
and I'll put a semicolon there and
a semicolon there and run it.
So now we have,
in the album field,
we now have this, and
so this was assigned,
and so Who Made Who-
Still have to write down that
Who Made Who is album 1,
and album 2 is Led Zeppelin IV.
That makes it even more complex
'cause the name of the album
is a Roman numeral four.
I'm sure I can figure that out.
Okay, so, the next thing that we're
going to do is we're gonna
insert the track record.
Now if you think about the track record,
the track has two foreign keys
and it's got a lot of stuff.
It's got the title, it's got the rating,
length, count, but then we've got
the two foreign keys, and so we
have to know these numbers, so this 2, 1,
this 2, 1, this 1, 2 is the genre.
We're specifying the genre and the album
that this track is from by those numbers.
Now, again, we have to
use this cheat sheet,
but if this was a program, the program
would know that 1 was Zeppelin,
and 1 was Who Made Who
and 2 was Led Zeppelin IV.
And so the programs, this kind of stuff
is easier for the program to understand
than for us to keep
track of and understand,
but just so we can get
through these few records,
and that's why I rely so
heavily on my cheat sheet.
So here we are, with all these numbers,
the foreign keys are the tricky part here,
everything else is really
quite straightforward.
So now I'm gonna insert four
records into my track table.
And then run that.
Okay, so I go to browse data
and I look at my track table.
This column here, this id, that's
the primary key to the track table,
then here are the two foreign keys.
Now the interesting thing is now
there is replication in these columns,
but the numbers are
what's being replicated,
and that's okay.
We (laughs) went a long time just
not to put Led Zeppelin IV in twice.
We could have made this a string,
but by making this an integer,
it saves tons of storage
and makes it super fast.
That turns out to be one of the key things
that makes databases super fast
is using these integers.
So we take a look at all this stuff.
We see that in a sense, by using
these little numbers, we are pointing
to rows in other tables.
The foreign keys are always pointing,
they always point to their id.
So these foreign keys are out here,
this is the primary key up here,
and they always point
to a row in the table.