- So, welcome back.
Let's talk a little bit more
about some more complex
conditional statements
that build on this concept
of if and if then else.
The first thing we're gonna look at
is the multi-way branch.
And so, the idea is it's
kind of like the if then else
where you're gonna pick one of two,
but now we can pick one
of three, or one of four
or one of five.
And it introduces a new
concept called the elif.
The elif is another
reserve word inside Python.
And the way it works is;
it's probably best to look at this here
where it checks the first one
and if it's a true then it runs that
and then it's done.
It doesn't check them all.
It's not like it sees that there are
two logical conditions.
It actually checks them the first one.
And how you order these matters
as we'll see in a bit.
And so if the first one is true, it runs.
If the...
If the first one is false,
and the second one is true,
it runs this one and it's done.
And if the
neither of them are true it falls through
and there's an else
clause that is otherwise
and it runs that.
So basically, it's either gonna run one
and then skip the other two.
Or it is going to
skip one, skip two
and then run this one.
But it only runs, in this case one of them
but the important thing
is it checks these questions in order.
And it doesn't check the second question
until it finds it, the first;
it doesn't check the second question
until it knows the
first question is false.
So if the first question is true
you're done.
You're done and you're done with this.
You're done with the
whole block at that point.
So only one of these three
is going to execute in that block.
So, here's some examples of this.
If we, for example, have x equals zero;
it's gonna come down here.
X is less than two.
That's true.
So it runs this code,
and then it skips; skips; skips
down to that.
And so it's like this;
runs that code, and then skips to the end.
Okay?
On the other hand,
if it's five
then this is false
and it skips that,
and it checks this.
This is true.
It runs this code, and then it's done;
skips to the end.
Goes like false;
true;
run;
end.
And then if x is 20, for example;
it runs;
it runs, false;
false;
run else clause and you're done.
So skip;
skip;
else.
Run that code and you're done.
So in this case, we ran that,
and we didn't run that;
and we didn't run that.
Again, one of them is gonna run.
They're checked in order.
These questions are checked
in order; not out of order.
It doesn't look ahead.
It just checks in the
order that you wrote it.
You're the one that wrote that order.
And so, there's a couple of
variations on this multi-way.
You can have no else.
You can have no else, as in this case.
And this just means that it
might not run any of them.
In this case x is five,
so it's not less than two,
but then it runs this one.
But if x was 50, for example.
If x was 50;
then this would be false
and it would skip,
and this would still be false
and it would skip.
And neither of these two would run.
So if you don't have an else
you're not guaranteed that
one of them is gonna run
because else is like the catch-all;
if the other ones are all false
then the else is the one that runs.
Similarly,
you can have many elifs.
But this is where it's really important
for you to make sure you know
what order they're being taken in.
So I've got;
if this is true, it runs.
It goes all the way to the bottom.
If this was...
If it's false, false, false, true;
it runs this one and it's done.
If on the other hand it looks at it as
false;
oops, go back.
If it runs false, false, false, false;
they're all false, then it runs the else.
Right?
This one has an else.
This one didn't have an else.
They don't have to have them.
The key is you can have more
than one of these elifs.
Okay?
So I got a couple little things.
I'll let you pause right now,
and look at;
the question is;
are there, looking at the three lines
or four lines of code;
x equals something.
Are there lines of code
that will never execute
regardless of the value for x?
And I'll let you pause and think about it.
And then I'll explain it to you.
Okay.
Hopefully you paused and thought about it
as long as you like.
But so, let me now explain it to you.
So, we come in here
and if x is less than or equal to two
it's gonna run this first thing.
And if x is greater than or equal to two
it's gonna run this.
And if neither of those are true
then it's gonna run this.
Well, the weird thing is
all numbers are either less than two
or greater than or equal to two.
I carefully constructed this
to the point where it would
never run this line of code.
It is either gonna run
this one, or run that one
but it's not ever gonna run this one.
So that one's like
a weird dysfunctional
one that I constructed.
This other one is a little different.
If x is less than two; we do this.
If x is less than 20; we do that.
If x is less than 10; we do that.
And if none of those are true; we do that.
Well, the problem here
is between these two lines.
The problem is if
something's less than 10,
like six, for example;
it's also less than 20.
So, even though there might be values
for which this is true;
those also are gonna have this true.
So, for something like six;
it's gonna run here.
And it's not even gonna look at this.
That's the point.
It doesn't even look at this.
And so that's;
I could've made this more sensible
if I would've moved this
little block of code
up to there.
And so this is where the order
in which you choose your questions;
the way you put these
elifs together; matters.
Because, it doesn't look at all of them.
It only looks as long as it can;
as long as it sees falses,
then it keeps on going to the next one.
But as soon as it doesn't see a false,
it doesn't continue.
So the last conditional
structure we'll talk about
is the try and except structure.
If you know any other languages
like C plus plus, or Java,
or Javascript;
you're like; whoa, that's
an advanced concept.
But it turns out in Python,
because of Python's propensity
to throw tracebacks
in situations
where you would like to recover;
it turns out you have
to use it a little more
and a little earlier in
your programming skill.
So the problem is
what if there is a line of code
and you absolutely know
it's gonna make a traceback.
It's gonna blow up.
(mimics explosion)
But, you don't want to blow up.
I don't wanna have code blow up.
If you're using my autograder
and you see a traceback in my autograder;
that's like I consider that a failure.
I can put an error like;
hey, you entered blank data;
or you didn't enter a number.
But a traceback?
That just seems like I'm
too lazy as a programmer.
So, we as programmers are
supposed to anticipate
parts of our code that are
gonna blow, potentially
based on, perhaps, the user's input;
and then do something about it.
And that's what the
try and except are for.
If you take this little
dangerous piece of code
that might break and might blow up,
and you surround it with a try
and says this might blow up;
and if it fails, run this code down here.
Okay?
So that's the try,
and if you get an exception;
the except is like if
you get an exception.
And the problem is
is if you are running code;
here's a little bit of code.
We put hello Bob in
and we convert it to an integer.
And we know from past experience
that this blows up.
Right?
You can't take hello Bob and
convert it to an integer.
It's just gonna blow up.
The problem is,
and here we are,
it says oh you blew up on line two.
That's great.
And I'm not very happy with
hello Bob; and whatever.
But the important thing is
your program stops.
These other lines...
These other lines, they don't exist.
Right?
It doesn't go any further.
Remember, the traceback is I'm;
Python is really confused.
And I don't know what to do next.
So Python is just gonna
be conservative and stop.
So Python stops, and your program stops.
No matter how much error
checking you put down here,
it doesn't matter 'cause it's gone.
It's all gone.
And, like I said; we take this personally.
Because the code that
you write is like the;
you being put into the computer
giving it instructions.
And if the code blows up,
well that wipes you out.
You're not in the game anymore.
You're not able to do anything.
So, we want to be able to;
especially in these situations
where we can anticipate
that an error that might
happen in the normal course
of the program's execution
might be something that
you want to compensate for.
And that's what the try and except does.
So here's a bit of code
for the try and except.
And we just have two little
bits of straight-line code.
And so we put a string
in here that's hello Bob.
And then we're gonna
convert it to an integer.
This is the dangerous code.
This code in this case with hello Bob
is gonna do a traceback.
And so, we say try
and then we indent the dangerous code.
And then we add this little except bit.
If it works, the except is ignored.
If this blows up, it runs the except.
So in this code, it's gonna come in.
It's gonna try this.
This is gonna blow up.
But instead of giving a traceback;
it's gonna say I've got
an available except.
I'm gonna run this except code
and then I'm gonna continue on.
And so that prints out first negative one.
'Cause we set this variable
istr to negative one,
like a little flag telling
us that something went wrong.
And then we keep on going.
And now we have put in one; two; three.
The digits one; two; three.
And now it's gonna work.
But we still have it in a try block.
And then this one works.
It does not blow up
and then it ignores the except block.
So the except block is only triggered
when something goes wrong in the code.
It is ignored if something
doesn't go wrong.
So it's like you bought
an insurance policy
on this line of code,
and when things go wrong
you're except block springs into action
and does whatever it is
that you want it to do
in the case of an error.
Okay?
So that's a pretty useful thing
You gotta be a little bit
careful that you don't overuse it
because if you put more than
one line inside the try part
and one of the lines blows up
it doesn't come back to the try block.
And so in this one here,
we have a simple silly one
where we set the string.
We're worried about some stuff.
Well, the print statement
is never gonna blow up.
So it's a bad idea to put
it in try except anyways.
Then we do this conversion.
And that's the dangerous part.
And in this one it's gonna blow up.
(mimics explosion)
And so then it's gonna
go to the except block,
and then run the except block
and then continue.
What it does not do
is somehow go back and finish this.
So these lines are gone.
So if you look at it
like this; this works.
The try starts.
Hello.
This blows up.
It goes to the except.
It runs the except and
then it continues on.
Never runs that code.
So it's not like you took out an insurance
on the whole block.
Any of those lines can
blow up in the block.
But whichever line blows up,
that is the last line that's
executing in that block.
Okay?
So, you tend to want in
this particular example;
you would probably near
the print statement
would go out there,
and this print statement
would come down here.
And you would only put in your try block
a single line of code that
you think might blow up.
'Cause you know print
statements aren't gonna blow up.
So this is an example that more common
real world example
where the user is going to type some data.
And that's users that get us in trouble.
So our program starts by
asking the user enter a number.
And we know that this could be dangerous.
So we're gonna put the
conversion from string to integer
in a try block.
And we're gonna set negative one
if that's a failure.
And then if it's greater than
zero; we'll say nice work.
And if it's less than zero; not a number.
So, first time we run this program
out comes enter a number.
We type in 42, which is a string.
That 42 goes back into rawstr.
Runs in here.
This runs.
It's fine.
That becomes a 42 number.
So we skip the except block.
And ival is greater than zero.
We print out nice work
and we skip the else.
Okay?
So, it says nice work.
On the other hand,
if we run it again,
this time,
the input says enter a number.
And we're silly, we
enter the word forty-two
but in words.
Forty.
F-O-U-R-T-Y.
So that's a string, and
that goes into rawstr.
And then the execution continues.
We run in here.
And now this is gonna blow up.
(mimics explosion)
That's gonna blow up.
Normally, we would see
a traceback right there.
There would be a traceback.
But we're not going to,
because we put this calculation
into a try and except block.
It's going to immediately
run the except block.
Set ival to negative one,
continue on with the program.
See, you are not blown up at this point.
And if ival is greater that
zero; well it's negative one.
So, we're gonna hit the else clause
and print out not a number.
So we've done error detection.
The user sent something
that caused a line of our code to blow up.
But we put that line in
a try and except block,
and so we caught it.
And so we dealt with that fact.
So, in summary in this,
we talked about if statements;
we talked about else;
we talked about try and except.
How important indentation
is to mark blocks
where they begin and they end.
And an else if and try except.
So up next, we're gonna talk
about loops and iteration.
(soft jazz music)