- Now I'm gonna talk a little bit about
object lifecycle and what
we mean by object lifecycle
is the act of creating and
destroying these objects.
Now I've been using this
term constructor already.
And so, when we declare a variable,
whether it's a string or a dictionary
or a party animal we create them
and then they're discarded,
and there's all this
dynamic memory that comes and goes.
And we as the writers of
objects have the ability
to insert ourselves at the
moment of object creation
and at the moment of object destruction
and we make special functions
that we call the constructor,
the object constructor
or the class constructor,
and the destructor.
And we don't actually
explicitly call them,
they're called automatically by the,
by Python on our behalf.
And so the constructor is
much more commonly used.
It's used to set up any initial
values of variables if necessary.
Et cetera, et cetera.
Destructors, we'll cover them but
they're used very rarely.
So here's a bit of code that we've got.
It's our PartyAnimal and
a lot of it is the same
as what we've been doing so far.
So we have this variable x.
And the constructor has
a special name, __init_.
Again we pass in the
instance of the object self,
and in this one all we're gonna do
is print out your constructed.
And here's this code that we've had before
and now we have __del
and then we pass in self
and we'll just print out
that we're being destructed
and what the current value of x is
for that particular instance.
So let's go ahead and run this.
Um, and so again this
doesn't really do any code
up to here, that just defines PartyAnimal
but this is the constructing of it.
And basically that says, oh!
And it really kind of
creates these variables
and then it also runs the constructor.
And so in this case, this line right here
is causing the I am constructed
message to come out.
Then we do, an.party
an.party and that says,
you know, one and two.
And here's an interesting thing,
we're actually gonna destroy this variable
by throwing away, an no
longer points at that object.
an's gonna point to 42
so we're gonna sort of
overwrite an and put 42
in it, and at that point,
Python's like, oh, this whole
little object that I just
created somewhere it's out
here, it's vaporizing it
and throwing it away, and so,
before this line completes,
it actually calls our
destructor on our behalf,
and so that message comes out.
So we are allowed as the
builder of these objects
to add these little
chunks of code that says
I wanna be involved at the
moment this object is created
and I wanna be involved at the moment
that this object is destroyed.
Now, in this last line, an
is no longer a party animal,
an is now an integer.
It's got a 42 in it.
It's gone, it's been created, it was used
and then it was destroyed, okay?
So you gotta be careful if
you overwrite something,
you could sorta throw the object away.
So the constructor is
the special block of code
that's called when the object is created
to set the object up.
So we can create lots of instances,
everything we've done so
far is we make a class
and then we create one
instance, one object.
And each of these objects ends
up being stored in its own
variable, we have a variable
an and we've been using it.
But the more interesting
thing begins to happen
when we have multiple
instances of the same class
sitting in different variables.
And it has its own copy
of the instance variables.
So let's take a look at this.
So, this code here, I've
taken out the destructor.
And it shows a little
bit more information.
So now we're gonna put
two variables in here,
we're gonna have a
current score or whatever.
And a name.
And we're gonna start it out as blank.
And this time we're
going to add a parameter
onto the constructor.
And so the self comes in
sort of automatically,
as the object is being constructed,
but if we put a parameter
on the constructor call
which is this PartyAnimal
call, then this comes in
as the z variable.
And so self is the object itself, and z,
this first parameter is
whatever parameter we put here.
Everything we've done so
far has no parameter here,
but now we have a parameter here.
And then, that means that
when we call this constructor,
this line of code comes and
then name is no longer blank,
name is gonna be Sally
in this particular thing.
And then it'll say, oh,
self.name, which'll be Sally,
has been constructed.
And so then, then we have
this, and that object
is now constructed in and
we put it in the variable s.
And then we call the party method on that,
and we construct a different one and so
this time it calls and z is Jim.
And we basically have a...
Oops.
Another copy of this.
And so, this is how it's going to look.
Right, as it runs down here.
As it runs down here,
when this is called, it makes one instance
and stores that in the variable s.
And there's a variable x in there,
there's a name in there,
there's an init method in party
and that's all in here, right,
all that stuff is in here.
And now we say, let's make, and that's
gonna have a Sally in there.
Alright, Sally in there.
And then we're gonna
do another constructor
and so it's gonna make a whole new thing
and it's gonna store that in j,
and this one's gonna have Jim in it.
s.party then this turns into
a one and then we're gonna
call j.party, that turns that into a one
and then s.party will
cause this to be a two.
Okay, and so what happens is,
we have now two objects,
one in the variable s and
one in the variable j,
and they have separate copies
of their instance variables.
These are the instance
variables or the object fields
or whatever but they're the variables.
But the key is, is that every time we
do a new construction, it duplicates this
and there's another copy of it.
So there's an x within s.
So s.x is this variable and j.x
is that variable.
Okay?
So the next thing we'll
talk about is inheritance
and that's the idea of taking one class
and extending it to make something new.