- Hello and welcome to Chapter 10.
Now we're gonna talk
about our third kind of
collection called tuples.
But tuples are really a lot like lists.
There's not too much to them.
They're really kind of
reductionist version of lists.
They function very much like lists in that
you know, they have things
and the difference is is
there are no square braces.
There is a parenthesis,
round brace or whatever.
And they have positions
zero, one, and two,
just like a list.
And you can look things up x(2),
so x(2) is the third element here.
And so that prints out Joseph.
You can assign, you
know make a tuples here.
This is a constant syntax for a tuples
and print that out
and a print statement shows
you that this is a tuple
not a list by showing
you round parenthesis
and a whole bunch of
functions that work with lists
work the same way with tuples.
You can put a tuple at
the end of a end statement
in a for as you might expect
and then it iterates through the tuples.
tuples maintain order,
so it prints out one, nine and two.
So, literally this bit of code here
could be identical whether
it was a list or a tuple.
It really would do the exact same thing.
The difference between tuples
are that they are immutable.
Once you create the tuple
you can only sort of assign a tuples
but you can't modify it.
You can modify a list.
So if we take a look at a list here.
We make a list that's nine, eight, seven.
And we say x(2) equals 6,
well that just means
this seven becomes a six.
And that's just natural,
meaning we can reassign slots.
We can delete things.
We can insert things.
We can mutate them.
We can change them.
So they're changeable, right.
They're changeable.
But if we try to do that
same thing with a string.
So we say y = ABC and we know
that this is position zero, one and two.
But if we tried to say
let's change the C to a D
by saying y(2) equals
D, that is not allowed.
And it says it doesn't
support item assignment.
And this little bracket,
you know, x(2), is what
they call item assignment
inside of Python.
And so if we do the same thing then
with a three element tuple,
put that in C and we try to
change this slot to be a zero,
it's gonna blow up
because it's the exact same thing.
And that has to do with the fact that
once this assignment is made,
this is not modifiable.
Now it turns out that the
reason it's not modifiable
is for efficiency.
They take up less storage,
they are quicker to access
and they're really designed
internally behind the scenes
in ways we don't really
need to understand.
They're just more efficient than lists.
If all you wanna do is store a list
and look at it and then throw it away,
you probably should use a tuple instead.
So there's a lot of things
that you can do with lists
that you also can't do with tuples
but they're really just a corollary
of this notion of non mutability.
And so like you can sort a list,
but you can't sort tuples.
You can add a five to the
end of three, two, one.
Can't do that in a tuple,
but you can in a list.
And flip the order.
Dot dot dot dot dot dot.
So anything that you can do to a list
that modifies the list,
not allowed for tuples.
And so you can take a look
at the kinds of things
that are inside,
the methods that are part of each list.
Append, count,
extend, index,
insert, pop.
All of these some of these many of these
are modifying and then count and index
are the only ones that work for tuples.
And so tuples are limited lists.
Now at some point there's
gonna be a but here
to say why do we like them?
And the reason that we like them
is that they're just more efficient.
They don't have build,
Python in its own internal
organization of these objects
it knows that they'll never be modified.
'Cause when you make a tuple,
you as the programmer are saying,
I'm never gonna modify this.
And Python won't let you do it.
So it's higher performance,
better memory use.
And you know, to a beginning programmer
that doesn't really matter
but that's the reason.
And so we tend to use tuples
in situations where we're
gonna make a temporary variable
and then temporarily
use it just a little bit
and then throw it away without
really messing with it.
And we tend to use lists
to build things up,
et cetera et cetera et cetera.
So, the other thing that's
interesting about tuples
and we've actually sort of seen this
is that you can put a tuple
that includes variables
on the left side of the assignment.
And this takes a little getting used to
but it's really cool.
And no other language
that I know of does this.
So if we say x comma y,
that's a two tuple,
both have to be variables.
You can't put constants on this side.
You know and it's like
saying x equals four,
y equals "fred", right.
So what happens is is you can put a tuple
on the far side of an
assignment statement.
And the four goes to x
and the "fred" goes to y.
And you say what's in y?
Well y is indeed "fred".
And so this is like two
assignment statements.
Now the way I've got this syntax,
I would probably do, you
know, two separate statements.
Just not to show off that
I know how to do tuples,
you know, and so you
can, here's another one,
and they just move correspondingly.
If you don't have two here,
and you do have two here.
Well if you have three here
or two here and three here
and you don't match the number there,
you get in some trouble.
Now if you just say x equals tuple,
then that is the tuple in the list.
But this is just a simple
straight 99 value going into A.
So you can put tuples
as the left hand side.
And you can even do things like
return a tuple from functions.
That's a real nice Python
feature that I like a lot.
tuples are also related to dictionaries
as we've seen in the previous chapter.
So here we make a little dictionary,
we make a empty dictionary by constructing
an empty dictionary,
stick it in d so d is sort of like this
place that can hold key value pairs.
And we put "csev" and
there's a two in there.
And "cwen" and there's a four in there.
So we have this, you know,
associative mapping
between "csev" and two,
and "cwen" and four, all stuff we know.
And now, we say hey.
We're gonna loop through
the key value pairs here
and we've seen this
syntax before, k comma v.
So this is a tuple.
So you can think of this
as each one of these things
is going to get assigned into this tuple
which means the key ends up,
and the first one's the key
and the second one's the value,
I use the variable k v all
the time in code that I write
just for my own sanity.
So k v are gonna iterate successively
through the successive
keys and values in that.
So this is gonna run twice
and k's gonna be "csev" two,
and "cwen" four,
the order just happened to stay the same.
And so if you say,
what is in one of these things?
You can actually take d items,
the items method within that dictionary
and say hey,
give me back, give that to me back,
and then print tups,
and this is a special kind of a class
but really ultimately
it is a list of tuples.
You know this is two, this is the zero,
this is the two, the one,
the first and the second.
And then within each thing you get,
you have a two tuple.
And so, in a sense this k and v
are iterating through those things
when we're putting d items
here and d items there.
One nice thing about tuples
is that they're comparable.
They're comparable in the same way
that strings are comparable,
meaning that they're
compared from left to write
with the left most or zero tuple
being the most significant.
And it doesn't compare any
further than it has to.
If its asking less than,
so if it's looking at
say this first tuple,
it starts at the left and says okay,
it asks the question,
tell me true or false.
Is zero less than five
and the answer is true
and so the answer to this
overall expression is true
and it doesn't even
compare those two numbers,
those second and third number.
They don't compare them.
If on the other hand we're
asking is this less than that,
it only looks at the first one
and asks if it can answer the question.
And the answer is well they're both zero.
And so I can't answer the question
so I have to go to the
second one, second pair.
And one is less than three and
so that means this is true.
And it does not check this,
even though 20 million
is bigger than four,
it doesn't matter because
these are the numbers
that cause the true to happen.
And the same is true
if you do this with strings.
Again, we start the first one.
So Jones, Sally, well that's the same.
So we don't know the answer yet.
And so Sally, Sam, well okay.
S, S, oh they're the same,
a, a they're the same.
Oh ...
l and m.
L is less than m,
so the actual letter that
makes the difference here
the l and the m and
leads to us being true.
And so this, it goes left to right
but then even when it's doing strings
it's going left to right.
That's just how string comparison works.
And if we say is Jones,
Sally greater than Adam, Sam,
well we check the first one
and we check the J and the A.
Well J is greater than A
and so we don't have to
look at anything else.
We don't have to look at these,
any more of these characters.
We don't have to look at the
second thing in the tuple.
We don't have to look at,
that is enough to be true.
So it only scans until it
has a definitive answer.
It doesn't scan any further.
So now what we're gonna do is
use this comparable capability
to sort these lists of tuples
and then bring this all back
and connect it more to dictionaries.
(slow jazzy piano music)