- Hello and welcome to
Chapter 4, Functions.
This is the fourth of our basic patterns,
we'll get to iterations next.
Functions is the store and reuse.
One of the things in programming is that
we never like to repeat
ourselves, we don't like to,
if we have four or five lines of code,
and we're going to do
the same thing later,
we don't like to put the
same four lines of code in,
even if...
It has to do with reliability.
If you find something wrong
with those four lines of code,
and you've got them 12 different
places in your program,
then you got to find all
12 places and fix them.
So collect those to one place,
and then call them and reuse them,
and that's the idea of store and reuse.
So, this is how functions
work inside of Python.
And the first thing we notice
is there is a new key word
"def" that stands for defined function,
and the def is like an if statement,
or we'll see fors and whiles,
that they end in a colon,
and then they have an indented block,
and then the indented block de-indents,
and that's the end of the function.
And so there's two statements
make up this function.
The key thing that you have
to understand and get used to
is this def part is actually not
running any code whatsoever.
It's actually remembering the code.
And that's what I call the "store phase."
The def creates a bit
of code and records it,
like a macro, although it's
much more complex than a macro,
and it names it whatever you chose.
You gave it a name.
We named this one thing().
And so it, as a side effect of Python
reading or parsing these three lines,
it doesn't do anything, but it remembers.
These two lines are what you would like
to run when you invoke thing().
So this is the definition of a function,
and this is the invoking of the function.
So this doesn't do anything.
So there's no output here
from that stuff right there.
But then what happens is you invoke it.
And this thing() looks like
it's part of Python, but you,
in effect, have extended
Python with your def statement.
And so when it sees thing()
it goes up and runs your code,
and so out comes "Hello
Fun," and then it comes back,
and goes to the next line, does print(),
so print() comes out, and
then it goes back like,
oh, this is the reuse part.
But we get to reuse it.
We define it once and we use it twice.
Then it runs this code again,
and then goes to the next
line, and it's all done.
So this little bit came out twice.
And, of course, this is really simple,
so that I can fit it on a page,
but you get the idea that
I don't wanna repeat.
This might be, you know,
15 to 100 lines of code,
and I don't wanna type
those over and over again.
So I say, hey, store these
in a name that I choose,
and then when I invoke them,
bring them back and then run them again.
So that's the basic idea.
We've actually already been using
functions from the beginning.
The print() is a function, right?
Print() is a function.
Every time we see print,
print() and then we
have some stuff in here,
we're calling the print function.
This is the syntax, with
two little parenthesis,
is the syntax for functions.
And so input is a function,
type is a function,
float's a function, int's a function.
All these things are built-in functions
that come with Python at
the moment that we started.
I mean, we installed Python
and these came along.
And then there's other functions
that we define and use,
and that's what the def is for.
In effect, we can create
new reserved words,
of our own making, that
extend the Python language.
After we define the function.
So it's just this bit of reusable code
that takes some arguments.
We haven't seen any with arguments,
there's a little parenthesis,
and we'll see how that works in a bit.
We define using the def
keyword, and then we invoke it.
There's the defining phase,
which actually doesn't run the code,
it just remembers the code,
and then there's the invoking phase.
You define it once and then
invoke it one or more times.
Calling the function or
invoking the function,
we think of those two
things as the same thing.
Call, invoke, are just the terms we use.
Most people just say call the function.
But invoking is a, perhaps,
more descriptive way to think about it.
So here's an example of a function.
It is built into Python.
It's called the max function.
And we can pass some parameters
into the max function,
so we pass the 'Hello world' string.
Now, like much of Python,
max knows what kind of thing
is being passed into it,
and it knows that it's looking
for the largest character,
the lexicographically largest character.
And in this case, it scans this little
that's inside the max code.
It scans through and finds
the largest character.
So, apparently, lowercase
letters are higher than
uppercase letters because
in English we get back a w.
And so this is what's
called the return value.
So this is an assignment statement.
Let me clear this and start over.
So this is an assignment statement,
and so it has to evaluate
this right-hand side.
And a function call is nothing
more than, like, x + 1.
It's something to evaluate.
It runs the function code,
passes in this argument,
and then this residual
value, this is called the
return value, we'll look
at this in more detail,
becomes the result of this
little bit in the expression.
And there's nothing else.
We could have w + 1 or something.
And then the w is what's stored into big.
So we print big, and big is a variable
that has the letter w inside of it.
And then we ask, what is the smallest?
And that finds the blank,
and so we get a blank
to see that there's a min
function and a max function.
Both of these are built in.
These are built-in functions,
they're always there for us.
Okay, so here is another
example of the max function.
And so we can think of this
as invoking, or calling,
this function, as this right-hand
side is being evaluated.
We are passing this variable in,
and there's some code in here,
and it's gonna do some stuff.
Yada, yada, yada.
And then it's gonna give
us back a bit of stuff.
That's its return value,
and then that goes up into the big, right?
That's how this works.
And so this is actually built in.
Or burnt in. I guess I can't draw.
And so you can think of this as sometime,
a long time ago, when Python
was being first formed,
somebody wrote some code.
And it's got some stuff in it,
and it's got a little loop that reads
through all the letters,
it has to figure out if
it's a string or a list,
etc., etc., etc.
But this is store, except
you didn't do the storing
because it's already built in,
and then this is the reuse.
Store and reuse.
So we build these things into Python.
They're already prebuilt, as if,
before the first line of your
code executes way up here,
someone put all this code in for you,
into Python, and created a
thing called max for you.
Now we've been using this already.
Built-in functions, we've
got type() conversions,
we've got the float()
that takes an integer
and returns a floating
point version of that.
And, again, this is kind
of like an expression.
So, it's like, I wanna divide this by 100,
but before I do that, I've
gotta convert it to a float().
So it has to sort of
do these function calls
as it's evaluating the expression.
Sometimes, like here,
we just have a print()
out the return value, that's what this is,
this is the return value.
If you just type a
function in a parameter,
it can be a constant or
it can be a variable.
And as we'll see in a second,
we'll give you many of these, if you like.
So you can either just run it,
or take the result of this.
This passes an integer and
converts it to a float(),
and then puts the float() into that.
Type() tells us what
kind of thing that is,
and you can use this
inside of an expression,
so it's like, what am I gonna do first?
Oh I gotta do 2 times this thing.
Oh wait, pause just briefly for a moment,
call out to some float()
code, pass a 3 into it,
and then something comes back.
The return value.
The residual value comes back,
and then that participates, in
this case it's gonna be 3.0,
participates in this 2 * 3.0.
And so, 2 * 3.0 then ends
up being 6.0, etc., etc.
But you can see, it's like,
oh wait a sec, I gotta
figure out what this is.
Call the function, get the return value,
and then continue
processing this expression.
We've also done this
with string conversions,
partly because, just as an example,
the input always returns a string.
The input function returns a string.
And so here's this string,
could be coming from input,
but we'll just take '123'.
We know that that's a string,
it's not the number 123.
And if we try to add 1 to
it, we get a traceback.
"Cannot concatenate 'str'
and 'int'" traceback.
But we can convert that
string to an integer.
And so int() can take a
floating point number,
or an integer, or even a string,
and it says, oh I know
what I'm supposed to do
with a string, I'm
supposed to look at this,
interpret these as numbers, and, you know,
multiply by ten, and figure out what
the hundredths place
is, and all that stuff.
There's a little bit of
work to that and it does it.
But then it gives us back an integer,
and we say, oh, what is that?
That's now the 123, but
it is of type int(),
and now I can add one to it and get 124.
And, as before, from this
example that we're kind of
reusing from a previous chapter,
you don't want to try to convert...
Oops. Sad face. Sad face. Sad face.
You don't want to try to convert something
that doesn't have digits using int(),
because it'll say, "I
don't know what to do",
and then your program quits.
You don't want your program to stop.
Tracebacks, you can, of
course, deal with that,
and try and accept, but
that's a previous lecture.
Okay, so up next we're gonna talk
about building our own functions.
Not just using the predefined ones.