- Hello and welcome to chapter
11, regular expressions.
The fun thing about this
chapter is unlike all
the rest of the chapters you sort of had
to really understand every single thing
and chapters one through
11 built on one another.
Or one through 10 built on one another.
But you can really get along
without using chapter 11.
It's not a really required topic
but it's a fun topic and
an interesting topic.
So, you can relax a little
bit and realize that you
may or may not like
regular expressions and
if you don't like them that's okay.
You don't have to use them.
You can go for your
whole life without using
regular expressions.
The idea of a regular expression is that
you come up with a language.
It's a little character
based programming language
where you can do smart
searching, basically.
Smart searching as
you'll see in a bit well,
smart extraction.
And it's really almost
programmable wild card expressions.
There's no looping but
there is looping and
there's all this implicit
thing you say look for
patterns that look like
this and then you get back
things that match those patterns.
You know, we do searching for everything.
We're looking through
large blocks of text.
Say, go find me everything
that has the word python
in it or something like that.
So, that's just such a common thing
to do and regular expressions
are a very structured way
to go about searching for information.
They are very powerful
but they're also very
cryptic and you may not like them
but they're a lot of fun actually
once you understand them.
Learning how to program them takes a while
or you can go back to expression programs.
Require some try it,
play with it, check it,
try it, check it, try it, check it.
But once you get 'em
they're really quite cool.
It's a very old programming language.
It comes almost from the 1960's,
the concept of it.
It's a theory of computing
where they were trying
to come up with theory of
languages and regular expressions
was one form of languages that
computers could understand.
And so it has some fun old words.
One of the advantages of
knowing regular expressions
is that you're kind of a cool person.
You can take a quick look at this
XKCD that sort of captures the
devil meg here,
awesome power that regular expressions do.
And while we're at it,
while we're talking about awesome,
I do want to take this
moment and show you my
awesome tattoos.
And so, you may not
notice but I got a couple
of tattoos here.
Here's the first tattoo.
This is where I went to,
got my PhD.
And this is my University of Michigan
faculty member position.
I got a PhD in engineering
and I teach in a school
of information and large array science.
And then, I have this other tattoo.
And this tattoo is what I'd call the
ring of compliance.
I work on learning management systems
in educational technology and standards.
And there's this standard called
Learning Tools Interoperability, which
if you're using this course
and doing the auto grader
it uses Learning Tools Interoperability
to integrate into whatever
learning management system
you happen to be using.
And one of those learning
management systems is the
open source learning
management system that
I helped write called Sakai.
And these are the rest
of the major vendors
and the idea of that tattoo was that
I would put the tattoo of
every vendor that would
comply with Learning
Tools Interoperability.
So, you'll notice Coursera.
I helped Coursera put Learning
Tools Interoperability
in and so the auto graders integrate
into Coursera or Blackboard
or Canvas or Sakai or Moodle
or half a dozen other things.
So, it's just like a cool techno thing.
Just like regular expressions.
So, I've got a URL here
for a regular expression
quick guide.
You might wanna print this out.
So, that you can
look at it even while
you're watching this lecture
because it's a little programming language
except that it's character
based not line based
and not keyword based.
It has certain active characters that
the character means something
versus the character
represents the character itself.
And so, the regular
expressions is not part
of the base python but it's
distributed with pythons.
So, you have to put a
import re at the top to say
that's really saying pull in
the regular expression library.
And there is a couple of
functions inside that.
Re.search which is kind of
like a really smart version
of the find method inside of strings.
And re.findall which is kind of like
taking and stamping
your way through a loop,
through a string and finding
all of the things that
match a particular pattern
and extracting those.
And we'll talk about both of these
in this lecture.
So, here's a really simple piece of code
where I'm just going to sort of show you
sort of before and after.
So, here's a thing where
we're looking for lines
that begin with from colon.
And so, we open a file.
We loop through the whole file.
We strip off the lines ...
text.
And then, we say if line.find
from is greater than
equal to zero, then we print it.
It gives you a negative
one if it's not found
and so, reads all the lines.
And once in a while it'll print it out,
reads all lines once while printing out.
So, that's kind of like
a needle in a haystack.
To use regular expressions to do that
we have to import the
regular expression library.
These lines are the same.
We're gonna loop through.
We're gonna strip.
Now, we're gonna say if re.search.
The way to say this is
within the library regular expressions,
go find the search function and search
for the string from and the string line.
Okay.
So, this is the line
to search whereas here
it was more object-oriented
where we say line.find.
Here we say re.search and we
pass in line as parameter.
These two things are
equivalent which means most
of the time it's gonna
run and once in a while
it'll hit a line and it'll print that out.
And it'll finish the whole thing.
So, that is taking and
doing what we would do
with the find operation
with regular expressions.
Now ...
searching with regular
expressions has these special
characters and so here we
have the same basic code
except now we're saying
if line starts with from.
So, we're not using find anymore.
And that way we're only
gonna get that thing
in the first position
not like blah, blah,
blah, blah from colon.
We don't want that to match.
We only want to match here
at the beginning of the line.
And so, we use line starts with.
So, it's gonna do the same thing.
And find lines that have the
prefix and print those out
and then be done.
Now, on regular
expressions search we don't
in a sense change the method.
We have a certain number
of things we can do with
strings based on what they've built in.
But a regular expression,
we actually can turn
this first parameter into code.
And so, what's happening
here is the carrot,
if you go back to the little cheat sheet,
carrot means this is
the beginning of line.
It's a virtual character that
matches the beginning line.
It's like from that
starts at the beginning.
So, from at the beginning
does match and from
in the middle does not match.
By putting that little carrot there.
Same thing, line is what we're searching.
And then from is what we're ...
Carrot from ...
from at the beginning
is what we're looking for.
And so, again it does
the exact same thing.
It only prints lines that have from colon
as the first character in the line.
So, the difference is,
is we look for a method
and the other one is we
program the regular expression.
So, we're gonna run out
of methods in the string
class long before we run
out of things that we can do
with regular expressions.
And so, couple other
special characters that
carrot matches the beginning of the line.
So, carrot matches beginning of the line.
This capital X matches itself.
Dot is a wild card that
matches any character.
And then, some of the characters
in regular expressions
modify the immediately
preceding character.
And so, that says
look for a line that
starts with x and then has
many characters,
that's with these two things,
zero or more characters
followed by a colon.
And so, you can see that it sort of ...
It's this sort of like expanding stamp.
It's like, oh there's an X
at the beginning of the line.
That line, it looks good.
I got some characters here.
And now, I got a colon.
That's good.
So, this I an X, some
characters, and a colon.
Check.
X, some characters, and a colon.
X and these things, you know, away we go.
And so, that's what's gonna match.
And so, you can see how
some of these characters
are special, again go
back to your cheat sheet.
Some of them are special
and some of them are
actual characters.
And this colon and X are just there.
They're not special.
They're just the characters.
Okay.
Now,
sometimes you wanna be a little more clear
on your match.
So, let's take a look at
these lines that match that
particular thing that we just did.
So, we have these two,
X dash Sieve colon,
X dash DSPAM dash result,
like these are for mail messages.
And then one of the
mail messages has a line
in it that says X dash
plane is behind schedule.
And this matches.
Is that what you really wanted?
And so, what we can basically say is
because this is an X,
this is some number of
characters and that's a colon, it matches.
It has to match.
That's this rule applied to
this line results in a yes.
It does.
And so, how can you be
a little more clear as
to what you want to match and
what you don't want to match?
So, we can write code.
So, now what we're going to say is ...
We want to match the
beginning of the line and
we wanna carrot capital
X and we want a dash.
So, now we're gonna match
those first two characters.
X dash at the beginning of the line.
Carrot X dash says first two characters
of the line must be X dash.
Now, we have another special character.
Again, refer to your cheat sheet.
Back slash capital S means
a non-white space character.
Right?
Any character other than white space.
And then plus means one or more times.
One or more non-white space characters.
That's what this whole thing says.
And followed by a colon
which is just a character.
So, now we have X dash
followed by one or more
non-white space characters
followed by a colon.
X dash followed by one
or more non-white space
characters followed by a colon.
Here we have X dash
followed by one or more ...
whoop, there's a space there.
And so, this doesn't match.
Even though there's a colon there.
It means that between
the dash and the colon
you can only have some number
of non-white space characters.
So, this is a no.
It does not match.
And so,
if you didn't want to match this,
you then sort of create a more precise ...
You know, we could even
have a thing that said,
I want X dash with an uppercase character,
uppercase letter if you wanted to.
And so, there's all kinda
fine-tuning if you sort
of learn the structure
that you've got to do.
And so, that's kind of the matching,
where you're taking a
whole line and taking this
template and deciding if the template
anywhere on that line matches.
And now what we're gonna
do is use this to actually
pull data out of strings
using the regular expression library.
("Fire Breather" by Silent Partner)