- So now we're gonna talk a
little bit about XML Schema.
XML Schema is a language
that allows you to decide
on whether or not a
particular XML document
meets a contract, an arrangement.
So you have two pieces of software
exchanging data using XML,
and what if one of them,
if they're all working
nobody really worries too much about it,
but if all of sudden one breaks,
you change one side
and another one breaks,
whose fault was it, right?
Was it the side that got
changed or the other side?
And so you could argue.
So what you like to do
is before you set up
these arrangements between
these applications,
set up a contract.
In a way, they're kind
of like the RFCs are
except that their scope is
between pairs of applications.
So it is in itself is XML.
Basically what we do is
we take an XML document
and an XML Schema contract,
and then we either say
that's good, or that that is bad.
And that's called validation.
A piece of software that validates XML
when given a schema is called a validator.
And so an XML document.
Here we have our little XML document.
We're passing it to the validator.
And then we have a schema
contract, which is itself XML.
It's kind of a particular kind
of XML, that xs:complexType.
That's just a tag.
Colon is a legitimate character
for the name of a tag.
Name equals person,
that's just an attribute.
And so XML schema is a
particular format of XML that
renders an opinion about what
XML is supposed to look like.
So, there's a number of
different XML Schema languages,
the one we're goin to look at is one
that kinda came a little bit later,
that's very common, called XSD,
which is the Worldwide Web
Consortium Schema specification.
Often you'll find files
that have suffixes of .xsd
that actually contain
the XML just like we're going to show you.
So if you recall there
are simple elements,
which have text children,
and then there are complex elements
where, other nodes or
children of other nodes.
And so we can say this.
And so here we have a little bit of XML,
and the XML Schema that
makes sense with that.
So, what we're saying
is the outer tag of this legitimate XML
is supposed to be a complex
tag, with the name of person.
And so there we go, that looks good.
Good, good.
Then there is a sequence,
and then there is a simple element,
name of last name, looks good,
and it's a string, that looks good,
another tag that's in it,
named age that's a type integer,
that's good,
and then a thing that's called dateborn,
and then there, it looks like a date,
so we check all these things
and we can basically say yup,
that is a good XML document
according to this Schema.
And, you don't have to
write this generally,
but there is software that
reads these two things
and comes back with a true or a false
and not even have some
detail as to what went wrong
with this particular schema.
Here's some more that
you can do with a Schema.
We can do things like, you know,
have a complex type, we have a sequence,
here we have a string full_name
and a string child_name.
But we have this min
occurs and max occurs.
So min occurs is the minimum
number of times it can occur
and maximum is the maximum,
so min occurs equals one,
max occurs equals one,
means it's required.
And so this is required.
And we don't have two of 'em,
two of 'em would be an error.
One of 'em is fine so that's good.
Here the child_name is
min occurs zero, max occurs 10.
So we have four here,
and so that's good too.
So that is another kind
of XML Schema constraint
that you can have.
Here's a few other data
types that we can do.
We've done the string,
we've done the date.
The date look like this.
Dates are four-digit year,
two-digit month, two-digit day
with dashes.
Now there's lots of different
ways to represent dates,
but the nice thing about this
and you don't, you have
to put the zeros in,
so zero nine for September.
It means that these are
sortable as strings,
so that if you do all your dates this way,
they're sortable as strings.
So you could argue what is prettier,
but for computers we
don't worry about that,
we're arguing about what's
the most functional.
And then the dateTime
is that same date format
with zeros followed by the letter T,
letter T,
and then followed by
hours minutes seconds,
zero-filled, right, so nine
o'clock is um, zero nine,
and then the time zone,
which we'll talk about a
second in the next slide.
You can have decimal numbers
and you can have integer numbers as well.
And so we are able to
sort of render an opinion
as to what is good, and what is bad,
in the resulting XML.
So dates are kind of interesting.
There's, again, we have lots
of different formats of dates,
you know, nine, slash 10,
slash 2002, right.
That's a format of a date but that's one.
There's another format of
the date which is you know,
12 December 2002, whatever.
And so this is how people show dates.
Computers don't wanna have
all those different dates
and don't wanna figure those out.
They have libraries that produce dates
and make 'em look pretty
for particular locales,
but computers really want
dates that work best for them.
So we just say okay, we're going to have
this year month day
time, and then zero fill,
hours minutes seconds,
hms, and then time zone.
Now computers even prefer a time zone.
I don't know if you've used
something like your Google calendar,
and you take a flight
or take a train trip,
and you end up in a different time zone,
everything switches
and that's because Google Calendar
is not really storing the time zone
that you're,
not storing the dates relative
in your current time zone,
it's storing them in what
we call universal time,
or Greenwich Mean Time,
Zulu time is another word for that.
And Z means this time that is
the time in London, England,
Greenwich Mean time.
And so the thing is that, that means,
if this data moves between time zones,
or crosses the International Date Line,
or Standard Daylight Savings Time,
or anything like that,
none of that changes.
And so we have this internal date and time
that's very common in situations
where computers are exchanging data
that then gets shown with
the time zone converted
to the time zone or the local format
that's the the right way to do that.
And there's a standard
for how dates and times
are supposed to look.
So here's another little
example of some stuff,
let's see what we got.
Now if you see this
little question mark XML,
that's not a problem,
that just is a way of
sort of putting a header
on the whole document that
says it's an XML document,
telling it that's a UTF-8 document,
and that's not really a tag
that's sort of like a marker on the file,
so that you can put that there
but it doesn't harm the XML.
The outer tag is this tag right here,
xsdet;schema, and then
um, what else we got?
We got an address,
we gotta string string
string string string,
we've seen all those,
here we have country,
and we're gonna have a restriction
that basically says,
this is a simple string,
but we're going to make it
so that you have to list
one of these four as the country code.
And so here we are down here,
and that's UK, and that's
UK, and so that is valid XML.
Another couple of examples here.
Let's see, string, string
string string string,
max occurs unbounded, that
means infinite number,
there's no limit on the
number, you can do that,
min occurs of zero,
x is positive integer, we've seen integer
but you can also say it's
gotta be a positive integer,
decimal we've seen that,
and then use equals required
is just another statement
that you can make.
I'm not trying to get you to the point
where you can do XML Schema,
just get you a sense of the kinds
of statements that we can
speak about when we're talking about
what is and is not legitimate XML.
So let's talk a little bit about
how we might talk XML inside Python.
And so, like most things
that are in this extended part of Python,
we have to import something.
And so this is the name of a
library xml etree ElemenTree
and then as ET this ends
up being a shortcut,
so we don't have to type these long things
and so ET is the same as typing that,
it's almost like a mac row.
Now, normally this XML is gonna come
somewhere from the network,
but I'm just gonna put this in a string,
I'm using a triple quoted string,
and so that means that
this triple quoted string
starts here and ends here,
and all these new lines that are here
are actually part of the string.
So this is kinda like I opened a file
and read the whole thing in.
But just to keep this
totally self-contained
I'm putting it in a string.
So the XML would come from some server
on the other side of the
network, we would get this XML.
So that's how it would
normally work, okay?
So,
this is the XML.
Right there.
And, we parse a string of data
and we call ET from string,
so we're passing in the
less thans, the new lines,
the greater thans, all of this
stuff we're passing it in.
And this could have syntax errors in it,
so this might blow up if
this had a syntax error
like we forgot the little
slash or something,
there was a syntax error.
But this doesn't have a syntax error
so then what we do is
we get back an object.
I just happen to call it tree,
because it kinda is like that tree
version of the XML.
That is an object that we can then query
to pull data out of it,
so we say tree.find
and look for a tag named name,
so that finds the tag named name is this.
It's everything, it's
the tag and the text.
If we want the text we add .text.
And then that .text, that .text,
that actually refines it
to only the word Chuck.
And, similarly,
if we do tree.find email,
that tree.find email,
that finds the email
tag which is this tag,
it has a child attribute
and you can get in any of the attributes
you say .get,
there's only one text child,
but there are many attribute children
so you have to tell it which one you want
and so this here,
this bit right here, all of that,
will resolve down to that string yes.
That's what you're
going to get there, yes.
And so you kinda build up
these little finds and call methods,
this is not a, clearly, a full
introduction to ElementTree,
but you get the idea,
you sort of dive down
in with these methods,
the call methods, the call methods,
to get little pieces out
and parse all of that.
Here is a different example,
in this one again we're
using triple quoted string,
we always have a single
tag on the outside,
and then I have a complex type of users,
and in it there are two user objects,
so this is kind of like a list,
right, so this is more
than one of these things.
So this user can occur more than one time.
And again, we take this and
we pass that into from string,
and get back an object that
represents the name stuff,
does not necessarily need to
be the same as this outer tag,
just a variable,
this could just as
easily be x if I wanted.
So now what I wanna say is Hey Stuff,
I wanna find the tag, the
path, users slash user,
I wanna find all tags
that match users/user.
So that's gonna give
me a list of two tags.
One tag,
two tags,
in a list.
Tag,
tag.
Oops.
So two tags.
Now I can print out how many I get,
that'll be two in this
case cuz I got two tags,
and then I can actually
iterate through the list,
so I can iterate through the list,
so this item is gonna
iterate first to this tag,
and that tag now, it's like
in the previous example,
we can look for the name tag within there,
and pull the text out,
so we pull that text out,
find the name tag, find the name tag,
and then within that, find the text.
And we can find the id tag
and pull the text of that out.
So that pulls out this zero zero one,
and,
I've scribbled too much.
And then we can item,
which is, this is item,
is that whole tag, .get x.
So that gets the attribute,
that gets the two,
that two comes down here, kay.
And then,
item goes to the next one,
cuz item is looping
through so item iterates
down to that one
and pulls out the name.text
the id.text,
and the attribute.x
and pulls all those pieces out.
So this is the basic pattern.
You saw one where you just,
you're tearing into a single thing,
and here you're tearing into something
that is expected to
occur more than one time.
And so that's a quick summary
of how you talk to XML in Python.
Up next we're gonna talk about
the other serialization format,
JavaScript Object Notation.