- Now we're going to
represent these relationships
in the database, and again,
what we're trying to solve
here is this notion of
database normalization.
Third normal form, there's
so much theory, right?
But, in this lecture, I'm
just gonna condense this
down to, don't replicate
string data and use,
what are called, keys.
Use integer keys to point at those things,
and we're going to use these
integers then to point.
So, assign each row an
integer, and then we're going
to point from one row to
another, using those integers.
And so we're gonna add
these special key columns to
each of the tables and help,
and the database will even
give us help managing those.
Now, and so we still need to keep track of
who is the creator of the album,
which album a track belongs to,
we've gotta create these relationships
and we have to come up with ways to store
those relationships.
And so, the idea is, is
we're going to have a column,
in a table which is the key column,
and we're going to call
this the ID column.
So this is a row, it might
have many bits of data here,
but in this case it's just
the name of an artist.
So this album is going
to belong to an artist.
And we're going to assign a
number, inside the database,
so that Led Zepplin is
one, and AC/DC is two,
and so we have this key,
this is called a primary key,
and then later, when we want
to say that the Who Made Who
album really was done by AC/DC,
we put the number two in.
So the difference here is,
instead of saying AC/DC in this
record, we just put the number two,
once we've established this number.
So we assign keys, and then
we have these pointers that
point back and so that's
how we model a relationship,
with these small integer numbers.
And so there are three basic
kind of keys that we use.
One is the primary key and
that is that little ID column
that is just a number, but
once we give Led Zepplin the
number one, Led Zepplin
has got the key one for the
rest of that database.
The logical key is the
text area that we use that
you might lookup, so
the title of the band,
or the title of the album,
that's the logical key.
And then the foreign
key is one of these keys
that is really pointing
to the primary key of
another row. That's called a foreign key.
You might think that you
want to use something
like an email address
as the primary key for
a user table or something like that.
The logical key should
always be separate and
there should always be a primary key,
that integer number.
Cause things like logical keys do change.
People do get new email addresses,
and if you've got that email address as a
foreign key pointing all over the place,
it doesn't work out so well.
So that's why you use
these small integer numbers
that have no meaning outside.
So sometimes if you're
on a system and you see
a URL and you see some
number like 422,016,
you're like, oh, that
turns out to probably be
my primary key in their database.
So, sometimes you can look at a URL and
you can see these primary keys in the URL,
but they don't mean
anything outside of that
particular system.
So, like I said, a foreign
key is the key that
is really pointing at a
row in a different table.
So, we have album has
a primary key for it,
but the artist_id points
to a row in the artist
table, as we will soon see.
I have a naming convention,
and in my naming convention
on this lecture, I use id
for the primary key and then
Artist_id I use uppercase
for the table names,
and then Artist_id says
this is a key this is just a
key that points to the id
key of the artist table.
And so that's what I do,
so you'll see, in all my
stuff I'll use that.
It's a convention, it's not
something SQL forces you to do,
but you will find when
you go to organizations
and work on their databases,
these conventions are
very important so I can
do something and you can
understand the rules
in which I created it.
Some of these, you'll find
this used by some people,
you'll find completely
different conventions,
and that will be okay.
Whatever convention
your organization uses,
learn that convention.
So now we're going to talk
about how we put these keys in,
and then how we actually
make the connections
from one row to another row.