- So welcome back we're going to continue
and start talking about
building our own functions.
So, again,
we use the def keyword
to define a function,
and then later we're going to invoke this.
And there's a bit to it.
We are defining the name of the function.
In effect we're extending Python
and creating new predefined things
that we can use except it's our code.
Starts with a def keyword,
has some optional arguments
which we'll see in a bit,
that's what the parentheses is,
and then the name.
And the function names
follow the same rules
as the variable names.
And then you have an indented block,
whatever code you wanna do,
and then you have a de-indented block
and that sort of defines the essence.
The key thing here is this is not
calling,
it's not invoking, it's not executing,
it's remembering, it's storing,
it's figuring things out.
So here is the output of a program
that defines a function
but then doesn't use it.
So this is a sort of broken function.
So here we go, we start
x equals five, print.
You don't have to def,
you have all the defs at the beginning,
the def runs whenever,
so you know, out comes hello,
and then we define a
function and this says,
oh, you wanna make a new thing here,
so I'll make a new thing,
it's kinda like a variable in a sense,
and then it copies this
stuff, copies it up there,
and says later you probably
are gonna wanna use this
so I'm gonna remember it, so
it doesn't do anything there.
It, no output comes out.
Then it says print Yo, and out comes Yo,
and then it adds two to
x, so x is now seven,
and then it prints x,
and there's no seven, there's seven.
These print statements never ran.
They never ran.
Why?
Because we did not invoke them down here.
We defined them but didn't invoke them.
So let's take a look at how
you invoke a function, right,
you define it and then you use it.
Sometimes you define it
once and use it once,
but more commonly you define it once
and use more than one time.
Again, the store and reuse pattern.
The def is the store and
the invoking is the reuse.
So here's just a slightly
different version
of that last program,
and so now it's gonna actually invoke it.
So x equals five, print hello,
def, so out comes hello, this produces,
the def produces no output, right,
but because there's a de-indent here,
that is the entire blob of the code
that is part of print lyrics,
so it prints out Yo,
and now we're going to invoke.
This is the call.
We're gonna call the function.
Now the function goes up,
let's clear this,
so we're down to here,
now the, this, like,
suspends at this place,
like, remember to come back
to here when we're done.
Go up, run this code, and then come back,
and then continue on.
So it like, leaves like a bread crumb
of where it's supposed to come back to.
And then it runs, and
then the print lyrics
of course produces
the two lines of output, and yeah,
that should probably, not've,
they should be up there.
And then x equal x plus
two, which makes it seven,
and then prints out seven.
Kay so this is the invoking.
Invoke, or call, the function.
Kay? You defined it, and
then later you called it.
Now, in addition to just
call and return and invoking,
we can pass parameters in.
And an example of a parameter is
in the max function we have to say,
this is the thing I want
you to find the maximum of,
the largest thing,
and part of it is,
in the whole store and reuse pattern,
we have a few lines of code
that sometimes we wanna do ever
so slightly different things
in a different invocation
so we use the arguments to subtly adjust
like, finding the maximum
is a general thing,
but what thing defined the maximum of,
that makes a function
that's much more useful
and reusable in a lot more situations.
So arguments are the thing we passed in,
and we defined for our functions
that we're going to build,
we, on the def statement,
so we say def, greet, name of function,
and then this is the arguments,
the things that are coming in.
Now this lang variable in a sense
only exists during the
life of the function
and it represents sort of a placeholder,
it's not a real variable
in the same sense,
it's a placeholder that refers
to how you touch that first parameter
that's sitting in there, okay.
And so lang,
so lang is our first
parameter, whatever it is,
we don't need to see this
part down here right now,
all we know is we're
going to make a function,
and we're going to take a parameter,
and this lang is the
placeholder that tells us
what that parameter is.
Kay,
so within the function
we're going to check to see
if the language is Spanish,
if we are print Hello,
also if the language is
French, print Bonjour,
otherwise print Hello.
We have a very highly simplified
language translation system, here.
So, the def of course, does nothing
except remembers that and
defines the concept greet.
So that comes down,
and now we're going to call it.
And it says go look up the thing
that I defined called greet.
If you don't put this in,
greet is going to give you
a traceback, but because you
extended and named it greet.
So it runs in, it starts,
suspends the code here,
starts up here,
but then
lang is now an alias to en.
So now we can run, if that is a yes,
else if, oop, I'm
gettin' it all wrong now.
Right so, en comes in as lang,
we're coming in the code,
if it's not es, it's not fr,
else then it prints hello,
and then it comes back to the next line.
And then we call it again,
and this time es is lang,
and so it runs this code,
and prints Hola.
And then next time it calls with this,
and it prints
Bonjour.
You get the idea.
So this is a placeholder so
that on the successive calls
or invokes, invocating,
invocation of the function
we can get at whatever
the programmer put in
as that first parameter.
And so we are saying in this definition
we are ready to receive a first parameter,
please call us with a parameter
and then we will be able to do
something slightly different
for the different values.
So this is a reusable bit of function
that prints hello in
three different languages
and then we tell it what language
at the moment that we're
actually invoking in.
So that's putting stuff into the function,
now getting stuff back out
is the concept of returning.
And the return statement,
the return statement,
is an executable statement
that does two basic things.
The first thing that it does,
is it finishes.
Now this is a one-line function
so that's kind of redundant
but it, when Python goes
into the return statement
it doesn't continue on to the next line.
It just returns.
That is the end of the invocation
of that particular function.
But even more importantly,
it takes as its parameter
you can say return without a parameter,
and it will stop the
execution of a function
kinda like a, break does for a loop.
It's kind of a break for a
loop, get out, we're done,
don't run that next line, get out.
But it also allows the
specification of what you want
as the residual value in an expression.
So we're doing a print,
and then we're saying greet,
and what's gonna show up here
is whatever this function
does in its return statement.
So that prints hello.
We call it again it prints hello again.
Okay.
And so,
and so basically the return statement
is the, I call this the residual value,
it's like what shows up here
when the function is all done,
and it's the string hello.
We call the functions that
return values fruitful
because they produce something
and uh, but you don't have
to, you can just say return,
or, you don't even have to
have a return statement,
it goes to the last line of the function
and it does a return automatically
at the last line of the function.
So here's a little bit of
a rewrite of our little
language program,
we are going to create a greeting program,
we're gonna take the language
as the first parameter,
and instead of just
doing a print statement
which is what we did before,
this is now more, more like a function,
cuz it takes some input
and produces some output it
as a return rather than just printing,
it's a little tacky for
a function to print.
And so, here we return
hola, bonjour, and hello,
based on the right thing.
So now we say print greet en,
so it runs the code once, lang is en,
and then it runs this code,
and the residual value is hello,
so it says Hello Glenn.
And similarly,
when it runs this code,
it passes es in as lang,
it runs through, and
it runs this statement,
it does, if there was
more statements it still,
it wouldn't run 'em as
soon as this return runs
that says that this bit right here,
is now hola.
So Hola Sally.
And the same with French,
goes in, runs again,
out comes the return statement,
and then Bonjour Michael.
So you see how we can control
as we're writing the application,
we can control as we're
writing the function
what the residual value
that we want to see
in whatever expression is calling us.
Sometimes we have returns
and sometimes we don't have returns.
So,
so if you think of the max code
that we talked about before,
we can kind of see that
somewhere inside that max code
there's a return,
and that's how it
communicates the w back to us.
So we pass in this argument Hello World,
it comes in as a parameter
and it's gonna loop
through this imp somewhere,
it's gonna loop over and over into imp,
and then at some point it's
gonna figure something out,
and tell us what it
wants to send back to us,
is a return statement,
and so the w comes back
and gets assigned into big.
You can have more than one parameter,
and they're just in order,
the first one and the second one,
three and five,
so three becomes a and five becomes b,
and away we go.
So we just use this to add two numbers
and so three plus five is eight.
So you can add as many as you like,
and the order matters,
and if you do things like,
you tell it you want parameters
and you don't give it to them,
then that'll become a traceback.
And it'll blow up.
You could also talk about
optional parameters,
if, later.
So, you don't have to have return values,
and that means that you simply
don't call a return with a value,
and return is always,
implicitly happening as the
last line of the function.
So, that's kind of the
basics of how functions
operate,
but, I don't want you to get too excited
about writing functions,
some programming classes are like,
gotta write a function,
gotta write a function.
Functions, to be clear, are
a very powerful mechanism
and as we write programs
150, 200 thousand,
200 lines of code, a
thousand lines of code,
10 thousand lines of code,
the concept of a function
is really important.
We would go crazy if we
didn't have functions.
But if you're only
writing 20 lines of code,
forcing yourself to write a
function is kinda pointless.
So, don't worry about the,
maybe the lack of urge to use this,
we are calling lots of
predefined functions,
and we will for the
next couple of lectures.
There will be a time when you go,
oh I'm sick and tired of repeating myself,
oh yeah, time to write a function.
So that's why we don't
push functions prematurely.
We just want you to know what they are,
use them, and at some
moment you'll be like,
oh I wanna define one.
But don't worry about,
it might take a while
before you really wanna define a function.
So, that kinda summarizes
our lecture on functions,
and, uh, up next we're
going to do iterations.