- So now what we're going to do is
we're going to switch from
just looping through strings
but instead loop through files
and it's going to take
a little bit of work
cause we have to open the file,
and we'll bring a lot of
things together at this point.
So here would be another task and that is
here's a bunch of text from the book
and you can just split this into words
and count and find out what
the most common word is
and how many times it occurs
so go ahead and try to
do this for a second
feel free to pause.
Actually don't bother pausing.
This is too hard, we should
write a program for this.
It's not easy, humans don't like this
it makes you concentrate,
and so here is a counting pattern
where we're gonna take a line
and then later we'll read this in a file
and so this is just an
adaptation improvement
of the previous thing.
So we're gonna start
with an empty dictionary,
we're gonna ask for a line
of text and read it in
and then we're gonna use split.
So remember the list of words?
Well what we're going to
get here is a list of words.
We'll print it out, and
we'll run this counting.
This is the little loop for
ever word in whatever this was
we're going to do this idiom
of either adding a new entry,
or adding one to an existing entry
and then printing that out.
So let's take a look at what we get there.
So if we run this we can give it some text
this would be all one line,
and then it splits it into words
and you see that these words here
are split, split, split, split.
I mean that's strings and splits
remember strings and lists, and split.
And so now the counting is
gonna go through this list,
"the clown ran after the..."
and it's gonna build a histogram,
"the, clown, one, clown, the,"
up, up, up these things
are gonna go up right.
That's this histogram.
And then when it's all said and done
we end up with the histogram
and so counts is the dictionary
that ends up with the histogram and we can
sort of by inspection see "oh
that is the most common word
and there are seven of those."
So if we sorta take a look at this,
we start out, we make a dictionary,
we read in a line of
text, the text goes in,
and then we split that and
we print the words out.
So these are the words, right.
Then we have a four loop
that's gonna loop through all those things
and then produce a dictionary.
And when we print the dictionary out,
that's what we're gonna get.
And that is seven, okay?
So that's one line of text.
That's how you walk across
the words in a line of text
after you split the line
into separate words.
Now we're gonna look at
ways that you can loop
through dictionaries,
we just produced a look
that can build a dictionary
but now we're gonna look at a dictionary.
So we'll start with a
very very simple example
and then we'll work to a
slightly more complex example.
So here's a dictionary just a constant,
Chuck is one, Fred's 42, and Jan's 100.
So we're gonna use a
definite loop with the four
four key in counts.
Now it doesn't have to remain
key but key is a good name.
Cause these are, these
are keys and values.
K, V, K, V.
Keys and values I just
mentally think of this
as keys and values and keys and values.
So this iteration
variable's gonna walk keys
it's not gonna walk the values
it's gonna walk the keys
Chuck, Fred, Jan, not necessarily
in that particular order
as you see it goes Jan,
Chuck, Fred because
just cause I typed it in in this order,
it's not like a list it
doesn't stay in that order
it might move around a little
bit as we add data to it
or as we set the data up.
So you can, in the loop
you can get the key
and so that's what prints
out the Jan, Chuck, Fred
but then you can also get
the corresponding count
for each one of these by just
pulling it out of the array
I mean pulling it out
of the dictionary right.
And so we can pull out
the corresponding value
and so we print out Jan
100, Chuck one, Fred two
and that runs this loop three times.
So if you just use the n and
you get a dictionary here
remember all the different things
we've been able to put there
on the end of a four loop
and the dictionary is
another thing we can put on
and we get a list of keys.
Now there's a couple of methods
that allow us to get the keys.
And so we have, you know we
can say turn this into a list
and we get a list of the keys.
So this is a dictionary,
the same dictionary,
we get a list of the keys.
You can also get the list of the keys
by using the keys method,
so that's take this dictionary jjj
and give me all the keys
which gives me a list
which is kinda the same thing.
And then we can ask for the values
and they give me just then the values
extracted out of this
dictionary so that's nice.
Now the one thing is
is that while I said you
can't predict the order
if in two statements you ask
for the keys and then the values
they at least come out in the same order
even though you can't
necessarily predict the order
that they come out, they
come out in the same order.
And then there is a third
thing that we can do
and that is ask for the items.
We can say give me the items.
And that gives us a
list, this is our first
really kind of composite
combined data structure
where it is a list, a three item list.
Zero, one, two.
And inside that there are what
is what are called two tuples
Jan maps to 100, Chuck maps
to one, Fred maps to 42.
Coming up next we're gonna
have a whole chapter on that
and so just take a look
at that for the moment
and we will come back to
that in some detail later.
This whole items idea
that gives us back a
list of key value pairs,
cause it's not just a list
of keys or a list of values,
it's actually a list of key value pairs
allows us to write in python a
very clever and elegant loop.
What we can do is actually,
this items gives us that
each item in the list
has a key and a value
and we can actually take
two iteration variables.
For aaa, bbb this is
two iteration variables
and if you're coming from
another programming language
this is super cool and
it's a python only feature
I never have seen another
language that's capable
of doing something this
simple and that elegantly.
So what this basically
does is says, we're gonna
simultaneously advance these
two iteration variables.
This is gonna be the key and
the value, the k and the v.
Key and the value it's gonna be Chuck one,
then they're both gonna
advance Fred 42, Jan 100,
and so that means in this
simple loop if we just
print them out we're gonna
get the key value pairs
of course in the order,
and so it's sort of aaa and bbb
simultaneously walk down
these key value pairs.
And so that's really pretty,
and it makes for a very succinct loop
syntax is a little sort of
disquieting when you first see it
but it's a super elegant thing
and you just have to say items,
if you don't say items
you just get the keys
if you say items you
get the key value pairs
and you have to have
two iteration variables
if you don't have two iteration
variables and use items
it'll complain and say
"what are you doing?
I'm giving you two things
and you don't have two
variables to receive them"
so two iteration variables and
items are basically related.
Now, we're going to take a look,
and this is code that I showed
you perhaps many weeks ago
about I said this is little
story about how to read a file
and count all the words in the file.
And now we're back to
it, and at this point
you should understand every
single character of this program
every single concept of the program,
you should literally stare
at this and look at it,
code it, play with it, until
you absolutely understand it.
So let's take a look.
Again I showed you this weeks ago.
So we're gonna ask for a file name,
then we're gonna open the file name,
then we're gonna make an empty dictionary
again this is all stuff
you've done before.
And then we're gonna have
an iteration variable
that's gonna go through
the lines in the file.
So line is gonna go line, line, line,
then we are going to split that line,
each line into words,
chop, chop, chop, chop.
So that's words is the list
of the words in one line
we're inside of a loop
that's gonna go through all of the lines
and then what we're going to do,
is we're going to have the word iteration
iterate through each word in the line.
And then what we're gonna do
is take each word in the line
and we're gonna do this histogram.
This is gonna run not just for every line
but for every word in every line
so we have a nested loop for every line
then we split it and then
we go across the line
so it's almost like a
typewriter where we go
ch-ch-ch-ch-ch ding!
Ch-ch-ch-ch-ch ding! Ch-ch-ch--
and that's what we're doing.
Ch-ch-ch-ch ding!
Ch-ch-ch-ch ding! Ch-ch ding!
So it's like the outer loop
is going down, down, down the lines
and the inner loop is going
across, across, across the words
and eventually we are going
to see in this last line
every single word in the file.
And we're gonna do the
accounts get word plus one
which is our magic
histogram making line that,
if you don't remember what that is
go back a couple of slides
I just talked about it.
At this point in the code,
and it's important to be
able to draw these lines,
at this point in the code
you have the histogram
and it's in the variable counts.
Now, we wanna find the largest one.
We have written loops that
can find the largest in a list
but now we wanna find the largest value
in the key value pairs of a dictionary.
So we're gonna start with
we're gonna know what
the largest count is,
and the largest word that has that count
and we're gonna set 'em both to none
cause we're gonna prime our loop
we have to prime our loop
and we're gonna say to none.
So then we're gonna write
one of these cool things
that say for word comma count,
so word and count are gonna
go through the key value pairs
because we've got items here,
so it's gonna go through
the key value pairs
loop through each key
value, whatever it was.
There could be 1,000,000 words in here,
we're gonna go through every one.
Now what we're gonna do,
is we're going to make sure
the key big count is the
current largest count
we've seen so far, and if it's none
well then we haven't seen
anything or the count
we just read is greater
than the big count so far
we are going to jump in
and this is sort of like
oh this is a new personal best count
for this particular data set.
And so we're gonna remember
the word in big word
and we're gonna remember
the count in big count.
So this is just a max
loop, it's a maximum loop
with the extra thing that
we're recording in addition
to what count is the
largest, what the word
that was associated with
that count recording it.
So again this is the
starting part of the loop
we're gonna do some work,
and then when we exit the bottom of this,
big word is going to be the
word that is the most common
and big count is the number of times.
And so if we run a file we see
"oh in that file to is
the most common word
and it's 16 times."
If we run the clown file,
well "the" is the most
common word and seven.
This could have a very large file
and give you the most common word.
And so that is sort of a
really good application
of dictionaries.
So dictionaries are the
most powerful, well,
they're the most powerful
collection we've seen so far.
It is good to see both
lists and dictionaries
to understand what collections are
they are things inside of python
that can handle more than
one item inside of it
and we'll learn about another collection,
about tuples in a second.
Just understand the get
method because that leads
to very compact code.
Understanding their
various ways to iterate
through dictionaries,
so we've learned a lot.
But in the next section
we will learn even more
and put these together and do some sorting
and do some other stuff,
and really start to see the
real power of dictionaries.
(jazz music plays)