- So now we are going to
write a search engine.
Doing some of the things
we're gonna do page rank
and we're going to visualize it
in a web browser and show the weights.
We're really only going to
do page rank on one page
because you want to have links that
more than one page that points to a page
so that you can figure out which pages
are more or less important
and then visualize it.
We'll run the page rank algorithm
and we'll separately do all this.
So at this point we're going to do
pretty much the web
crawling, the index building,
and the searching we're not
really going to search it.
We're going to visualize the index
but you could write a simple program to do
searches for keywords
and figure which page
was the most likely page for a keyword.
And that would be a fun
additional thing to do.
So the web crawler is this program that
hits a page, pulls down
the html, parses the page,
looks for links, make a
queue of incoming links
that are as yet unretrieved.
And I'm going to do this in
a simple SQLite database.
It starts out with the
database basically starts
with one link as the starting point
and then it retrieves
that page and then you see
the database ends up with
lots of unretrieved pages.
And then it goes back in
and picks a random page,
retrieves that one, and then
it just expands and expands.
This code that I've built
that you're going to play with
only stays on one website.
Otherwise it would go crazy
and of course google doesn't use
a SQLite database running
on your hard drive.
But you'll get the idea.
You'll see this thing
exponentially gain links.
And you'll run it for a while,
pull down a thousand webpages or whatever.
But of course make sure that
you don't violate any terms or conditions
and again I've got some data
sources that you can use.
And they're not rate limited,
but you can also use things like Wikipedia
which I think they sort of discourage you,
or dr-chuck.com which has no rate limit,
or who knows what, right?
So just be careful.
Don't do this on you facebook
and don't do this on google.
Don't get yourself into trouble.
And...
if you're using an internet connection
where you are paying with
bandwidth be careful.
So this is the idea of the web crawler
and this isn't my picture.
This is a classic
picture of a web crawler.
Read a page, parse it, take all the URLs
and stick them in a queue,
grab again and again.
So for us the scheduler's going to do it
as long as... you say,
"oh, do a hundred pages."
Or it runs until it blows up.
And again these processes that have
the network in the loop,
it's really important
that they behave well when they blow up.
And that's why databases are so useful.
Because you can be writing
along to the database
and some random thing
happens and blow your data up
and you start over.
So you're reading these things,
you're storing each page,
building up your storage, etc. etc.
So you just keep on doing that.
And with this program,
you'll be able to retrieve some stuff
then run the page rank and
then you can retrieve some more
and then you can run some more page rank
and you can kinda see how Google
sorta evolves its index over time.
Of course we're so much simpler.
And like I said be careful when you crawl.
You're going to run a crawler
that just goes as fast as it can.
But Google doesn't do that.
It's careful not to
overwhelm any websites.
it's trying to be smart about the use
of your bandwidth on your website.
There is a file,
our code won't bother looking at this.
But there's a file called robots.txt
that real web crawlers look at
and it give a list of the things
you're allowed to look at,
and not allowed to look at.
And so if you go to Google and
you see a search that says,
"We're not allowed to
show you the summary text
"of this page because of the robots.txt."
It's there and you can go
and actually see a robot.txt.
Like on a...
Just go to any website,
it's at the top root
blah blah blah blah blah /robot.txt.
It's not a path, it's not slash this,
slash that, slash something else robots
it's at the very very top of a website.
The index building uses
the page rank algorithm
and the whole goal of the
page rank algorithm is to
figure out which pages
have the most best links.
So having the most links is really easy.
You can just say how many links go to this
but the problem is that
you got to figure out
the value of those links.
And then you have to...
how do you figure out
the value of those links?
By looking at how many
good links comes to it.
So it turns out that
it's an infinite problem.
It's an infinitely difficult
problem to use page rank.
But you can approximate it
and what happens is after a while
it converges to a reasonable value.
And so we're going to run the search index
and each time it runs you're
gonna see that it says,
"How much did these numbers
change?" and what happens is
in the beginning they change very wildly
but quickly they flatten
out. And it has...
The best way to think about...
the page rank...
is... (sighs)
think about how water runs.
Where you have a small little
stream going by a house
and sometimes it rains,
sometimes it's dry,
and sometimes...
And there's a little lake
and the streams always
running and it doesn't
go up and it doesn't go down.
It might go up a little
bit if it rains a lot
but in general there's
sort of a steady state
meaning that whatever water coming in is
about the same as the water going out.
So we think about this
in term of web pages
the value of the links
coming in is roughly the same
as the value of the links going out.
So when that starts to balance the
in and the out value
from each of the nodes
then you've got pretty stable.
And so what Google does is they have a
really relatively stable assessment
of goodness in value of pages
and they use that commute page rank.
And then they throw a few more pages in
and it kind of has to adjust for a while
but it reconverges.
And so this is a calculation
that generally converges
and it does it very wildly
and that's why Google's pretty good at
kind of arriving at the
true value of something.
So let's take a look at
what we're going to do
in this application.
Again, we have a file
that is going to spider the web
and we only have one
database again in this one.
We'll have two databases
in the next one and so
this is spider... is the restartable part
and what we actually do
is we put one URL in,
the starting URL, and then spider walks in
are asks, "Are there
any unretrieved pages?"
And it does that randomly.
It sort of picks among
the unretrieved pages
and says, "Okay, great.
I'll go retrieve that page"
"and I'll parse that page
"and then I'll put in a bunch
of new unretrieved pages."
Okay? As well as the text of that page
and then a bunch of unretrieved pages.
And then it'll go back up and it'll say,
"Oh give me one of the
randomly non-retrieved pages."
and it will retrieve the next page
and pull that page down
and then add to it.
So this is like there's a
page and then a to do list.
And then this one becomes a page
and then adds a few more
things to the to do list.
So the to do list, or
the unretrieved URLs,
grows very rapidly.
And the retrieved ones grow sort of as
you would retrieve them one at a time.
But you've always got this long list.
If you have a really short site
that only has like two links,
if you start at dr-chuck.com/page1.htm
it will go to page two and
then go back to page one
and it will be out of things.
It will have retrieved all of the pages.
So if you had a website
that has no external links
or has a very few pages and
they point to each other
this will run out of things to do.
But if you go to a page like my blog,
or the code... sample stuff
that I have up for you
for spider for testing,
on dr-chuck.net.
It'll run for a very long time.
And you'll have far more pages to retrieve
than pages you have retrieved.
But that's okay, at some
point you can stop this.
Maybe it stops because
you ran out of bandwidth,
or maybe your computer went
down, or who knows what, right?
But it's okay, this is
a restartable process
because it always has some
pages that are retrieved
and some unretrieved pages.
You start it back up,
it picks randomly from
the unretrieved pages.
The database is sort of the
persistent state of your spider
rather than a bunch of dictionaries
or lists inside the python
which go away when the program dies.
And so at some point you have...
Let's just say a few hundred pages in here
and a few thousand unretrieved pages.
You can run the page rank algorithm.
And what the page rank algorithm does
is that it loops through all of the pages
and figures out which pages
are linked to which pages
and then reads the numbers
and then updates the numbers.
And then does that some number of times.
And so this is where the numbers...
All the pages sorta start
out with a goodness of one.
I think this printout is
showing that goodness of one,
and then it changes...
and then the goodness goes to...
some of the goodness goes up to two,
some of it goes to seven, and whatever,
but then it does this over and over
and it uses these numbers
and then they change again.
And so there's a number of time steps
that this page rank runs and you will see,
as the page rank runs,
when I show you the code
you'll see the average sort
of change in these numbers
across all these things
and you'll see that
the average goes down very
rapidly as you get through.
So usually with a few hundred
or a few thousand pages
like a hundred plus times
to run this algorithm
and these numbers have converged.
And that's when you sort of
can begin to trust the numbers.
Now there's this one
program called spreset
which sets all the pages back to one.
So you can start this over.
So if you were to spider for a while,
run sprank for a while, play around,
and then you wanted to spider some more
and start it over, you could say,
"Oh, let's start the page
rank completely over."
Or you could simply take the
new pages and watch it adapt.
Either way this is just a
way to reset all the pages
to have sorta their initial
value of a goodness of 1.0.
So at some point you run this,
this runs really... this
part here runs really slow.
This part runs super fast
like in a blink of an eye.
This one is pretty fast.
And then at some point you got these pages
that have numbers on them.
They have values on the pages.
And there's a couple programs
that allow us to visualize that.
One is the dump which just reads it
and checks to see that it shows up,
the new page rank, the old page rank,
and various of other things.
It shows just a way to dump it
and then there's this thing
that read the whole thing.
You'd say you'd like to do
25 of the top, the best,
it sorts it by page rank and
it produces a java script file
that has just the numbers in it.
And then there is some HTML
and a visualization library called d3.js,
which you can read about,
that when the HTML starts it reads this
and has this nice force direct
layout of the page rank.
And you can hover over
things and you can see
what page rank you've got.
And so...
And so that is the page rank algorithm
that we are going to do.
And up next we'll do the largest
and most complex of these things
and that is the email.
We're going to spider some email
which is about a gigabyte of data. Okay?
(slow jazz music)