- Hello and welcome to chapter 9.
Now we're going to talk
about Python Dictionaries.
Python Dictionaries are probably the thing
that most programmers love
the most about Python,
because they're very powerful.
They're like a little in-memory database.
It's the second of our
kinds of collections
and probably the best collection.
To review what a collection is,
it is a situation where we
are going to have a variable,
like a list, or a dictionary,
and we can put multiple
pieces of information in,
rather than a single piece of information.
And, of course, prior to collections,
we would put something into X
and then we would put
something else into x
and it would be overwritten.
And, now with lists we can
upend things on to the end.
And, so if we compare
lists and dictionaries,
the list is sort of the
organized version of collections.
Everything stays in order,
you add something it
always adds to the end,
you take something it
sort of compacts itself,
it's zero through n-1 where
n is the number of items.
And, so it's very organized,
kind of like a Pringles,
where the potato chips are nicely stacked.
Dictionaries are messier.
You can put things into dictionaries,
there's no real sense of
order in dictionaries,
everything has a key.
So, you sort of throw things in
and they sort of mix
around in there somehow,
and you pull things out based on the key.
It's like you sort of stick a label on it
where you say, okay,
I'm gonna take this thing
and I'm going to put Chuck on it
and I'm going to take
these sunglasses with the Chuck label
and I'm gonna throw it
in to the dictionary
and I'm gonna like,
hey give me back Chuck,
then I'm like oh, here's your sunglasses.
Cause, you mark everything,
this is like the key,
this is the value.
I took a pair of sunglasses
and I threw it in.
So, it's kind of like a purse
or it's sort of like a mess.
So the idea is, you have these labels
that you put on everything
that you're going to throw in.
Like, I'm gonna put, oops
it won't stick to my keys.
What else have I got here?
Then I stick a label on my pen.
Chuck label and I'm going to store my pen
in my dictionary with a Chuck label.
And so, it's like having a
purse or a bag or a backpack,
where you have things labeled
and you can throw things in and label them
and you can shout into your bag and say,
give me the calculator, give me the candy,
or whatever it is that
you have labeled them.
You have to come up with the labels
and then you can use the
labels to get things back out.
And, like I said they're
probably the most powerful thing
and they're basically a concept
that's generally referred
to as Associative Arrays,
which means they're like lists
but they have these keys.
And, the associative means,
the association between a key and a value.
Where is, in the list, there's
a position in the value.
A position is less
powerful and less flexible.
Most modern programming languages have
this notion of associative arrays.
If they don't, they're sort of unpopular,
because once you get using them,
you're like, whoa they're so powerful.
If you ever find yourself in a language
that doesn't' have them, you'll freak out.
They can have different
names like, property maps
or Hash Maps or Property Bags,
depending on the language you're using,
but they all are the same thing.
They're key value pairs.
So, the idea of a dictionary is that,
or the idea of any collection,
is putting more than one thing in.
And, then the difference is that
you have ways of indexing it.
So, this basically line says,
let's make ourselves a dictionary
just like we constructed an empty list.
And, I want to start
twelve into this dictionary
and I want to label it, money.
And so, on the left hand
side, when we use this money,
that's the label that
we're going to give it.
And so, twelve is being
placed in the dictionary
that's like taking the twelve,
throwing into the dictionary
with the label of money.
I can't, yeah.
Three is going in with the label of candy.
And, seventy-five is
going in with tissues.
We say, what's in there?
And, there's no order to it
and sometimes it even,
the order can even change
inside of the dictionary.
Although, there are more advanced versions
of dictionaries that
maintain some kind of order,
but for now, let's just not worry
about the ordering of them.
Um, if we say, what's in there?
You say, well there's
three things in there.
There is twelve, seventy-five, and three,
and stored under the keys
money, tissues, and candy respectively.
We can ask, using the index operator,
what is purse of candy,
and that's like saying,
hey, give me back candy
and out comes the number
three which is that.
And, we can update stuff, so we can say
go grab the candy version
and add two to it.
Make five and then store
that back into candy.
And, so now we see that
candy has been up to,
set up to be five.
And, um, and so, if you
look at the difference
between lists and dictionaries,
They both can have new
items added to them.
We haven't talked a lot about deleting,
but items can be deleted from them.
The difference is the indexing mechanism,
how we look things up, how we store things
and how we look things up.
So, we make an empty list,
we make an empty dictionary.
We add twenty-one to the end
and we add 183 to the end,
and we ask it, and it says oh,
position zero is twenty-one,
position one is 183.
And, we don't see the positions
when you print it out,
because it's sort of implicit.
Here we're going to
mark twenty-one with age
and stick it in, and mark 182
with course and stick it in.
And, then we're going to print it out
and there we got course and age mapped.
And, we can add twenty-three
and stick it back in age
and that overwrites,
so the twenty-one
becomes the twenty-three.
We can do the same thing in a list,
except we say lists of zero,
because in lists the indexing is position,
and so this twenty-one
becomes twenty-three.
And, again, you just look at them
and you can think of each
of these as pretty much
doing roughly the same thing,
except the indexing mechanism.
The values are the same
but the keys are different,
so in lists, the keys
are always the position
and you don't get to assign those,
other than the fact the order
in which you put them in,
implicitly assigns a position
and in dictionaries the key is a string.
You can actually use other things.
I use strings a lot in this lecture
but that kind of keeps things simple
until you get good at it.
Um, you can actually use
numbers as the dictionary index
or dictionary keys, if you want.
But, the values are things you put in
and manage in those dictionaries.
So, we can, just like lists
we have dictionary literals
and what's nice about
dictionary literals is that
they use the exact same
syntax as the printout.
And, so it starts with a curly brace,
ends with a curly brace,
then has a series of key, colon, value,
key colon value,
key colon value.
And, this is sort of the
associative array bit,
we're associating one with the key Chuck,
we're associating forty-two with key Fred,
we're associating Jan and a hundred.
Then we print it out it kind
of looks exactly the same.
So, the print statements
in Python are nice,
in that you ask what's in a thing,
you show the stuff and it
shows you in the syntax
that if you type that in to Python
that would be how you do a constant.
And, if you just say, empty array,
you see me also do dict,
this is constructor,
where you say make a new empty dictionary.
This is an empty dictionary constant.
These two things are pretty
much the exact same thing.
This is a shortcut to doing this.
The empty curly braces is a shortcut
to do the construction.
So, up next we're going
to talk about sort of,
one of the really common
applications of dictionaries.
And, that is counting.
(slow music)