- So now what we wanna
do is use some of these
newfound skills in some
more practical applications
of regular expressions.
So let's go back to the way
we first tore apart strings
and look at the situation
where if you recall
we just wanted the host name, right?
This is an email address
and we're interested
in the host name.
So we have this string, and
we go find the at, right?
The find looks up and tells
us the at is at position 21.
And then what we do is say
okay, let's look beyond there
to the space and that tells us the space
is in position 31.
And then we're saying
we can extract starting
beyond the at sign, up to
but not including the space
by saying atpos plus one
colon space position.
And when we get that,
now we have to have a thing that decides
to only look at this on from lines,
but then it can print out the host
that is extracting of this information.
So that was one way
that we did that, right?
One way we did it.
The next way we did this was
the double split pattern, right?
So we said, okay let's take this line,
let's break it into
words, based on spaces.
That's what words is.
So that's zero, one, two,
three, four, five, six.
And then we know that the
email address on lines
that start with from
space is the second one
so we pull out email address
which pulls this bit out into email.
And then we're gonna split that again
based on the at sign.
So we're gonna split this part
again based on that at sign
so it splits right there
and then this becomes
the zero and one in pieces.
And then pieces sub one is that host.
And if we print that out, we get the host.
So that's the double split pattern.
Nice thing about that is you
don't have to keep track,
the little plus one's kind of annoying
to use the space position.
That previous one, that's
just hard to remember.
I've written this code way
too many times in my career
and I've made mistakes,
and I have to debug it
every single time and I
print all these numbers out.
I'm like did I get it right?
No, I did it in Python, I did
it in Java, I did it in C.
Wait a second, did it differently.
So this is a lot cleaner.
I mean I can write this every time
and I know it's gonna work every time.
I barely even need to test this
code 'cause it's so obvious.
So double split is another
way of extracting stuff,
but if we look at this thing
with the regular expression,
we can say, oh okay.
Let's use a regular expression to do this.
So we'll start looking through the string.
We'll start so by saying hey, let's look
until we find an at sign.
Then let's start extracting
with the parentheses
and then once we have found the at sign,
let's look for non-blank characters.
This is a set of characters.
This caret as the first
one means not a blank.
So that's another way to do non-blank.
Not a blank, set of characters which are
everything but blank.
That's what this little bit is saying.
Star means zero more times which means
it's gonna run, run, run, run,
run until it finds a blank
which is gonna stop it.
The greediness is what
keeps pushing it, right?
This is a greedy match.
That asterisks is greedy because
there's no question mark after it.
And so that does go and
starts at the at sign
with the parenthesis, goes to the space,
and that's the end parenthesis
and that's what prints out.
Now Y is gonna be a list.
There's a one item list
that has the string in it
that we're looking for
but you just go sub zero
to get that guy right out of there.
Okay, so that's sorta the
regular expression version of it,
but we can make this a
more fine tuned thing.
So we can say, look we
also wanna pick the line
and we wanna know if there are
if we don't get that
line, we wanna skip it.
If we do get the line, we
wanna extract the data.
And we can do this all in a
single, regular expression.
So again, we say start from
the beginning of the line,
and it's gotta be a
from followed by a space
and then followed by
any number of characters
dot star, followed by an at sign
and so this has to match.
We see a space.
Then we're gonna have
any number of characters
and then we're gonna see an at sign
and then we're going to start extracting.
Then we're gonna go non-blank,
non-blank, non-blank,
up-blank, and extracting,
and out that comes.
And this has the advantage
of the previous one
in that that makes it much more precise.
There, if we look at the previous one,
while it works on good lines,
it might actually trigger
on lines that we actually
don't wanna see, so this
allows us to refine it
so it only actually does this
to lines that we care about.
So it's sort of a both and if statement
and a splitting extracting,
going on all at the same time.
By having a bigger string
that we're matching
than we're extracting.
It's a way to kinda clean up your data.
So here is a simple program
that we're going to just
put all this together and
actually accomplish something.
And so we're gonna read through
and look for lines in a file
that have this form.
And we're gonna extract this number
and then we're going to compute
the maximum of this, okay?
And so we're gonna extract this number
and then convert it to a
float and compute the maximum.
So, you know, we're gonna open a file.
We're gonna write a four loop.
We're gonna strip.
So we're gonna do this for
every line of the file,
but the first thing we
wanna do is not get light.
We're gonna discard all the lines
except ones that have this.
So our regular expression
is look for lines
that start with X dash
DSPAM dash Confidence colon.
So that's a pretty strong match.
If that's not there, we're
not gonna get anything.
And then there's a space, there's a space.
And then start extracting,
and then go as long, one
or more digits and dots.
That's a single character
and that's one or more,
and then stop extracting.
So that says start extracting da da da da
greedy, greedy, greedy,
greedy, stop extracting.
And so that's what we're going to get.
Now, if the line doesn't have this,
and it's missing in some way,
whether it's this prefix or this number.
If the number's missing,
it's gonna fail too.
We're going to get back
a list, an empty list.
So the first thing you
have to do is check to see
if you actually got a match.
So you say if the number
of items in the list
len of stuff is not
equal to one, continue.
And so this is the skip all
the lines that don't match.
Skip, skip, skip, skip, skip, skip.
So there could be thousands
of lines that don't match
but then when this match
hits, it's gonna come down
and fall through, right?
So that, most of the lines will skip up
but then when we actually get one,
and we know instantly that we've got one
and stuffs of zero because
that's what we extracted
is this number.
And we can take the floating point of it
when you pinned it to our list.
We made a list to store 'em.
That runs, the list grows.
Choo choo choo choo choo choo.
And then we just say
what was the largest one.
And so you can run this and see that.
We have an escape character
and the whole idea is that
sometimes all these
little special characters
that make a lot of sense to us,
we actually wanna search for.
So what if we wanna
search for a dollar sign?
Well we just prefix it with the backslash.
And that just means this
is a real dollar sign.
So backslash dollar is a real dollar sign.
So this says, I would like a dollar sign
followed by one or more digits or dots.
And so that's going to match a dollar sign
followed by one or more digits.
Dots are okay, this is a set, remember?
Zero dash nine or dot, that's a set
of the list of legit characters.
This is a range of characters,
that's a shortcut to
how it'd make the set.
You could make it be zero,
one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine, dot,
or zero dash nine and it assumes that.
And that's one or more so then stops
because this is a space.
It's greedy matching.
Then it pulls this out.
So that's kinda why greedy
has to be the default
because otherwise if it
wasn't doing greedy matching,
Oops, come back, come back.
If it wasn't doing greedy matching,
it would
If it wasn't doing greedy
matching, it would stop here
because it would find a dollar sign,
non-greedy would find a dollar sign
and one character and then
it would give us dollar one
rather than dollar ten.
So, in summary, regular
expressions are a cryptic
but powerful language and
they're an acquired taste.
I think that I bet eventually
you'll find them fun
even though on your first impression,
you might not think that they're so fun.
(rock music)