- So, definite loops
use the four key word.
And the idea of a definite
loop is it's going to loop
through some set of things.
It might be a set of lines in a file.
It might be a set of
characters in a string.
It might be set of strings
in a list of strings.
But whatever it is, it's sort of gonna run
a finite number of times,
depending on the thing
that it's looping through.
And we like this.
And it's an easier way to construct it,
and actually don't have to
deal with iteration variable.
The four loop includes
a mechanism to construct
the iteration variable for us.
So it's definite loops iterate
through the members of a set.
So, here's a very simple four
loop and so you see the four
key word.
And in is also a key word.
And the iteration variable is
something we put right there.
This I is declared.
This "I" is like an assignment statement.
And "I" is going to take
on successive values.
So, "I" is going to be five
the first time though the loop.
Then "I" is going to
be four the second time
through the loop.
Third, two, one.
So, "I" is gonna be assigned
five different times
to five different values.
And then the loop is going to run.
It's gonna run once with
five, once with four,
once with three, once with
two and once with one.
So this block of code, we have contracted,
say executed five times with these values
of "I".
"I" is that iteration variable.
"I" is that thing changing through
each iteration of the loop.
So, that's why this prints out
five, four, three, two, one
and then when it's done it finishes it.
So, this is a much more direct
syntax for looping five times
and setting an iteration variable.
You kind of all combine
it into this one thing.
All into one thing, so it's quite nice.
So, you don't have to be going
through a list of numbers
there's all kinds of things
that we can iterate through
with four and by the way,
while I'm sitting here,
don't name my variable "friends"
because that's a list of strings
and "friend" which is
the iteration variable.
I'm using singular and plural
because it helps you read it.
Python doesn't understand
singular and plural.
Just because you say
"friends", doesn't mean Python
knows it's a list.
Python does know it's a
list, but it doesn't know
by the name of the variable
I've chosen, that's your basic
mnemonic variable warning.
These are cool variable
names, but I don't want you
to get confused by them.
So, you can loop through a variable,
so we're gonna take this
list, the three strings
and stick it in friends
and so "friend" is going to
iterate through that.
So the first time through,
"friend" is going to be Joseph,
2nd time through it's gonna
be Glenn, 3rd time through
it's gonna be Sally.
So, that just says, run
this code, the indented code
three times, each time the
variable friend takes on
a successive version that's
in the friends array.
So, it says Happy Birthday
Joseph, Glenn, Sally
and then we come out of
the loop and we print done.
If we try to draw a picture
of what this is really doing.
The four loop is actually
doing a whole bunch of stuff
that we would have to do with
maybe separate statements
in the wild loop.
First, it decides how many
times to run the loop.
So it's answering the done
question, which way do we go.
And it is also then moving "I" ahead.
It's managing the iteration variable.
If you go back to, it's
initializing it too,
if you go back to the while loop,
we have n=0, whilen
greater than zero, n=n-1.
So we had like three
lines to control the loop,
to manage the iteration variable.
Where with the four loop,
we don't have to do that.
And so, that's all taken care
of, so that basically says
you know, by you using
a four loop are we done?
No, we have five things to work well.
So, out of the first one, run it.
But we're not done,
because we've got one more
set, to the second one, third
one, fourth one, fifth one,
and now we're done and that
is all handled in a single
line of code
and that includes the iteration variable
and the set of things that
we're gonna iterate through.
I really like the word "in".
It is mathematically, it
reminds me of the set theory
where you say this is a member of this set
or the four each.
Math isn't important here,
but if you do know math,
the vertical bar means such that.
As a member of this
set, that kind of stuff.
A member of this set.
I'll erase the math stuff,
so we don't over math.
But it's like, four each
of the values in the set,
5,4,3,2,1.
Run this loop, setting
the iteration variable "I"
to the members of that
set, so in reminds me
for those of us who are
math oriented, a really
nice concept in mathematics.
Now, you could think of
this as sort of this looping
structure where the four
loop and this is pretty much
how it actually runs
inside the computer, right?
Where it initializes it
"I" it runs this, runs this
thing five times and executes.
That's one way to think about it,
but you could also think
about it in a somewhat more
abstract way and think of
it as all we're really doing
is we have a contract
with Python that says,
"We're supposed to run
this code five times
and I's supposed to be five,
four, three, two and one.
So, you can imagine this
might be what's going on.
The four loop sets I
to five, runs our code.
to four, runs our code.
The four loop sets I to
three, runs our code.
The four loop sets I
to two, runs our code.
The four loop sets I to
one, and runs our code.
All we know, is our code ran five times
and by contract, each
successive time we'll get
a different value for
I and the value for I
is taken from this set.
And so this is just one
way to think about it,
to say to yourself, "Oh,
yeah, this is one way to think
about it as it's actually
how it really works."
But this is also kind of
logically the contract that Python
is making for us.
So, up next, we're gonna talk about
taking this notion of doing
something to a lot of items
but accomplishing something with that.
And I call these loop idioms.
(slow jazz music)