- Hello, and welcome to our final chapter
Retrieving and Visualizing Data.
In this chapter, we are going to basically
bring this all together,
databases, web services,
code, loops, logic
and we're going to solve a problem that is
a multi step data analysis.
We're going to find some
data on the internet
might be HTML, might
be an API or whatever,
and we're going to write
a relatively slow process
that's going to pull data slowly,
cause these are all rate limited,
this is a slow and restartable process,
so you can restart this
and what we're going to
do is we have a database
that's going to hold the
data that we're pulling
and so this might take
several days actually,
if you're really have to do it
and then you'll build up
your data in your database
and then what you tend to do is,
you tend to produce two databases,
one is kind of a raw
database, that you know is
really it's, all of it's data columns are
aimed at helping you figure
out what you've gotta retrieve
yet and what you haven't retrieved yet.
So that's kind of a
crawling, spidering process.
And then you find that the
data is kinda nasty and ugly
and you find that before you're
going to do any analysis,
you probably want to clean and process it.
So you, in a lot of these
you're going to go from
a raw database to a clean one.
And this is going to be really large.
And this is going to be really small.
And you're going to do this
sort of once but slowly
and you'll do this as
many times as you need,
changing this program,
cleaning the data up,
over and over and over again
and then you'll end up
with really clean data
and it's relatively small
and you might run programs
that'll loop through this
to do visualizations or analysis
or somethings or whatever.
You'll actually sort of use this database
as a source of information.
So that's the basic pattern
of what we're going to work with.
Now, this is what I call
personal data mining
and if you're going to do this seriously,
python is used in lots
of data mining activities
but if you're going to do
data mining seriously with
really, really large data sets.
We're doing small to
medium size data sets,
as you might do for sort of for
an individual personal
research versus like
an organization research where you're
processing the logs of a web
server or something like that
and there's lots and lots
of wonderful technology
and what's really cool
is, this technology just
keeps getting better and
better cause the whole
data mining, data analysis,
natural language processing
field is just so hot right
now, it's so awesome.
We're going to keep it simple and do stuff
for ourselves for now.
And I gave you a bunch of sample code
that's going to make it so
you can adapt the sample code
to solve the problems
that you'll need to solve.
So like I said, this is more
of a programming exercise.
Data mining might be a lot more complex.
If you're doing simple research,
this might actually model
what you do pretty well.
So the first thing that
we're going to do is
what's called, use the Google's
Json API for Geo-coding.
And there are two versions of this.
One version requires a key and
one version doesn't require a key.
Google used to make all
this data available for free
with just a rate limit
but now they're making,
increasingly requiring the key.
So I give you code in the zip
file that kind of does both.
If you really want to do
something in production of
taking user entered places
and names and getting
precise latitude, longitude coordinates,
so you can produce a nice
little Google Map like this.
Since Google has made a rate limited API,
I've actually pre-spidered
a copy of the Google data
and I have my own sort of fake Google API
and so you can do your
assignments and test all your code
using my fake API which
has no rate limits and has no problems
but it's only a limited set of the data.
So this is the basic process
and it's one of those things that
it follows that basic
personal data modeling,
personal data mining pattern.
And so here's this API which
is either Google or me,
I've got my own doctor
chuck version of this
drchuck.net version of this,
and there is an input
queue of the locations.
So this is the user data
where they just put in
the name of where they think they live,
The University of Tubagan or something,
so this is the queue of
the things that are to be
retrieved and in my case,
when I built this map for the first time,
there was like 15,000 and
it took me days to get this
and so it would stop
and so what I would do
is, I would, you know,
read the first one into this geoload.py,
check to see if I already
had it in my database,
if I didn't already
have it in my database,
I would go into the API
and pull the data down
and I would put it in the database
and then I'll go to the next one,
and the next one and next one
and so I might get a
thousand in my database
and then it blows up or I'm
told I can't go any further.
So I wait 24 hours, I start it up
and it reads the first 1,000
and says, oh they're all
in the database already
and then it starts at 1,001.
And then it adds that and
adds that until it stops
and so it took me several
days of processing
to get this data right.
Now, I didn't have a
separate cleaning process
cause this data is pretty simple,
I was pulling out the Json and
latitude and longitude etc.
So I didn't have to do
two separate processes
to clean this data up.
It was clean enough right as I pulled it.
Cause I was talking to an API.
If you're talking to an
HTML sometimes it gets
nasty and ugly.
So then I wrote this program
that just reads through it,
it just does a select and
reads through the stuff
and it prints out some summary information
and tells you what to do.
It also prints out, and
you'll see this pattern,
cause you know I'm visualizing
using browser's HTML
and this happens to be
using the Google Maps API.
And putting all the data in
a little Java script file
so these end up being assignment
statements in java script.
You can take a look at that file.
And all the data shows up
as assignment statements
in the Java script and
when this HTML loads,
it reads this file and
puts up all those pins
as long as you have access to
the end browser Java script API.
So the next thing we're
going to talk about
is pagering which is spidering now HTML.
We talked a lot about this,
spider HTML, get some links
and so up next we're
going to actually build
a real database, full
featured, search engine
using pagering.