- So now that we've carefully
constructed our
relationships in the tables
we need to reconstruct the
data to show our users.
You can kind of see how you would
go pull this stuff together,
but there's the wonderful capability
in relational databases called "join"
that brings this all back together.
We have done this for
efficiency of storage,
efficiency of scanning, etc.
But we do need to reverse
these foreign keys at times.
The database software will
do this for us automatically.
The join operation basically
is a way to specify
in a select statement
that you want to pull data
out of more than one tables.
And then specifying using what's called
the "on" clause exactly how
you want that data pulled out.
So here we go.
We already have a table.
An album table to the artist
table and the foreign key.
We want to in effect pull data
from both the album and the artist.
The album title and the artist name.
We want to show that.
So we are going to say "Select",
which is the same select statement.
Here's a little different syntax.
This is the list of fields.
This is table, dot, fields.
So it's the album title
and the artist, dot, name.
Comma there.
From the album...
I always start with where
the little arrow starts from.
Album joined with.
So that is going to walk
down this connection
from album to artist.
Album joined with artist.
Don't say "with", I just say it.
"On", and then this is
the conditions upon which
that join is going to happen.
When the album's artist_id,
which is this column here,
matches, this of that as
"is equal to" or matches,
the artist_id.
So it only connects the rows here
when there is a match
between these two tables.
If we look at this and we see that
this one matches this one and
this one matches that one.
So it's the "join" connects conditionally
and it connects when the
"on" clause is satisfied.
When this whole join
runs this is what we get.
You select all this stuff.
Now this is an abstraction.
Are you writing a loop,
are you doing two nested loops?
How exactly are you bringing
all this data together?
We don't care about that.
That's the beauty of SQL.
That's the beauty of how
we do this in a database.
Now if we can just run this command.
So let's grab this command.
"Select track title, genre name
from "track", join "genre",
that exact query.
Case of keywords doesn't matter.
We go over here and we run this as SQL.
We run it, we get...
Oops, I got too far.
Let's do this one.
Let's do that one there.
Select artist name.
I have to add that one
to my little cheat sheet.
The next time you see the
cheat sheet it'll be right.
The title.
This is coming from one table
and that's coming from another table.
So that's one.
Here is something we can do
that gives us a little
more detail on that.
We can say, "So this is
where the connection is."
You can think of the join as
sort of spreading one table
and connecting it to the other table.
So what we're going to show
here is, it's exactly the same.
Only thing we're going to do is
we're going to add these two columns
so you can see where the match happens.
This is one table.
This is another table.
These are the columns in
common, even though they're not.
They're the columns that match.
This is where the "on"
clause is happening.
We have taken this table,
joined with this table
on these two things
connecting with each other.
You can almost in some language,
in some variants of SQL,
this would even be "where" clause.
You connect these two rows,
but only connect them when
those two numbers match.
You can see if we run this.
I'll just run this.
Again, you just see this
is where it connects.
Now, interestingly, we
can see what happens
and what the purpose of the "on" clause is
if we omit it.
So this is exactly the
same as that previous query
except there's no "on" clause.
It's select all four of those fields
from the track, join with the genre.
So it's basically taking the track table
and the genre with a
join, but no "on" clause.
So it's not filtering for matches.
This is a match. This is a match.
That's a match. That's a match.
But we don't have an "on" clause
so the matchingness doesn't matter.
So you're gonna get all
possible combinations
and literally if there we 10 on one side
and 30 on the other side
you would get 300 rows
in that join.
So it would be all combinations
except the "on clause
reduces the combinations.
You might think, "Whoa,
this is really inefficient."
I will say that's what
my first reaction was
when I first saw this,
but it's not inefficient.
That's the beauty of abstraction.
That's the beauty of SQL.
You say, "Do it!"
and it just figures that out.
Let me grab this and you will see
that we can run this one as well.
That kind of gives you why
the "on" clause is important.
Because now we have a whole
bunch of these things.
The "on" clause just filters that out.
So if we just add the "on" clause back in
then that would only show the ones
we showed on the previous slide.
So that's why the "on"
clause is important.
The join is like all possible combinations
of all pairs of rows
between these two tables.
"On" is only where these two things match.
You might think that it's inefficient,
but the "on" clause turns out to be
the way it becomes efficient.
Okay.
So now we're going to do the same thing
where we're just going to take
the track title and the genre
and gonna connect that together.
We select this.
We need to join from one table.
Join to the genre table
with an "on" clause.
We're gonna make those connections.
The only thing we're gonna look at
is the title and the genre name.
Oops.
And then run that.
So we got the title and genre name.
The thing you'll notice
is for the first time
we now have replication of string data
in the vertical dimension.
That's okay.
Because the data is not
replicated in the database.
The data is now replicated
as a result of the join.
So we are going to reconstruct
what the user wants to see,
which the user originally,
all the way back at the beginning,
wanted to see the duplicated information
in the vertical axis.
But now we're reconstructing it.
We didn't waste the space or
performance in our database,
but we still have to show them.
So now the next thing we're
gonna do is a monster.
We're gonna reconstruct
across all four tables.
You might think, "This is really hard."
And sure, it's gonna be a little tricky,
but as long as you follow
the naming convention
and the naming convention makes sense.
We're gonna do a select from
the track's title, the artist's,
the album's title, and the genre name.
From the track join genre, join the album,
join the artist.
The joins follow the little arrows.
And then the "on" clause
qualifies each of those arrows,
when to follow the arrow.
Then this becomes pretty easy.
It's a foreign key that tracks genre ID.
That's a foreign key.
Equals Genre.id.
That's primary key, that's a foreign key
because I name it that way
and I know this goes to that genre table
because I name it that way.
And track's album ID is
equal to the album's ID.
Foreign key, primary key.
And album's artist ID
is equal to artist's ID.
After a while you can
type these pretty fast
as long as you follow a naming convention
and you know the naming convention.
So this looks like it's hard to do,
but after a while it's
really just a pattern.
So let's go ahead and run that one.
It will, assuming we've
done everything right,
replicate all the data.
So, there's all kinds of vertical
data now being replicated.
Every column has vertical data.
Again, it's not in the database.
The select and the join are
reconstructing vertical data
as it needs to be shown to the user.
And so if you've been following along,
(laughs) probably a
couple hours later now.
We started with a picture
that was a mock up
of what we wanted our user
interface to look like
and it had vertical stuff.
We're like, "Ah, we can't put
that in a database model!"
And then we carefully
built a database model
that didn't have the data.
And then we're like, "Ah,
we gotta reconstruct it!"
So we used join to reconstruct it.
After all that we went here
with a clean little
model with four tables,
all beautifully connected together
and then we had to join
it all back together.
Join reconstructs it.
Again, the key is the
storage is efficient,
the scanning is efficient,
and we still use the join
to produce the output
that we ultimately want
with all the vertical
replication that our users
really want to see.
One more kind of relationship.
That was called a
one-to-many relationship.
That was actually three
one-to-many relationships.
The other major relationship
is what's called
a many-to-many relationship.
(heavy metal music)