- So now we're gonna talk to you
about one of the common
applications of dictionaries
and that is making histograms.
It's counting the frequency of things.
And so if you think of a histogram as
you know, it's a little graph
and there is A, how
many A's, how many B's,
and now many C's, and there's
a histogram that says,
oh there's this many of
that and this many of that.
And these are like buckets,
these are frequencies
and this is how many times it happens.
So a histogram.
But we're gonna do this thing
where we're gonna count people's names
and we're gonna kinda
count how many that we see.
The interesting thing
that we're gonna solve,
just like many of the
things in the computer,
is we can't just sort of look at the data,
we gotta look at the data iteratively,
one piece of data at a time.
So I'm gonna give you a little problem.
I'm gonna show you a series
of names, one at a time,
and I want you to count, for each name,
make a little bucket,
and then keep counting
how many things for each
of the different names.
You'll notice that you
have to start with one
and then you move across.
So just watch this and tell me how many,
how many, what's the most common name
of the set of names I'm about to show you
and how many do we see.
(classical music)
So how many, what was the most common name
and how many times did you see it?
That's the question.
Now, here comes the reveal.
So for humans, it's so much easier for you
to just look at this, and you think
how did my brain look at
that, and you're like,
okay what is pretty common?
Oh, maybe...
Maybe cwen is common.
Oh, cwen, cwen, cwen, no.
Maybe zhen is common.
Do one, two, three, four, yeah.
Anybody else, marquard's got three,
csev...
So you'll notice how our
minds, without computers,
we just sort of bounce, branch and bound.
We have hypothesis and then
we decide, oh, it's zhen.
That's it, and there's four of them.
Now, how did your brain think about this
as we were going through
them one at a time?
Well, my guess is if you
really had to do this a lot,
you would make a little picture like this.
Then what you would do
is if you saw a new name,
XYZ, you'd add it to the list
and give it a tick mark of one,
and then if you saw csev again,
you'd give that a tick mark,
and if you saw XYZ again,
you'd make a tick mark,
and then you'd make,
you keep adding to
these tick marks, right?
And that's how you would do it,
and you wouldn't, like many
of the things we do in a loop,
you wouldn't really know
what the most common was one
until the end, and then you'd sorta
take a look at these
numbers, and you say, okay,
that's the most common number,
and then you'd be done.
But you have to watch 'em one at a time.
You can't just bounce around.
And so that's how we're
gonna use dictionaries
to achieve that.
Again, instinctively as humans,
we just look at the stuff,
but if you had a million things,
you'd probably wanna
write a Python program
and use dictionaries.
And so this is the idea,
and there's two basic things that happen.
One is the first time you see a name,
you gotta say, is this name there already?
If it's there already, you
really just wanna add one to it.
That's the adding of a tick.
Or, you wanna see for the first time,
you know, blah blah blah
blah blah, and give it a one.
And so you can use the name as the key,
and then one is the value, and
then first time you see cwen,
you stick one in there.
And so at this point,
inside the dictionary,
sorta dynamically adding as
soon as it sees a new name,
it adds another slot in here.
But then if you see the same
name again, like cwen again,
then you end up with a one,
add one to it and so it's two,
and so at that point, cwen is two.
And so you can see how you
can both extend the dictionary
by encountering a new name,
or adding when you see a name
that you've already seen before.
The problem with dictionaries
is, like everything in Python,
there are rules about
what you can and can't do,
and one of the, I think,
kinda frustrating things
about dictionaries is that you can't just
look for a key that doesn't exist.
So this is a fresh, brand new dictionary.
We do a constructor there,
and we print out sub-csev, and boom,
it blows up, and that's bad.
But we can solve this by the in operator.
The in operator we've
used in the for loops,
we've used it in the lists,
we've used it in strings.
So that is a question.
It's saying, is csev in ccc?
Well, this is this empty one,
and so it is, no it is not.
Csev is not in ccc.
And so not using this in operator,
we can avoid the traceback.
We can say, if it's not there, put it in.
If it is there, add one to it.
And that leads us to this bit of code.
And that is the kind of
code that we're gonna build,
this is a histogram code, okay?
And so this is gonna have
name as our iterator.
Names, sorry, I made
them singular and plural.
That's nice, but...
So name is gonna be
csev, cwen, csev, zqian.
Now normally we'll be
reading this form a file,
but for now we'll keep it easy.
We're gonna go through this.
And we're gonna have
counts as our dictionary.
So that starts out empty,
and we're gonna do a simple
if then else every time through the loop.
If the name we're looking at
is not in the dictionary
already as the key,
then set it to be one.
If it's not, go get the
old value, counts of name,
and then add one to it
and stick it back in.
So this is, this line right here, is new,
adding a new thing, and
this line right here
is adding some things to existing things.
And you do this long enough,
you start with an empty one,
and you do this long enough,
at the very end it will
print out the histogram
that you're looking for,
histogram you're lookin' for.
And so you say, oh we've seen csev twice,
zqian once and cwen twice.
And so that's the idea.
And so this can run a
million times if you want.
Now, this notion of checking
to see if a key exists,
and doing one thing if it doesn't exist
and doing another thing if it does exist
is such a common practice
that the dictionary object
has this method called get,
that collapses these
four lines into one line.
And so the idea is,
you're gonna do one thing
if it's in there, and
you're gonna retrieve
the current thing,
otherwise you're gonna pick
a default value.
In this case we'll pick one.
I mean, pick zero.
This is like the default, right,
meaning what is not there.
And if you say counts, now
counts is a dictionary,
.get, that's like
string.upper, that's a method,
you give it a key and then a default,
and if the key exists, you
get back what's in the key,
if the key doesn't exist,
you get the default, okay?
And with no traceback.
This works, so the best
way to think about this is,
those four lines are
equal to that one line,
cause x is either gonna be
whatever was in there before,
if it exists, or it's going to be zero.
Now the nice thing about zero
is the next thing we're gonna do
is we're gonna add one to it,
so that's gonna get us to one.
So, collapsing that
loop that we saw before,
collapsing that loop, we can
make it just a one line loop,
and this will become an idiom.
This will become something
that you will get used to
and you will use over
and over and over again,
and after a while, right
now you're looking at it,
boy-o-boy, that's a lot of syntax
and semi-colons and whatever.
After a while, you just type this
and not even think about it.
It's an idiom.
It's basically, included in this idiom,
is how to both create new
entries in dictionaries
and update existing entries
by adding one to them.
So, everything else in this is the same.
Name is gonna go through
these five values,
and we're gonna say counts of name equals
counts.get(name, 0)+1.
And so if, for example, this
already has a one in it,
then this is gonna be
one plus one becomes two.
If it's not, it's gonna be
zero plus one equals two,
and so this is the idea of, if
new, set it to one, not zero,
set it to one, 'cause the
first time you see something,
the count should be one, not zero.
So that's why we make this default.
Now the get can be used for anything.
It just so happens that
zero is a common default,
because it's really common
that we're using this
to basically make a histogram, right?
A little histogram of A, B, C, right?
And so we need to make a D,
but then the histogram
has to start at one.
So that's basically the
simplified counting with get,
and there's a lot of things
that we're going to do
inside of Python that do
have to do with frequencies
and how many times have
certain things happened
and this pattern is a really good pattern
to absolutely know.
(classical music)