- Hello and welcome to
Chapter 5 Loops and Iteration.
Now we're going to work on our fourth
basic pattern of sequential,
conditional,
store and reuse,
and loops and iteration.
And this is the one where
we teach the computer
how to do things a lot.
We can tell it to do
something a million times.
And so that's where we get
the doggedness of computers.
Or the fact that they're so
good at doing work for us
because we can set 'em off to a task
and they'll do it until it's done.
So here's a very simple loop.
A very simple loop.
(dishes rattling)
Let's put the coffee over here.
The key word that we're gonna start using
is the while loop.
We're also gonna use the for later on.
And the while loop functions
very much like an if statement.
The while starts it
and then this is just
like an if statement.
It's a question that leads
to a true or a false answer
and then there's a colon
and then there's an indented block
and then we use the de-indent
to determine how long the loop is.
And so this print is de-indented
so that indicates the end of the loop.
And so at some level,
what's going to happen here,
is it's just gonna run and if this is true
it's gonna run this code
and if it's false it's
gonna skip the code.
In that way it functions like an if.
The place that it doesn't
function like an if
is after it's run the code once
it goes up and then
asks the question again.
And so you can think of it going back up
kind of to the top of the while loop
and then re-asking the question.
Like okay is this going to run again?
And then it's going to do
that some number of times
and then it's going to finish
and so that's the loop.
That's the iteration.
And we're going to make a variable,
construct very carefully,
a variable that we call
the iteration variable.
And that's n.
And it's a variable that's gonna change,
and it's our way of running the loop
but not running the loop forever.
So let's just run this.
We come in and it's five.
Is n greater than zero,
yes it is, so we're gonna run this code.
So we're gonna run this code,
we're gonna print out five,
now we're gonna subtract one
and then we're gonna go back up
go back up and ask the question.
Is n greater than zero.
And the answer, since it's
four, the answer is yes.
So and it runs again.
And it prints out four,
subtracts again,
checks,
prints three,
subtracts again,
prints two,
subtracts it again,
prints one,
subtracts again,
now n is zero and so it comes back up,
comes back up is this
question has now become false.
So it's gonna take the exit
so it's gonna come down and
run this line right here.
Then it prints "Blastoff!",
and we can kind of print
out the residual value of n,
just to sort of prove to
ourselves that it ran until n
was no longer greater than zero
and then zero was the final value for n.
And we carefully constructed
this n, n equals oops.
Go back.
We carefully constructed n.
We set it to five,
then we carefully subtracted
one each time through the loop.
And then we're using that to
control when to exit the loop.
And so you can think of this loop as
for now running five times.
True true true true true
and then false finally.
So this question was true for a while
and as long as it was true
the loop ran and then when it finished,
when it turned false,
the loop stopped.
And so this variable that we
construct to control the loop
is called the iteration variable
because it tells how many
times this loop is going to run
over and over or otherwise
known as iterate.
So this is a badly constructed loop
with an iteration variable
that we didn't do very well.
And so, if we take a look at this,
we start it with n five,
and then this is greater
than zero so it's true
so it runs it,
then it runs it again and
it's still greater than zero
so you can pretty much see
because we're not changing it,
this is gonna be true true
true true dot dot dot dot
forever, true forever.
And so this is an infinite loop.
And it's just gonna run
until your computer runs out of battery
or your hit the buttton.
This is the kind of thing where
you often see your computer
spinning like a spinning beach ball
or some other indication that
your computer's super busy.
It's in some kind of a loop
really tight and it's running something
and it's using up
all of the processing
resources of your computer.
That's an infinite loop.
And so the problem is
is we did nothing with
the iteration variable.
Now here's a different loop.
And so this one demonstrates
a different idea.
So in this case,
we start out with n as
zero and it comes in here.
And is n greater than zero?
Question mark, and the answer is false.
So it skips it.
It doesn't run these lines of code at all.
And so this loop doesn't run at all.
'Cause it comes in,
asks the question,
says no and then it skips right around it.
So never run, never run.
And so this actually is,
sometimes you write a while
loop on purpose like this,
not quite as simple as this one,
but the idea is this
emphasizes that these loops
are what we call zero trip.
They are not even guaranteed to run once.
They're gonna run maybe zero times.
And in this respect it functions
exactly like an if statement, alright.
The first time through the loop,
if it's not true it's just
gonna skip right by it.
So, there's a couple of ways
of getting out of loops.
In this case I'm
constructing an infinite loop
because remember the kind of
definition of an infinite loop
is if this is gonna stay true.
Well true is the constant true.
So this is gonna run forever.
And what it's gonna do
is it's gonna prompt
with a little arrow
and then let us type
and read whatever we type
into the variable line
and then if the line is
done we're gonna break.
Now break is an executable statement
and if you hit the break,
it exits the innermost loop
out to the place beyond
the end of the loop.
So, when this runs the first time.
And we say hello there,
line is not done so it prints it.
So it prints out hello there
and then goes up
and then we type in again,
we type finished and so it's not done
and so it prints it
so now comes that print statement
and then we type in done
and now this becomes true
and it comes out and runs the code
beyond the end of the loop.
The key is is it doesn't go back.
It's like once you've done a break
that loop is done.
And so you look at basically, you know,
the block that is the loop.
So here's kind of the loop block.
And then the break goes to the line
after the end of the loop block.
And you can think of this as sort of like
just a hyperspace jump.
There is nothing really
this could be literally
hundreds of lines with if statements,
and you can be running and
doing all kinds of stuff
and running and doing all these things.
You know, and these things could run
all kinds of ways, right.
The point is is as soon as
you hit a break statement,
however much stuff is down here,
however much stuff is up here,
it exits to whatever the next line is
beyond the end of the loop.
Continue is another
loop control statement.
But it works differently than break.
So break says get out of this loop.
Continue effectively says,
stop this iteration, we're
done with this iteration.
And so continue says,
go up back to the top of the loop.
Oops, yeah.
Go up back to the top of the loop.
(mimicking whooshing)
And so, here we read a line.
If the first character is a pound sign,
line sub zero.
If that first character is a
pound sign we're gonna skip it.
And this is a way for us to
make like little comments
in our typing.
And then, if the line is done,
we get out and otherwise we print it.
And so that's why there
is not printout here.
Because it comes in,
runs, oops.
It comes in,
this is true and then it goes back up.
But it comes back and
prints out the next one
and does another thing.
And so the loop continues
whereas the break ends the loop.
And so again, the same kind of notion
that you're sort of doing
all kinds of complexity.
Wherever you're at in this loop,
you hit continue and it does not,
it doesn't go any further,
it goes back up and
runs the question mark.
It asks the question mark.
And so, I mean asks the question,
and it might exit the loop
in that particular case.
But this one here is a true.
This is an infinite loop
that I've constructed.
This is not an infinite
loop because at some point
the break gets us out of the loop.
And so it's an infinite loop
with break to escape it.
And that's another common
way to construct a loop.
So, these loops that
we've been drawing so far,
the ones that use while as their key word,
are called indefinite loops.
And that's because they
kind of go for a while.
Till a break hits,
or until some value becomes true.
I mean, along as that value remains true.
So all the ones we've done so far
are easy to look at
and know that they look pretty good
and they're probably gonna finish.
But there are some times
if they're long and complex
and their exit or termination conditions
are a little more complex,
it's not clear that they're
really gonna terminate.
And so we can use while
loops for a lot of things
but for most of our looping,
we're gonna use what are
called definite loops.
And that's what we're
gonna talk about next.
(jazzy piano music)