- So one of the two ways
that we mark up data is XML,
the other is JSON.
First we'll talk about XML.
We'll talk about XML more
and for a longer time
than we talk about JSON.
XML stands for extensible markup language.
There was a number of
markup languages in the 90s
that were out there, ways to
send data between computers
and none of them was amazingly
better than the other,
but in the early 1990s, as HTML came out,
the idea that we could use
less thans and greater thans,
or angle brackets some people call them,
once HTML made angle brackets popular
as representation format
it was pretty natural that we would find
a data representation format
that would take a similar approach.
So inside XML we're gonna talk about tags,
we're gonna talk about attributes,
we're gonna talk about data,
and we've already talked
about serialization
and deserialization.
Serialization is the act of taking data
inside of a computer in
one programming language,
setting it up for transport,
transporting it across,
and then taking it back apart
and turning it back into the data,
whatever internal data it needs to be
in the destination system.
So here is some basic XML.
We can take a look at various
things that make up the XML.
So it's very much like
HTML in that we have tags,
less than greater than.
The difference is we get to
name the tags anything we want
rather than the a tag or
the p tag or the h1 tag.
And there's a beginning
tag and an ending tag
and they're bracketed together
and there's syntax errors in the XML.
Syntax errors in XML are more severe
than syntax errors in HTML.
It's supposed to be right
and if you send bad XML it's likely
that the far end will not understand it.
So we have a beginning
tag and an ending tag
and so like name and slash name
or a beginning and ending pair.
Then there is the actual textual content
and that is the material between it.
And then here is a phone and slash phone
and we have this thing
called the attribute.
Key equals value.
The key doesn't have double quotes,
the value always has double quotes.
And this is like href
equals on an anchor tag.
And sometimes you have what
is called a self closing tag
where you don't actually
have a closing tag,
you have all the data that
you need in the attributes
and so you don't even bother
putting an empty text
area in in a closing tag.
So that is a start tag,
end tag, attribute,
and then a self closing tag.
Those are some basics of XML.
In general, XML doesn't care
too much about white space.
It does in the text areas,
so in here it matters and here it matters.
But things like,
we can indent this a
little bit differently.
And we tend to indent it in a
way to make it look reasonable
although once you have programs
sending it back and forth,
they tend to send it more compacted
just for efficiency purposes.
So one of the concepts is that there is
a hierarchical structure
within an XML document
and there are parent nodes and child nodes
and you can think of
these as simple nodes,
that is a tag and some data
or a complex element that has a tag
that includes other tags, some child tags.
And there's a couple of different ways
we can take a look at this.
The simple, more natural
way to think about this
is a tree with parent child relationships.
So here we have this a tag on the outside
and that's the top level one.
You can only have one outer tag
and you can't have another tag down here.
So you have to have one tag
that's sort of the root tag
for everything in this XML document.
And it has two children.
So the c tag and the b
tag are two children.
So the b tag is a child of a.
And then c has a d and an e
tag that are children there.
And then the textual data we model
as a child of each of those tags,
and you'll see in a bit
why it's best to do that.
So that is the way to think
about this, as a tree.
To represent that XML as a tree.
If we add attributes to it,
and this is where you
kind of see why it's nice
to take the text area and
make that a child of the node,
an attribute is different.
So the text is a special kind of child.
And you can literally have
more than one attribute.
You could have x equals two,
you know zap equals whatever.
And these could have a
couple different attributes.
The w attribute is a value of five.
And that's the five down there.
And so you could have multiple ones.
You can only have one text node.
Now, in the case of a you have
a whole bunch of text nodes,
but these are because
these are child nodes.
Within one simple node you can
only have one text element.
You can also think of XML as paths,
and the easiest way is
to sort of look down
this tree version and look at
from the path from the parent.
So you go to a
and then the parent of
the child b and then x.
So at position ab you find x.
So ab is the path up to the root.
So acd, that's this one, is the path to y.
And ace is the path to z.
And so you can think of these as paths.
Part of what we're doing
is we're coming up with
ways to walk through
and parse trees of XML data.
So the next thing we'll talk about
is how we determine if a
particular XML document is legal
or meets the contracts that
two applications have set up.
(piano music)