Now we're gonna talk
about API rate limiting
and security, the key thing
is that the Google API
and the Google data is super valuable.
And you could build a
website that did nothing
but sort of like asked
the person for something
and then showed them that place
and make them be a map searcher.
And you added so little value and
Google did all the hard work.
And so they protect these somewhat.
Sometimes, they'll say you can only do 50
of these a day or 500 a day or whatever.
That's called rate
limiting, and sometimes they
say you've got to login, you've
got to create an account
and get a key with us.
And then present your key so that means
that your account only gets so many.
And they keep track of
whose using their service
and how much they're using it.
Google gives you even sort of a dashboard
that tells you some of this
stuff, it's kinda nice.
And so, the other thing
is that sometimes and API
is free and then it becomes popular
and they decide they're gonna put a key
on it or a rate limit on it.
So you gotta kinda play
this game with them.
And the rules kinda
change as things progress.
So that geo coding API
that we were talking about
has at one point in time
2,500 requests a day.
You can get more request if you get a key.
Now, another API that we can talk
about, is the Twitter API, now Twitter API
started out as a free public API.
But then Twitter realized that people are
making more money off of
Twitter's data than Twitter
was making off of Twitter's data.
And so Twitter makes is so
that you have to have an
account, you can only
request data from their API
if you use your account key to sign that.
And so, there's a whole series of getting
and issuing keys and
then using those keys.
And I'll just give you
a short summary of the
kinda code that it takes to build those
requests up that have to be signed.
So you'll look through
the Twitter documentation
and it'll say oh, this url
to get the tweets, etc., etc.
And it says do a get request to this url
and that url and maybe
substitute a little bit
of things here for the screen name you're
looking for or how many tweets you want.
And they tell you how to
carefully construct these urls.
And so here's an example
bit of code that talks
to the Twitter, for now I'll
ignore the security bit.
And that's all hidden in this twurl, so
it looks a lot like the last
one, we're gonna use json
and urllib and we have found
that this is the API name,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, list.json.
Getting a friend list
for a particular person.
And so that is the base
url that we're going to do.
And we're going to ask a
person for a Twitter account.
If we hit enter, we're gonna break out.
And twurl augment, we're
gonna say give me the
first five friends of this
particular screen name,
the one we just read in from input.
And this twurl, you'll
see in a second, it adds
a bunch of stuff to prove
that you are who you are.
It's signing that url, so
you're sending a signed url.
Which is nothing more
than a whole bunch of
crazy characters, we'll
see that in a second.
We retrieve it and this is
pretty straight forward.
We can just, you know, open
the url, read it and decode it.
Decode solves the utf8
thing, makes it all so that
data is a real string and it's
in the Unicode internally.
Now we can actually get the headers.
Remember I told you earlier
that url open bypasses
the headers, but it stored them for later.
We can say hey, give
me back those headers.
And it gives us back a
dictionary of headers.
And the headers if you
go all the way back,
are a bunch of key value pairs.
Key:value in the headers
and in Twitter, if you
read the documentation, there's
this x-rate-limit-remaining
that tells you each time
it returns to the API,
response to the API call that you made.
It says, look, you've got
12 left, you've got 11 left,
you've got 10 so you can print that out.
So this prints out how
many you've got left.
Then we parse the json data.
We're gonna print it so we can debug it.
This dumps, dump to
string and then print it.
Indent=4, this is called pretty printing
and it's indenting things really nicely
so that you can make more sense of it.
Whereas when these things
are talking, when programs
are talking to each
other, they don't really
make the output look particularly pretty.
And then if you, we're
gonna go through and we have
the outer thing of users
and we're gonna print out
the screen name and go grab
for each user and users,
we're gonna print their
screen name, we're gonna
grab their status text and print that out.
And so this is what that data looks like.
Kinda chopped a bit,
so the thing we get is
an outer layer, we get users
and then we get a list.
And here's the first user,
now if you look at the
actual data, it's much larger than this.
Here's a second user and
then we have status text,
status text and the screen name, right.
And so those are the bits that
we're extracting from that.
If you look, we are going
to grab the screen name,
we're gonna grab the status
text and away you go.
So, you can start with
this, but you realize
that once you're looking
at this and you're printing
this out with pretty
printing, you can sort of
work you way in knowing that it's
either a dictionary or a list.
Cause the dictionary you look up the key.
If it's a list, you say
which position it is.
And then you get more
dictionaries within dictionaries
within dictionaries and away you go.
And so this code, actually,
you know, when it runs,
it prints out the screen
name and then that status.
And then the next person
so it's my first five.
In that case, my first
five friends and their
most recent status, the first five people.
Now, let's talk a little bit
about how the security works.
And so you have to go to the website,
you have to have a Twitter account.
You can't talk to Twitter API
without a Twitter account.
And then you go to this website
and then you set up a key.
You say, I'm going to build
an application that is
gonna consume the Twitter API.
And then you go in, you
have to work through.
There's documentation on
how all this stuff works.
You set up an API key,
you set the application.
So I made a key called
python on my laptop.
And it gives us some values,
it gives us a consumer
key, a consumer secret, a
token key, and token secret.
And you get to regenerate these.
And there's this file called hidden.py.
And you edit them and copy
and paste all the stuff
from those pages, those four
values into these strings.
Now, if you download my
code, I don't have my keys
in there, I've got some
place holders for this stuff.
So you've gotta get to this
webpage that's on Twitter,
copy these things in and then
the twurl code will start to work.
It uses a technology
called OAuth which is a way
to sign a url in a way
that proves you have
the key and a secret and the tokens
and it can't be modified in the middle.
So once you send this url, they can check
the key and the secret to make sure that
you've truly signed it without
actually sending the key and the secret.
It's actually kinda cool and fascinating.
But we won't go into it
in great detail here.
And so if you look at
the code in twurl.py,
this is the code that does it.
It actually pulls in an OAuth library,
that hidden.py, that is
that code that you've got.
And it's got the consumer
key, the consumer secret,
secrets, and this is
pulling that from hidden.py.
This is a lot of stuff that's
using this OAuth library.
Don't worry too much about that.
Eventually, it produces a
url that looks like this.
And what happens is, this is the base url
you were told to use,
then you have count=2
and screen_name=drchuck,
those parts are your
parameters to that web service call.
And then all this OAuth stuff is produced
by this OAuth code and the
consumer key and the secret.
What happens is a key gets
sent, the key gets sent
and the secret does not get sent.
But they send this signature
which is based on the secret.
And then what it does is
it rechecks the signature
on the far end, signature's a long string.
By regenerating the
signature because the secrets
aren't available to both you
to generate the signature
and to them to check the signature.
So it's kinda like a hash, etc., etc.
You don't have to worry about all this.
These urls get really long and your values
that you need are in,
the name of the url's in.
And you call this routine,
that's called augment,
that takes a url and then parameters
and then augments it by
adding all this OAuth stuff.
And so that's why it's called
augment, to augment the url.
And once you've got this
set up and hidden working,
then you sort of just augment
the url and then hit it.
Now, you know, if you
don't have the right keys
or secrets or you don't
have an account on Twitter,
then it's gonna blow up,
but if you get it set up,
you will be able to talk to
the Twitter API with this.
So this whole web services section,
we've done quite a bit of stuff right.
We've looked at how instead
of reading html or flat text,
we are creating structured data according
to contracts whether it be xml or json.
We can retrieve and
parse that information in
a deterministic way,
we talked about schemas
that define the contracts
so that you know if the
data you're getting is
wrong, you know who to blame
because the schema gets violated.
And we've played with
APIs, where you're talking
to someone else, whose
defining what the rules are
and how to read their documentation.
And even if they have an API key or need
signed urls, showed a little
bit about how to do that.
(piano music)