- So our last major topic is called
many to many relationships.
So up to now everything that we've done
is what's called a one
to many relationship,
and that is there are many tracks
associated with one album.
There are many albums
associated with one artist.
There are many tracks
associated with one genre,
and you can think of labeling and as
you look at data models they put
little labels on each arrow that
tell you which end of the arrow
is the many and which end of the
arrow is the one, and so in this
case the Foreign key is pointing to.
There are many of these rows over here,
many rows that point to one row over here.
So it's a many to one relationship.
There are various ways, sometimes
they'll put two arrows at this end
and one arrow at that end, but
whatever it is, this kind of thing we've
been showing is the many
to one relationship,
and that's probably the most common thing,
but there are times when you just can't
model things with the
one to many relationship.
So like if you have a mother and children
well that's a many to one relationship,
and it's just fine and it works fine,
but sometimes you have a
many to many relationship
in that there might be many books.
One book has many authors and
each author has many books so you
don't have the one side, there's no one.
So you have to end up building
a table that what we call, I'll call it
a connector table, they
call it a junction table,
on Wikipedia, but we need a little table
that allows us to break a
many to many relationship
into into an effect, two
many to one relationships
in a connector table, and so this
is a connector table.
So you could think of this as, you know,
there are many, many links here,
but we don't have a way to model
the Many over here to here so
what you do is you basically say
oh there's a lot of these things.
There's many that go to the one.
The many that go to the one, and
then in here you'd sort of create
that manyness that you want to create.
So it's probably just as easy
to look at a sample of this.
So let's imagine a
learning management system
where you're taking a class and
there's some people that are teachers
and som people that are students
and many students are
members of many classes.
A student can be part of many classes
and a class has many students in it
so you can't really find the one end,
and so what we do is
we make a table called
membership and in that table
of membership we actually often
don't put a primary key at all.
We simply put in two foreign keys,
and if we're going to put a uniqueness
constraint, we put a combination of
the two foreign keys as
the uniqueness constraint.
So we say there could be duplicate
user id's and duplicate course id's
but there can only be, you know,
user id, course id combinations.
That has to be unique.
So you can make unique
be more than one column.
And so if you imagine a course table
and a user table, there's a user id,
the name and email, and the course has
a title and an id, and then we
have this little table that's just
is the connector table that shows the,
it points out so we can
expand this membership.
So let's take a look at how that works.
So we're going to create some tables...
and these are very classic tables
because these are the one end of it.
So these are the one end of it.
So it has a primary key, a title,
a logical key, email,
there's a primary key
here for course, and then there's text.
So we add this unique to kind of indicate
that it is a logical key.
We're not even going to allow ourselves
to put any duplicates in here.
Now that the connector database here
is a table member, and it has
two foreign keys, user id and course id,
and you can model some data here.
So I'm going to model role which
is going to be zero equals student
and one equals instructor, and then
I'm going to indicate that the
primary key, or uniqueness constraint
is the combination of the
user id and a course id.
Now when we say the primary key
it both limits our ability to
insert duplicates but it also
allows the database to optimize it
scanning because it knows that that
combination is always unique and so
it can organize its disk structure
and storage structure to understand
how to look things up more efficiently
and knowing that once it's found
a user id, course id combination
it doesn't have to look any farther
because they're unique, and so
all of these contracts that we add
speed things up, save storage, and
makes things more efficient, but in ways
we don't always know
exactly how they happen,
and so let's go ahead and make these.
Let's go ahead and make these guys.
I think I will start with a new database.
I'm going to call it LMS for
Learning Management System.
No I don't really want to do that one,
and so I'm going to not create the table.
I'm going to do everything in SQL,
and so let me see if
it's in my cheat sheet.
No that's not in my cheat sheet,
so I'll have to fix the
cheat sheet again for you.
By the time you see the cheat sheet
all these things will be in there.
So I'm going to go in here and
I'm going to grab create table user.
Actually, I'm going to grab them all.
Watch this.
Grab them all.
Highlight all of these.
Go over to my SQL browser.
Blast them all in, and then I'll
put a semicolon at the end of
each one of the statements,
and I want to run them.
So did I, does it look good?
Yep, yep, yep.
So I've got a course.
I've got membership, two foreign keys,
and I've got user, so that all looks good.
Okay?
So now we're going to have
to insert some data in.
Now we're going to insert
from the outside in,
and so we're just going to put
the name and email, the id will
be automatically assigned for the users,
and we're going to do the same thing
and the id and the courses
will be automatically assigned.
So let me just grab all of this stuff.
Go into SQL, that has the semicolons
at the end already for me.
Thank you very much.
Now I'm going to run it, and if
I take a look at my data, now
I've got primary keys for the courses
and I've got primary keys for the users,
and I've got nothing in
the membership table,
and I have course have to remember
what these values are because Jane
is one, and Ed is two,
and Sue is three, right?
And Python is one,
SQL's two, PHP is three,
and so when I go into membership
I've got two foreign keys here
and role and they just have to be
for the course, person combination,
and so it's a little tricky to
figure all of this stuff out, but again
these are just numbers and if you
look at these numbers,
user id, course id, role.
Well user id one is in course one.
User id is in course as the teacher.
User id is in course one as the student,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
So I'm making these connections
by just putting these little numbers in
and once again, conveniently,
I have all of my semicolons
perfectly in place.
So I go to SQL...
and then I run that...
and then I take, and I look at my
membership data and there it is.
So two foreign keys and a bit of data
modeled at the connection.
That's the way we say that.
The role is modeled at the connection.
So now that we've built
all of this stuff up
we can write some queries that
take a look at this, and so what
we're going to do is look at who's
in what course and what role are they
and we're going to sort
this in a nice way.
So let's just take a quick look
at the code we're writing.
We're going to do a select from
three tables, the user name, the
member role, the course title.
So in effect we're not showing any
of the foreign keys or the primary keys.
We're going to go from the user table
joined to the member table
joined to the course table.
This is pretty easy to write.
You know there are three tables
you want to go across.
The on clause is also
very easy to write, right?
The on clause models
each of these connections
where the member's user id...
is equal
to the user's id and where the member's
course id is equal to the course id.
So we're going to concatenate all
three of these tables together
but we're only going to
keep rows where it matters.
Now this role doesn't participate,
but we're going to print that out,
and we're going to order it by
the course title, first, and then
the member role, second, and the
the name, third, and so let's run that.
So we've reconnected it.
So Ed's the teacher of the PHP class.
Sue is the student in the PHP class.
Jane is the teacher in the Python class.
Ed's a student and Sue's a
student in the Python class.
Ed's the teacher in the SQL class
and Jane is the student in the SQL class,
and so we have many people, there
are many students in many classes
and so we have modeled that, but
we have modeled that
with this sort of table,
and if you look at a piece of
software that I've written called
Tsugi which is a stand alone learning
management system, that's built
with learning tools, you will see
in anything we're in membership
or we have a...
we have a user table.
We have a context which
is also the course table,
and then we have a membership table,
and look, here's these foreign keys.
It's kind of like that's the many side,
that's the one side, many to one,
and so this, you know, this is now
in effect a many to many between
these two but then it's modeled
as a series of many to one, many to one,
relationships, and you see this
all of the time in all kinds of things
where membership or other kinds of things
are necessary in many
to one or many to many.
So, with all of that,
there's so much to learn.
It's both easy and
complex at the same time.
It's easy when someone shows you
how to do it, but at some point
you will learn how to
build database models
and you'll realize oh it wasn't so bad.
It takes a while to get used to them.
This really just is quick walk.
The bottom line is, what we just did
seems like it was, while that's nice,
do you really have to do that?
And the answer is, if you're going to
scale at all, you absolutely have to
because you simply can't read
and write data sequentially.
You can't read through, update one
little piece of data in a file
by reading all the way through
and then writing a new copy of the file.
That could take seconds in a system
like an online system you get a
hundredth of a second to
do something like that
and the databases make it so that happens
at a thousandth of a second.
So ultimately you simply have to
take advantage of this.
You just can't, if you're
going to modify data,
you can read data from flat files,
but even if you're going
to read a lot of data,
if it's big, it slows it down terribly.
So it might seem like there's a trade off,
that you could debate
whether this is worth it,
but if you're going to
deal with a lot of data,
you've got no choice.
It's really not as much
a trade off as you think.
So this has been a quick
run up through databases.
We talked a little bit about indexes.
There are constraints.
We talked a little bit
about the not, null stuff.
We've talked about that,
the uniqueness, that's a constraint.
Another whole area is what's called
transactions, and that's the locking
a little area so you can read an area,
then lock it, and update it to
make sure nobody else reads it,
and so they make sure they either
get the version before you looked at it,
or before you changed it,
or after you change it.
So that's how you make sure you can't
do things, having to do with bank account
balances, and get yourself in trouble.
So these are a lot of SQL.
It's really fascinating.
SQL is a fascinating thing to use
and learn and performance tune and enjoy.
So relational databases are cool.
This gets us started.
The big thing is don't allow replication
vertically of string data.
Pull that out into a separate table,
establish a primary key, and then
have foreign keys that
point to that primary key.
It is not just how much data you store,
it's sort of a compression way
as a way of compressing data.
You might think strings
take no data but they do.
Numbers take a lot less data and it's
both how much data that's stored
but also how much data has to be scanned,
and that way joins work.
That's part of the magic of why
Oracle's such a successful company.
It's a bit of an art form and it's
something that you can
work your whole life
and always get better at.
(Metal music)