- So now that we're solving our problem
using a series of cooperating applications
communicating across the network,
we're gonna talk a little
bit more detail about
a notion of what we call web services.
And in this, we're going to
take a different perspective.
Instead of building our application
and breaking it into pieces,
we're gonna have an
application that's gonna really
consume an API from somebody else.
So there is some other provider
of this API that's not us.
And so if you're gonna
talk to somebody's data
like Google or Amazon or Twitter,
they're gonna say, you
have to use our API.
So what's that?
So an API is a contract that says look,
if you do this, and
this and this and this,
we're gonna give you data this way,
and they set the rules, they
study what the URLs are,
they'll tell if it's XML or JSON,
and this is called the
Application Program Interface,
and it's something you
read and you understand.
And so you go look at the documentation.
This is the documentation
for the Google Maps API.
So it turns out that Google
knows a lot about Maps.
It knows a lot of data, it
knows how to search Maps,
and it actually provides
some of those features to you
that your application
can take advantage of.
I took advantage of this at one point by
asking all the students in one section
in one of my online course
where they were from.
And I just let them type in where it was
and then I said, well I don't
know how to code any of that
so I used this API using
what's called geo-coding
to look all those places
up and get precise
latitudes and longitudes for the ones
Google could figure out and
that saved me a lot of work.
Now, these are expensive resources
but I could be patient and
make use of these resources
which as long as you use them
not too much they can be free.
We'll talk a little bit
more about rate limiting
and what's free and what's not in a bit.
But you start by reading documentation.
It says, do this, hit
this URL, hit that URL.
So if you read that documentation,
you'll find that there
is a URL that you can hit
and they tell you where to
go and then you go this URL,
you got a question mark and then you say
address equals and then ann arbor plus
and there's all these rules.
These are called URL encoding
rules when you have key values
on URLs, the plus means space
and percent two C means comma.
So these are called URL encoded.
Don't worry to much about
that, 'cause we're gonna have
a magic library like
we always do in Python
that takes care of this.
And so if you were to hit this URL,
you type in the exact
right way in your browser,
you will get back a JSON document.
It's an object that has key value pairs.
First value's this status.
Then it has these results and it's a list
and you dive down and eventually,
you can kinda find that
latitude and longitude
of the thing that you are looking for.
And so the idea is can we right a program
that can read this.
And so here's our little
program that reads this.
And a lot of this is sort of comfortable.
You've already seen some of this.
You import your lib,
we've deparsed in JSON,
we grab the URL, and
then we're gonna write
a little Y-loop that's
gonna ask for a location,
and we can type that location that in.
And we've got to concatenate with this URL
the location equals, and
there is a bit of code,
a library that called parse URL and code
that takes the key and the
value so the address equals
and then whatever this text
is that read in from the user
that goes in here and it
does that URL and coding
with the pluses and percent
two C and all that stuff
is taken care of.
And that is our URL that
we're gonna pass to URL Open.
So we print out that
we're gonna retrieve it.
It prints this out and if
you look at this too long,
it has all that fancy stuff
on it, and then we read it.
I mean, we open it with URL Open,
and then we read it and decode it.
So these two things, hit this URL,
decode it, and then we
retrieved 1669 characters
'cause it's just a, in this case,
because we've decoded
it, data is a string now
that's read is bytes and data is a string.
So we read that many
characters, 1669 characters.
And then we're going to take this data
and we're gonna parse it with JSON
and we might get the bad data here.
It might blow up, but it might work.
And so in this case, it works.
We have an error that basically
says if we got a bad thing
we're gonna blow up, but in
this case it doesn't blow up.
And so now we're going
to sorta dig through.
And if you go back
Let me just go back.
So the results, sub zero geometry.
Let's show you how that works.
So results is the first key.
So this is a dictionary
with a key of results
but then it has a list and the zero item
this list starts here and goes there
and there's, I'm only
gonna show part of it
but there's many things here.
So the zero item is this.
This is the subzero.
And then geometry within
that sub zero item.
So if we look at that, it is
the outer dictionary,
the first item in the list, sub geometry.
So that grabs one part.
That grabs this part right here.
And then we're going to
go into location and lat.
And those are just keys within keys,
a dictionary within a dictionary.
And so you see it says,
sub location, sub lat.
And so that is literally gonna pull
out of that complex
structure, that will pull
the latitude out and
then in the next line,
pull the longitude out, so we can pull
the latitude and longitude
out and then we print it out.
We can go into results of
zero formatted address.
And that goes into results
zero formatted address
and that pulls this little bit out.
Now, it takes a little
while to write this stuff,
and you have to put a lot of debug
and you don't necessarily figure out
this complex bit here at the end,
but you know, you print it,
you don't get what you want,
you say, oh wait a
second that wasn't a ray,
so I gotta add a sub zero
there to get the first one
out of the ray but
eventually you figure it out.
And it's not all that difficult.
The first few times you do it,
you're like what am I doing?
But after a while, you
realize, oh I'm just sort of
tearing this apart and
digging deeper and deeper
into this data structure
which I just retrieved
over the internet from
Google and I learned
something good from that.
So up next, we're gonna
talk about how sometimes
these APIs protect themselves with keys
or signatures and why that happens
and how to solve those problems.
(slow piano music)