- So now we're going to
talk about what you would do
with a web page once you've retrieved it
in a Python program.
Call this web scraping.
And so web scraping or web spidering
is the act of retrieving a web page,
extracting the links from those web page,
making a queue of un-retrieved links,
and then moving on.
And eventually the idea
is, if you had enough time,
energy, bandwidth, and storage,
you could find your way
to most of the web pages
on the Internet that
are pointing, that point
point to or are pointed
to by other web pages.
And so, you might have
all kinds of reasons
to scrape data.
You might have a blog that you posted.
You might have, who knows?
Maybe you put some data in a system.
Maybe, maybe the system's being shut down
because it's being retired.
You can do all kinds of things.
You can write a little thing.
I was talking to somebody who wrote
a thing to retrieve something and check
and then send a text
when something changed.
All kinds of stuff.
Or you might make
yourself a search engine.
But be careful.
Not all websites are happy
about you using a robot
to retrieve their content.
Some of the websites as we'll see
demand that you log in
and they track what you do
and if they think you're
doing something bad,
they will shut your account off.
Other websites will
track what you're doing
without you logging in but
then shut your address off.
And so you have to be careful.
You should read up.
You should figure out what
sites allow you to scrape them.
Now I have some sites that I've set up
that you can play with
to make it so that it's legit.
So, parsing HTML is difficult.
Some of the simple examples, you know,
you can probably write
a regular expression
or you know, certainly some
splitting and some whatever,
and what you would find is
you would write that code
and you'd retrieve your
first five web pages
and it would seem to work,
and then it would encounter
some really weird but legitimate HTML.
Or maybe even sort of
slightly broken HTML.
So the Web is full of broken HTML,
and your browsers just look at it and go,
"Oh, wow, more broken HTML."
But they don't put up error messages,
and so people just leave broken pages up.
But your Python proram's
gonna see those broken pages.
So what you would do
is, you would be like,
"Oh, here's a new weird
way to do an anchor tag.
"I'll change my code."
And then run for another
hundred pages and like,
"Oh no, here's a new weird
way to do an anchor tag."
And the problem is is
that you're gonna find
a lot of different ways
to mess up an anchor tag.
And someone's already done that.
There's a software called Beautiful Soup.
And we have installation
instructions on how to use it.
And really what it is is
it's, somebody just spent
months figuring out all the
nasty things that could happen
and compensated for it
and gave you a nice, wrapped
interface that just says,
"Look, you give me the HTML
"and I'll give you back the tags. Okay?"
And so it's called Beautiful Soup.
And so you have to install this.
There's a couple of ways
that you can install this.
If you're good at extending your Python,
you can just, you know, extend
and install Beautiful Soup
for all Python programs.
If you can't change your
computer's configuration
because you're on a school computer
or you're using a USB stick or something,
then there's a way to download
this file that I've created
called BS4.zip and so what you do
is you end up with your
file called URLlinks.py
and then a little folder called BS4,
which is a folder that
has a bunch of files in it
from the zip file.
And then you can run it,
and so it'll pull it in
and you'll import from
BS4, Beautiful Soup,
and that's either gonna pull
it in from the folder you do
or if you have installed it
using the Python installer,
it will also just, you don't
have to put this file in.
So it's up to you.
You can either do it one of two ways.
So this is a little bit of code.
Now, Beautiful Soup is a complex library
and so just because this looks easy,
doing things in Beautiful Soup,
you might have to actually read a bit more
to figure it out.
But we're going to just read this.
We're going to
import Beautiful Soup,
we're gonna ask for a URL right here.
We're going to take that
URL, we're gonna open it.
URL open, give the URL
and read the whole thing.
That means we're not writing a loop.
We've read the whole thing.
That's okay as long as you know
that the file's not so large.
And then we're going to
pass the data we got back
and this is gonna be bytes,
but Beautiful Soup knows all about bytes
and all about UTF8
and it figures that out, and you just say,
"Hey, take that stuff I just got
"and tear it apart using HTML.
"And give me back an
object, a Soup object."
Now, the Soup object is something
that you can run queries against.
So it parses it, it deals
with all the imperfections
and inconsistencies in
this HTML byte array.
And it fixes that.
It gives that back.
And so there's various things you can do,
and you got to go look at the
Beautiful Soup documentation.
It could be a whole
class on Beautiful Soup.
So here's a thing you
can do is this object,
you can sort of call it like a function
and say, "Hey, give me
back the anchor tags."
And anchor tags, of course, are the tags
that say href equals
blah, blah, blah slash-a.
So all of this is an anchor tag.
And then we're gonna
loop through the tags,
because there could be more
than one of those anchor tags
in the file.
And then we're going
to pull out that href,
and that's what this does.
We're gonna loop through all the tags
and print out the href.
So if you tell it to go to dr-chuck.com
it will tell you the one
external link in dr-chuck.com.
And so, I've got an assignment
that sort of goes into that
in some more detail.
But this chapter has been
a whole bunch of interesting stuff.
We started with the TCP/IP model
and talked about sockets
that are phone calls
between computers.
And then how applications
protocols are developed
to say what we say on those phone calls
And we've explored then the HTTP protocol,
which is probably the most
likely thing you're going to see.
And then we played with
all this in Python,
and saw that Python is
really good at this.
You can write extremely
simple and small programs
to do some extremely
complex and powerful things.
And again, that's why people like Python,
is because it makes the complex simple.
(light music)