- So the service oriented
approach is a way we
approach solving a complex
application problem
where all the data really isn't present
in one computer system.
It's somehow spread out over the internet
connected by the internet
or internal network.
And so the idea is
that some applications just can't
contain everything.
The perfect example is a travel website,
that can book you a flight,
book you a car, buy tickets,
book you a hotel
and do all these things.
Well, that travel website is neither
a hotel, nor a rental car company,
nor an airline.
But what it really does
is it talks to all these services
somewhere else on the web on your behalf
and it makes reservations for you.
And so you have this convenient
user interface that says,
oh here's your whole vacation
I'm going to figure all this stuff out.
Now you say, go, and it goes
book, book, book, book.
And it books on all these other systems.
Now it requires a lot of infrastructure,
a lot of coordination
and a lot of effort to make sure
that your application can talk
and these other services
that are out there on the internet
have good contracts and you know exactly
how to send data to them.
And get data back from them.
And so initially when you're building a
service-oriented architecture
often you have one application.
And it's all internal,
often it's all one language.
And then maybe you'll say,
oh wait a sec we wanna take part
of what we do and put it in
a second system.
And then sort of come up
with a set of rules between the systems
and then more, and more, and more.
And this is a video
that talks a little bit
about the process and complexity
about taking these interfaces
between applications and applying
standards to those interfaces.