- So now we can take
advantage of the notion
of comparing tuples and use sorting.
And so what we'll wanna
produce is a list of tuples,
and then we're going to sort them, right?
And so, we can get a list
of tuples from a dictionary,
and then we can sort that list of tuples,
and then we can end up
sorting dictionary items
by taking this two-step process,
convert dictionary to
a list, sort the list,
and then we can have a sorted
dictionary values, okay?
And so we'll do this a
couple of different times.
So if we take a look at
this code right here,
we have our happy little dictionary, ABC,
map, A maps to 10, B maps
to one, C maps to 20,
what are we gonna get here?
Well, it comes out the
mapping is the right way,
but the order is whatever.
And now we say, this
function called sorted,
which takes inside a
sequence, and then returns us
a sorted version of that,
a list that's sorted.
And so, it says "sort D
items," so it's basically
gonna take this list and
compare the As and the Cs
and the Bs, and because it's a dictionary,
and all the keys are
unique, there's never gonna
be equality, so it really
is gonna just sort this
by keys and never get to
looking at the values.
You could construct a
list that had duplicate--
you could make a list of tuples that had
duplicates in the first,
like we did before,
but given that this
coming from a dictionary,
the first thing is gonna
always be unique and distinct,
and so if we say "sorted D of items,"
that we're passing this stuff into sorted,
sorted's gonna go around,
move stuff around,
and then get us back
a sorted version, sorted
in ascending order,
based on key without looking at the value.
And so that's a way
to see
dictionaries sorted by key,
is just, say, "sorted of Ds of items,"
and sorted is a function,
and so it just fixed stuff.
And so, this is the kinda
loop that you're gonna
write to do that.
Now, we did this before, we took sorted
and we got the sorted by keys,
and so you can just make
this nice and simple.
For K value, by the way, you can eliminate
the parentheses here,
and I think it's prettier
if you eliminate the parentheses,
but you could put parentheses.
This is still a tuple
without the parentheses.
For K, key in value in
sorted, so that says
go through D items, but
before I go through them,
please sort them.
So that means K is gonna
go through A, B, and C,
deterministically, every single time.
It's gonna go, and of course
value is gonna go through
the corresponding values, so now we can
print this out nicely, sorted
by key, and that's a real
nice, succinct little
way to say that.
I mean, again, these are
one of the kinda things
that people really like about Python,
is that you can do pretty powerful things
with easy to under--
I mean, you know, you might've seen this
for the first time, but
ultimately, you look at that
eventually, you'll be like,
oh yeah, that's, I see
exactly what that's doing, easy.
Not hard at all.
So, but let's say we're
looking for the most common
word, which we have been for
weeks and weeks and weeks now.
And so we wanna sort by values, not key.
So, this is an example of where we're
going to construct a data structure.
We're gonna imagine a data structure,
and then we're gonna
write code to construct
the data structure, and
then that's gonna make
our problem easy.
So this is an example of
using cleverly constructed
data structures to do this.
And the data structure
that we're going to create
is a list of tuples
where the value is first
and the key is second.
So you can just with items get key value.
I want value key.
So, let's take a look at this code.
Take your time, and get it right.
So, KV goes in C items.
Well, that is unsorted and
going to go through whatever,
A, B, and C, in whatever
order, and we're going
to make a new list.
So this is a data structure
that we're creating temporarily.
And what we're going to
do, is this is a list...
And we're going to append to that list
a tuple, so this going
to be a list of tuples.
Except, we're not gonna append them
in key value order, we're gonna flip 'em,
and append-- the first of the
tuple is gonna be the value,
and the second part is gonna be the key.
So, we end up with this.
This is sort of our
temporary data structure
that we have constructed to
make our job really easy.
So,
this ends up being 10 A,
22 C,
1 B, now, we just kinda flipped 'em.
We took this order, and
then we flipped 'em around,
and so now we have this nice little list,
sitting in memory, in a variable.
And now it's really simple.
We can say, "Oh, look, we can use sorted."
And we can sort by, now,
the values because they're
the first thing.
The sorted doesn't know that they're--
how we produced this list,
it just looks at that,
and says, "Oh, that's a list of tuples;
"I'm gonna always sort
by looking at the first
"item in any tuple."
And I'm gonna add reverse equals true,
so I get a descending sort.
So I see that
the value that is highest
ends up being first.
And so that changes this,
and I'm just, sort it,
and then reassign it back into temp,
and I'll print this
out, and so now you see
it's sorted in descending order of key.
So it's value,
key,
value,
value, key, but it's sorted
in descending order, 'kay?
And so, that's an
example, sort of, of just,
you know, if I just made a data structure,
and I flipped those things around,
I could use sorted to sort these things.
There are many other ways you could do it,
but there's sort of like
the more elegant way
of doing it, and the clever bit here
is, make a new list and make
it be a little bit different.
'Kay?
So, here we're going to print out
the top 10 most common words in a file.
And most of this code
is review, so if we take
a look at it,
we're gonna open a file,
we're gonna start a dictionary
for our counting, we're going to,
you know, there's gonna
be words, and lines,
alright? And so we're
gonna have a for-loop.
This for-loop is gonna
go through each line,
and then, of course,
we're gonna split 'em,
which is busting them into pieces,
and then we have a for-loop within that
and this for-loop is gonna
go through each word,
and so that means that
by nesting these loops,
we're going through each
line, and then within the line
we're going through, we're-- then we go
to the next line, and
go through the words,
and eventually, this line
of code, counts sub word
equals counts dot get word zero plus one,
our idiom for making a histogram,
alright, this line right here is an idiom.
If you don't know already what that is,
go back to the previous dictionary lecture
and understand it.
Understand it 'cause
you're just gonna use it
over and over again.
So now, at this point,
and I always like drawing
horizontal lines in code when we write it.
At this point, coming
through at this point,
counts as right, counts as the histogram.
It's not sorted.
So now we wanna sort it,
so we're going to make
a new list, we're gonna
loop through key value,
and then we're gonna make a tuple.
I'm making this be two lines
to make it a little easier.
Value key, so I'm flipping it, right?
So I'm flipping the order of these things.
That's making a tuple,
and then I'm appending
that tuple to the list, okay?
So at the end of this,
we have a list of tuples
in
value key order,
VK,
right?
So, at this point, coming through here,
I've got, in my LST variable,
I've got this really
useful bit of code or useful bit of data
that I produced.
And then I'm like, "Oh! Now
it's ready to be sorted."
Poof! Sort. So take list and
sort it in descending order,
and then stick that back in list.
Now, we wanna print it out, but
we don't wanna print it out.
We don't-- so we got a nice
sorted list coming down here.
We don't wanna print it out in value key,
'cause that's what it is, it's in
parentheses V comma K
order, but it's in sorted.
And we know that the highest value is here
on down, and so we're gonna say, you know,
we're gonna run through
and now we're gonna
go through this new
list, only the first 10.
Start at the beginning, up to,
but not including number 10,
which is the first 10.
For value key in, and so value is good.
So this is the iteration
variable that's gonna go through
each of these things on and down,
and then we're just gonna
print it out flipping it,
so we re-flip it, flip, flip.
We print it out key value.
And it's going to work.
Okay, so,
that is one way of doing this,
and this slide right here
you absolutely do not need to figure out,
but some of you will look at
this slide, and you'll like,
"Why didn't you show us
that in the beginning?"
And others of you will be
like, "No, no, no, no, no,
"keep telling me this stuff here."
So,
I don't know exactly the term for this,
but this is a very procedural,
this is a classic algorithms
and data structures approach
to solving this problem.
This next thing uses
what are called lambdas
and they kinda create
what I call a closed form,
where you kinda do it
in all one statement,
and there's all this
implicit stuff going on.
So if you don't get this right away,
don't worry too much about that.
But,
roughly, this single line does everything
that bottom half of that program does.
I mean, if you go back,
if we go back to here,
it's pretty much this
line does everything,
does that in one line, 'kay?
It doesn't create the counts,
and it doesn't print out the top 10,
but it does everything in that middle bit.
So let's take a look at this.
So we all are gonna collapse this down,
so we have a print, that
parentheses the end of the print.
And then, we have sorted,
and remember that sorted
takes as input, a list.
And so that's not too bad,
and returns us a list,
and so we'll print the return from sorted.
And then this is the funny part.
The fun part, funny part.
This is called list comprehension.
And we have square brackets,
and we say to Python,
"This is a list."
But instead of a listing of
things, or having a constant
of one comma two comma three,
or append, append, append,
we are going to create an
expression that will act
as a generator for all the elements.
And so this basically says,
this is a list of two tuples,
V and K, and then this is sort of implied.
For all KV in c dot items,
and so this is like a for-loop
that is sort of driving
this, think of this as like
stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp, stamp.
However many times it has to make a stamp,
and so that's producing a list,
right?
It just manufactures this
list, and then that list
is sort of manufactured in the moment.
There's no sto-- that's
not put in a variable,
Python makes that list according
to the stamping pattern
that you've told it to
stamp out this list,
and then it passes that stamped out list
without even storing in a variable.
Into sorted, sorted moves the list around,
'cause it is just a list of tuples,
and then gives us back the sorted list.
And so, I didn't put
reverse equals true on here,
but you see that this is
sorted in ascending order now
by key, and I did that all
in one little statement.
So, look at this; this is
also one of the beautiful
things about Python that
you can build these things,
and you can build more
complex versions of this.
And there's a lot of real
elegant things that you can do
in Python; they're really succinct.
You should be careful
because in the beginning,
I think this is easier to understand
even though after a while you're like,
"Wait a sec, why am I putting
all these extra lines in?"
Because this is not so hard to understand,
but at some point, you know,
you will want to master
this more powerful and more
succinct version of Python
that expresses it in terms
of the data you wanna see,
rather than the steps you wanna take.
So this sorta finishes up tuples.
We've done a bunch of
stuff, I mean, really,
they're simple and elegant.
Tuples, lists, and
dictionaries are all related.
They're really three different,
kinda three foundational
data structures, three
foundational collections of Python.
And we combine those in
a lot of different ways.
("Soul and Mind" by E's Jammy Jams)