- So the last topic we'll talk about,
here in object orientation,
is the notion of inheritance.
This is a form of code re-use.
It's one of the more advanced aspects
of object orientated programming,
so just kind of understand
what it is at a high level
and then you'll know where
you need to come back to
when you need to learn a
bit more about inheritance.
So, the idea is instead of
making a new class from scratch,
we actually make a new class by starting
with an existing class.
We are extending it,
or another word for this is subclassing.
It's sort of a situation
where you're like,
I've got this code and I've got this data
and I just need to add a few things to it
and I'll then I'll have a whole new thing.
As you design objects,
and what we call object hierarchies,
you often do this.
It's a form of real clever code re-use.
Don't necessarily think
that you're supposed to know
when to use this or why to use this
because right now it's just
terminology, just terminology.
We have, what call these as
parent child relationships.
The original class is called a parent
and the new class is
called the child class.
Subclasses are another word for this,
you have a class and then you subclass it.
I think extending,
inheriting and parent/child
are probably better ways of
expressing it than subclassing.
So, here's a bit of code.
Let's take a look at this.
This code is unchanged.
It's the party animal code
that we've been saying all along.
It's the one that we
construct and put a name in.
Now what we're going to do is extend it.
You'll notice that this code down here
is the part that is doing the extending.
We're making a new class, football fan,
and by putting in parentheses
before the colon party animal,
that says football fan inherits everything
that is party animal, meaning
the X, the name, the init,
the party, all those methods and data
are sitting there.
Now we're going to add a new variable.
Football fan has, in addition
to all those other variables,
it has points and it has
a touchdown method and
self points is added, we
add seven to the points,
and then we call the
party and that does that.
So, this is calling this
method because football fan
includes X, name and party
and init and everything
and all this stuff, this constructor.
So this football fan is
really an amalgamation
of all these things together.
Party animal is just this stuff.
So we now have two classes,
we don't just have one.
We didn't erase the party animal class.
We take a look at the
code that we can run here,
we can say oh, okay, let's
make a party animal, Sally,
and so that constructs
an object like this,
and then stores that in S,
with an X starting out zero.
Then we call S party.
Oops, I better change that color.
Starts out at zero and then
we call the party method
and that changes it to one.
So, this bit of code, it's as if
this part doesn't matter at all
because it is a party animal,
it's not a football fan.
Now, if we take a look
at this code, down here,
take this code down here,
we're going to construct a
football fan and pass in Jim.
But, football fan has no
underscore, underscore, init,
so that actually uses the
underscore init from party animal
because we extended party
animal to make football fan.
So we inherited all the
good that was in there.
There it's going to make
a name, a variable X,
which is going to start at zero,
a variable name that's
going to have Jim in it
and a variable points that's
going to have a zero in it.
This J variable has more things in it
than the S variable has.
So, we can call the J party
and if we call J party, that
goes here and adds one to X.
So, it adds one to X, and
then we call J touchdown.
Well, that comes down in here
and adds seven to the points,
and then calls party within us.
So self.party is a current object,
i.e. self and J are the same thing.
Self.party and then it goes up here
and passes self in and
it adds one to the X,
in this case, of this J variable.
So this becomes two and
that's where it prints out.
It prints out seven and
two and away you go.
So, it's a way for you to
kind of take all this stuff
and stuff it into a class,
by making a new class
and just add the extending bits,
the bits that are in
addition to the other stuff.
So, like I said, inheritance is a powerful
and wonderful concept.
It is an excellent form of re-use,
but basically the whole
purpose of this lecture
was so that I could, in the
future, just use these words
and you would understand
them, as compared to,
I just want to say method.
I've been saying method all along,
and it's high time that I defined it.
So, let's just review one last time.
Class is a template, it
is not actually a thing,
it is a shape of a thing.
We define it and say when
we make one of these things
it's going to have these variable in it,
it's going to have these methods in it.
Attributes, variables within a class.
Method is a function that
is inside of a class.
Object is once we construct a class,
we get back an object.
So object here is the snowman cookies.
Class is the snowman cookie cutter.
Constructor is a bit of code
that sets up our object,
our instance, when it first is created.
And inheritance is this
ability to create a new class
but take all, import and
effect all the capabilities
of an existing class.
So, object oriented is awesome.
For the rest of this
class, we're not going to
write any object code, we're
not going to use class at all,
but we're going to use objects.
Literally, you have been using objects
from the beginning of this course.
As soon as you said,
Print, oops.
As soon as you said X equals hi,
that's an object.
As soon as you said X.upper,
you were calling a method.
You've been calling a method all along.
When you're doing something
like FH equals open,
this thing you're getting
back, that's an object.
Then you do FH.read or whatever,
you're calling a method
in the dot operator.
So, you've been using objects all along.
I now am just finally explaining to you
when I say "call the read method" or
"call the upper method"
or "what's this little dot
"and why is that there".
So again, it's time for
us to understand that,
but it will take you a long time
before you encounter a problem
that's large enough where
as part of your solution,
you're going to make a new object.
When you do, it's really a powerful thing.
It's a really bad idea
for me as a teacher to say
oh write a bunch of objects.
It's premature for that.
Later is when you will actually
learn how to use objects
and you'll be like Oh thank
heaven these objects are here.
So, that's all for now.
Thanks for listening, see you on the net.
(jazz music)