- Okay, so now it's time to teach you
a bit of complexity about text processing.
Up 'til now we've kind of been ignoring
the complexity of text processing.
Everything that I have been doing,
or most of what I've been doing,
is in ASCII, the Latin character set,
a character set that, you know,
United States, Europe, lots
of Western civilizations
use this character set,
and if you go back to the
1950s and 1960s, they,
we were happy to have one computer,
and we didn't care what
the character set was
as long as what you typed on the keyboard
came out on the printer,
the internal representation didn't matter.
And as the seventies
and eighties came along,
certainly seventies,
we needed some interoperability,
and so they standardized
the character set,
but they standardized that character set,
certainly in the West,
that did not represent anything.
And so if you look at
this sheet, basically,
what it's telling you is
for the various characters,
there are some non-printing
characters, white space,
non printing characters,
and then here are some printing characters
like the and key, the zero,
and then the uppercase characters
and then the lowercase characters.
And there's 128 of these possible values.
And there are nothing even
for Spanish or French in here.
And it's also why, by the way,
uppercase letters in Latin
sort lower than lowercase letters,
and we saw that in some
of the string stuff.
And what these do is
it maps and says okay,
and a lowercase A maps to the
number, integer number 97,
which in base 16 is six one,
and in octal it's 141, but in
binary it's eight bit numbers,
and so these are eight bits,
otherwise known as a byte.
And they're very efficient, like you know,
when you buy a disk drive,
its megabytes or gigabytes or whatever,
that's how many of these kind
of characters it can store.
But unfortunately,
this doesn't work for
more complex characters.
You can figure out these
numbers inside of Python
by using the ord function,
and so you say what is the ordinal,
or the numeric representation
of the uppercase H,
lowercase E, and new line
as a character as well.
And so, like 10 is the
ordinal position of new line.
And this actually has to do with sorting,
so the E, lowercase E, is
higher than uppercase H,
and that's just because
in the simplest of sorts,
we just sort them numerically.
So new line, if you go back
to the previous little sheet,
new line is this 10
right here, it's that 10,
which is a line feed, and that's a 10,
and that's why when we print
new line out we get a 10.
And so, again, in the early
days when strings were simple,
we just represented them
as one byte per character,
but the problem is that, you know,
as we have gotten more complex
and in today's modern world,
it's simply unacceptable to say
that the only thing computers
can understand is ASCII.
And so this leads to a very, very,
from the simplest of character sets
to a super complex character
set called Unicode,
which basically is billions of characters,
potential billions of characters,
for every language and
every character set,
and because there's so
much space in Unicode,
it's easy to take small
variations of characters
and give them a space.
It's so large that you can have,
you can have pretty much
any character that you want,
so that's Unicode.
The problem is that if we sent
Unicode across the network,
it would be way too large.
It'd be this UTF-32,
which instead of being
eight bytes per character
would be four bytes per character.
And so it would take all
of the data that we build
and make it four times larger.
And it'd be very difficult.
And so what they've come up
with is ways to compress this.
And UTF-16 is this weird thing,
UTF-32 is really sort of the
full Unicode, pretty much.
UTF-16 is a subset of Unicode.
It's used in some countries,
but the best practice for
moving data across the internet,
or in a file that you're
gonna move between computers,
is what's called UTF-8.
And so what happens is that
UTF-32 is fixed length,
ASCII is one byte,
UTF-16 is two bytes, UTF-32 is four bytes,
and UTF-8 is dynamically,
has dynamic length,
meaning that it is one to four bytes,
and if it's only one byte long,
it's perfectly compatible with ASCII,
meaning that an ASCII
file is also a UTF-8.
And so here's this little sheet.
It's not critical that you
understand this graph too much,
but basically, as time passed,
2000 internet's coming,
coming, coming, coming up, 2014,
pretty much overwhelmingly
the documents on the internet
that you might retrieve are UTF-8.
Now, so UTF-8 is the recommended practice,
and it's sort of a compression of,
UTF-8 can represent all the
things UTF-32 can represent,
it's just a compression of it so that,
with an overlap of ASCII,
which is awesome, it's what you want.
I don't need to talk anymore.
So in Python,
we have always had sort of two
ways of representing strings.
In Python 2, the normal
string was a byte string,
was an ASCII string, was a Latin string,
and if you wanted to represent Unicode,
there was a separate kind
of object that we had,
and so you would do that,
and in Python 3.0 or later,
one of the main features of Python 3
was to make Unicode and string the same,
so that that means inside of Python,
when you have a string
variable, it's a Unicode,
whereas inside of Python
2 it was a byte variable.
And so now we have this notion,
separately in Python 2, and on Python 3,
where we have byte variables,
and so byte variables are
in effect an array of bytes.
So if there's A, B, C, that
means it's three bytes,
it's three bytes long.
Whereas a string might be
three, a three character string
might be anywhere from
three to 12 bytes long.
So Python 2 had bytes and
strings that were the same.
Bytes and strings are the
same, and Unicode is weird,
and in Python 3,
strings and Unicode are the
same and bytes are weird.
Okay, and so that's what
we've got to deal with,
and there'll be times when
we get bytes from APIs.
When we call things,
we have to then figure out
what kind of thing those bytes contain,
'cause the bytes might contain ASCII,
they might contain UTF-8, they
might contain various things.
And so internally all the
strings in Python 3 are Unicode.
Most of the time if
you're inside the program
or reading and writing
files, we just work,
and that's why we haven't mentioned it.
But now that we're talking over sockets,
and we're talking to the sort
of random world out there,
we have to be a little more aware
of the data we're dealing with.
Now, the good news is
98 percent of the time,
or 95 percent of the time,
it's UTF-8, which might
also include ASCII,
and so it's quite nice.
But we have to be aware of this.
And so if we are going to take data
that comes off of the
network in the bytes,
then we have to make sure
that we interpret it,
or decode it, in the right way
so that internally, the
strings, which are Unicode,
are properly represented.
And so that's why when we read data in
from a network connection like a socket,
we have to say hey, decode it.
Now, there's a couple things going on
at that moment of decode.
And so this is where we're doing it.
We see this, we have to
manage this in this code,
where we, before we send this stuff,
we're going to encode it,
which takes a Unicode string
and turns it into UTF-8 bytes.
There's actually a parameter here
that you could do it different than UTF-8,
but no one ever does.
You might have to for certain situations,
but, so that says that we're
gonna encode this into UTF-8
before we send it, and then
when we get something back,
before we print it, we're gonna decode it.
And that's how this ends up working out.
And if you look at the documentation,
you will see that sometimes
it says it's a string,
or it's bytes.
And so you take a byte array
and you decode it to get a string,
and you take a string and
encode it to get a byte array.
And so that's what we're doing.
So you can think of the
process as this way,
and that is the network has these UTF-8,
mostly UTF-8 resources, not ASCII.
If it's ASCII it's okay.
So you read with the receive,
so this receive here pulls data,
or well, let's, we have a
Unicode string, we're gonna,
let's start with the send.
So up here, we have a Unicode string.
That's a Unicode string.
Even though there's no
special characters in it,
no Asian characters or French characters,
that's a Unicode string,
and before we can send it,
we have to send it in UTF-8.
If that was, if that had Asian
characters, it'd be okay,
and that would be set up just right
so that the UTF-8 would be right,
so we encode it first,
and that's this cmd.
This is now bytes, okay, cmd is bytes,
and then we actually send the bytes,
and that goes across the network.
We get back out thing,
and when we receive,
and we're receiving the data,
well data is bytes,
not string, it's bytes.
We can say how big it is.
Functions kind of like a
string, and it has len,
except that it is one byte per character,
which means some of it might be UTF-8,
and then all we have to do is say decode.
Again you could,
if you were dealing with a situation
where you're weren't expecting it
to typically be UTF-8 or ASCII,
you could tell it UTF-16 or something,
and it's more complex, but the
simple thing is you just say,
I'm gonna clean up my data on the way in,
I'm gonna clean it up by
running it through decode,
and I'm gonna encode stuff on the way out.
And so sockets are the place
where this comes into play,
and so you'll see, we'll always
do this encode and decode
every time we're sending data
kind of outside of Python
and inside of Python.
So now that we've talked a
little bit about character sets,
we're going to make this even easier
so you don't have to use sockets.
Urllib is a bit of Python
code in the library
that does all the socket stuff for you.
(soothing music)