- The last visualization application
that we're going to take a look at
is mailing lists, and
that's kind of ironic.
We started with the mailing lists,
and we're gonna end
with the mailing lists.
The mailing lists, of course,
are from my open-source archive project,
which I love and am very proud of, and,
and so, what we're going to do
is we're going to crawl the
archive of a mailing list,
and then we're going to
do two visualizations.
One is a activity visualization,
and another is a word cloud.
So, probably the more important thing is,
when I do the demonstration
of how the software works.
So, this is a large data
set, so you gotta be careful.
This could spider gmane.org,
which is a very free and friendly archive.
This data originally came from gmane.org,
but I've got a copy of it.
And so, gmane.org is not rate-limited,
but if everyone who is watching this
starts spidering gmane.org
at the same time,
you will crash it.
It just doesn't have the horsepower
to give you this data as fast.
And so, I've got something
that can give you the data super fast,
and has no rate limit on
it, really good server,
and it's cached all around the world
using a technology called CloudFlare,
so please, please, please,
don't point this at gmane.org,
point this at the URL here,
mbox.dr-chuck.net, et cetera et cetera.
And then you can run
this as fast as you like.
Now, another thing to worry about
is if you,
have a metered connection,
so don't do this on a
cell phone connection,
'cause you'll pay, thousands
of dollars, perhaps.
Make sure you're on a no cost connection,
before you start running this,
'cause this is gonna
pull a lot of data down.
If you just start this from
scratch, and you let it run, it,
on a super fast connection,
downloading the whole thing
is probably about four hours.
On a, on my home connection,
when I had like about 10 meg connection,
it took several days.
So just understand that, in this one,
it's both fun to deal with a ton of data
and it's scary to deal with a ton of data.
So this one is big, this one is,
you'll see the process in action
'cause it'll run for a while.
Everything you do, the
things will take a long time.
So here's basically the flow of the data
in this particular one.
You are going to have
the restartable spider
that talks to the API, mbox.dr-chuck.net,
which has a scalable copy
of all this information.
And again, it's going to
do kind of a raw database,
not very clean database,
it's sort of a mess.
It's just, just enough
columns to keep track
of whether or not we've
got this page or not,
and so, so this has, you know,
the ones we've retrieved so far,
and so what gmane does
is it sort of scans down
to see where to retrieve next, gets that,
and then starts scanning,
and then adding things here.
So it just adds it, and then it blows up.
And then it comes in again, and says,
okay, I'll start here, and then
it starts retrieving stuff,
and fills this in, fills
this in, fills this in.
And sometimes you put
like a delay in this,
so you don't overwhelm networks,
you don't overwhelm servers,
but basically this is pretty much
a raw retrieval of the email messages.
And this file can get rather large.
This is the one that's
greater than a gigabyte.
Now this data is actually really nasty.
It's email data, the date formats change.
This is data that lasted from
2004 to like, 2012 or 2013.
And so this,
this data has got a lot
of things wrong with it.
It even has things where
people's email addresses changed,
and so it has this mapping file,
this comes along with it,
this mapping file, it says,
here's this one person, and
here are the six email addresses
they used throughout
the life of the project.
And so, there is a relatively complex,
and so this is, this
part here, is super slow.
Very slow.
This part here is slow,
but it'll take like,
depending on how fast your computer is,
somewhere between two
minutes and ten minutes.
This'll, this first
part'll take days, perhaps,
depending on the speed of
your network connection.
And so what gmodel does
is it reads through this,
it actually recreates it, wipes this out
and recreates index.sqlite
every time it runs,
so that you can change any number things,
you can respider things,
you can do whatever.
And often the cleanup,
this is one of those cleanup processes,
and you have to tweak the cleanup process.
You like, look at your data, like, oh!
The cleanup missed something,
so I gotta run it again.
So this produces index.sqlite
every time it runs,
so this is like two to ten minutes,
gmodel is two to ten minutes.
And it, like, maps names.
And when it's all said and done,
this is a very small, highly normalized,
it's a nice data model.
This one here had the,
content.sqlite has the ugly data model.
index.sqlite has a pretty data model.
It's got foreign keys,
it's got all this stuff,
and all those things that we've
talked about in the database
where, it's efficient.
And so, in your mind, keep
track of how fast it is
to scan all the data in a
database with a bad model,
and then watch when you run
like gbasic, which is a scanner,
or gline, which produces
line data, or gword,
and watch how fast they run.
They run in like, a couple
of seconds, at the most.
And this runs in two to ten minutes.
And the, and the difference is,
is that's because the data
is efficiently modeled
in index.sqlite.
So you can take a look at
that using SQLite browser,
and take a look at the data model,
and you'll see it looks just
like the stuff we talked about
in the database chapter.
It's got foreign keys,
and, and all those things.
And so that runs, and you got this,
and then we do our
visualizations and our analysis
from this clean version of all the data.
And so gbasic just loops through
and prints some stuff out.
It's a great way to test things,
it's a pretty easy to understand program,
and you could take a look at it.
gline does some bucketing and
makes a, makes some histograms
to produce a line graph.
And then gword does a different histogram,
it does a histogram of word frequency,
and then produces that
as the word frequency ends up in gword.js,
and then we have two HTML files
that use the d3.js,
visualization to produce
a line and a word chart.
And so, you know, I'll,
in another video, I'll show
you how this code works,
which is probably more
useful than this picture.
But this is a whole bunch of good stuff
in this particular application, and,
if you really understand
everything in here,
you can build a pretty sophisticated
data retrieval and analysis pipeline.
And so, so that's it.
Thank you for watching all these lectures,
and look forward to
seeing you on the 'Net.
("Soul and Mind" by E's Jammy Jams)