- Hello, and welcome to chapter seven.
This is the chapter where it
all really starts to pay off.
We have been learning bits and pieces
and doing little two lines, three lines,
four lines of code to learn
the basic building blocks of Python
and learn some of the syntax
and find lots of terms.
But now we're actually going
to start doing something.
So if you look at what
we've been doing so far,
we're inside this little computer,
Python says what next and
you give it it's command,
and it does something and
you do something else,
and does something, and you
do this three or four times,
unless you write a loop and
then it goes 10-20 times,
and that's it.
And maybe we write a
thing that reads something
from our keyboard,
gives us something back,
and then we write something
that prints something out,
print a few foot things out.
And so we've been pretty
much using the keyboard,
the screen, the CPU, and the memory.
That's kinda where we've been living.
While it's important to talk
to the keyboard and the screen,
the real world is things like
databases that live out here,
files that live on our systems,
and connecting to the network,
and reading data from the network.
And so that's what we're
starting to do right now,
is we're starting to be able
to work outside our code,
and create things that are permanent.
And so we're gonna be talking initially,
we're gonna work on files.
We'll later talk to
databases and the network
and other stuff, but for now,
we are talking about files.
And so really kinda, we're
stepping out a little bit,
and reading things that are permanent,
and creating things that are permanent.
The kinds of files that we're
going to talk about mostly
are text files, and you can think of these
as a sequence of lines in a file
that are easily read by Python.
You've been making text files all along.
Your HELLO.PY,
that file's a text file too.
You're using a text editor
to create that file,
you put your Python commands in the file,
you run those files,
and that's what it is.
And so a file can be thought
of as a bunch of lines,
you know, one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven,
a blank line here.
Now it's possible,
but the reality is is that
these are actually just lines
and we have a special
character called the newline
that we'll talk about in a second.
So to read a file, you have
to call the open function.
And open returns what
we call a file handle.
Open doesn't actually read the file.
Open makes it possible so
that you can read the file.
So the parameters to open are,
it takes one parameter that's required
which is the name of the file.
Another parameter that's
optional whether or not
to read it or write it.
If we're reading the
file, it doesn't harm it.
You can read it over and over.
If you write it, if there's
already data in the file,
it truncates it and writes something.
And we're not gonna really write files.
We're mostly gonna read them.
And so open sort of,
you pass it in a file,
it gives you back this file handle
and then you have a
variable in what you stored.
I often call it fhand to be pneumonic.
You'll see my code, I
use fhand all the time
to indicate that that is a file handle.
And so if we were to run
this in interactive mode,
we'll open mbox.txt,
and that is a function
built into Python, and then
it gives us back a handle.
Does not give the data.
And you can kinda see this when
we print out the file handle
using the print statement.
It doesn't print the lines
that are in the file.
The lines that are in the
file are sort of out there.
There could be 10 million
lines for all we know.
Lines in the file.
The handles like a little
opening outside your program,
and you can talk to the file by opening it
and you can read stuff, if
you're writing to the file,
you could write stuff,
and then you close the file
to shut the handle down.
But handle is a thing that
allows you to get to the file.
It is not the file itself and
it's not the data in the file.
It is just a wrapper
that kinda allows you.
So if you print it out, it's
like that's the file we opened,
we're reading it, and
encoding has to do with the
different kinds of character
sets, which we talked about
at the end of the last lecture,
that Unicode character set, etc.
UTF-8 is a great character set.
It's probably the most
typical character set
that you will run into,
although you can have
different character sets of files,
but most of them are UTF-8.
So, of course, this is
Python, if you make a mistake,
and there's a file that doesn't exist,
we get a traceback and it blows up.
I'll show you how in a
second, how to deal with that.
Now, the newline character is
an important part of file reading.
In strings, we can put
the newline character in
by this \n character.
And the \n is the character that indicates
that we're supposed to go to another line.
Go to a new line.
And so what is this?
Well that's a \n, that's a \n.
And so, if we print it
out, we print it this way,
we see that the \n is in there.
This is how we type it.
We actually type \n to Python to indicate
that we're supposed to put that there.
But if we do a print statement,
it actually interprets the \n,
and so the \n causes kinda
this movement to the beginning.
Now the print actually, at the
end of this, adds another \n.
So the \n that we put in by
putting it into this string,
is that one, and then print
always puts a \n at the end.
There's actually a way to
override that \n behavior
by putting something
on the print statement,
which we'll talk about later.
Now, it's important to note
that the \n is one character,
and so even though this X\nY prints this,
and then print adds another
newline to go down to here,
if you ask how many characters,
what is the length of this,
well it's only three.
That's because that's a
character, \n's a character,
and the Y is a character.
So it's a three character string.
So the \n is a character like all the rest
of the characters, but we
encode it by typing \n.
It's called an escape, where
the backslash is the escape,
\n is a way to say newline,
cause we can't see it,
it's a way for us to encode in a string
this non-printable character,
this invisible character.
The white space, it's part of white space.
So as we're reading through the file,
we can think of it as a sequence of lines,
and we can read these a line at a time.
We can also read them a
character at a time if we want.
But it's more common
to say read this line,
read the next line, read the
line after that, etc, etc, etc.
But the way to best thing about this,
it doesn't really matter, you
can think about it as lines,
and we will in most of the
programs that we write,
but realize that the way when we see this
we see it like this, it
comes back to the beginning,
it comes back to the beginning,
there's a character in the
file at each of these points
to say go back to the beginning.
It's like hitting the
enter key on your computer.
And that is a newline.
So you have to think that in the file,
in order for your text editor and Python
and everybody to know where the lines end,
you put newline's in the file
and that's another character.
So, this looks like an empty line,
this line here looks like an empty line,
but really it has a single character,
and the character is a newline.
And it turns out that in a bit,
we're gonna need to keep track of the fact
that every line is ended by a newline.
So up next, I'm gonna talk a little bit
about how to read files in Python.
(classical music)