- Okay so now we're going
to write a web browser
again in Python but it's going to even
be shorter than what we did before.
We did it in 10 lines using sockets.
Now we're gonna do it in
four lines with urllib.
So urllib really is just because the idea
of opening a connection,
sending a get request,
sending the new line,
retrieving the stuff,
breaking the headers out,
doing all this stuff,
that's so common why
not put it in a library
to save ourselves some effort?
So here's how we do it.
We're going to read it in, right,
we gonna import this
library so it's not part of,
we had to import sockets before,
but we're gonna import urllib now.
And so this is really quite simple,
it's like elegantly simple.
You say urllib, that's a library that's
a part of a module within the
library, and this is function.
So let's call URL open
and then give it the URL.
Now that's a string, which it's gonna
encode automatically for us.
So it's taking care of all
kind of pretty thing for us.
It does the get it does the encode.
Look back at that previous code,
that's kinda what urllib
is doing for us, 'kay.
Now what urllib also does is it
makes the connection,
encodes the get request,
and then it actually
retrieves at this moment,
it retrieves all the headers
and keeps it for you for later.
You can get the headers but
we're not gonna see the headers
and then it returns to you an object
that looks pretty much like a file handle.
Because you can put this in
the four clause after the end.
Now it's going to read, run that loop
one time for every line of this file.
And so the lines we're
gonna get back are bytes
and so we have to say
decode, it doesn't do that
for us automatically, we are
gonna have to decode them.
And that's because we
might need to decode them
with a particular character set here.
And then we're gonna do our strip
and we're gonna just print this out.
So that's just, that's like, open a file,
read through it, and print it.
This is open URL, read
through and print it.
And that's as simple as it is.
And so that's what happens,
this is romeo.txt and it prints out.
Now the thing to notice is that
there are no headers here,
the headers have been
sort of consumed in the URL open.
Again there is a way to say
"Hey, give me my headers."
But for now, this just
gonna eat the headers
and keep them and then you
get to read all the data
and the loop runs, and this loop runs
four times and out come the four lines.
You can go ahead and run
this one, it's super easy.
I mean, literally, super easy.
You can do anything you want,
I mean treat it like a file.
You just have to remember
to do the decode bit
when you treat it like a file, and so
that code imported, we're gonna open it
we're going to make a dictionary,
we're gonna loop through,
we're gonna split it.
We have to add the deep
code just to make sure
because that line is bytes not string.
And then we're gonna go, our words.
We're gonna go through the line
and then each line we're gonna
bounce through the words.
The inner four loop is
bouncing through the words
and then we're gonna go to the next line
and then we make our cell loop.
And this, a dictionary, and
we print that dictionary out.
Now this, in effect,
other than importing this,
opening it differently
and doing the decode,
this is exactly how we
would process a file.
And so by using urllib you really sort of
reduce the complexity of retrieving
and reading network resources
to the same complexity of
reading and dealing with a file
locally on your hard drive,
which is kinda pretty.
One of the things then we
can do is read web pages.
That was a text file, but you can HTML
and so here's how you read a web page.
And it's the same kinda code.
We open a URL, this one
happens to have HTML on it
and we read through it
and out comes the HTML.
Remember that the headers are there,
but they've been eaten by URL open for us.
And now we could write a browser
that would parse these
less-thans and greater-thans
and make links, et cetera,
et cetera, et cetera.
So if you can come up with
ways to find these links
you could actually write bit of code
that would then have a loop that
would go up and open a new one,
pull out the links, open a new one,
pull out the links, open a new one.
And so you could, you could make a thing
that would retrieve,
you could write program
that would retrieve a page,
find the links in the page
and then retrieve those links.
And we'll actually do that
before the end of the class.
And so Python is a very
popular language at Google
and I wonder if, I think
it's a pretty safe bet
that the first crawler that they wrote
to crawl the web to build
the index was Python.
Because literally that's all
it takes to read web pages
and pull those web pages into
your web crawler database.
So, I don't know, are
those the first four lines
ever written at Google, who knows?
So the next thing that we'll talk about
is how you handle that HTML.
HTML's kind of yucky and nasty and so
it's not as simple as regular expressions.
Regular expressions might
help string parsing and split
might help but it's just too crazy.
So we'll talk a little bit
about how to use a library
to make HTML parsing a lot easier.
(smooth jazz music)