- [Instructor] Hello and
welcome to Python for Everybody.
I'm Charles Severance and now
in this little bit of lesson
we're going to talk about some tuples
and we're going to create a list
of the most common words and find out how
to sort a dictionary by the
values instead of by the key.
We're gonna use the clown.txt file
and the intro.txt file and
I'm gonna start with the code
from exercise nine that I
just did from chapter nine.
It's not exactly one of the exercises,
but it's very similar to them.
And I'm going to make a
copy and I'm gonna keep it
in the same folder, I'm gonna
keep it in the ex_09 folder
and just call it ex_10 because this code
is going to do much of the same stuff
and it's gonna read these same files.
And so I got myself exercise 10.
Exercise nine is still here.
Exercise 10 is now what
I'm editing, exercise 10.
But I'm in the exercise nine folder.
So in exercise nine, we looked
for the most common word,
but we wanna find the
five most common words,
which is gonna require us to sort.
So I'm gonna get rid of that code
'cause it's not really
how we're gonna do it.
There we manually looped through it
and found the maximum and
so I'm gonna just run this.
CD Desktop Python four everybody, ex_09.
And if I do an LS, you see that I've got
ex_09.py intro.txt, so
I'll run Python3, ex_10.py.
And run the clown data and we see that
we see the dictionary and
it's properly making it
in this code right here.
That doesn't change, it reads
the file, reads all the lines,
goes through and splits it into words
and then goes through the words
and does the idiom of using
dictionary get to maintain
the counters and we print
it out at the very end.
So the new code we're going
to write is down here.
Okay?
So let's first do a few things.
If I can say X is equal to
the dictionary dot items.
And this gives us basically a list,
print X, this gives us a
list of the key value pairs.
This prints out the dictionary,
but if we do it this way and use items,
it gives us the key value pairs.
And so that's what we got.
Key value pairs.
Now we can sort this based on the value,
'cause tuples can be compared.
This can be compared with this
and because D is lower than
R then this one is lower,
this whole, this ran tuple
comes after the down tuple.
So we can sort this whole thing.
And I'll do this by just
putting the word sorted here
and say give me a sorted version of that.
Now it's gonna do it based
on the order of the tuples.
This is gonna be more
higher precedence than this.
So if I print it this way,
run it again, you'll see that it's sorted.
And now is after and, car,
it's in alphabetical order
by key.
And so we could actually
print the first five
up to but not including
five by adding a list
on the list slice here.
And so that will show you
only the first five, right?
Except that that's not
what we're trying to do.
We really wanna sort by this.
Okay?
So we have this mechanism that can
take a list and sort it
based on the tuple values.
If we could create a list
where it was one comma after,
instead of after comma one,
and make it exact same thing,
then we could actually then
sort it and it would be fine.
Okay?
So let me show you a couple of ways,
at least one way to do that, okay?
Get rid of this.
We're gonna hand construct the list
and just call it temp
equals, give me a new list.
Temp equals new list
and then for K comma V
in the dictionary dot items.
And I'll just start by
printing K comma V, so we see.
And this is where it's really nice
to do these with the clown code first
and then only do your test
on the bigger file later.
And so it's pretty much the same thing.
We are going through in key value order,
which is dictionary order,
which is not sorted at all.
Okay?
Now instead of printing
this out, we are going to,
let me do this in a couple of steps.
Make a new tuple.
And we'll just call it newt,
equals parenthese, V comma K.
Okay, so this is I'm
saying make a new tuple.
This is like a new tuple
with two items in it
and I'm gonna make the value
for and the K, the key.
Okay, so then I'm going
to say temp dot append.
Newt, new tuple.
So I'm gonna end up with a list of tuples.
Let me comment this one out.
And under then, when I'm done
here, I'm gonna print temp.
So if I run clown.txt, you
see what happens in temp.
It's still, well, let's print temp twice.
I mean, it's not sorted, it's flipped.
Let's print it.
Well, that's okay, we'll
just, that's the flipped one.
Okay, so it's flipped.
And all we did is we made it,
instead of car comma three,
it's three comma car.
But now we have a list.
Okay?
So now it's flipped and
now we can sort that.
We can say temp equals sorted temp.
So that says takes temp and
sort it and give it back to me.
And now I'm gonna say
print sorted comma temp.
Okay, so here's the first print.
When we flipped it, we've got two tent,
but it's not sorted at all.
But after we sorted it, it sorted by tuple
and the lowest is one
after, so you'll notice
that one is the same as one, so it checked
the second item in the tuple,
so down comes before after,
fell becomes after down.
Intro, on, alphabetical order,
but now we get the twos.
So all the ones sort there
and then the twos come here.
But then within the twos it's
sorting alphabetical order
'cause like a string, if
the first character matches,
then it looks to the second character.
And then we see, oh,
here we go, the threes
and then the one we actually wanted,
the highest one, is the seven.
And so one of the things
we can do is we can say,
you'll notice that we
want the highest one,
not the lowest one.
So we can just tell this
with this parameter.
Reverse equals true.
And we just say hey,
sorted, do this backwards.
Do it from highest to lowest,
rather than lowest to highest.
And now our sorted one
says seven the, et cetera.
Okay?
And so if we want the
first five, we can say,
up to but not including five.
So this is now the top five.
So the sorted one is, that's the top five.
If there is, it's a tie, we're gonna go
in reverse alphabetical
order, but let's not
worry about that too much for now.
So it makes a flipped list,
then it sorts the flipped list.
Now, if I just wanted
to print it out nicer,
I could loop through this new list.
I could say for V comma K.
Remember this is a flipped list
so the sensible thing is,
what's coming out of this list
each tuple is value comma key in temp
and I'm only gonna go up
through but not including five,
so the first five.
And so I'm pulling them
back out as value key,
'cause that's what they
are, they're value key.
See value key, value key, value key.
So V is gonna go through these
and K is gonna go through these.
And then I'm just gonna print,
K comma V, so this kinda
my flipping backwards
'cause I wanna see them this way.
And the is the most common one, car three,
and so it's just going through this
up through the fifth one
and then printing 'em out.
Okay?
So let me comment this out.
Let me comment that out.
Let me just delete this.
So we have a dictionary.
Let me comment out the dictionary.
We have a dictionary, we make a list,
and we make these reversed tuples where
we have the value first
and the key second.
We're setting it up so
the sort's gonna work.
And then once it's sorted,
we have to flip 'em back.
So we flip 'em for sorting from key value
to value key for sorting.
We do the sort, then we flip 'em back
with key value and print them out.
And it works fine, so let's
try our big file intro.txt
and there you go.
Those are the five most
common words in intro.txt.
So you might ask yourself
why did we use tuples?
We probably, we could have
really used lists for this,
but tuples are more efficient than lists
and you noticed that we
weren't going to modify.
We did modify the temp
list, it's a list of tuples,
but the tuples within the
list we weren't gonna modify.
And so we tend not to make lists if we can
get away with using tuples.
And so that's why we made this
flipped tuple thing, okay?
So I hope that was useful to you.
Hope to see you on the net.