- [Charles] Hello and welcome
to Python for Everybody,
I'm Charles Severance and
now we're going to take
a look at how we would write
some code to do some parsing,
read some data; as a
matter of fact we're going
to read through our famous
mailbox data, look for lines
that begin with from-space
and extract the third word.
Matter of fact, we already
have some of this code
already written, we're going to debug it,
we're going to look at code
and we're going to debug it.
And so here we go, here we have it,
it's a pretty basic
program, it opens a file,
loops through the file,
throws away the whitespace,
splits it into words and checks to see
if the zeroth word,
the first word is from,
and if it's not we skip
and read the next line,
and otherwise if we find a line
that starts with from-space then we print
the third word which
is word sub two, okay,
so this is what we got,
and we've carefully
saved this file into the
same folder that we've got,
EX zero eight, and so let's go ahead,
CD, desktop, python for everybody,
EX_08, and so this is, so files,
we've got our day of the week, python,
and our inbox short so
that's sitting there, okay.
And so let's run this
program, this is the program
that we've got right here, python three,
dow.py, and it doesn't work.
Now, by now you've seen a few trace-backs,
and there you go.
So you know, when you look
at a trace-back, you think
to yourself, well, I made a
mistake, something's wrong
on that line, and you've
gotten pretty good at
going and looking, oops, hang on.
Woah.
And you've gotten pretty
good at looking at that line,
so there you are, you're
like this is the line,
there must be something
wrong on this line,
and you want to change it,
but that line's not actually the problem
in this particular thing, and so
you've got to be careful sometimes,
and one of the things that
you didn't notice in this one
right away is that it actually worked.
It printed the first line out.
So if we take a look at our data set,
it found the line
starting with from-space,
it split it, and printed
out the third word,
and it blew up later.
And so part of the
problem is we don't know
what it was doing when it blew up.
And so the first thing
I like to do in this
kind of a situation is, find the line
and make sure there's a print statement
right before it, and so I'm going to print
words, colon, and then
comma wds, I want to print
right before the line that
blows up so that I know,
I know really when this
finally does blow up,
what was going on in that line.
So I'm going to run it again,
and ooh, did I forget to save it,
no, I forgot to save it, look at that,
see the little blue dot?
Forgot to save it.
So now we see a whole
bunch of output and we see
that it's actually doing
a whole lot of work
before it's blowing up, and so
you see that it prints the words out
from that first line,
it prints out Saturday,
which is exactly what we
expect, it's the third word in
the line, and then reads
a whole bunch of stuff,
and it's actually, what it's doing now
is ignoring, let me
just put something here,
I'm going to say print, ignore,
so I can keep track of when
these lines are being ignored,
so let's run it again and
have the word ignore pop up.
Right, and so it's
doing a lot of ignoring,
it prints, finds these
words, prints out Saturday,
reads this line and ignores it.
Reads this line, and ignores it.
Reads this line and ignores it.
So a lot of stuff's going on here
that you might not realize and so
we have to take a look
at what the problem is,
and so it is now blowing up word sub zero,
and now we can scroll
down and we can look at
exactly what happened right
before the trace-back,
so we really now know
exactly what happened
before the trace-back and
the interesting thing is
is that there is an empty, empty string.
I mean empty array, there's
an array with zero items.
So I'm going to print the line out too.
Print, line colon, now I haven't
changed my program at all, I'm just
trying to figure out what's going on here.
So save that, and then
I'm going to run it.
And we've got a lot of
stuff and it's still
working, it reads a line, it reads a line,
splits it into words and then prints out
Saturday, which is the
third word on the line.
Now here it reads a line and this line
is a blank line, and it has,
because it's a blank line,
the split returns no
words, and that's what
blows up, and the problem now is,
oh wait a sec, list index out of range.
So word sub zero is not valid,
which is the first word,
when there are no words.
So this is a statement that
works most of the time,
now you might think, "Oh, I want to just
put a try and accept in there."
Well, the right thing to
do is to say to yourself,
"Oh wait a sec, if,
I don't have enough words,
if the length of the words
is less than one, continue."
So basically it's going
to come through here,
it's going to split it,
and if we don't have
any words, meaning it's a blank line,
then we're going to skip
it, so let's run that.
So now this ran all the way to the end,
it did a lot of stuff
and it did not blow up,
specifically, it didn't have a trace-back.
Another way to protect this would be
to take this part out, this
is called a guardian pattern,
right, guardian pattern because
this, this is dangerous,
this could blow up, but
this, it won't blow up
if it makes it past
here, and it won't come
through there under the
conditions that are causing
it to blow up; another way to do this
might be to protect it as follows,
to say, "Oh wait a sec, if the line
is a blank line, null continue."
So now what we're going
to do is we're going
to skip blank lines, I even say this.
Print, skip, blank.
So if it's a blank we're
going to skip blank
and keep going, this'll skip blank lines,
it'll come through here, and this'll skip
lines that don't have
from, but because we're not
processing blank lines,
word sub zero always works,
so I can run this code and it works again,
so here we have a blank
line, we skipped it,
here we have a blank line, we skipped it.
Here we had a non-blank
line so we parsed it,
but then we ignored it, and then up here
we'll find a from somewhere,
let's find a from, here it comes.
Oh, no, ignore ignore ignore.
I got too much debug
print, I can't find it.
Here, I'll just hunt for from with find.
Okay so there we go, here, it's from,
and we print the thing out.
So we're getting a lot
of, lot of extra stuff,
so I'm going to comment
out some of these debugs,
and I'm actually going
to get rid of this whole
skipping of the blank
line, I'm going to do it
with the words; going to
go back to the guardian
we had before.
If the number of words that we got,
len of words, is less than one, continue.
Okay, so now this is going
to be a working program.
Oops, I got to take another
print statement out.
Got to take another print statement out,
we can sort of know what we're doing here.
Okay, so this looks like
a pretty safe thing,
this guardian is
protecting this dangerous,
I'll get rid of that one too.
This is the word that was traced back,
and nothing else in this thing
changed from when we started
except we've added this little guardian.
Now the interesting thing
is, if it comes through here
and prints word sub two,
what happens if somehow
we find a line that has
from as its first word,
and there's only one word
on, this is going to blow up.
So we can make our
guardian a little stronger.
And we can say you know what, we're going
to skip this line if it
doesn't have three words in it,
so it has to have at least three words,
and if we see less than three
words we're going to skip it,
and that just makes the
guardian a bit stronger.
And so the program works
safely, and you see these things
where you, sometimes
you want to check to see
reasonable, that your assumptions about
the data are reasonable
and skip things where
the data's not reasonable.
Now there, so that's one guardian pattern.
Let me show you a slightly different way
to do this, and this is
with an or statement,
so I'm going to take this code,
copy that, and put it here with or.
Get rid of all this stuff.
This is the guardian in
a compound statement.
So what we're saying is
if there are less than three words,
on the line or if the first
word is not from, continue.
Now, we were doing this in an order
because the way it works is, or is true
if either that's true or this is true,
but if it knows that this is true,
then it doesn't bother checking this,
and the checking of this is what blows up,
what causes the trace-back.
So if we flip this order it would fail,
if we do it in this order, it will work.
So let's do this one right, it works.
What if I get this, if
I get this backwards.
It's going to check this
before it checks this.
And we're going to go
back to failing again.
So you got to get the order
of these things right.
The guardian comes before, and the or,
the guardian comes before
and if this is true,
then it doesn't check this, this is called
short circuit evaluation, where it knows
that as long as this part's true,
it doesn't evaluate this second part.
And so now we have a guardian
in the compound statement,
you'll see this a lot.
Sometimes if it's more
complex you do it in multiple
statements, or you start
your follow through,
check for sanity, check for sanity,
and only run the code.
So I hope that that was useful to you,
looking a little bit about how to debug,
where you don't just start chopping
on the line that had the problem,
it's not always that
line, because we never did
change that line,
although we did change it
a little bit at the end, we added this
guardian here, but we
also fixed it without it.
You know, sometimes you
add some print statements
to figure out what's
going on before you just
stat chopping on that line, so again,
I hope this helps, thanks.