hi I'm Guido van Rossum I created the
Python language I have worked on Python
for 25 years and I've worked with a
large group of others of course in the
Python community I'm very excited to see
you all in this class and I'm very proud
that you're using my language to learn
that your teacher is teaching you I
phone is just the first step you're
setting on the path to programming there
are many exciting things to learn in
programming many that you can learn
using Python many that you can learn
using other things and you won't be
alone there will be millions of people
who have gone before you or who are
learning Python at the same time as you
and you you can help each other and you
can learn together