(instrumental jazz)
- [Charles] Hello everybody.
Welcome to Python for Everybody.
We're doing some code walk-throughs.
If you wanna get the source code
you can take a look at the sample code
and download it and work through it.
So what we're working on now
is doing some retrieval and
visualization of email data.
It's kind of ironic.
We are going to now
look at the email data,
look at the email data
that we started with.
It's the same Sakai
developer list email data.
There's this service called Gmane.
And Gmane archives developer
lists and various email lists.
And I've made a copy of their data
because all the students in
my class hitting the same,
their server with their
API would crush it.
So in order to be a nice guy
I put up a much more powerful server
with just the data from this one list.
And it's about a gigabyte of data.
So be real careful if
you're paying for network.
So the basic process
we're gonna go through
is we're gonna have a Spydering process
that's a simple, restartable,
focused on the network
problems, data pulling,
to pull content on sqlite.
There's gonna be a database there.
And then we're gonna
have a cleanup process.
This database is gonna get
large, about a gigabyte.
And then we're gonna have a process
that kind of grinds through this data.
It takes a while.
And then it's gonna read this mapping.
And I'll show you that when it comes
because things like
people's names have changed
over all these years.
And it doesn't cleanup.
It makes a really nice
highly relational version of this data.
And then we visualize from here.
So this could take you
several days to finish this.
This will take like a few minutes to run.
And then this'll just take seconds to run.
So this is a multi-step process
where if you were doing something
like running something for two days
to produce a visualization,
and it blew up 3/4 of the way through,
it wouldn't be good.
So that's why we break
this into simple parts.
But right now we're just gonna focus
on this part right here.
And take a look at the mail bit.
The mail bit, we retrieve the mail.
And then we'll have another video
to talk about the rest of this stuff.
So let's take a look at the code.
So here is gmane.py
that is the basic code.
Hopefully this stuff is
starting to look familiar.
The thing that's weird here
is we gotta do some daytime parsing.
And there is code that's out there
but you may have to install it.
And I had to write my code
in a way that didn't assume
that you could install the daytime parser.
And so it has it even.
If that's not there it uses
my own date time parser
and that's what this code is.
Don't worry too much about that.
And of course we have to deal
with the blackout
certificates inside of Python.
And so we start things out.
And this is really a simple table.
We've got a messages table
that's got a primary key.
The email itself, when it was sent,
what the subject, and the
headers, and the body.
And so what we're going to do is
because we have to pick
up where we left off.
We're going to select
the largest primary key
from the messages table.
And retrieve that.
And then we're gonna go
to the one after that.
And so we know what the ID is.
And we're gonna pick up where we left off.
And so we have a starting point.
That starts either zero or one.
And we're gonna ask how
many messages to retrieve.
Got some counters.
So we're gonna say C if
select ID from messages
where ID equals whatever that starting is.
It's the highest number we've seen so far.
And if we got, if row is not none,
that means we've already retrieved
this particular email message.
Otherwise we're gonna keep on going
and we're in good shape.
And this is one that we want to retrieve.
And we're subtracting that so we know.
And so this is the base URL.
This is the URL of our API,
the one that I,
I have a nice copy of all this data
on a server that's accessible
worldwide and won't crash.
So the format is you can say
I would like the email
address for one to two,
or from 100, oops.
From 102, 101.
Message 101 to 102.
We can just kind of walk
through these things.
So that's the message ID.
And so if we're going to make the URL,
we're gonna take the base URL,
add the starting address,
and then add plus one.
So we got the slash at the
end of the starting address.
And so that's how we form those.
And we're gonna retrieve that.
And we're gonna decode it.
We've seen this in some other ones.
We're gonna check to see
if we got legit data.
If not, like 404 not
found or something else
we're gonna quit.
If someone hits control
c which is our control z,
we get the program to
interrupt, then we'll stop.
If there's some other problem,
we're going to complain and keep going.
And if we have five failures
in a row we're gonna quit.
But it will just keep on going.
'Cause these things do
have glitchy bits here.
And so at this point,
if we've made it this far.
We retrieve the URL,
and we've got the number
of characters we retrieved.
And if we get bad data,
if it doesn't start with from,
'cause this is a mail message.
And they all start with from space.
If it's right, it starts with from space.
Then what we're going to tolerate
up to five failures there
for bad data.
'Cause it could be bad.
And then we're gonna find a blank line
'cause that's the new line
at the end of one line.
And then a blank line.
And then we're gonna take and
break this into the headers.
The mail headers,
which the mail headers
is this stuff right here.
Up to but not including the blank line.
And then the body is
everything after that.
So we'll just break that into pieces.
Otherwise we'll complain and
tolerate up to five characters.
And then we're gonna use
a regular expression,
kind of from the regular
expressions chapter
to pull out an email address
from the from colon line
somewhere in these headers.
From colon right there.
It's gonna go find a less than,
and then, oops.
Hold this stuff out up to it.
So you got the left stand,
you got the parenthesis,
you got one or more non-blank characters
followed by an at sign,
followed by one and characters.
And we'll get back a list of those.
We should only get one.
If we find one we're gonna grab the email.
We're gonna strip the lower case.
And if we've got some little
nasty less-than sign in there
we'll tolerate that as well.
So this is kind of cleanup,
and you get used to this,
where you're like oh how come
all those email addresses
have this other stuff in them?
And then we also look for it
if there are no less than signs.
And we do this way, that's different,
some mail messages have
it this way and others.
Again you write this code
after you watch it for a while
like oh it's crapped out
and giving me bad stuff.
And I make them all lower
case so they match better
and get rid of bad characters.
Now I got an email address.
Then what I do is I look
for the date of this.
I'm gonna add these by dates.
So I look for this line
and use a regular
expression to pull that out.
So I'm looking for a date
followed by a blank
followed by any number of characters
followed by a comma.
So I'm not interested
in this Wednesday bit,
so I'm skipping that bit right there.
And going and grabbing everything
after that comma space.
So it's really here to
the end of the line.
So that's the new line.
It's going all the way.
It's gonna pull this bit right here.
That's the text.
And this is where we're going to say
oh that's kind of a funky looking date
and we want to standardize that date
so we're gonna, let's see.
We're gonna chop it off
at the 26 character.
I don't know why do we
care about the 26 character
but we chop that off the 26 character.
And then we're gonna parse it.
And that's gonna give us
back a nice clean date,
sent at date.
We're gonna complete,
we're gonna quit.
And can't parse it.
Then we're gonna tolerate five
bad email addresses in a row.
Then we're looking for the subject line
using another regular expression.
Subject line, regular expression,
that's pretty easy.
Up to but not including,
there's a blank there.
It's subject.
We pull that out.
We get the subject.
Now at this point we parsed it.
We got good stuff so we
reset the fail counter
'cause I kept saying
if you fail five straight times you quit.
And we're gonna print it out,
and then we're just
gonna insert that stuff.
We've got the ID of the message,
which we've got,
the email address that it came from.
The time it was sent.
The subject, and then basically
the headers and the body.
Now we're just inserting it.
And now we're gonna say every
50th we're gonna commit it.
So that speeds things up.
And every 100th we're gonna wait a second.
So that's, count is going up, up, up, up.
And every 50th you'll see it pause.
And then every 100th
it'll pause for a second.
Mostly that's to let me hit control c
or to not overload any server.
Okay so that's the simple one.
The problem is that the
data just gets ugly.
And so you'll find yourself
wanting to reset this
and start it over.
This one's gonna work of course.
But these are hard to build.
And that's why it's a good idea, oops.
Python.
3gmane.py
How many messages?
Well let's just do one.
Okay so it went and grabbed,
oh do I have this already running?
51 through 52, let me start over.
Let's run a cell, start sqlite.
Okay RM content,
I must have run it to test it.
So let's run it again.
Python gmane.py
and ask for one message.
Okay so there we went and got message one
from one to two.
We got 2662 characters.
And we printed out the email address.
The time we got it after all that hacking.
And the subject line.
That's what we got.
So if we take a look at the database,
and we go into Gmane,
any time you see the
content sqlite journal
that means it needed to run a commit
And it hasn't run a commit,
but I'll hit enter and
that will do the commit.
And you see that vanish.
So now I can open it.
And I take a look at,
how come there's no messages?
That will not get stored
in there for some reason.
Needs to refresh.
Let's run it again.
Maybe it didn't commit.
We've got a bug in it.
Let's make a change to the code.
I'm going to, see this
connection dot commit.
See that?
Connection dot commit.
Gonna commit there.
And the other thing I'm
gonna do is every time
I stop to read,
I'm gonna commit right before I read it.
So I think we should, I
hope that doesn't blow up.
We'll see.
So the idea is if I wanna stop,
I want it committed.
So let's do this.
Let's do one message.
And now I should hit,
is it commit it.
Now that I've put the commits in,
I think that it will look better.
Refresh and so there it
is 'cause I committed it.
And I don't have the general file,
so that's good.
So that's a good idea,
put those commits there.
So I'll just leave those commits in.
When you download it it'll
have those commits in there.
So again I put a commit here,
and a commit at the very
very end to make sure.
So I missed that.
But now we get one.
And so let's just run it again.
And you'll see how by
selecting the max of the ID,
it's gonna select the max of this.
And then add one to it so
it doesn't do the next one.
So if I run it again,
I say give me one message.
So it goes two to three.
And give me two messages.
So I hit enter, and I can do refresh.
And now you see we've got four messages.
And so let's just fire this baby up.
Tell it to get 100.
Run, run, run, run, run, run, run.
It just goes and goes and
it pauses once in a while
to do a commit.
And if I made a commit every time,
oops it just paused there.
Now it finished.
So this'll run and we
will get a bunch of data.
The problem is is if I just run this,
it'll take about five hours.
To run this and get this all.
And I have a really fast connection.
So I have got a file
that you can download.
Let's go find it.
Let's see if I can,
we'll see how long it'll
take me to download this.
I've got a file that you
can download and save.
Now I'm gonna use the command line.
Curl or wget is another
command that we Linux
and Mac people can use.
Or not, you all might have
to use your browser to do it.
Let's see how long this is gonna take.
Retrieving.
Minute three.
Well I'll just wait and just come back.
(instrumental jazz)
Okay so now that's done.
I was averaging 10 megabits a second.
I downloaded about 600 megabytes,
10 megabits a second.
That will probably be slower for you.
So now if I take a look,
you're gonna find that
that content dot sqlite
is 624 megabytes.
Now what happens is
I've pre-Spydered this.
So now if you run gmane.py
and it asks for five more messages,
it will pick up where I left that one off.
So it's up to message 59,000.
And I think that, oh we saw an error.
Saw a bug in that one.
I don't know what's wrong with that one.
So let's see if,
so at this point we're
gonna have most of the data.
It might find its way to the very end.
Once you get this it should
be not too much more.
Maybe it's like 63,000 or something.
So what we'll do is we will let that run.
And we will come back
when that one's finished.
And run the next phase after
it's got all of its data.
So thanks for listening.
(instrumental jazz)