- [Narrator] Hello everyone, welcome to
Python for Everybody,
I'm Charles Severance,
I'm the instructor for the class,
and right now, I want
to go do Exercise 3.1,
rewrite the pay computation that we did
earlier in the previous chapter,
and give the employee one and
a half times the hourly rate.
This is rather simple, it's a
very classic computer problem,
'cause it gives us our if-then-else,
and there's a lot of
different ways to write it.
So we're just gonna do enter the hours
and the rate and do the pay.
And so, I'm gonna start
by going to my terminal,
cd into my Desktop, cd
Python for Everybody, and so
here we go, let me go into
Atom, and get things started.
I've already got this
folder, I mean this file
from the last one, assignment
2.3, and I'm just gonna
Save As, so I'm gonna duplicate this file,
and I am going to go up to py4e,
and then I'm gonna make a new folder,
I'm gonna call that folder
ex_03_01 for Exercise 3.1.
And then I'm gonna call this ex_03_01.py.
Now that's just the
same files I had before,
if I do an ls, you'll see
I've got the new folder,
so I cd into the ex_03_01 folder,
so that's the folder that I'm in,
all the way down into this folder,
and I do an ls, and I see this file,
and so life is good,
and I can say python3,
ex_03_01.py, I'll just
put in 10 10, so it's 100.
Now the thing is, is that
we're supposed to give
time and a half for overtime,
so that means if there's
more than 40 hours,
10 and 50, it's not supposed to be 500,
it's supposed to be 500
plus half of 10 extra hours,
'cause the 10 extra hours
are the 10 above 50,
so that should be, I don't
know, we'll figure it out.
It's easier to run a computer.
Okay, so this is the code we've got.
So, what I'm gonna do is change this,
I'm gonna make a new variable called ar,
I'll call it fr, stands
for floating point rate,
and floating point rate
is going to be the float
of the string rate, let me just call this,
sh for string hours
and sr for string rate,
and sr, so my variable is
fr for floating point rate,
just so I can keep them
straight in my head,
sh is string hours,
and so now I wanna say,
floating point hours is equal
to float of string hours.
And now I can change this so
I just enter in fh times fr.
So I split this out, I can
even, like, print (fh, fr).
It's perfectly fine
when you're writing this
to add extra print statements
just for your own sanity.
So now we're gonna read the two values,
we're gonna convert 'em
to floating point numbers,
we're gonna print those
floating point numbers out,
we're gonna multiply 'em, and then
we're gonna have the pays.
And then I save it, always
remember to save it, right,
so it has this little dot up here,
all editors give you
some thing that tells you
you didn't save it, so
I always keep saving it,
because if you come down here and
you run it, and it's
like, it didn't change,
well, that's because you forgot.
So let's do our 10 and 50 hours,
so we see this extra print
statement that came out,
that's that extra print
statement right there,
let me make this a little smaller
and let's move this over here,
so we can see it a little better.
Yeah, make it a little bigger,
so we can see a little better,
so that print statement's there.
Just for yuks, I'm gonna comment that out,
and so commenting things out
is a good way to keep stuff in
that you might wanna kind of turn back on,
it's a way of thinking
about it, I don't want
this line to run, but
I'm just keeping it here.
Comments are usually for
users to read, but they're
also a way to tell the computer
to ignore what we're doing.
So, the problem here is this calculation,
that is not time and a half for overtime,
so the way we're gonna solve
this is with an if statement.
If the floating point hours, fr,
is greater than 40, we should,
I'll say, print overtime, and then,
else, colon, the if and the else
have to line up, print regular.
So, I'm not gonna do anything different,
I'm just gonna print the words
regular and overtime, OK?
And I just save that, I'll do it so fast,
you watch the little blue
dot happen and then go away,
that's 'cause I hit Command+S to save it,
because I've done this way too many times.
So I'm gonna run it,
I'm gonna say, oh wait,
hours is 10 hours, $10 an hour,
it's regular pay, if I do it this way,
I can do 50 hours at $10 an hour.
That's not good, what'd I do wrong?
fr is greater than 40,
what did I do wrong,
it's still saying for 50
hours, something's wrong here.
It's saying it's regular,
if fr is greater than,
oh, that's 'cause I just
messed my program up.
So look, I called this
variable sh, and this sr,
and then I get the floating
point for the hours
but look, I'm checking if the
rate, fr, that's the mistake.
So it's really I've got to look for fh,
that's a logic error, it's
a perfectly fine program,
Python's perfectly happy with that,
and I was messin' up, I kept puttin',
see, I was typin' the rate in, I was just
typin' it backwards, I
was crazy, and again,
that can be the kind of mistake
that you run into, I mean I
didn't do that on purpose.
I did it, 'cause I haven't
drank enough coffee yet
this morning, hang on,
lemme get some coffee.
(sips coffee)
I have more coffee, I'm
still gonna make mistakes.
So now, there's no little blue dots,
so it should work better now.
Python, run it, so, 10 hours, $10,
is regular pay, run it, 50 hours, $10,
I did it wrong again, I
told you what I wanted
to change and then I didn't change it, fh.
I'm like, crazy, again, you can
be crazy, too, can you look right at it?
I looked right at it,
I did the wrong thing.
Hooray, it says overtime, and
now you'll notice, I'm not
being silly here, where I
put this print statement in,
and it's so tempting for a programmer
to just immediately try to bam, finish it,
and I don't know why I did it this way.
Maybe 'cause I know that I'm flawed,
and I know that I make dumb mistakes
like that, and what can I do?
So I was just being really careful there.
Now I know, let's just be sure, if it's
under 40 hours, it's gonna
be a regular computation,
and I'm gonna leave these print statements
right in here for a
while, 'cause whatever.
So, here's the interesting thing,
so I'm just gonna indent this,
'cause the regular pay is to take
the number of rate the
hours times the rate, OK?
And now I gotta come up with a slightly
different pay, xp is equal to,
and so there's a couple ways to do this.
We can say, time and a
half can be calculated
by saying the number,
the rate times the hours,
let's do it this way,
let's call it regular,
the regular pay is the
rate times the hours,
fr times fh, and then the overtime pay
is equal to the, now we know that we have
more than 40 hours, 'cause
we couldn't do this in here,
so if I say the number of hours
that you've worked, fh minus 40.0,
that is the number of hours above 40.
So if this is 50, then the
fh minus 40 is gonna be 10.
And then I'm gonna multiply
that times the rate, fr,
except you get one and
a half times, right,
so your overtime pay is the excess hours
times one and a half times the rate.
Actually, no, see, I see
I made a mistake already,
the extra overtime pay, 'cause
you're gonna get all your
regular pay, so the 50 percent,
or the half, is the extra.
And see I'm confused, so
I'm just gonna print out
reg, otp, and if those numbers are right,
I can do xp which is the
pay is equal to reg + otp.
See, my program is, I have
to make it a little smaller,
let's make it so you
can see the whole thing.
So I think I got this right, I figure that
the regular hours, which
is giving you the base rate
for all 50 hours or 45 hours,
or whatever, figuring out
the excess hours, and
this is the bonus amount.
There's lots of different ways
that you can calculate this.
But in general, we have an
if statement on this side,
and this else is the easy one,
and that's 40 hours or less,
so if we're doing greater than 40.
So I just hit Command+S to save it,
and so let me clear my
screen with Command+K,
so I'm gonna do 10 hours at $10 an hour
and that's a regular
calculation, and it's $100.
And so if I do 50 hours at $10 an hour,
so my regular pay was 50 times 10,
and then the excess pay is $5 an hour
times the extra 10 hours, which is $50,
and so my pay is $550,
and so it looks like
I've got this calculation right.
And so, here's the
thing, I've been putting
these extra print statements in,
it's a real common thing for a programmer,
and you can look on GitHub
and see code that I write,
and I just leave these
in, because you know
that could be broken, but
you're not supposed to
print this extra stuff
out, and if you do this
in the auto-grader, it's gonna complain
about these extra things, it's
gonna consider you broken.
And again, so I comment those
out to do one final test,
and notice the little blue
dot, so I have to save it,
and now I can run it one more time.
And I do 10 hours, $10, and it prints out
exactly what I wanna see and not
the extra stuff, 'cause
I commented 'em out.
And I do 50 hours and $10 an hour is $550.
So I've got it right, and at that point,
you should be able to go back
and go to your auto-grader,
if this was in the auto-grader,
and paste the stuff in, OK?
So, I hope this exercise 3.1 was useful,
and thanks for watching.