- Hello and welcome to
Python for Everybody,
my name is Charles Severance,
and I'm the author of the book
and teacher of this class.
In this particular
session, we are going to do
exercise 6.5 from the textbook.
It's an exercise in parsing text strings.
And so the basic idea is is
we're going to see strings
of various kinds and various lengths
and we're gonna want to
extract pieces of them, ok?
And so the idea is to
somehow get this part out
and then convert it to
a floating point number.
This is a proxy for later things
where we're actually reading files,
or reading stuff off the internet,
but parsing strings is an
important thing for us to do, k?
And so let's take a look at a couple
of different ways to do this.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Let's go bring up our Atom
and I've got it open nicely
to the right spot here,
and I'm gonna make a new folder.
Hopefully by now you're finding Atom,
Ex_06_05;
Atom or whatever your program or editor,
is a sort of a powerful tool.
I'll close this one, file, new file.
Powerful tool, that lets you sort of
save a lot of keystrokes, etc., etc.
Print,
exercise 6.5, just for yaks.
Ex-er-cise,
and file, save as, and
again, until I save it,
it's not gonna have the pretty colors.
I'm gonna save it in
6_05,
Ex_06_05.py,
and now it has the pretty colors.
And here I am.
Now I've been doing these,
and so now I'm actually
already in a directory.
So let me show you how to
do relative directories.
So, I'm in this path right here,
and I can use, both in Windows
and in Mac and in Linux,
I can use the command: cd ..
That sort of thinks of the one before,
the one that came before.
And so I'm up one directory.
And if I do an ls, I will
see that this new ex_06_05
that I just created in this directory
from Atom is already there.
cd ex_06_05.
In the next chapter we'll
be talking about files,
and this is where you really
need to know this concept
of folders and files.
So ls, and I'm gonna
run python3 ex_06_05.py.
There we go, exercise 6.5.
So we're sort of in the right
spot, we've got this going,
and we got this going.
Pretty soon we'll be putting
stuff in these directories
that need to be there,
and you'll see how all
that'll work in a second.
Well, in the next chapter,
we gotta know all this stuff.
Okay, so we'll just grab
this first line here
and paste that in.
print str, so.
Let's run it, and there we go.
Actually there's supposed
to be a space right there,
so I don't know why this space
didn't get copied and pasted
from my copy and paste, so
I'm gonna put that space in.
There's supposed to be
a space right there.
I think, but we'll see.
So, the key thing is if you look at
the lectures from this section,
you can, like, look for things,
and you look for a pattern.
And so what I'm gonna do is
I'm going to look for a pattern
that says, find me a colon.
Okay, and I'm gonna say,
where is there a colon, equals str.find,
and then print out ipos.
So I'm gonna say, where in
this string is there a colon?
Now that's gonna give me the
position and offset of that.
So that says that the
colon is in position 18.
Now, it's not always gonna be 18.
Sometimes these strings will
be a little bit different, k?
So, the next thing I can do is I can say,
a small piece of this
string is do str, and then,
starting from that position,
ipos through the end of the string.
And then we're gonna print that out.
Print out the piece.
And when I'm doing a string
parsing, tearing strings apart,
I tend to have a lot of situations
where I print over and
over and over again.
So now let's see if that
piece is the right piece,
and the answer is it
doesn't quite look right,
because, see, I've got that colon there,
and that's because, it says,
start at 18, position 18,
where that is, and then keep on going.
And so I need to do
ipos + 1, so let's see.
I'll just sort of advance past
this little colon character
and get into that space, okay?
So let's run it.
So now I've got space 08475,
and, now I can just see, value,
equals float of piece.
'Cause piece is a string, it's a string.
And then I'm gonna say, print value,
to see if I got the value right.
And let's remember that
there's a space here,
this might mess up float.
I don't think it's gonna mess up float,
cause float's trying to
find a floating point number
and it kinda, well, let's
just see if it works.
Let's just see if it works.
Okay, so the key is there,
is it's in position,
the colon is in position 18,
the string we pulled out is blank 08475,
and the floating point number is 0.8475.
So we've sort of solved this.
Now, I can clean this up a little bit
by making that plus two, so let's just,
I'll just change that to plus two,
and you'll see how that
changes what I'm doing.
And so now, this here is the string,
that one there is the string,
this is the actual floating point number,
they're the same thing other than the fact
that it's a floating point number,
and you can add something to it.
So I could do something
like, print, you know,
value + 42.0, and that
would actually work, right?
So 42 point, and if I did, print piece,
plus 42.0,
that will blow up, right?
Because piece is a
string, and 42 is a float.
And it says, can't convert float object
to string implicitly, okay?
And so, other than sort of
taking out this extra stuff,
I'm just commenting out a
whole bunch of stuff here.
So I take out all those print statements,
these five lines are the lines
to do this particular assignment,
where we are tearing apart a string.
And in the future, the source,
this is just so that we
can play with strings,
but later, we'll be taking this data
from all over the place.
Finally, we're gonna
start opening some files
and then later in the
course, we're gonna be
doing opening data from databases,
we'll be opening data from the internet.
And so there's all kind of data
where we get these strings,
but for now, we're in chapter six,
and we're only focused on strings.
So I hope you found this useful,
and coming up soon,
we'll be opening files.