- [Charles] So hello!
Welcome to Python for Everybody,
I'm Charles Severance, your instructor.
In this assignment, I mean in this video,
I want to work through exercise 2.2.
And it's just a basic
hello kind of hello world.
So I'm going to show you how
I want to do these things.
And I've got this folder
called Python for Everybody,
and I'm gonna use the Adam text editor.
So the whole thing is it's supposed
to say hello, enter your name.
There's the last one we did.
Okay, so I'm gonna make
in Python for Everybody
I'm gonna make a new folder.
New folder, and I'm gonna
say ex zero two, zero two.
Make myself an exercise, and
I'm going to create a new file.
And I wanna say print hello.
And I'm gonna save file, save as,
and it's important to get
these in the right folder.
And so I'm gonna call
this ex zero two dot py.
Always end these in Python
because then you get
the syntax highlighting.
Okay, so now... (sighs)
Again you're not gonna like this
but I want you to learn
to execute these things
using the tool, the real tools
that we're gonna really use
because when you're applying this,
I want you to know how
to actually do real work.
So I need to get to the point
where this Terminal program,
and I can say start run Terminal.
That's another way to get
the Terminal program started,
but I've got it down here in my dock,
so that saves me some time.
And of course if you're on Windows,
this is the command prompt.
And so in Windows you'd type cd,
but in Mac I type pwd and that shows
where I am at in the directory structure.
And I can go into my desktop.
This would work the same.
And I can do an ls.
In Windows I would say der,
and I see this desktop folder.
And I'm gonna go into py4e
and if I keep doing pwd,
you see I'm navigating deeper and deeper
into this directory structure.
And then I do an ls here,
and I'm gonna cd one more
time and if to a folder.
Oh, I did that really quick
and didn't tell you what I was doing.
Cd ex tab, so that's because if
the name of the file or folder is unique,
you can hit the tab in the command line.
And away we go, so now
we're in this folder.
In the user's folder py4e desktop,
py4e ex zero two zero two.
And then if I say ls...
And that's where you wanna get to.
You wanna get to where you know
where you're at in the folder structure
and you know the file
that you're going to run.
And I've saved, and so if I save
python three ex zero two dot py, it runs.
And now I know that what I'm doing
in this screen can be run in this screen.
And oh, I did that again.
I hit the up arrow and I can run it again.
So you'll find that the way
you write these programs
is you write them here,
and then write them
here and run them here.
And again there are shortcuts,
and those are crutches
and you might like them
but I just want you to learn
how to use your computer
like a real person uses the computer
because when we start dealing
with databases and files,
you're gonna wanna know where
you're at on your computer.
And so if there's some
fancy clicky button thing
that says automatically run Python,
that's convenient but I want
you to know all this stuff.
Okay enough about...
(laughs)
Well probably I'll just keep talking
about that all the time.
So now that we've got our problem.
Write a program that uses input to prompt
for their user name and welcomes them.
So this is pretty simple.
Go back to Adam, come one Adam.
Okay, so we have to have a variable, nzt.
Later we'll talk about
choosing variable names.
Right now I'm gonna choose
a crazy variable name.
Input is a function and
then you put a prompt,
and that's supposed to be enter your name,
colon, and I'm gonna put a space in there.
So I'm gonna save that,
and just run it for yucks.
And there you go.
That's one thing you'll get used to
is just typing gibberish really quick.
And then we're gonna say print.
What do we gotta say here?
Print hello.
(types on the computer)
And go pull that variable back out,
save that command s,
is how I'm savin' that,
save command s, I saved it.
So I didn't make file save,
but I could've said file save
but command s saves it,
and now I can run it again.
Zap. Hello zap.
So now I can run my thing.
Oh and command k clears it.
I don't remember what it is on Windows,
but there's a way to clear your screen.
I like to keep my screens clean.
Hello chuck.
And so we have completed exercise
2.2 with a little program.
Oh and by the way, I'm using alt tab.
When you see this, I'm
using the alt command tab
and the same thing works
on Windows as alt tab.
Okay?
Okay, so I hope that was helpful to you.
Just to kind of walk through
one of the assignments,
assignment 2.2 in Python for Everybody.