("Soul and Mind" by E's Jammy Jams)
- [Charles] Hello,
everybody and welcome to
Python for Everybody.
We're going to do some code walk-through
and if you want to follow
through with the code,
you can download the sample
code from Python for Everybody.
And so the code that we're gonna play with
is the Twitter spider code
that is both talking to
the Twitter API and
talking to the database.
So what we're going to be
doing is we're going to
run code that's going
to hit the Twitter API,
much like we did in a previous chapter.
And we're gonna retrieve
the data, but we're gonna
remember the data so we don't
have to retrieve it again.
Okay, and so we're going to
keep track of peoples' friends.
And what we're doing here is
sort of illicitly pulling down,
slowly but surely, based
subject to our rate limit,
we're pulling down who our friends are.
And so let's take a look.
We're gonna use urllib and urllib.error,
the Twitter URL, which was
code that augments my URL
to do all OAuth calculation.
We're gonna get json data back.
We're gonna make a database,
and we have to import SQL
because of the way Python
doesn't trust any certificates
no matter how good they are.
So this is our URL to
talk to the Twitter API.
We're going to make a database.
And again, the way sqlite
works is if this spider.sqlite
doesn't exist, it creates it.
And we get ourself a cursor.
And we're gonna do a create table.
This if not exists, some
SQLs, but sqlite3 does this.
Create table if it doesn't exist.
And you wanna start this over and over,
unlike the tracks example,
I wanna start this
over and over and not lose data.
This is a spidering process.
And we'll see a lot of these.
We want a restartable process
where we use a database.
So if we're starting with nothing,
and there's no file spider.sqlite,
it creates this table.
And it's the name of the person,
whether we retrieved it or not,
and how many friends this person has
that we know of in our database.
Now this little bit is to deal with
the SSL certificate errors.
The certificates are totally fine,
but Python doesn't trust
any certificates by default,
which is frustrating, but whatever.
So here we're gonna have a loop.
We're gonna ask for a Twitter account.
We have to type quit to quit.
If we hit enter in this case,
we're going to actually
read from the database
an unretrieved Twitter person,
and then grab all that person's friends.
Okay?
And so then we're gonna
do a fetchone, get one,
and that's going to get the name
of the first person, the sub zero.
If we had more things than name here,
sub zero is the first of those.
Fetchone means get one
row from the database,
and sub zero means the first
column of that first row.
And if this fails then we've
retrieved all the Twitter accounts.
We're gonna augment this
Twitter URL using this makes,
you can look at the twurl.py code.
This basically requires
the hidden.py file,
which has your keys and secrets in it.
You gotta get hidden.py updated.
I've got it updated, but
I'm not going to show you
because it has my keys and secrets in it.
And so we're only gonna
take the first five,
which means we're
probably not going to find
friends of friends of friends.
It's only the most five recent ones.
We could run this with
a much higher number,
so we have more than one friend.
We'll show the URL while we retrieve it.
We will do our urlopen, we'll do a read,
and then we'll do a decode
to make sure that this utf.
This will give us data in utf-8,
and then decode will
give us data in Unicode,
which is what we need inside of Python.
We will ask for the headers
from the connection.
We'll say give me the headers,
give me a dictionary of the headers,
and the x-rate-limiting
header from the Twitter API
tells us when we're going to get told
we can't use this API anymore.
Because this is one of those things.
And then we're gonna
parse and load the data
that we got from Twitter and get a,
I think it's a list, yeah it's a list.
And then we could dump this, if you want,
in yours you can undo that.
And then what we're going
to do is we just retrieved
this person's screen
name and their friends.
And so the first thing we want
to do is update the database
and change the retrieve from zero to one.
And that's because we want,
we're going to use this
to know about unretrieved.
So retrieved being one means
we've already retrieved it.
And we did retrieve it,
so for that account we've retrieved it.
And then what we're going to do is
we're going to parse that.
And so this is similar to the Twitter code
we did previously in Web Services chapter.
We're gonna go through all the users,
we're gonna find their screen name,
we're gonna print their screen name out,
okay?
And then what we're going to do is
see if, let's see,
so we're going through all the users
who are friends of this
person and we're gonna say
oh, okay, let's select
the friends from Twitter
where the name is the friend person.
And what we're gonna do is
we're going to do a
cur.fetchone of this Twitter,
the name of the friend's,
this is the friend's screen name, right?
So, we're going to say oh, okay.
If we get this, we're going to
get the friend's screen name
and we're going to get how many friends
this particular screen name has.
If we find a URL, we find it in there,
we're going to do an update statement
and add one to their friend count,
how many friends they have.
And then keep track.
This count here is not in the database,
it's just so I can
print it out at the end.
If there is no record for
this particular friend,
we're going to insert them into with new,
and we're going to say
here is the new person
that we just saw.
Here, that's their name.
We're going to set retrieve to zero.
And we're going to say
that they have one friend.
Okay?
And then we're gonna
commmit the transaction,
and then we're gonna close
this at the end, okay?
So, let's go ahead and run this.
The first time it's gonna
create an empty database.
So I'm gonna say python3 twspider.
So, ls *sqlite...
Nothing there.
Python3, oops, that's
because I removed it.
Python3 twspider.py.
Okay.
So I'm gonna start with a
Twitter account, drchuck.
So its doing its retrieval,
and don't worry, showing the token
and the signature is not dangerous,
because you don't have
the keys or the token.
I mean the secrets and the token secrets.
So don't get all too worried.
So I have 11 calls left, so
I gotta hope this all works.
One of my friends is Stephanie Teasley,
and I do, these are in reverse order,
so let's grab Stephanie and
ask for Stephanie's friends.
So now we've just retrieved
Stephanie's friends
and here are Stephanie's
most recent friends.
And then I can just hit enter
and it will randomly pick.
Let's see if I can in the
database, let's open this up.
File, open database.
Hope I don't lock myself.
Sometimes it's a little scary
when you look at the database
and you're just checking.
So this is what my database looks like.
We retrieved Stephanie and she has,
this is how many people,
so these are the friends
of Stephanie and me,
and these are how many, I'm not in there.
So we've retrieved Stephanie,
which was a friend.
So let's go grab, oh I don't know,
let's grab Tim McKay and get that one.
Remaining 10, I don't
have too many of these!
Tim McKay, alright, so there we go.
Remaining nine.
And so if I do a refresh on this,
then you see I've got some more folks.
If I hit enter here, it will retrieve,
it will pick one randomly based
on the retrieve being zero.
So it won't pick Stephanie
or Tim because they're zero
but we have lots of other
folks to pick randomly.
And we'll hit enter, so it
picked, who did it pick?
It picked screen name
liveedutv, which is ironic
because I'm recording this
on liveedutv right now.
And so we can keep hitting refresh,
and away we go.
So I'm gonna stop now because
I only have eight remaining.
And so I'm gonna type quit
and so we will see how that works.
So that's how it works.
Now, remember that you've got to
edit the hidden.py file to make this work
because we're talking to the Twitter API.
If you don't edit that file,
it won't work for you.
Okay?
So I hope you find this useful.
Cheers.
("Soul and Mind" by E's Jammy Jams)