- [Charles] Hello and welcome
to Python for Everybody.
My name is Charles Severance.
I'm your instructor,
and in this particular video,
we are going to do exercise 7.1.
And this, honestly, even though
it's a really simple exercise,
is one of my favorite
exercises in the book,
because in chapters one through six,
we've been just kind of
learning the basic mechanics.
It's like we just, you know,
it says, "Bonjour," and we say, "Bonjour."
And it's, we're learning,
but it's not very fun,
'cause we're not really solving it.
So this is our first program
that's gonna read a file
and do something with it.
And the only thing we're gonna do
is we're gonna convert it to uppercase.
So it's just a really simple file, okay?
So here we go.
But the nice thing, so
this is important, though,
I keep it simple, because
you gotta figure out
how to manage files.
And that's the payoff for everything
that we've done up till now.
So let's close that one
and say file, new folder.
E-X-0-7-0-1, welcome to
files, here we are in files.
File, new file.
And I'm gonna say file, save as,
and put it in E-X-0-7-0-1,
and I'm gonna call it,
I could probably come up with
a better naming convention
than these things,
but it works for me, and I'm a programmer.
And so here we have this file.
Let's start up a shell,
a terminal program,
command line in Windows, shell in Unix.
Cd Desktop, cd python for everybody,
folder in the desktop.
Oh, py4e, cd_ex_07 +
tab to get me to that,
in this working directory,
and I have these files in there,
and so I say, python three.
Python three, ex_07.
I saved this, so it's an empty file.
Python's perfectly happy
running absolutely nothing,
because I guess you've made no mistakes.
Okay.
Now, here's the key thing.
We have, in this situation,
we've got to have this file.
And this, this version of the
website has pythonlearn.com.
This could also py4e.com,
but what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna control + click on this.
Control + click, open
link in new tab, 'kay?
So now I have this new
tab, and this is the file.
Okay, and this is the file
that we're gonna read.
We're gonna read this file, 'kay?
Lots of stuff in this file.
You're gonna get to know
this file really well.
The key is, is we've got to put
this file in this directory,
because this program is
running in this directory
and this program needs to open the file.
And this is where if you
got some magic little button
and, you know, whatever, click run Python,
it doesn't know what
directory it's running it in.
That's, so we gotta get
this file in a directory
so the program runs in the same directory
so it can open the file
we're looking at, right?
So here's the directory we wanna go to.
And I'm gonna say, so I've
got this file sitting here,
and this works for text files,
once they're sort of
viewable in the browser.
I'm gonna say file, save page as,
and I'm going to go to my desktop.
Make this a little bigger.
Python for everybody, ex_07_01.
And you'll see this is sitting here,
and I'm just gonna say, save.
So that's now been saved as
if I'd downloaded the file.
So let's go into the
terminal and do an LS.
And so you see that by my
action here in the browser,
I have saved a file into
the exact same folder
that I've got the code for 7-1.
So now I can open this file
and I can make sense of this file, okay?
So I'm going to Atom, and you
see Atom even sees the file.
So now I can even open the file in Atom.
And here's the file in Atom.
Atom knows how to read these text files.
And so away we go.
So now ex07.py.
This next few lines of code
you're gonna get to know pretty well.
And so I'm gonna create a variable called,
oh, come back, I was in the wrong place.
I'm gonna open the file
with the open command,
fh = open('nbox-short.txt').
Now remember that open does
not actually read the file.
It kinda gives us this little portal
where we can take a look at the file.
And so if I print fh, you might expect
it will contain all this
data, but it doesn't.
It just is a file handle.
So let me run that.
Python3 ex_07.py, okay.
So it's, it knows some information.
This, we'll learn later what objects are.
This is a Python object that
has some information in it.
But the information in this object
is not actually the file data.
To read the file, we're
gonna write a while loop.
I mean a for loop,
sorry, not a while loop.
So we're gonna say for lx,
again that, line is a good name here,
but I wanna use a non-mnemonic variable.
For line in fh: and then
I'm just gonna say print lx.
Okay, so this is gonna
loop through every line
in the file and print it out.
Gonna have to make this
a little bigger now,
'cause it's gonna be very chatty.
So that is just our loop to read through,
maybe make this a little smaller.
There we go.
Oh boy, oh boy, oh boy.
Missing parentheses in call to print.
What am I doing wrong here?
Well, problem is, is
I've been using Python 2
for so, so long that when I'm
not drinkin' enough coffee,
then I'm gonna talk Python 2.
So the right way to do this,
so let me just run this
in, ah, never mind.
I won't run it in Python
2, I'll just fix it,
'cause prints go in
parentheses in Python 3.
And so I save it, and
now let's run it again.
Okay, so there you go.
Now, as we scroll through this,
you see right away the problem that
I'll get rid of that print
statement right there.
Let's get rid of that
guy, just delete him.
We know how that line works.
But you see this extra space, remember?
Because in the file, there is a new line.
So if you go over here,
let me make this wide, as well.
There is a non-printing character
at the end of every line
called the new line,
which is the way in
files we store the fact
that it goes back to the beginning.
So it's like, character,
character, character,
character, character, k-ch!
Go back to the beginning,
that was a new line, you know?
Character, character,
character, character,
character, character, character,
the next character's a three,
the next character's a new line,
and so it goes to the
beginning of the next line.
So that's the new line, and print,
the print statement
automatically adds a new line.
And so in this case, we have
one new line from the file,
and then we have another new
line that prints adding, 'kay?
And, but that's okay.
We can say ly = lx.strip,
actually rstrip,
to strip the characters
from the right-hand side,
the non-printing characters
from the right-hand side.
And then we'll print out ly.
So I'll clear my screen
and run that again.
So it does exactly the same thing,
but you don't see all these blank lines.
And so this, so ly's a different variable.
I made a strip of it, and then I did,
printed ly instead of lx.
If I'd have printed lx, I'd
get these extra blank lines.
And so this is a very common thing.
You open a file, you loop through it,
through all the lines in the file,
and then you throw away
the non-printing characters
at the end of the line.
And then you do something with it.
And so right now, we're just printing it.
But what we're supposed
to do in our assignment
is make it uppercase.
And so let's just call, the upper method,
to make 'em all uppercase,
see if that works.
And there you go.
And so now the line has been shouted,
they're only one line and
everything is fine, right?
So, it's been shouted, all uppercased,
this little syntax here
is what's called a method.
This is a string variable,
and upper is a method
within the string variable
that returns us an
uppercased version of that.
And again, that's
object-oriented terminology,
and we will learn about
that in a upcoming chapter,
but for now we just sorta
type it and understand it,
and later we'll understand better
that there's a whole
series of things you can do
after this dot for a variable in Python.
And so there you have the exercise 7.1
for the book Python for Everybody.
I hope you found this useful.
See you on the net.