(smooth music)
- [Charles] Hello everybody.
Welcome to Python for Everybody.
We are doing some code walk throughs.
If you wanna follow along with the code,
you can download the source code from
Python for Everybody dot, the
Python for Everybody website.
Okay?
So, the code we're playin' with today is
T W friends dot P Y.
And, this is a step beyond
the simple T W spider.
It is a restartable spider.
But, we're gonna data model
things a little bit differently.
We're gonna have two tables
and we're gonna have a,
a many to many relationship,
expect that it's sort of a many
to many relationship between
the same table, which is okay.
Friends is a,
Twitter friends are a
directional relationship.
And so, so we start out
here in T W friends dot P Y.
Remember that the file hidden dot P Y,
I'll show it to you but
I'm not gonna open it
'cause I've got my keys and secrets in it.
So, this hidden dot P Y file,
you gotta edit that and you
gotta go to apps dot Twitter
dot com and get your keys
and put them in there, otherwise
these things won't work.
But, if you have Twitter
and you set your API keys up
and you put them in hidden dot P Y,
then all these things will work.
It's kinda fun, actually, and impressive.
Not hard to do, actually.
So,
(clears throat)
the Twitter URL, that's my
library that reads hidden dot P Y
and augments the URL and does
all the Oh WOT stuff, jay son
and S S L, because Twitter
doesn't, I mean because Python
doesn't accept any certificates,
even if they're good certificates.
So, we kinda crush that.
Here's our friend's list
that we're gonna hit.
We're gonna make a database,
friends dot S Q lite.
Now, here we're doing
create table if not exists.
So, what this really is saying is,
I want this to be a restartable process,
and I don't wanna lose the data.
If we're starting out,
we do not have S Q lite,
any S Q lite files,
and so this is going
to create the database
and create these tables, but
the second time we run it,
we're not gonna recreate the tables.
We're not gonna, we're gonna
be able to restart this
because we're gonna run out of,
we're gonna run out of rate
limit before we finish this,
but, so, we just have to
wait however long the rate,
the time it takes to reset.
We'll watch the rate limit go down.
And, so we're gonna have a people table
and we're gonna have a
primary key and the name.
The name is gonna be unique.
And, whether or not we've retrieved it.
And, that's kinda from a previous one.
But then there's the who follows who.
The from ID to to ID.
So, this is a direction and
we're going to put a uniqueness
constraint in just like we do
in many to many that basically
says the combination of from ID and to ID
has got to be unique.
We don't allow ourselves to put duplicates
of the combination.
So, from ID can be one in many
records and to ID can be one
in many records but one,
one is only allowed once.
And, this is the crud we
have to do to convince Python
to accept the Twitter certificate.
And, so this is similar
to some of the other stuff
that we've done.
We're going to enter a
Twitter account or quit.
And, if we hit enter by itself,
then we will actually go
and retrieve a record that
was not yet retrieved.
And, now we're actually pulling
out two values: ID and name.
And, so we will, we will grab,
fetch one is gonna give us a
two tuple, basically.
And, we're gonna store
that in ID and account.
Of course, that's like, this
is, this is coming back with
a two tuple, first of which
is the ID from the database.
Limit one means we're only
gonna get one of these,
or zero of these.
If there are zero of these,
that means there are no
un-retrieved Twitter accounts.
Retrieved equals zero, well
you'll see in a second that the,
all the new accounts
we put in are the ones
for which we haven't retrieved.
And, again given that our rate limit,
we wanna know which ones we've retrieved.
Okay?
And, and so what we're gonna
do next is we're gonna check
to see if the person that we just checked,
which means the length of the
account is greater (mumbles),
that we just were entered.
We're gonna check to see
if they're already there.
Okay?
And, we're gonna select ID
from people where name equals.
So, that's the one we just entered.
And, we're gonna fetch one
and grab the first thing,
'cause we only got one thing
in the select statement, here.
And, if this person that
we just asked to see is not
in the table, that means
this is going to fail,
we're going to do an insert or ignore.
This or ignore is kinda redundant
because we just checked
to see if it was there.
But, we'll put that in just to be safe.
And, we're gonna put the name in for,
as the new, new account
that we're looking at.
And, we're indicating
that retrieved is zero.
So, that we will, we will know
that we haven't retrieved it yet.
You'll see we'll update that in a second.
We commit it so that later
selects will see this.
So, the, so you gotta do the commit.
This later select wouldn't
see the one we just inserted.
And, we're gonna ask how
many rows were effected.
And, if it's not equal to
one then we're gonna complain
about we inserted it.
And, we are going to do this thing.
We're gonna ask, "Hey, member
there was an ID up there?"
Do do do.
Right here: ID integer primary key.
And, we did not insert this here,
but we wanna know what that ID is.
And, every time I was
showing you that in lectures,
I was saying it's really
easy in Python to do this.
And, that's what we're saying,
is this cursor did the insert,
but one of the things happens is,
after the insert we're
gonna grab the last row ID,
which is the primary key
that was assigned by S Q L.
Okay?
And, so that means that one
way or another coming through
this code, here, in line 45,
one way or another we're either
gonna know the ID of the
user that was there before
or we just inserted one and so
we're gonna know the primary
key of the current user.
And, you'll see why we need that.
So, ID is the primary
key of the current user
that we entered right here.
Okay?
And, now what we're gonna do
is do the Twitter URL augment
with the oh off and all
the keys and the secrets
in hidden dot P Y.
And, instead we're gonna go
through, let's count 1000,
let's go count, what
the heck, let's go 200,
up to 200 friends.
Save, no let's do 100.
Let's keep it that way.
And, then we're gonna retrieve it.
And, we're retrieving the account.
We're not gonna print the nasty URL out.
We could.
Then, we're gonna open
the URL with a connection,
and then we're gonna read
that and we're gonna get
the UTFA data from this
and then we're decode that.
And, we're gonna have the uni-code data.
So, the data in string is a
internal Python string with all
that data representing all
the wonderful characters.
And, of course we're gonna
ask URL open to give us back
the headers as a
dictionary, using this call.
And, we can see what the,
how many we have left for the remaining.
Right?
What's the remaining
rate limit that we have?
Okay?
And, so then what we're gonna
do is parse the data with
jay son load s.
If, oh wait, I need a continue in here.
Continue.
Okay.
Save.
If we are going to parse this
data, we'll print it out.
Right?
So, that means that this, this died,
which means it's not
syntactically correct,
jay son, basically.
And, who knows if we're
ever gonna see that.
But, at least when it blows
up, it'll print this data out.
We'll have to catch it,
and then it'll continue.
Actually, I'll make this a break.
'Cause if that's blowin' up
that bad, we should quit.
Now, we don't, I don't yet know
what happens when this rate
limit says you can't have it.
And, so, but I do know that I
expect when it's successful,
that there will be a key of
users in this outer dictionary
that we're going to get.
And, if this outer dictionary that we're,
if we, if users is not
in the parsed dictionary,
then I'm gonna dump out
this data so at least I can
debug what happens when I've
got some broken jay son.
So, the difference between this code,
this code is gonna fail when
the jay son syntactically bad,
meaning a curly brace
isn't right or whatever.
This code will trigger
when I get good jay son,
but I don't have a users key in it.
Okay?
So, then once we've retrieved it,
we're pretty happy with it,
we're gonna update for our
account that we are retrieving,
we're gonna set this is one
of our retrieved accounts.
Okay?
And, then what we're going
to do is write a loop
that goes through all the
friends of this particular user
that we're asking, and
gets their screen name.
Prints it out.
And, then we're going to check
to see if this one is already
in our people database
'cause this is a spider,
we're grabbing accounts.
And, and so we'll do a friend ID.
And, do a fetch one,
grab the subzero thing.
And, if that works, if
this person's not in there,
this fetch one is gonna blow up,
which means we're gonna drop
down to the except code.
But, if it does work, we have
friend ID is the, you know,
they're in there and they're
already in our database.
Right?
They just weren't retrieved.
Okay?
And, so now, if friend ID wasn't there,
we're gonna do an insert into
setting retrieve to zero.
And, then we're gonna commit, right?
Now, member, row count is
how many rows were effected
by this last transaction.
Cur dot row account.
And, we're gonna die if that
(mumbles) insert doesn't work.
This is unlikely,
unless somehow we ran out
of disk drive or something.
And, we're gonna grab the
friend ID as the, as they key,
the last row that was inserted.
We're only gonna insert one row,
so it's basically the primary key
of the row we just inserted.
So, if you look at this code right here.
It comes out the bottom one way or another
with friend ID successful.
Right?
'Cause friend ID is either
they're already in our database
or they're not.
And, if we insert them, then we have it.
And, so now this count new
and count old is just so
I can print out a nice print out.
Now, we are gonna insert
into the friend's table,
which is called the
follows table in this case.
From ID and to ID, those are
the, those are the two outward,
outward pointing foreign keys.
And, we have the ID of the
account that we are retrieving
the friends of.
And, then this particular friend.
And, so we're inserting the connection
from this person to that person.
And, then we commit it.
We wanna commit these again
so that later selects,
when the loop goes back up,
later selects get all of
that data that's going on.
Okay?
So, we do want to commit
from time to time.
And, then we close the
cursor at the very end.
Okay?
So, let's run this and see what happens.
Okay.
So, Python.
T W friends dot P Y.
Oh, of course.
I am a refugee from Python
two so I always forget
to type Python three.
Okay, so we're gonna start.
If we take a look right now,
I'm gonna start another tab over here,
and L S minus L star S Q lite.
Now, that S Q lite file is there, right?
And, it's actually made the tables.
If you go up here, it ran all this stuff.
Create the tables, yada yada,
and we're sitting right here
at this line.
As a matter of fact,
I think without causing too much trouble,
I can open that database
and get into this database
right here, and there is no
data in the follows table
and there is no data in the people table.
It's completely empty.
Okay?
So, we're waiting for the first one.
And, I'll go with mine, Doctor Chuck.
So, it's retrieving the hundred
friends and they all were
brand new, they were all
in the serted, right?
And, so now if I hit refresh,
we will see that Doctor
Chuck is retrieved.
Who follows, so these are
all the people I follow.
If one follows two.
So, of we look at here,
we see that Doctor Chuck
follows Stephanie Teasley.
Because we grabbed the
followers of Doctor Chuck,
you know, we're gonna have a
record in all of the follows
for all the ones that I did.
Right?
So, these are all the people I followed.
And, we put them in.
Okay?
So, we can go back,
and we can, let's see, grab somebody.
Let's go grab Stephanie Teasley.
And let's pull out her friends.
So, we grabbed a hundred of her folks.
I got 14 left, that's my ex-rate limit.
So, I did Stephanie Teasley,
so let's go back here.
So, you'll notice there's 101,
there's probably gonna be,
oh 182, that's interesting.
So, we've retrieved Doctor
Chuck and Stephanie Teasley,
and let's go take a look
in the friends table,
the follows table.
Okay.
So, we have all of the people I follow
now all the people Stephanie follows.
Okay?
So, there we go.
So, let's go ahead and do somebody else.
Let's see, I think we
both follow Tim McKay.
Where's Tim McKay?
Yeah, let's follow Tim McKay.
Let's see what, who Tim follows.
See if we can get like an overlap.
Oh, we revisited some.
Let's see if we can see
this in the follows.
See people.
So, we've got Doctor Chuck retrieved,
and Tim McKay's somewhere down here.
It might take us a while before we get
any really good overlaps.
Let's see, let's do a database call,
let's see, let's do a database SQL.
Select.
Count.
Eh.
Okay, so let's just run this some more.
It's clearly working.
Now, one thing I can do
here is I can hit enter
and it will just pick one randomly.
So, it grabbed live E D U TV.
And, I can, and let's
see how many I got left.
We got 12 left.
And, now I can hit enter
again, it picks another one.
That was the next one.
Oh, it's kinda pickin' 'em in order.
Is it pickin' 'em in order?
Let's go to people.
Yeah, it's pickin' these.
So, it's gonna, we can see that
it's gonna just do the first
un-retrieved person, who is Nancy.
Let's let it retrieve Nancy.
So, it grabbed Nancy.
No.
So, we're finding some, and
this table's gettin' really big.
So, if we look at the people
table, we now have 455 people.
And, we have 467 following records.
And, so there we go.
Oops.
Hit enter, it does another one.
And, away we go.
So, you get the idea.
I can type quit to finish.
And, just to give you a, a
little interesting bit of code
to show you how to do selects,
I'm gonna do this TW join,
now you'll notice that we're not talking,
oh let's show you one thing.
LS one S L friends star SQ lite.
So, this database has it so
I can restart this process
and run it again, and the
database is still there.
And, so we just grab, (laughs) swear trek,
and so we can keep doing this.
And, and so this data it keeps extending.
So this is a restartable,
restartable process.
I can run it and then tell it to grab
the next un-retrieved one.
And, so away we go, right?
And,
so that's part of it.
So, so I can, if I run out
of my, I've got eight left,
oh how many do I have left, really?
Let's keep going.
How many do I got left?
I've got five left.
Okay.
Wait, oh I guess we'll just run it out.
So, I got four left.
You know what I should do is I should,
I can't change the code.
Yes, I can't change the code.
I can stop the code and
I can quit the code.
So, what I'ma do is I'ma change this code
a little bit really quick.
And, I'ma print the
headers of rate limiting
at the beginning
and at the end.
So, now I can run it again.
I changed the code, hopefully
I didn't make a Python error.
Tell it to go get another one.
Hannah Devaro.
And, so I got three left.
Oops.
We'll see what happens when
I run outta rate limit.
Run outta rate limit.
So, we have one left.
Hit enter.
Hit control k.
Open source dot org.
So, we have zero left.
That worked.
Now, let's see what happens.
I don't know what happens next.
Oh, we blew up.
Too many requests.
Oh we got a H T to be error four 29.
So that means that, going from Mark Cuban,
that was in line 48,
so the right thing to
do would be in line 48,
we should really put this
in a tri, tri except block.
Tri except block because
it gives us an error.
Print.
Oh fiddle sticks.
How do I print the exception message?
I always am forgetting.
Print failed to retrieve.
Okay.
So, we'll put that in.
Now, if I run it.
And, then I have to put a break here
because that's not good.
Break.
Failed to retrieve.
Now, I gotta figure out, oh I,
see I never know how to print
out the error message.
Yeah.
So, I have to, I never,
see that's the weird thing
about stuff is that I
don't ever remember enough.
I don't remember the
syntax what I say here
to print the error message out.
So, I'm gonna go to Google,
and I'm gonna say print out the
exception message in Python.
Print out the exception message in Python.
Oh, Python three, hello.
Okay, so let's go find it
here in the documentation.
Except.
Is this it?
Is this what I say?
I just wanna print out the message.
Ah, that's it.
Except.
Let's try this.
So, this is part of Python
programming is like,
for me at least,
'cause I'm just not like a
genius expert at this stuff.
(laughs)
This is one thing I like about Python,
is you can guess stuff and
sometimes you guess right.
So, there we go.
We got the error, we got the
nice little error message
and we see error four
29, too many requests.
So, that cleans that up nicely.
So we're, we have run out of requests.
And on that, it is a good,
good time to say thanks for
listening and I hope that
you found this valuable.
(smooth music)