- [Charles] Hello, and welcome
to Python for Everybody.
I'm doing a worked example,
my name's Charles Severance,
and I'm the instructor for the class.
And the worked example that
we're gonna work on right now
is in Chapter 5, and it is Exercise 1.
We're going to repeat asking for a number
until the word done is entered,
and then we're gonna print the,
the total, and then we're
gonna print the count,
and then we're gonna print
the average at the end.
And we're gonna enter some numbers,
then we're gonna do some error checking.
And we're gonna keep on
going, so we'll ignore this,
we'll just say invalid input,
and then we're gonna ignore it.
So I'm gonna start from scratch.
I'm going to write a,
I'll start my terminal,
start some Atom, and so,
I can, I've opened the py4e folder,
and that's kinda cool, because
now I can do things like,
say, New Folder,
and say, I'd like an
exercise, oh-five-oh-one,
and then go into ex_05_01
and say File > New File.
And then say, File > Save As.
And put it in ex_05_01,
and then name the file ex_05_01.py.
I'm gonna start from scratch,
on this one, instead of
adapting another piece of code.
I'll say, print('Five'),
and I'm gonna do this,
because now I need to get to the point
where I'm in the same folder
in this Terminal window.
Let's see, Desktop,
py4e,
ex, I can string these together.
And there I am, and I say python3, ex,
and there I go, okay?
So I'm in good shape.
So, there's a couple things right now,
and we're gonna do the
total count and average.
And so this is just the basic pattern
where we're going to have,
we're gonna need a iteration
variable for the count,
I'll call that num, we start that at 0.
And then tot, and I'll start that at 0.0.
So that's the running count
and the running total.
Now we need to write a loop.
And I'm gonna write this
as an infinite loop.
while True, with colon,
and then I'll indent.
And I'll prop first string,
and remember, input gives us a string, so,
I'm gonna call this sval = input,
enter a number, colon, space.
I'm gonna deal with the
try and except later,
but you can just kinda know
that the floating point value
that we're going to do is,
sometimes this little bit of code,
will fail,
I'm just gonna take the
string value here, sval,
as input returns us a string,
and I'm gonna convert that to float.
I'm gonna say print (fval),
so I can print that out.
And then I'm gonna do the,
num = num + 1,
and tot = tot + fval.
Now, I do need to deal with the situation
where I'm entering the word done.
Now, we wanna check that before
we convert it to a float,
because done, well, we can run this.
It's an infinite loop, but
it'll only run a little bit.
Won't cause us too much problem.
If I run Python, lemme
drag this over here.
And I go,
1,
2,
3,
and if I put in something bad,
it's running, I don't
have a way to get out.
But you can see that,
you know, it blew up on line 5,
it blew up right here on line 5.
So what we wanna do is we want it to say,
you know, 1, 2, 3, done.
But we want it to detect
that we've typed in done.
So here we'll just say,
if the string value that
I got back from input
is == 'done',
break.
So that basically will break us out.
And now I,
print ("ALL DONE").
I should be using single quotes here.
Too much Java coding.
print ('ALL DONE'),
then I'm gonna say print,
what do I want to print?
The total, the num,
and then,
tot comma num,
comma,
tot over num.
Now we're, we gotta be careful,
because we don't wanna divide by zero,
but that'll get us sort of a ways.
So this is gonna run, it's
gonna read these things,
it's gonna cumulate here,
this is the accumulator pattern,
this is a counter pattern,
where we're adding 1
to a current variable,
and a cumular pattern where
we're adding a value to it.
So now we should be able to see the done.
Um, 4, 5, and 6,
and then done,
and the total of 4 plus 5 plus 6 is 15.0,
the number is 3, and the average is 5.0.
And so that's really good,
the ALL DONE prints out.
I just did that for yocks,
and you can see the
value that's coming up.
So that's in pretty good shape,
so I'm gonna comment this out,
and comment that out.
So this is pretty good,
it works just the way we want it to work.
4, 5, 6, but if we do something
other than the word done,
then we're gonna blow up in this float.
And so this is where we're
going to do a try and except,
because we just know
that this line, line 7,
line 7 is the danger zone, okay?
So what we're going to do
is we're going to put a try in here,
and then we're going to indent
the part of the code that seems strange,
and then we're going to
have some except code.
And the first thing we have
to do in the except code
is print out the word Invalid input.
Come back.
print('Invalid input').
Now,
just like in an earlier example,
we have to do something here to make sure
it doesn't just keep on going,
'cause fval doesn't work.
We're not gonna see the error message
that would be the
traceback here on line 9,
we're gonna run here, but
we still don't wanna add,
'cause fval will be, um.
So this is where we can use the continue.
So in this code, we're
using both the break,
to say, if I'm all done, break,
and if I have a problem,
I'll print a message out,
and then I'll say continue.
So the continue basically
says, go back to the top.
So that is how, when we
see, enter some bad data,
we print our invalid input,
and without adding anything new,
you don't really see it here,
without adding anything new,
you go back up to the top
and enter a second thing.
So now, if everything is right,
I should be able to type,
bad input.
4, 5, 6,
bad input, bad input, done.
And I have a total of 15, and 3 items,
and the average is 5.0.
So, there we go.
That's what we're going to get,
and that roughly achieves this same thing.
And it's a combination of,
a loop, with a exit mechanism,
we have some sanity-checking of our input,
some making sure that we
have some valid input,
and we catch it, and we use
continue to loop back up
to run the next iteration of the loop.
Now we have an accumulator pattern,
and then we can use the accumulated data
to print what we want to print.
So, I hope that this
has been useful to you.
Exercise 5.1, for Python for Everybody.