- [Charles] Hello, and welcome
to Python for Everybody.
This is another of our worked examples,
and I'm your instructor,
Charles Severance.
The example we're going to do right now
is exercise 4.6 in chapter four.
This is an exercise
where we're taking code
that we've already written,
and redoing it in a way,
to prove that we can
do it with a function.
So it's not like it's going
to do anything different.
It's going to do exactly
the same as before,
we're just going to do it a different way.
So let's go ahead and start
up our text editor Atom.
Show you a couple new features of this.
It's already been opened,
let me open it again.
I'm going to open, get a new window,
and then I'm going to open,
but what I'm going to do
is to open this folder,
it's this folder right here,
and I'm going to open that.
So instead of opening a file,
which is what I've been doing so far,
I'm going to open a folder.
So now you can see all
the folders that I have,
and they're just exactly the same folders
that I've been making under desktop PY4E,
so I can go and look at
my previous assignments.
The other thing I can do is
I can control click on this,
and say New Folder, and I
can say EX, exercise 04 06.
Again, I like the 04 and the
06 just so things line up
when we get to chapters 10 and 11.
That's why I'm naming my files this way.
And I'm going to adapt the
code from exercise 3.1.
We can do exercise 3.2, but it's longer.
The difference between 3.1 and 3.2 was
one uses try except and
the other one does not,
so I'm going to start with this one.
I always clean up and get rid of that.
So here is our time and a
half for overtime logic,
and I am going to say, File, Save As.
So I'm making a copy of it,
and I am going to put this
in this folder exercise four six,
and I'm going to make sure to
rename my file 04 06, okay?
So now I've got exercise 04 06
which is this one right here.
That's the file we've got, it's there.
So let me pop up my terminal window.
CD desktop, CD PY4E, CD EX 04,
hit tab for 06 because
there was only one in 04,
so I can see where I'm at.
I have one file here, LS.
Line SL gives extended information,
and I can say Python3 EX 04 PY.
10, 10, and away we go, okay?
So this is this code.
I'm going to get rid of
some of this logic here.
These print statements,
which I commented out,
just to make it a little more dense.
Okay, so let me start by just
putting a function in here.
Of course def is the keyword for function,
and compute pay is the
name of the function,
and it's supposed to take two parameters,
hours and rate.
And then you add a colon,
and then we're indented, right?
So the indent is to determine how long
the function lasts, how many lines it is.
I'm just going to say print
In compute pay.
Give myself a blank line,
I'm going to save that.
Now, I'm going to run it now.
I'm going to run it now,
and you'll notice something real quick.
This line never came out,
and that's because the way this works
is this simply defines the function,
and then it continues running,
but it doesn't run that code.
And it ran this code,
and then it did in this
case the else code,
and then it did the print,
but it never came up and
actually ran this code.
We have to call the function, okay?
We have to call the function
before it's going to actually run.
So now let's make a call, compute pay,
and let's pass in our variables
that we have in this main code, FH and FR.
So the compute pay FH and FR,
and then I'm going to
print out hours and rate.
So now you'll see it's
going to do the input,
the input, convert to floating,
call the function, which is
going to run this one line,
and then continue down here, all right?
So now what it's going to do,
is going to define this,
run this, run this,
call compute pay which is
going to temporarily suspend,
come in here, run this code,
and FH is going to map to hours,
and FR is going to map to rate,
and then it's going to come back,
and it's going to continue down here,
running this code, and then finishing.
Okay, so that's what's going to run.
So this time we will see compute pay,
and we will see the
number for hours and rate.
So I'll run it again, 40
hours, 10 dollars an hour.
Ah, we see a mistake.
I'm like, "And then you're going to see
"the word compute pay here."
And I'm like, "Okay, that didn't happen.
"What's going wrong?"
Let's take a look at what's going wrong.
I don't plan to make these
mistakes, I just make them.
Let me show you what's wrong here.
See this little blue dot?
That's what's wrong with my code.
And if you don't catch
that, then you'll say,
"Oh, I'm crazy."
Well, I'm not crazy,
I just made a mistake.
I forgot to save it.
File, Save, or Command S.
So now I saved it.
I didn't change a single line of code.
It was right, I forgot to save it.
So I'm going to run it again now.
40 hours, 10 dollars.
And look, now I see this line.
So it came into compute
pay, and then came back
and then finished this part
and did compute pay, okay?
Now, this isn't enough.
What I need to do is I
need to move this code,
the actual pay computations,
so I'm going to cut that and
I'm going to put it in here.
But now this variable FH
belongs to the main program.
It doesn't belong to this code,
and I don't want to use that.
So I want to say hours,
so I'm taking whatever
hours are being passed in,
and then using rate,
and I'm just changing all of these
to match the parameters
inside the function.
This is hours, and this is rate,
and this is hours, and this is rate.
Now I'm going to print a
print statement inside.
I'm going to say returning,
and then I'm going to print XP.
And then, still inside the function,
I want to return a value
from this function,
so I'm saying the returned
value for this function
is actually in the current
function variable XP.
And then I'm going to not call this XP,
I'm going to call this pay in here.
Not with a capital, I don't
want it to be capitalized.
Pay, and pay, and pay.
So it's returning pay.
And then in here I'm going
to say XP equals compute pay.
So what we've achieved here is,
let me get rid of that,
what we've achieved here is,
it's going to come down
to find a function,
then read the input, convert
it to floating point,
and then call compute pay,
passing in FH as hours,
and FR as rate, right?
And then it's going to
take hours and rate,
do whatever it does with the if then else,
it's going to print these things,
and then it's going to return it,
and whatever this pay variable is,
effectively goes back into this expression
as the return value, and
then gets assigned into XP.
Okay, so that's basically
what's going to happen,
and then we'll print.
It'll come back, and then print XP, okay?
So let's go ahead and run.
Oh, wait, I almost did it again.
Look at the little blue dot.
You guys can watch the blue dot,
and when I forget to save it,
and when I then run it, it'll blow up.
So, 10 hours, 15 dollars an hour.
So now it worked.
So you can see these two print statements
come from while this is running.
The input happens, it calls the function,
and then it prints off the pay.
And now to finish this to get it right,
I will simply comment out my little
helpful debugging print statements,
and run it one more time.
40 hours, 10 dollars an hour.
And run it again, and have it be 50 hours,
and 10 dollars an hour, so 550.
So that one is now working,
so that one is completed,
and we have moved our computation
inside of the function.
So I hope that you find this useful.
I hope that you find this
entire course useful,
and thanks for watching.