(piano music)
- [Charles] Hello and welcome
to Python for Everybody.
We're doing some code walkthroughs
if you want to follow along.
We've got a sample code
ZIP that you can download
and take a look at all the code.
And what we are in the middle of is
we're in the middle of the PageRank code
and we just done running the PageRank
and so we have spydered the code,
we've run PageRank a bunch of times.
Spreset allows us to restart
the PageRank algorithm if we want.
But we're not going to play with that.
We're just gonna play
with spdump and spjson
and do the visualization,
which is the fun part.
So, I'll go into spdump.
So this is simple code, because
it's really just running
a SQL query and then
printing stuff out, right?
So we connect to our data
base, create a cursor,
and then just do a SELECT COUNT
and we're going to show
the number of links,
we're gonna order by the number
of inbound links descending,
so we see the most linked things,
and we'll see the top 50 of that,
so this is just a sample.
You'll tend to write
little helpers like this
that make your life easier
just to show you the kinds
of things that you want.
Spdump.py, and like that.
You just kinda test to make--
That's like, "Oh, is
this looks right to me?"
You know, and so here is
the number of inbound links,
so that's my blog that has
the most inbound links,
followed by my uncategorized,
whatever that is.
And these are the number of inbound links
within my own blog, somehow.
I don't know, because
this is not looking at
whole internet at all.
So there we go.
So that's spdump, pretty straightforward.
And now we're going to go through
the visualization process.
And so this is going to
look at all that data
and produce a JavaScript file.
It's gonna write a JavaScript file
that will then be fed into
my visualization using d3.
And spjson is going to do a big long join
that joins the links with the thing
WHERE html IS NOT NULL
and ERROR IS NOT NULL.
Ordered by the number of inbound links.
So we're looking at these,
the things that have the
highest number of inbound links.
We're going to read all this stuff.
We're going to read through all those rows
and pull out the Pagerank for each one.
We're looking for the
highest and lowest rank,
because these numbers
can vary quite widely.
They go all the way from,
you know, .000 to 20 or 30.
And so it asks how many do you want to do?
So it only does the top,
like, 20 or something,
and you'll see why we need
that in the visualization.
And so this is just checking.
And so we're gonna write out a file.
We'll see what the format of this is.
It's just a JavaScript file,
and we're going to write out--
We're basically normalizing the rank.
We're subtracting the minimum rank
and because we're going to
turn this into line weight,
the thickness of the line,
and so we're dividing by--
We're normalizing the rank to
be the thickness of the line,
and the size of the ball.
You'll see all this.
And so this is really just
writing some JavaScript
with the little strings
and stuff like that.
And then we're gonna
finish the JavaScript.
write all the links out.
So these are the balls that you'll see,
and this is showing--
This is drawing all the lines,
and this is again normalizing
things for thickness
and printing these things out.
Now, I don't want to go through
this in tremendous detail,
so I'll do python spjson.py.
Let's do the top 20 nodes,
and if I take a look
at this file spider.js,
you can see that it's some objects
that basically put the PageRank in,
which i.d. it is, and that's a way for me
to be able to link back and forth,
weight is how big the little circle is
and then I have the links.
And I only asked for the top 20, right?
And then this is the
thickness of the line,
where the line starts,
where the line ends, okay?
So, this is read by this html file,
and it's going to read
somewhere this force.js file
and my own spider.js code.
This is some JavaScript, I mean--
No, the force.js is
the visualization code,
and this is d3, the visualization library,
so I'm using this d3.js,
which is a really great
visualization library,
and this is just drawing the circles,
and making the circles colors,
and making the circles bigger and smaller,
and then connecting all
the lines in between it.
So, this is just there.
This data feeds that thing,
and so when we're all done,
you simply say "open,"
you don't have to do anything,
open force.html.
And so all this beautiful JavaScript stuff
is like, "Oh, wow, that's really cool,
"'cause you can move these things around."
Whoa!
You can see the circles are bigger
if you hover over it for a while.
It shows you the big ones.
You can see these things,
and it's kinda cool.
So I gave you all this
force.js and force.html,
and so that kinda visualizes the PageRank.
And you could use this to
visualize quite a bit of stuff.
It'll take you a while
to pull down enough data
from a real website.
But after you've pulled
down four or 500 pages,
if you have some time,
and then the visualization
is quite interesting.
But you can see why we had to pull down
several hundred pages just to get
this much PageRank information.
So that gives you a sense of how
to run the PageRank code
in Python for Everybody,
so thanks for listening.
(piano music)