- [Instructor] Hello everybody,
welcome to Python For Everybody.
We're gonna do a little
bit of sample code.
If you're interested in
getting the sample code,
you can download this zip here
at py4e.com/materials.php.
And you will download, and
you will get all the files.
All the files that I'm looking at here.
The one I'm gonna play with today
is the file called urllinks.py.
So the first thing you gotta
do before urllinks.py works
is you have got to install Beautiful Soup,
and I've got some simple instructions
at the beginning of the file.
And so one way to do it is install it
using python install process
to install this Beautiful Soup
for all python applications.
If you are the owner of your computer
and you're going to use
Beautiful Soup a lot,
it's a fine idea to do that.
But I wanna show you a simpler way that,
if you don't own your own computer
and you just wanna make it
so that Beautiful Soup works,
you can download this file.
This file right here. Bs4.zip.
Unzip it, and put it in
the same folder as here.
And so if you look in this folder,
I have a subfolder called bs4,
and that's the unzipped version of this.
It has these things.
I didn't write this code, so
I'm sorry if the name is bad,
but this is the code to bs4.
And this is what's in bs4.zip,
and it's in the same
folder as urllinks.py.
And so what happens is
when you do this from bs4
import BeautifulSoup,
that either can go to
sort of this global magic place
that python installs stuff,
and pulls in the Beautiful Soup object,
or it can go to the folder,
bs4, and pull it in.
Okay? And so that's how that works.
So you have to do one of these two things.
I prefer to keep it simple;
download and unzip this file
and put it in the same folder
as this code, and away you go.
So, from the previous example,
we're gonna use urllib of course,
and then we're going to pull
in BeautifulSoup from the bs4
library, we're gonna get
the BeautifulSoup object.
Now, if you do this with ssl,
these websites we're
gonna play with have ssl,
you pretty much have
to do this little hack.
And these three lines, don't
worry too much about it.
The whole idea, you can do
Google on stack overflow
and figure this out.
But this is the way that you ignore errors
when you have ssl certificate errors.
And so we have to add this
parameter, context=ctx,
which is this variable that we create.
So this part and this part,
sort of, just do them.
You can take them out, actually.
Otherwise you won't be
able to do https sites.
So let's take a look at what we're doing
other than dealing with the https problem.
We're going to ask the user for a URL.
We are going to retrieve all the HTML,
we're gonna do a urlopen,
just like we did before.
Now this would return us
something we could loop through
line by line, with a for loop,
but instead we're gonna say,
hey, read the whole thing.
And that basically returns
us the entire document
at that webpage in a single big string
with new lines at the end of each line.
And this is not in unicode,
but it's probably a utf-8 string.
But it turns out BeautifulSoup
knows how to do deal with
utf-8, and it also knows how
to deal with unicode strings.
So what we're saying is,
"BeautifulSoup, read through and
deal with all the nasty bits," right?
So html is like, very very flexible.
So dr-chuck.com/page1.htm.
And so if we take a look
at the source of this,
View Page Source, make this bigger.
You know, you might be able
to do regular expressions,
but it does things like
break stuff across lines.
There could be a line break here.
There could be all kinds of things, right?
And so writing regular
expressions or splits or whatever
is really hard for html.
And so what we do is,
someone has written this,
it's called BeautifulSoup.
This is the code, and it's based on a joke
from a children's story.
Basically, someone has just went through
and figured all the bad things
that could possibly happen
when you're reading and parsing html.
So either you use it, or
you will slowly but surely
derive all the things
that it doesn't work.
And so when we look at
this line right here,
this line, at a high level, is saying,
we're giving you ugly, nasty
html that could make no sense
whatsoever, please read it, and
have all the brains that you
have, and all the weird
stuff, figure that out for us.
And give us back an object.
I happen to call it soup, you
don't have to call it soup.
An object, and that is
a proxy for that html,
but this soup object is clean.
And so what we can do is we can
sort of retrieve all the anchor tags.
So we can talk to this object and say,
ask it, give me the anchor tags.
What's an anchor tag?
Well, if we take a look at this source,
the anchor tag is the a through the /a.
That is the tag.
It is the tag, it is
attributes that are on the tag,
it is the text within
the tag, and everything.
And so that's what we're going to get.
Now, I called it "tags" plural,
not because plural matters at all,
but because we're gonna
get a list of tags.
Because even though this webpage
has lots and lots of tags,
if we look at, say, dr-chuck.com,
and View Page Source,
and we go look for anchor
tags, we got 45 of them,
and they all kind of have
weird stuff in them, right?
So this line will give
us back a list of tags.
It will give us all the
tags in this document.
So the tag goes from there to there.
And then what we're
gonna do is write a loop,
to loop through all the tags.
So that's basically hopping,
like it's hopping through the
document, sorta like this.
That's what it's doing. Hop,
hop, hop, hop, hop, hop.
And it's pulling out the
text of the href attribute,
so it's gonna pull out
this bit right here.
Woops! Oh darn, that was so cool!
Because that's a flaw, look at that!
This is my own page.
There is no closing quote here,
but it's gonna work
because html soup is like,
"Oh I know what to do about
that. I can deal with that."
So let's check to see if that one works,
because that's like a mistake.
But that's one of the things
we like about BeautifulSoup.
So we're gonna read through,
and then we're gonna
pull out all the hrefs.
So, this is probably
thousands of lines of code
that you really don't want to run.
So python3 urllinks.py.
And so let's start with a simple one,
http://www.dr-chuck.com/
And it reads it.
Oh, that's actually the hard one,
because we got a whole bunch.
See, the tsugi one
worked. It found that one.
It's right after
sakaiproject.org, where's that?
Is there another tsugi?
Oh, no, it didn't find that
one, that's kinda funky.
Look, it found it wrong. But that's okay.
So you see, it found all these,
and did a lot of nice stuff for us.
If we do it
python3 urllinks.py and do the easy one,
http://www.dr-chuck.com/page1.htm,
we will only see one.
And there we go.
Now, the ssl is if you are
looking at a page that has ssl.
Python3 urllinks, so I'll go to like
https://www.si.umich.edu/
and that will get a bunch of links.
And so you'll see.
If it wasn't for that, so all
kinds of stuff coming back,
if it wasn't for this bit right here,
and this bit right here,
this https wouldn't have worked.
And it's not that that
website had a bad url,
it has a certificate that's
not in python's official list.
So the url is okay.
So that gives you a quick summary of
using the BeautifulSoup
library in python, along with the urllib.
(soft jazzy music)