(slow piano music)
- [Instructor] Hello everybody,
welcome to Python for Everybody.
We're playing with the web
services chapter right now
and if you want to
get the materials
for this course
you can
go here and download the sample zip
samplecode.zip.
I've got this all sitting
already on my computer.
I also have the whole
thing in GitHub if you
wanna get it out of GitHub.
So the thing we're talking about now is
we're talking about the
json1.py example from the book.
And, so, JSON is kinda like
XML except a lot simpler
and that's why a lot of people like it.
It's not that JSON is
always better but JSON
is better in a lot of
situations that don't require
the complexity of XML.
So, we start to import JSON,
JSON is built into python
but we have to ask to import it.
Again, we're using a triple quoted string
to put the JSON in there.
And JSON looks a lot
like python dictionaries:
key-value pairs,
key-value pairs.
In this case, this is a key
and the value itself is another dictionary
or in JSON terms: an object,
but again key-value pairs
within key-value pairs
within key-value pairs.
And all these little cursor guys,
all these little curly brace
guys have to line up properly.
And so, like all the time,
this is
a string which we normally
would read and decode from
the Internet but for now
we're just gonna have it in there.
Load json.loads says go in
the JSON library and pull out
load string and parse this
which turns this set of curly braces,
spaces, commas,
perhaps syntax errors
into a structured object.
And if we'd made a syntax error in here
then this would blow up.
But if this doesn't make a syntax error,
if this doesn't blow up
then we have a structured representation.
Now the difference between XML and JSON
is that this turns into
a python dictionary
with key-value pairs.
Okay?
And so once we have this,
this is a dictionary
and we can say info sub name
And that's the exact syntax
that we would use to get the dictionary
and that's gonna extract
this value out of there.
And if we wanna go in deeper, we can say
info sub email and that's
what info sub email is right there.
And then sub hide.
So that's a dictionary
within a dictionary.
So, if we run this,
python3
json
1.py
it digs in really fast.
And so this is why
people tend to like JSON
is because you read the
JSON which is actually
a syntax derived from Javascript,
but it looks just like
the syntax for python.
So, that's moving an object,
a JSON object that turns
directly into a python dictionary
with nested dictionaries.
Now, we're going to look at json2.
And, so, json2, we're going to see a list
or an array in JSON terms
but it turns into a list in python terms.
So, this is a list of dictionaries.
In Javascript that would
be an array of objects
but in python it's a list of dictionaries.
So, we'll just pretend it's
a list of dictionaries.
Again, we load the string, parsing,
looking for syntax errors, so
let's just make a syntax error
here and run
python
json2.py
and you'll see where it blows up.
It blows up at line 15
which is right here.
It's like this load s blows up.
Now, you could put try
except around it to save it
but we're not gonna do that.
And it even complains, it
says: look we're expecting
something here in line 11 and
that's line 11 of the JSON
which starts on line 4.
And so I'll put my little
square brace back in
so it's not syntactically broken.
So, let's run it again and
make sure that she runs
and yes she does.
So, this parses it and
converts from the JSON syntax
into a python, in this case, list,
because it's got square braces
instead of curly braces.
The previous example had square braces
and we can then take a LEN
of it and it's an array,
it's a list.
And we see there are two things in there
and now we're gonna iterate through
and this item is gonna iterate
through these dictionaries,
that dictionary followed
by that dictionary.
So, the first time, it's item,
sub,
name,
which is this value right here.
And then item, sub, id,
which is this value,
so you can dig right into
this but you're not using
get and you're not using
the weird extra find
or find all or anything.
You just are going at
these structures directly.
And so you can quickly
extract this stuff out
and we read through "id" is 001,
"name" is Chuck ...
There are no attributes, by the way.
"x" is 2
So we had to make x.
So if you look at the XML we
had this concept of attributes
on the outer tag, these
things are also not named,
we just have to know
what we're looking for.
So, JSON represents simple structures
but it's much simpler
to use.
So, I hope this has been useful to you
and talk to you in a bit
about some more JSON.
(slow piano music)