- Hello everybody and welcome
to Python for Everybody
we are going to be doing
some code walk throughs
if you want the sample code
you can download the zip
from our website.
The work that we're doing right
now is we are in the process
of building a spider
and visualization tool
for email data that came originally
from this website gmane, but
I've got my own copy of it.
And so what we've done
before is we ran gmane.py
and I grabbed a url,
I have a url that has all this data
and I downloaded that and
then I ran gmane again
to catch up so it took
quite a bit of catching up
but by the time I get
to, remember how I said
it tries to fail five times?
Well it ran out of data at 60,421
and then it started
failing and then it quit.
So we pretty much have all of our data now
we have finished this
process in content.sqlite
and if I take a look in
the data base browser
we can see we've got 59,823 email messages
and so if I look at any
of these things you see
the headers, you see the subject line,
you see the email address
you see the body of it
remember I split the body in half
and headers and so that's,
I made this as raw as I possibly
could because as you saw
I had to spend so much time in the gmane
just getting the data
successfully retrieved
and so I don't like cleaning
the data up too much.
So what we're gonna look at next,
is the data cleaning process.
There's a gmodel.py is what
we're gonna take a look at now.
So let's get rid of those
guys and look at gmodel.py.
I don't think I need urllib in this code,
do I have any urllib?
No. So I don't need that sorry, fix that.
So it's gonna read from the
database it's got a call
it's gonna use regular expressions
and zlib is a way to do some compression
in this one I'm gonna
compress some of the data
to make it so that I have less data
some of the text fields
are gonna be compressed.
I wanted to keep these fields
uncompressed inside of messages.
So we have some just clean up messages
and cleans things up and it turns out
that the way email
addresses in this particular
mail corpus they changed over time
and there's certain
kinds of things sometimes
the gmane.org is the
email address when people
wanna hide their address and
I made all kinds of stuff
and I split it and checked
to see if it end with this
and I cleaned up things this
that and the other thing
and so I have all kinds of
clean up stuff going on in here
and just mapping and DNS mapping
that I'll talk about in a bit
where organizations sometimes
sent email with different
addresses over time
and people sent email from different time.
And we're gonna do the parsing of the date
and that is the code for that.
We're gonna pull out
the header information
this is sort of borrowed
from the other code,
we'll clean up the email
addresses and the domain names,
and we'll pull the data
out, pull the subject out,
pull out the message id, various things.
So here's the main body of the code.
We're gonna go from
content.sglite to index.sqlite
and what I'm going to do every time
is I'm going to wipe out index.sqlite
and drop the messages,
senders, subjects, and replies
so this is a normalized database
in that it has foreign keys.
So there's a messages table here,
with an integer primary
key, the guid for it.
Guid stands for Global Unique
Id, sent times under id,
and it's gonna have a BLOB.
These are BLOBs, binary
large objects for the headers
and the body cause I'm gonna
compress them in this database
to make them.
And then the senders,
each sender has a key,
and then subjects, each subject
line is gonna have a key,
and then replies are a connection
from one message to another and so
this is like a many to many.
Now, I also have this
file called mapping.sqlite
so we can take a look at
that one, mapping.sqlite.
And so what happened
is this has two tables
that I hand deal with,
and so sometimes indiana--
this was a email address
that mapped to that.
So indiana.edu that's a way to
take and ax the email address
and then these were a
bunch of people that had
email addresses changing
throughout the project
and I just sort of kind
of mapped them in a way.
So this is just sort of like
a, I pull this in really quick,
and I read all this stuff
from the DNS mapping and I,
other than stripping and making
this lowercase et cetera,
I just am gonna make a dictionary.
DNS mapping which is the old
name to the new name and the
email address mapping from
the old name to the new name
and I'm using fix sender.
Fix sender is cause the email addresses
even within gmane were kind of funky.
So don't worry so much about this, okay.
So now what I'm gonna do
is I opened up a connection
just to read all of that stuff in,
and now I'm going to actually
open the main content
and I'm asking it to open
this a little trickier
I open that read only.
That was so that I could
potentially be running
the spider and running
this at the same time.
I get a cursor and so
I'm gonna read through,
so in the content file this is the big one
I'm gonna read through
and go through every one
and write all of these things in.
I'm gonna take all the email addresses
and I'm going to put those in a list
so I loaded that, I've
got the mappings loaded,
and so now I'm going to go
through every single message
I got all the senders, all the subjects,
and all the global unique ids.
So I read in each message,
so now I'm going through
content one at a time,
I parse the headers,
I check to see if the
sender's name email address
after it's been cleaned
up is in my mapping,
mapping.getsender and the
default is I get back sender
that's what that's saying.
Look up sender if it's in there,
give me the entry of that key
otherwise give me sender back.
We're gonna print every 250 things we do
we'll complain if this is true,
we're gonna go get the
mapping between the senders
which is a way to look up the primary key
I could have done this
with a database thing
but I wanted it to be fast so that's part
of the reason I read
all of these things in,
so I could have those
mappings to be really fast
you'll see this takes a
little while even though
even though I got all the stuff cached.
So then if I don't have a sender id,
meaning that I haven't seen it yet,
then I'm going to do an
insert or ignore into senders
and then I'm gonna do a select
and then you've seen this
where I grab the row
back and I'm really just
trying to look at the recently assigned id
and then I'm going to not
only set the sender id
for this ideration loop but
I'm also gonna store it in
the dictionary, and so that
builds this dictionary up.
And you'll see the same
thing is true for subject id.
I'm gonna insert it
into the subjects table
and get a primary key if
I don't know what it is
and then I'm gonna put it into,
not only am I going to
put it into the database,
but I'm also gonna put
it into my dictionary
and the same thing I guess
I didn't do it for the guid.
So now what I have is the
sender id and the subject id
which are foreign keys
into the center table
and the subject table and
I'm gonna insert the message
with a sender id, subject id, the sent at,
headers, and body.
The values here are the guid, sender id,
subject id, sent at.
Now this here zlib compress,
so what I'm taking is the message,
the header, and the
body, and this little bit
ends up with a compressed
version of this stuff
and you'll see it in a second
and this keeps the size
of these text things down
at the cost of the computation of,
the cost of the computation
to compress and decompress
when we wanna read it okay.
And then I pull the guids out,
the id, which is the guid,
and I pull out the
primary key for this thing
based on the guid and I
update this dictionary.
Let me run that code, it
is doing a lot of clean up.
And I'll tell you it took me
a long time to make this work
so this code that I'm running now, oh.
(laughs)
Don't forget to take a python 3 Chuck.
So you'll, this is gonna run every 250
so it did all this pre-caching
so that's how long it takes to do 250,
now there's 60,000 in here.
And so this is really busy
the reason it's bouncing back and forth
is that every time it
makes this journal file
and then doesn't commit.
So you can kinda see that it's busy
making journal files and
committing and there's
a lot of activity going on here.
(buzz sound)
It so happens that Adam
shows me these files.
(jazz music plays)
Okay so it's finished, it
took about three minutes
to finish that, right,
and so if we take a look
at the size of the files
we will see that the
index is much smaller.
It's fully normalized,
it's still 263 megabites
it's all compressed
so let's take a look
at that in the browser.
So it's 200 megabites, but
it loads up a lot faster.
There we go.
So we have a senders table, right,
which is just kind of a many to one table.
We have a subjects table
which is a many to one table.
And we have messages,
which has foreign keys,
it takes a little bit to load that up.
So we see the foreign keys
for sender and subject
and that saves us, all
those foreign keys save us,
and so we have you can
kinda see that I can't see
the headers and the body
because they're compressed
that saves me a whole
bunch of stuff, right.
It saved me a whole bunch of stuff.
So that's what in that file.
That we've finished this process okay
and we finished modeling the
data and making it really clean
and we'll pick back up,
and the rest of the stuff
we will do is actually
visualizing pulling data out
of index.sqlite.
The idea is this can be restarted,
this can be run over and over and over
even though it takes like
three minutes to run this
that's way better than
five hours to run this.
So three minutes.
Five hours.
And then we'll see now
reading this is in seconds
cause we got it all nice and normalized
in a quite pretty way.
So I hope this has been useful,
in the next one we'll
actually do the visualization.
(jazz music plays)