(jazz music)
- [Charles] Hello everybody,
and welcome to Python for Everybody.
We're gonna do some code walkthroughs,
actually running some code.
And if you want to follow
along with the code,
the sample code is here
in the materials of my
Python for Everybody website.
So you can take a look at that.
So, the code we're
going to look at is from
the database chapter.
And we're gonna look at tracks dot PY.
So a lot of the lectures that I give in
this database chapter are just about SQL.
And this is really about SQL in Python.
So I'll go through this in some detail.
So the code that I'm going
through is in Tracks.
There's also Tracks dot
Zip that you can grab.
It has these two things.
It's got this Library dot XML
file, which you can export
from your ...
If you have iTunes you can export this.
Or you can just play with my iTunes.
And so this is also gonna
review how to read XML.
So we're gonna actually
pull all this data.
And this XML that Apple
produces out of iTunes,
is a little weird in that
it's kinda key values.
And so you see key value pairs.
And it even uses the word dictionary.
And so it's like, I'm gonna
make a dictionary that has this,
then a dictionary within a dictionary.
This to me would be so
nice if it was Json,
because it's really a
list of dictionaries.
This is a dictionary.
Then another dictionary.
Then the key for that dictionary.
And it's ...
It's a weird, weird format.
But we'll write some Python
to be able to read it.
And so, you export that from iTunes.
And you can use my file,
or you can use your file.
Might be more fun to use your file.
So here's Tracks dot PY.
We're gonna do some XML.
And so import that.
We're gonna import
SQLite3 because we wanna
talk to the database.
And then we're gonna make
a database connection.
And in this, once we run this,
you'll see that that file
will exist.
And so right now, if
I'm in my Tracks Data,
that file doesn't exist.
But, what we'll see, is this
is going to actually create it.
Now remember that we have a cursor,
which is sort of our ...
Like a file handle.
It's really a database handle, as it were.
And in order to sort of
bootstrap this nicely,
we are going ...
Because this code is
gonna run all the time,
it's gonna run and read
all of Library dot XML.
In later things we won't wipe
out the database every time.
And so, I'm executing a
script, which is a series
of SQL commands separated by semicolons.
So I'm gonna throw away the
artist table, album table
and track table.
Very similar to the stuff
we covered in lecture.
And then I'm gonna do the create table.
And I'm doing this all automatically.
And so ...
And you'll notice this is
a triple quoted strings,
so this is just one big, long string here.
And it happens to know that it's SQL.
Thank you Adam, for that.
And so it creates all these things.
Now, it's not quite as rich
as the data model we built,
because there's no genres in here.
And so it's artist, album, track.
And then there's a
foreign key for album ID,
and a foreign key for artist ID,
which it's sort of a
subset of what we're doing.
And so when that's done,
that actually creates all the tables.
And we'll see those in a
moment, once we run the code.
Then it asks for a file name for the XML.
Right?
And so that's what that is.
And we're going to ...
I wrote a function that does a lookup.
It's really weird.
Because if you look at these files ...
Like in this dictionary
there is a key, right?
So the key of this dictionary ...
This really, coulda shoulda
been a key value pair.
But, so I had ...
There's this weird thing
where the key for an object
is inside of the object.
And so we're gonna grab ...
We're gonna loop through all the children
in this outer dictionary,
and find a child tag that
has a particular key.
And so you'll see how this works.
And this will ...
Something I was gonna
use over and over again.
And so the first thing we're gonna do,
is we're gonna just parse this string.
And this is the string.
And then this, of course,
is an XML ET object.
And then we're gonna say ...
We're gonna do a find all.
And so this shows how the find all ...
We're gonna go ...
The third level dictionaries,
we wanna see all of the tracks.
And so we have a dictionary,
and a dictionary,
and a dictionary.
And so what we want, is
all of these guys, right?
All those guys right there.
Right?
Track ID.
So we're gonna get a list of all those.
That'll be the first one.
This'll be the second one.
Because the find all says go to the ...
Find the dictionary key, then
a dictionary tag within that,
and a dictionary tag.
So it's ...
And then we'll tell
how many things we got.
And then we're gonna loop through.
And entry is going to iterate
through each of these.
And see, you'll get our
name, and our artist:
Another One Bites the Dust, Queen.
And away we go.
And then the next time through
the loop we'll hit this one.
Okay?
So, then what we're going to do,
is we're gonna go through
all those entries.
And if there's no track ID ...
And that's this track ID field.
Where are you hiding?
Track ID.
We don't have that, we're gonna continue.
And then we're gonna look
up the name, artist, album,
play count, rating and total time.
Okay?
And so, here they are.
Play count.
A lot of those things that
we had in the sample lecture
that I did.
And we're gonna look those things up.
And we're gonna do some sanity checking.
If we didn't get a name
or an artist or an album,
we're gonna continue.
We're gonna print them out.
And then, we are going to get ...
Remember how you have
to get the primary key
of a row so you can use it?
So, the way we're gonna do this,
is we're going to do an insert or ignore.
So this or ignore basically says,
because I said that the artist name ...
Go up here.
I said the artist name is unique.
Which means if I try to attempt to insert
the same artist twice,
it will blow up, okay?
Because I put this constraint on that.
Except, when I say insert or
ignore, that basically says,
'Hey, if it's already there,
don't insert it again.'
So, what I'm doing here is
insert or ignore into artist.
So this is putting a new
row into the artist table,
unless there's already a
row in that artist table.
And, this syntax right here ...
You know the question mark
is sort of where this artist
variable goes.
And this is a tuple, but I have
to sort of put this comma in
to force it to be a tuple.
So this is a way you have a one tuple.
And then what I need to
know, is I need to know
the primary key of this
particular artist row.
Now this line may or may not,
if it'd actually done the insert.
And so I need to know what the ID
for that particular artist is.
So I do a a select ID from
artist where name equals.
Now it either was already
there, or I'm getting it fresh
and brand new.
So I do an artist ID equals.
I fetch one row, and it's
gonna be the first thing,
given that I only selected ID.
And so this artist ID
is going to be the ID.
Now I have the foreign
key for the album title.
Right?
And so now I'm gonna insert
into the title, artist ID.
This is the foreign key
to the artist table.
And I got this value that I
just, moments ago, retrieved.
And I got the album title.
But this also is insert
or ignore, because ...
And now if you'll look, I have
unique on the album title.
Yeah, unique's on the album
title, so that'll do nothing.
It doesn't blow up.
Or ignore says, 'Don't
blow up, just do nothing.'
Because this next line is gonna select it.
And I grab the album's foreign key
for either the existing
row or the new row,
and then I'm going to insert or replace.
And so what this basically says
is if the unique constraint
would be violated, this
turns into an update.
Now not all SQLs have
this, but SQLite has this.
That basically says insert or replace.
Some SQLs are totally standard.
Some things we do like this is ...
This select statement is
a totally standard part of
SQL.
Then the insert is totally
standard, but insert or replace,
and insert or ignore,
is not totally standard.
But that's OK, it works for SQLite,
which is what we're doing.
And so we have the
title, album ID, length,
rating and count.
And don't we have a tuple
that does all of that stuff?
And of course, the title is unique.
The title is unique in
the track table as well.
And so we've inserted that.
And so the clever bit here is
dealing with new or existing
names in these three lines.
And we see that pattern twice
here, where we're doing that.
Okay?
So there's not much left
to do except run this code.
Hopefully it runs.
Python3, Tracks dot PY
and Library dot XML.
(surprised noise)
So that is my ...
So we found 404 of those
dictionaries, 3D dictionaries.
And now it's starting to insert them.
Insert them, insert them, insert them.
And we can take a look at ...
So we can do a LS minus
L for Duran Windows,
we'll see that we made a track database.
We extracted the data from this library,
and we made a track database.
And we have all these foreign keys.
So, let's go and take a
look at the SQLite browser.
File, open database, Track DBSQLite.
And come on up.
Where'd you hide?
I've got it minimized, so there you go.
Let's look at the database structure.
We have an album.
This is the structure.
Artist and track.
We have no genre.
And this is all like we did it by hand,
except Python did all this work for us.
If we take a look at the data,
and we start from the outside
in, we have the artist names
and their primary keys.
There's the artists'
names and primary keys.
And then we have the albums
and we have the artist IDs.
See the artist IDs, how nice those are.
So we have the primary key
here, and the foreign key there.
And then we have the title.
And if we get to the track,
we have the album ID, and away we go.
So, if I was clever, I could
be able to type some SQL.
Oh great.
If I was smart I'd have
had this in a paste buffer.
So, select ...
Select Track dot Title.
Album dot Title.
Artist dot Name, I think.
Artists have names and albums have titles.
Yes.
Okay so, I can do that.
From Track join Album.
Oops.
Album join ...
Make that a little bigger.
Bring that over here.
Album, Track, join Album, join Artist.
I need an ON clause, and I can say,
'Track dot Album ID equals Album.'
Notice how I know the name
that I named these things.
'And Album dot Artist'
This is so great when you
use a naming convention.
Artist ID.
Golly, I think that might work.
Let's just see what we
get when we type that
into the SQL box here.
Execute SQL.
Run.
Yay, I got it right the first time!
So that's basically my nice,
little, joined-up track list.
Oh, I'm so happy that I got
that right the first time.
Okay, well you can ...
So you can play with this yourself.
Play with this tracks.
Maybe make an export of
your own iTunes library
and run it with that.
And so, I hope that you found
this particular bit of code useful.
Okay?
Cheers.
(jazz music)