- [Instructor] Hello, welcome
to "Python for Everybody".
I'm Charles Severance, your instructor.
And in this short video, we're
going to do exercise 3.2,
which is really just a
rewrite of exercise 3.1.
We're going to deal with some
error conditions using try
and accept.
So let's go ahead and get started.
But this is a good example of something
where you want to start with
the previous assignment.
So let's open the file that I did before.
And so this happens to
be right here, ex 03 01.
And there's my previous program
that I wrote for exercise 3.1.
And let me set myself up with Python,
so I can actually run it.
cd desktop, cd py4e.
These will get better.
cd ex_03_01 ls.
And I can say python3 ex 03 01 dot py
and you know it works fine
if you give it the right data
but if you give it bad
data, ten and T E N,
it blows up, right?
And like always, you're getting tracebacks
for all kinds of things.
But this one is pretty clear if you slowly
but surely don't get mad.
Just say, oh line four, what
could be wrong in line four?
Could not convert string to float ten.
So what it's complaining
about is on line four,
this variable 'sr' which
is the string T E N,
the letters T E N,
is not working so this
function is blowing up.
Okay?
So that's what it's complaining about.
And that's what we want to deal with.
Now when you're using try and accept,
you don't want to just put a try.
You want to limit how much
data that you put in the try
and accept or how much go you
put in the try and accept.
So, let's get started on assignment 3.2.
So the nice thing that we can do here,
is we can say File > Save As,
and go up a folder to py for everybody.
Make a new folder called ex 03 02.
And then save the file as ex 03 02 dot py.
Okay, so now make sure, get rid of that,
make sure this is different.
We're in a different
folder, so we're not editing
that old file.
And the first thing I'm going to do is,
come on,
well I'm going to get rid of
some of these print statements.
I mean the code's going to work.
Come on.
Okay, so the dangerous
line of code is right here
and so the problem becomes
how are we going to deal with this?
And, and oh, let me do this as well.
So here's, if I do pwd, I'm in ex 03 01.
This could drive you crazy.
Oh wait, I'm in the wrong folder.
How come this is in the wrong folder?
I put the ex 03 01, oh.
Why is this in...
See, you got to watch this.
I think I'm in the wrong folder.
File > Open
ex 03 02
Okay, so now I'm in the right spot.
I don't know why that
wasn't showing up right.
But keep your eye on this,
especially when you're using file names
that are ...
So I'm going to, I'm in this ex 03 01.
So I'm going to use a command,
and you can use this both
in Windows and in Linux
and in Macs,
c d dot dot.
And what that does is
that goes up a folder.
Part of the goal of this
course is to teach you
how to use things like this.
Just how to use these command lines
because to be a programmer,
even doing the simplest stuff,
you've got to manipulate files
and you've got to be
able to use command line,
you've got to be able
to use all these things.
Not every thing is a full
screen clickety pointedy thing.
Okay?
And so what does c d do?
Well, it looks at this.
And it goes up one folder.
So it moved us up into here.
And you can see after the cd,
my current working directory
is that and I could do
ls to see the folders.
And now I see my new ex 03 02.
So say cd ex 03 02.
And part of the being a
programmer is having a lot
of folders with weird names
to organize your stuff.
So here we go.
Now we have this file and
this file in the same place,
pwd, this matches this,
that file matches this name
and I can say python3 ex 03 02 dot py,
10 10, okay, so.
Now I'm just nervous enough
to want to double check this
and so I will do something like this.
I will say XYZ pay and save
it and then run it again,
python3, I don't care about the numbers.
See the XYZ pay?
So now I know I'm in that file.
So I do stuff like this all the time
to triple check that I'm
really working with the files.
So now I'm in this file.
And now let me make my mistake again.
Ten, ten, and now there's
my failure, right?
So there's the mistake
and that's the thing
we've got to fix.
So, we have these lines of code.
So what you do in Python, when you know
that there's a dangerous set of lines,
and you want to take
out insurance on those,
you put them in a tri-catch
block or tri-accept block.
And,
now what are we supposed
to say when it blows up?
It says 'error, please
enter numeric input'.
I'll just copy that and paste this.
Print 'error, please enter numeric input'.
Make that a little bit wider.
Print that out.
Now I want to put this
print statement back in.
Okay?
So here we go.
So now what's going to
happen is that we're going
to come in here, we're going to run these,
if they work, we'll skip the
accept block and continue.
If they blow up, then it's
going to run this accept block.
So let's run it.
Let's start with a working case.
That still works.
That's good.
It comes and does this extra print that
I've got on line nine.
Let's go in the bad case, 10, 10.
Okay, so we're going to
parse this a little bit.
So it says 'error, please
enter numeric input'
but then I still get a traceback.
And you're like 'I hate computers'.
Because doesn't this look beautiful?
I've got a try.
I've indented.
It looks just like what I saw, right?
It's so beautiful.
Why does this computer hate me so badly?
Well then take a step back
and say you know what,
the computer is admitting
that it's confused
by what you have given it.
And so just look.
What line are you mad
about, dear computer?
Line nine, okay let's
take a look at line nine.
It's always this line
or the one before it.
Almost always.
Almost always or it gets it right.
It says name 'fr' is not defined.
Hmm, so let's just focus on this.
It's complaining about this.
And the problem is is
that it came down here.
It ran through here.
Came down here, ran through here.
And this blew up.
That line never ran.
That's the line that blew up.
And then it ran this error.
So it never got a varible
or a value in 'fr'.
And that's because in
this particular case,
we either have to put a new
statement in to make sure
the rest of this code
or we can say you know,
if everything is just so bad in this thing
and I don't want to continue,
quit basically says do not continue.
Okay?
So when it comes in here, it runs this.
It blows up.
It come down to here.
It prints this.
And it quits.
And then it doesn't continue on.
So now I can run this again, 10, 10.
It works.
10 and T E N, and it fails
exactly the same way.
This part here is exactly the same
as this part here.
The difference was as
soon as we print this out,
we quit so we don't continue on.
Okay?
So if you're doing really
simple sort of input checking,
sanity checking is one of
the things we call this
where just does the data make
sense then don't continue.
If the data doesn't make
sense, if these two statements
don't work then whatever we've been given
is nonsensical data
that we're not capable of handling, okay?
So that is how to write exercise 3.2.
And I hope that you have found
this little video useful.
And thanks for watching.