(slow jazz playing)
- [Charles] Hello and welcome
to Python for Everybody.
We're doing a bit of code walk through
and if you want to
you can get to the sample
code and download it all
so that you can walk
through the code yourself.
What we're walking through
today is the page rank code
and so the page rank code,
let me get the picture of
the page rank code up here.
Here's the picture of the page rank code.
And so the page rank code is a
has four chunks
of code that are gonna, uh,
five chunks of code that are gonna run.
The first one that we're gonna look at
is the spidering code
and than we will do a separate look
at these other guys later.
So the first one we'll
look at is spidering.
And again, it's sort
of the same pattern of
we've got some stuff on the
web, in this case, web pages.
We're going to have a database
that just sort of captures the stuff.
It's not really trying to
be particularly intelligent,
but it is going to parse
these with Beautiful Soup
and add things to the database.
Okay?
And so then we'll talk about how we run
the page rank algorithm
and then how we visualize the
page rank algorithm in a bit.
Now the first thing to notice
is that I put the Beautiful
Soup code in right here.
Okay, so you can get this
from the BS4.zip file.
There might be a read me.
No, but there's a read me somewhere.
To use Beautiful Soup you
got to put this BS4.zip
or you have to install Beautiful Soup
for your stuff.
So I provide this BS4.zip
as a quick and dirty way
if you can't install something
for all of the Python
users on your system.
So that's what it's supposed to look like.
You're supposed to have
it unzipped right here
in these files.
And I don't know what dammit.py means.
That came from Beautiful Soup.
If you look it's in their source code.
I'm not swearing.
It's Beautiful Soup
people that are swearing.
I'm sorry, I apologize.
Okay, so the code we're
going to play with the most
is in this first one
is called "Spider.py".
And ya know we're gonna do databases,
we're gonna read URLs,
and we're gonna parse them
with Beautiful Soup, Okay?
And so what we're going to do
is we're gonna make a file.
Again this will make Spider.sqli
and here we are in page rank
and la - el
Spider.sqli is not there,
so this is gonna create the database
We do "Create Table If Not Exists"
We're gonna have an integer primary key
cause we're gonna do foreign keys here.
We're gonna be URL
and the URL which is unique,
the html which is unique,
whether we got an error.
And then for the second half,
when we start doing page rank,
we're gonna have old rank and new rank
cause the way page rank works is
it takes the old rank,
computes the new rank,
and then replaces the new
rank with the old rank
and then does it over and over again.
And then we're gonna
have a mini to mini table
which points really back
so I call this "from_id" and "to_id".
We did this with some
of the Twitter stuff.
And then this "webs"
is just in case I have
more than one web,
but that doesn't really
make much difference.
Okay, so, what we're gonna do is
we're gonna select "ID" URL
from Pages Where html is Null'.
This is our indicator that a page
has not yet been retrieved.
And "error is Null Order by Random"
So this is our way,
this long bit of stuff,
and it's not all this SQL
is completely standard,
but this order by random is
really quite nice in SQLI.
"Limit 1" is just randomly
pick a record in this database
where this "True" is true
and then pick it randomly.
And then we're gonna fetch a Row
and if that row is "None", right,
we're gonna ask for a new web
a starting URL
and this is gonna fire things up.
And we're going to insert this new URL
otherwise we're gonna restart,
we have a row to start with.
And otherwise, we're going
to sort of prime this
by inserting the URL we start with.
And insert into it if you enter
it just goes to Dr.Chuck.com
which is a fine place to start.
And then what we do is
we, what this does is it's
page rank is it uses this
web's table to limit the links.
It only does links to
the sites that you tell
it to do links and probably
the best for your page rank
is to stick with one site.
Otherwise you will just never
find the same site again
if you let this wander the web aimlessly.
And so I generally run with one web
which this should be
probably called 'websites'
And I pull on all the
data and I read this in
and I just make myself a list
of the URL, the legit URL's
and you'll see how we use that.
And the webs is how many,
what are the legit places
we're gonna go cause we're
going to go through a loop
ask for how many pages
and we're gonna look for a Null page
again we're using that random
order by random limit 1
And then we're gonna have
a we're gonna grab one
we're gonna get the from
ID, which is the page
we're linking from, um, and then the URL.
Otherwise there's no one retrieved.
And so the from ID is
when we start adding links
to our page links we gotta
know the page we started with.
And that's the primary
key we'll see how that
primary key is set in a second.
So, otherwise we'd have
none and we're gonna print
this from ID the from ID and
the URL we're working with.
Just to make sure we're gonna
wipe out all of the links
because it's unretrieved,
we're gonna wipe out
from the links, the links
is the connection table
that connects from pages back to pages
and so we're gonna wipe out so we're gonna
go grab this URL we're gonna read it,
we're not decoding it cause we're using
Beautiful Soup which
compensates for the UTF-8.
So we can ask this is the html error code
and we checked it, 200 is a good error
and if we get a bad error
we're gonna say this
'error on page' we're gonna set that error
we're gonna update pages
that way don't retrieve it ever again.
We basically check to
see if the content type
is text/html, remember in
http you get the content type.
You only want to look for
the links on html pages
and so we wipe that guy
out, if we get a jpeg
or something like that we're
not gonna retrieve a jpeg.
And then we commit and continue.
So these are kind of like,
oh those are pages we
didn't want to mess with.
And then we print out how many characters
we got and parce it.
We do this whole thing
in a try/except block
cause a lot of things can go wrong here,
it's a bit of a long try except block.
"Keyboard Interrupt"
that's what happens if I
hit "Control C" at my keyboard
or "Control Z" on Windows.
Some other exception probably
means Beautiful Soup blew up
or something else blew
up and so we indicate
with the "Error = -1" for that URL,
so we don't retrieve it again.
At this point at line
103 we have got the html
for that URL and so
we're gonna insert it in
and we're gonna set the page rank to 1.
So the way page rank works is
it gives all the pages some
normal value then it alters
that, we'll see that in a bit.
So it sets it in with one,
we're gonna insert or ignore,
that's just in case
this pages is not there,
but, and then we're gonna do an update
and that's kind of doing
the same thing twice
just sort of doubly making
sure if it's already there
this or ignore will
cause this to do nothing
and the update will cause us to retain it
and then we commit it,
so that if we do selects later
we get that information.
Now this code is similar, remember we use
Beautiful Soup to pull
out all the anchor tags
we have a for loop we pull out the H-ref
and you'll see this code's
a little more complex
than some of the earlier stuff
because it has to deal
with the real nastiness
or imperfection of the web.
And so we're gonna use "URL parse"
which is actually part of the URL lib code
and that's gonna break the
URL into pieces, come back.
We use "URL parse."
We have the scheme which is http or https.
If it's a relav, this
solves relative references.
This is solved relative references
by taking the current URL
and hooking it up.
URL join knows about slashes
and all those other things.
We check to see if there's an anchor,
the pound sign at the end of the URL
and we throw everything past
including the anchor away.
If we have a JPEG or PNG or a GIF,
we're gonna skip it.
We don't want to bother with that.
We're looking through links now.
We're looking at all the links.
Uhm, and if we have a slash at the end,
we're gonna chop of the
slash by saying minus one.
And so, this is just
kind of nasty choppage.
And throwing away the URL's,
but we're going through a page
and we have a bunch that we don't like
or we have to clean them up
or whatever.
And now, and we've made him absolute,
by doing this, it's an absolute URL.
This is just, you write
this slowly, but surely
when your code blows up
and you start it over
and start it over and start it over.
Then what we do is we check
to see through all the webs.
Remember those were the URL's
that we're willing to stay with
and usually it's just one.
If this would link off the sites,
of the sites we're interested in,
we're gonna skip it.
We are not interested in
links that leave the sites.
So this is like link
that left the sites. Skip it.
But now, we finally here a page, line 132,
we are ready to put this into pages.
URL and HTML and it's all good, right?
Uhm, and.
That one's going to be null right there
because we haven't retrieved the HTML.
This is null because this is a
page we're going to retrieve.
We're giving the page rank of one.
And we're giving it no HTML
and that way it'll be retrieved
and then we commit that, okay?
And then, we wanna get the ID,
so we could have done this with,
one way or another,
but we're gonna do a select
to say: "Hey, what was the ID
that either was already there,
or was just created?"
And we grab that with a fetch one
and say retrieve two ID.
And now, were going to put a link in.
Insert or into links from ID to ID
which is the ID,
the primary key of the page
that we're going through
and looking for links
to ID the links we just created.
And, a way we run.
So, it's gonna go and go and go.
Uh, let's go look at the create.
Create statement up here.
From ID and to ID right there.
Okay.
So.
So, let's run it.
Python three, oops.
Python three.
Spider.
Python.
So, it's fresh and so it wants a URL
with which to start.
And I'll just start with
my favorite website.
www.Dr.Chuck.com.
Now, this basically, this
first one you put in,
it's going to stay on
this website for a while.
Okay?
So, I'll hit enter.
And, let's just grab like,
let's grab one page.
Just for yucks.
Okay, so I grabbed that, and uhm,
it printed out that it got,
85, 45 characters.
And it printed out
that it got
six links.
So, if I go to this
and
open database
and I go to code three,
and I go to page rank,
and I look at this.
Oh, let me get out, so it closes.
So, notice this SG lite journal?
That means, it's not done closing,
so I'm going to get out of this
by pressing enter.
And so, you'll notice now that
that journal file went away.
Otherwise, we would not
be getting the final data.
There we go.
Okay, so, webs, let's
take a look at the data.
Webs has just one URL
that's the URL we're allowing
ourselves to look at.
You can put more than
one in here, if you want,
but most people just leave this as one.
Pages, so we got this first one
and we retrieved this
and this is the html of it
and we found six other URL's in there
that are Dr.Chuck.com URL's, right?
There was lots of other URL's in there,
but there are only five other ones
that we found, okay?
And so, what we'll find
is if you go to links
we'll see that page one links to two,
links to three, links to four,
links to five, links to six.
Cause the links is just
a many to many table.
So, page one points to page two.
Page one points to page two.
Page one to three, page one to five.
Okay? So that's what happens
when we have the first page.
So, let's retrieve one more page.
Now, we could have started a new crawl,
but we're just gonna, it's
gonna stay on Dr.Chuck.com
and I'll just ask for one more page.
And so now, it went and grabbed.
It randomly picked among these null guys
and I'm gonna hit enter to close it.
And then, I'll refresh this
and oh, so, it looks like
we retrieved OBI sample
and we didn't get any new links.
And so, the links page,
no, we didn't get any new links.
So, that page, whatever that was,
OBI sample had no external
links, so let's do another one.
One more page.
So, that one had fifteen links.
So, let's take a look now.
So, now we have fifteen pages.
It picked this one to do, right?
And now, it added fifteen more pages.
And then, if you look at links,
you will see that page four
which is the one it just retrieved
links back to page one,
so now, we're seeing,
this is where the page
rank is gonna be cool,
four links to one, four
links to is whatever,
away we go, right?
One goes to four, four goes to one.
I should have probably put a
uniqueness constraint on that.
It's not supposed to duplicated that.
Okay, so let's run this
a bunch of times now.
So, let's run, let's just
run it a hundred times.
For a hundred pages.
It'll take a minute.
So, you'll see it's like
freaking out on certain pages
and not parsing them.
You know, found it's way into my blog.
It's finding like 27 links.
This table is growing
wildly at this point.
It's gonna take us a while
before we get to a hundred.
It's kind of slow.
Now, the interesting thing is,
I can hit "Control C"
at any point and time.
[blowing air]
Right?
And so, that blew up,
but it's okay because
the data is still there.
So, if we go back to pages, for example,
and when we refresh our data,
we see we got a ton of stuff
and this will restart and all the things,
so if we search this,
I sorted that by html,
you see that there's lots of files
that we got and it's never
going to retrieve those again
because those have html.
So then, I can run this thing again
and start it up.
And when I say "Control C"
your computer might go down,
your network might go down.
There's all kinds of
things that might happen
and you just pick up where it leaves off.
It just picks up where it leaves off
and that's what's nice about this.
Okay?
So, that's pretty much how this works.
We've got this part running.
We're seeing it flow into Spider.sqlite.
We're seeing that we can
start this and replace this.
And so, what I'll do, I will
come back in the next video
and show you how all
these things work together
and how we actually do the page rank.
So, thanks again for listening
and see you in the next video.
[soft jazz piano music]