(jazz music)
- [Narrator] Welcome to
Python for Everybody.
We are going to be
talking about some code.
If you want to download all the code,
it's right here.
It's all single big zip file.
And all the sample code,
the one I'm going to talk about
is urllib1.py.
It is not very exciting,
it's short.
That's what's kind of
nice about python code.
And it's really,
if we go and take a look
at the code we played with
just previously,
which is socket.
The idea here is urllib is something
that Python has produced for us
to make socket communications
and http communications
a lot better.
So socket,
this is making socket calls underneath it,
but there's a library that
makes this quite simple.
And so we have to do some imports,
and instead of importing
socket, we'll import these,
we are going to create a handle,
urllib.request.urlopen
and just pass in a string.
So we're not encoding this,
we're not sending get command.
All the stuff we did in the
previous sockets example is gone
and then we can just
put this as a for-loop.
And so we're not using this
lower level read and write code,
we're just using a for-loop.
And so that's literally
is going to read the text
line by line.
And the line does come
back as an array of bites
so we have to do a decode,
but then we gotta have string,
and then we can do a strip on it.
So this is like a super simple,
super simple.
So there we go.
Now the interesting thing is
you also don't see the headers,
we just read the contents.
Now it turns out in urllib,
we'll see this in later
more complex application,
you can get the headers if you want,
you can get various other things.
So that's urllib,
a simple urllib tool.
Now we can also use this in urllib words
to show you something quite interesting
and that is,
if you look at this from right here,
other than the decode,
this is exactly the code we wrote
to compute the words, right.
So line,
and then this line.decode,
this is just a open something up,
in this case we're going to open a url,
we're gonna create a dictionary.
We're gonna loop through each
of the lines in that thing,
we're gonna decode them
and then split them.
So once you do line.decode,
this is now a legitimate
internal Python string.
We split it,
we run through the words,
and run the counts.
So this is exactly like
code that we did before
to run counts.
And so,
python3
urlwords.
And so that gives us a dictionary
which is the word frequency.
And we could do all kinds
of crazy stuff in here,
you know, with assorting
and the kinds of things.
But the important thing
is once you've done
this and this,
the code,
other than the need to decode these lines
when you first get them,
it really works just like makes a urllib
makes url's function inside Python
very much like files.
So these are short and to the point
and very simple,
and I hope that they were useful to you.
(jazz music)