- [Instructor] Hello, and
welcome to Python for Everybody.
My name is Charles Severence.
In this short video I will be explaining
how to run Exercise 2.3
where we prompt for some
Hours, prompt for some Rate,
and multiply them together
and print them out
with a little paid message.
So this is 2.3.
Some of you will immediately
want to go to the Autograder
and do your homework on the Autograder.
I really would rather you didn't do that
unless of course you're doing
this on an iPad or an Android
or something where you
can't install Python.
But you have to realize that
the Autograder isn't forever.
You can only go so far with the Autograder
and eventually you have to
write a real Python program.
So I'll eventually show you
how to run this in Autograder
but I'm gonna instead show you how to
run it in the terminal.
So I'm first gonna go into my
Python for Everybody folder
and I'm gonna make a new folder.
Command+shift+N is what I just did there,
ex_02_03 for Exercise 3.
And so there's Exercise 3.
And I'm also gonna go into Atom
which is my text editor
and see, I have that folder.
So I'm gonna make a new file
and I will say print,
I'll just say ("PY4E")
and then I'll say File, Save As,
and I want to make sure it's in here,
and it's gonna be ex_02.
I don't like putting spaces in file names.
Some operating systems can handle them
but that's why I'm using underscores here.
So I would avoid using
spaces in file names.
So as soon as I give that a ("PY4E"),
as soon as I give it a
Python suffix, I'm there.
And so it shows up there in my desktop.
And now I'm gonna run the terminal program
so that I can get there.
So, cd Desktop,
cd Python for Everybody, that's
the folder on my desktop,
and if I even do an ls, I see
a couple folders and a file.
We can say ls minus l and
see a little more detail
that these two are folders
and this one's a file.
So, change directory, cd ex_02_03.
And so now I'm in that folder
and if I do an ls minus
l, I see that file.
I can also do an ls without
the minus l and see the file.
And now I say,
python3 ex_02_03.py,
and it runs.
You'll see me, no matter
how many times you watch me,
you'll see the first thing that I do
is get to the point where I
know I'm in the right directory
and I can run a little hello
program before I start coding.
I just don't like being crazy, right?
So now I'm gonna go back and
take a look at my assignment.
Enter Hours, you gotta prompt
for hours, ask for a number.
Enter Rate, prompt for rate,
and then calculate pay.
So there's a couple of
input statements here.
xh is my variable I'm gonna choose.
Later I'll choose more effective variables
but for now I'm gonna make them silly.
Enter Hours colon space
and then I'm gonna copy and paste
and call this xr for Rate.
When you're doing this, you
need to be very careful.
And so now I'm gonna calculate xp
which is xh times xr,
and then I'm gonna say print ("Pay:",)
I don't need to put a space
because this comma effectively
creates a space, xp.
And then I'm gonna save that.
I'm gonna switch to my terminal program,
clear my screen in my terminal program,
and I'm gonna type up arrow,
because I already typed
python3 ex_02_03.py
so my Hours, I'll just start
with something really simple
that I can calculate in
my head, 10 and five.
Whoops.
"can't multiply sequence
of non-int of type 'str'".
Here we have a traceback
and again, I encourage you to
realize that these tracebacks
are not personal attacks by Python on you
even though they might
be frustrating. (sighs)
So the way to parse this
is start by saying line 3,
something's wrong at line 3.
It's pretty good at
knowing what line it is
or it's either that line
or the line above it,
and it's something about multiplying.
What it's really saying is, "I'm confused.
"I have to stop
"because I cannot understand
your instructions."
So the problem here, of course, is that
this is of type string
and so you can't multiply a
string times a string, okay?
So we can convert this using a float,
so that's a function call now.
We're passing the string xh
in and the value we get back
is the floating point version of that
and then we call float for this as well.
Now I'll save that,
always remember to save.
So I'm gonna run it.
I'm gonna run my Hours
of 10 and my Rate of 10,
and it's 100, and so
that looks pretty good.
So let's go ahead and try to
run this in the Autograder,
and this is my idea, is you'll take this,
and you'll copy it, and you'll
go back to the Autograder now
and just paste this in.
And so it says, "Use 35
hours and a rate of 2.75."
So let's check the code.
35 hours, OK.
75.
Oh no, 2.75.
Two point seven-five.
And so it's running, and it's
running, and it's running,
and it works!
And, of course, now I've got my Grade.
So this idea where you work here
to get your assignment done correctly
and then you run it in the Autograder
is the way I intend for you to do it,
but again, if you can't do it that way,
it's a great way to get started
to just write your code in the Autograder.
And, you know...
You can change your code in the Autograder
and then run it again.
Of course, this is gonna fail.
35.
And 2.75.
And of course you get a Mismatch,
and now it's angry at you.
The Mismatch here of course
is because I print Howdy Pay in Pay,
and it's real picky
about it, and you think,
"Oh, I got the 96.25 right."
Well, it doesn't really
care so much about that.
So let me go ahead and fix this and run it
so we leave on a successful note!
35 hours
and 2.75 as the rate per hour.
That's kind of a low rate per hour.
And we're getting successful
and of course that means that you now have
a grade on Assignment 2.3.
Look at that, I got a
grade on Assignment 2.3.
Unless, of course, you're running this
in some other environment, okay?
Thank you so much
and I hope that this
has been useful to you.