(slow jazz music)
- [Instructor] Hello and
welcome to Python For Everybody.
We are doing some code samples here.
If you wanna follow along,
you can download the sample
code all in a big .zip file,
I've got it.
We are going to be working
with the Google Maps API.
In the old days, this Maps API was free
and did 2,500 requests per day,
but now they've made it
so that parts of it are behind API keys
and you start having
to use OAuth and stuff,
but not, they haven't put it all behind
this one address service
that we've been using.
That continues to work.
And the basic idea of an API is,
you go read the
documentation, you find a URL,
and this is going to Google servers,
and you pass in the address.
And we have to pass in the address
using what's called URL encoding,
so spaces are pluses,
that's a comma,
and then that's a space.
And so, we have to pass
this in a certain way
but if we do it right, we hit this,
we're gonna get ourselves some JSON back,
and that's really cool.
And so deep inside here
we get the real address,
you know, a good address,
we get a geometry,
we have the location, we got
the latitude and longitude,
and we can extract stuff outta here.
And so, we're talking,
and this one here's still
rate limited to 2,500
but it's one of the few
parts of the Google Maps API
that is not hidden behind an API key.
In a later chapter, we'll
show you how to actually talk
with the API key in the geodata code,
the geoload shows you
how to use an API key
if you want to jump ahead
and take a look at that.
But for now, we're just
gonna take a look at geojson
which is gonna retrieve
one page and tear it apart.
So let's take a look.
So we're going to grab the
urllib stuff and import json,
so now we're gonna use json,
but we're gonna actually pull the data
out of the Internet.
And so, I just take that
serviceurl for Google Maps API,
I found that somewhere
in the documentation,
and then I'm gonna have a
loop that's gonna run forever,
I'm gonna add, for the, at the location,
and then if I hit enter,
that's what this is saying,
get out of the loop.
And then what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna concatenate the,
the serviceurl, which is this,
and this urllib.parse.urlencode
gives a dictionary of address=,
and this, this bit right here,
gives me the string that leads
to putting this address=,
but encoding these spaces the right way.
So if you type a space,
that bit of code turns it into the plus,
so that's important.
And I've got the question
mark sitting here
at the end of that.
Then what we're going to do
is we're just going to do a urlopen,
to get a handle,
we're gonna read the whole document,
and because it's UTF-8,
coming from the outside world,
I'm gonna turn it into unicode
inside our application,
we say .decode.
We can ask how many characters we got,
and we put our json.loads.
Now, up 'til now,
we've just been doing loads's
from internal strings,
but this is now a string that
came from the outside world,
and we'll put a try-except in,
and we'll set js to be none,
and that'll be our little trigger.
Now, we can look for,
they give us, take a look at the output,
they give us this OK, and
that status can be a problem,
and it can complain about things.
So we have to check to see if
we got a good status, and so,
at this point, if you look
at the outer bit of this,
the outer bit that we get
is a curly brace, so it's a dictionary,
then there is within that
dictionary key results,
which is a list,
but then the second thing in
the outer dictionary is status.
And so we can ask,
if, the word, the um,
(clears throat)
If we got a false, if we got
nothing, that we'll quit.
If we don't have a status key
in that job, in that object,
or that dictionary, or
it's not equal to OK,
any number of those things,
like this,
or this,
are all, either of those are
true, we're going to quit,
failure to retrieve,
and print the data out.
And when you're starting
to read stuff off the 'Net,
you often have to put
debugging in here like this,
like, oh, something
quit, I gotta figure out,
something, so debugging it.
Next thing we're gonna
do is call json.dumps,
which is the opposite of loads,
which takes this array that includes,
uh, dictionary that includes arrays,
and we're gonna pretty print
it, with an indent of 4.
and then we're going to print that out,
and so, if you look at my code,
you'll see that the first
thing we do, once we parsed it,
is we print it back out so we can see it.
And then we're going to dig into it.
So let's go ahead and run this code.
python geojson.py.
Arrgh!
One of these days I will
always type python3.
Ann Arbor, comma, Michigan.
Okay, so it ran,
and so you see that it retrieved this URL.
This URL was constructed, and
it retrieved 1736 characters,
and it's JSON pretty
printed with an indent of 4,
and this is that, this is that json.dumps,
all the way down to here.
So that's just json.dumps,
and then it starts extracting.
So it's gonna pull things out.
Now when I, when you write this code,
it's really easy to look at this and say,
oh, great, it's easy!
I tend to have to print this stuff out
over and over and over as I
kinda construct this expression.
But if we look at it,
the outer dictionary,
the outer dictionary sub
results leads to this array,
and if you go look at
this array carefully,
you find there's only one thing in it,
and so that the results is an array.
Sub 0 gets us this, this dictionary,
I keep wanting to say object
'cause that's what it's called,
and that goes all the way down to here,
so that's what we get there.
And then, within that,
we now have an object,
and we look for,
geometry within that
object, where is geometry?
Right there, geometry.
Geometry goes from there to there,
there's geometry in there.
Gotta get used to it,
that's why it's nice to
have this stuff indented.
Geometry, sub lo--, whoops, come back.
Come back.
And then we go to location within that,
so location within geometry.
And then within location
we have lat and lng.
So this is pulling out this 42 and 83.
And then, so we print that out,
take a look, (whooshes)
and that prints that out,
pulls that right out of the JSON.
These are tricky to write,
but after a while you'll win,
and you'll get it right,
and it's just fine, 'kay?
And so we do the same thing, result sub 0,
formatted_address gets us this,
and so that's how we
print the location out.
And so that's a real quick
look at how we would do that
with the JSON talking to the,
the Google Maps API.
'Kay?
Hope this helps.
(slow jazzy piano)