(relaxing jazz music)
- [Narrator] Hello, and welcome
to Python for Everybody.
We're doing some sample code.
You can get ahold of the sample code zip
if you want to follow along.
And so, we're picking
up in the middle here,
where we are running a simple
spider that's retrieving data
and putting it into running
this spider.py file.
And it's cruising around and doing things,
and the beauty of any of
these spider processes
is I can stop anytime
and just hit CTRL + C.
And so, we take a look
at the spider.sqlite file
and retrieve it, and it
looks like we got 302 pages.
I don't know how many we got retrieved.
70, okay, there we go.
We got about
a hundred.
Oh wait, I'm looking for the wrong thing.
No, no, no, no, no.
No.
Yeah, we got about 107 pages.
So, what we're going to
do now with 107 pages
is we are going to run
a page rank algorithm.
Okay, so let's take a look at that code.
So, the idea of page rank.
We're gonna run this page rank algorithm.
The SP reset just resets the page rank,
and SP rank runs as many
iterations of page rank.
So, the basic idea
is that if you're to
look at the links here,
you know, we think of page
120 to page two gives some
of page one's love to page two.
Page four has some value
that it gives to page one.
You go on, and page two
gives love to page 46.
Over and over and over again.
And so, but the problem is
that how good is page one,
and how much positive karma
does it give to page two?
And so what happens is,
we start by give every page
a rank of one.
We say, look, everybody starts out equal.
But then what we do is, we divide up,
in one iteration of the
page rank algorithm,
we divide up the goodness of a page
across its outbound links,
and then accumulate that,
and that becomes the next rank, okay?
And so, let's take a look at the code
for the page rank algorithm.
So, this is pretty simple.
It only imports sqlite3,
'cause it's really doing
everything in the database, right?
It's gonna be updating
these columns right here
in the database.
And so,
we're gonna do some things
here to speed this up.
This rank runs, if you're
thinking of Google,
this rank runs slowly, and
it's gonna run continuously
to keep updating these things.
So, the first thing I do is I
read in all of the from ID's
from the links.
Select Distinct throws out any duplicates.
And so I have all the from ID's,
which are all the pages that
have links to other pages.
'Cause all the pages are
in pages, but in links,
to have a from ID, you also
have to have a to ID, okay?
And so, we're also going
to look at the pages
that receive page rank,
and we're kind of
pre-caching this stuff, okay?
And so we're gonna do a Select
Distinct, a from ID and to ID
and loop through that group of things.
And we're not gonna...
We're making a links list here,
and so we're saying,
if the from ID is the same as the to ID,
we're not interested.
If the from ID is not already
in my from ID's that I've got,
I'm gonna skip it.
If the to ID is not in the from ID,
meaning that this is a
to ID that's not also...
We don't want links that
point off to nowhere
or point to pages that
we haven't retrieved yet,
and that's what this is saying.
So, this is really going to give us...
It's a filter on the
from ID's and the to ID's
from the links table so
that it only are the links
that point to another page
we've already retrieved.
And then, we're going to keep
track of the entire superset
of to ID's, the destination ID's.
And I'm just putting these all in lists
so that I don't have to
hit the database so hard.
Okay, so this is getting what's called
the strongly connected component,
meaning that any of these
ID's, there is a path
from every ID to every
other ID eventually.
So, that's called the
strongly connected component
in graph theory.
Then what we're going to do
is, we're gonna grab the...
We're gonna select New Rank from pages.
For all the from ID's, right?
And so, we're going to have
a dictionary that's based on
the ID, the primary key.
That's what node is.
Equals the rank.
And so, if we look at our database,
that means that for the
part of the strongly
connected component in links,
we're gonna grab this number
and stick it into a dictionary
based on the primary key of this.
Based on the primary key
of this number right here.
So, we're gonna have a dictionary
that's this map to that.
Again, we wanna do this
as fast as possible.
Now, we're only doing one
iteration at the beginning,
so that's how many times
you want to run it, okay?
And so, we just make an integer of that.
We check to see if there's
any values in there.
If there are no values, we are bad.
And now, we're going to go
I equals one to range many.
This is gonna be one to one,
so it might run however many times.
And then what it's gonna do is,
it's gonna compute the new page ranks.
And so what it's really gonna do,
is it's gonna take the page
rank, the previous ranks,
and loop through them, and...
The previous ranks is the
mapping of primary key
to old page rank.
Okay?
And for each node,
we're gonna have total
equals total plus old rank,
and then we're gonna set the
next ranks to be zero, okay?
And then what we're gonna do
is figure out the number of outbound links
for each page rank item.
So, node and old rank and the
list of the previous ranks.
These are the ID's we're gonna give it to.
And so, for this particular node,
we're going to have the outbound links,
and we're going to go through the links
and not link to itself,
although we made sure that doesn't happen.
We make sure that this.
But then we're going to
make a list called Give ID's
which are the ID's
that node is going to share its goodness.
And now what we're going
to do is we're gonna say
how much goodness are
we gonna flow outbound
based on our previous rank
of this particular node
and the number of outbound links we have.
So, that's how many times.
That's how much we're gonna
give in our outbound links.
And then what we're doing is
all the ID's we're giving it to
we started with the next ranks
being zero for these folks.
These are the receiving end,
and we're gonna add the amount
of page rank to each one.
So whatever this is,
so we'll go through all of the links,
give out fractional bits
of our current goodness,
and it's accumulated in each one,
and so eventually all the incoming links
will have granted each new link a value.
Okay?
Now I'm just gonna run through
and calculate the new total,
and this evaporation,
the idea is, is that,
you can't, you can't...
It has to do with the page rank algorithm
that there are dysfunctional shapes
in which page rank can be trapped,
and this evaporation is
taking a fraction away
from everyone and giving
it back to everybody else.
And so, we add this evaporative factor.
And then we're gonna do some computations
just to show some stuff, and that is,
we're calculating the difference,
the average difference,
between the page ranks,
and you'll see this
when I start running it.
And that is telling us, this
is gonna tell us the stability
of the page rank.
So, from one iteration to the
next, the more it changes,
the least stable it is,
and you'll see in a sec
that these things stabilize.
And we say, what's the average difference
in the page ranks per node,
which is what this is.
And that's what we're gonna print.
And now, we're gonna take the new ranks
and make them the old ranks,
and then run loop again.
So, I'm not actually updating
the database each time
through the page rank iteration,
but then at the very end,
I am going to do the updates
for all of these things
and update all of the
rankings with a new rank.
So, I'm doing an in-memory calculation
so that this runs, this loop
here, runs screamingly fast
even if I wanna do, like this
loop 100 times or 1,000 times.
It's really all just
in-memory data structures.
Okay, so it's probably easier
just for me to show you this.
It'll be very...
The code runs quite simply.
Python
three
print sprank
rank
dot py.
And so, I'm only gonna
run it for one iteration,
and that means that its loop here
is just gonna run one time.
And so, it's gonna start
with the page ranks,
the new rank of one, and it's
gonna just run one iteration
and put the rank there, okay?
And then update this as well.
So, let's go ahead and run
that once for one iteration.
Okay, and so it ran one iteration,
and the average change
between the previous rank
and the new rank is one.
So, it's actually quite crazy,
so I'm gonna refresh here,
and you'll see that the old
rank was one and the new rank
went way down, way
down, way down, way down
down a little bit,
down some, up a whole bunch,
down, down, up.
So, you see that they went down and up.
Now, the sum of all of these numbers
is gonna be the same, right?
'Cause all it did was like flowed it out
and recalculated it.
And so, that's what
happens with page rank.
And so, what'll happen is,
if I run one more page rank iteration,
these numbers will be used
to compute the new, new rank,
and then these will be
calculated to the old rank.
And so, you'll see that these will get...
They will change again, so
I'll just run it one more time.
So I'm gonna run one iteration.
And then I'm gonna hit refresh.
So, you see all these
numbers got copied over,
but now there's a new rank that's computed
based on these guys.
And so, they're getting, this one went up.
This was .13; that's gone up a little bit.
This one's gone up some more.
This one's gone up.
This one went down, right?
So this one went down from six to eight.
And you can see that the difference
is now the average difference
between this number and this
number across all of them
went from one point something to .41.
And you'll see that with
these very few pages,
as page rank converges really quickly.
Okay?
So, let's run it again,
and I'll just run 10,
and you'll watch how this converges.
Okay, so there you go; it converges.
So, and you're seeing now,
after like 12 iterations,
that the difference between
the old rank and the new rank,
well, that's because it's that old rank.
I'll run one more iteration
so that you can see.
So, this old rank is less
than, you know, .005,
and so now you can see
that these numbers are sorta stabilizing.
This is the average.
That 005 number is the average difference
between these two things.
Now, if we're gonna pretend
to be Google for a moment,
we can say python3,
spider.py, so...
So, let's just do 10 more pages.
Now, what's gonna happen here is
these new pages are gonna
have page ranks of one, okay?
So, let's get out.
So, if I do a refresh now,
and I look at new rank.
So, there's these guys
that have high rank.
What you'll see, I hope, if we get...
Okay, see new pages, right?
These are the new ones
that we just retrieved.
I don't know if they're linked
or not, and they all got one.
So, some old pages are way up, 14.
Some pages, if we go
downwards, are way down, right?
So, these are like useless pages.
They, you know, they point to somewhere,
but nobody points to them.
That's what happens with
these page ranks, okay?
So, what happens is, is the
new records get this .1,
and so if I run the ranking
code again, and I run...
Let's just run five iterations.
You'll see that the average
delta goes up just briefly
as it sort of assimilates these new pages,
and then it goes right back down again.
And so that's what's
happening with Google.
It's sort of running the
spider to get more pages,
then running the page rank,
which gets disturbed a little bit,
but then it re-converges very rapidly.
And of course, they're
got billions of pages,
and we've got hundreds of
pages, but you get the idea.
Okay, and so I can run
page rank like 100 times,
and after awhile, it just
sort of hardly is changing.
So, that's 2.7 to the negative 10th power.
So now, you know, let
me run it one more time
to update the stuff,
and if I refresh this,
you're gonna see.
Look at how stable these numbers are.
14, nine, four, three,
five, nine, one, five,
six, seven.
The difference is there
in the seventh one.
So, that's why this whole
page rank is really cool.
It seems like it's really
chaotic when it first starts out,
and away you go.
Okay?
So.
That was just this.
SP rank, right?
SP rank
and SP reset.
We can look at that code.
I won't bother running it.
It just sets the old
rank to one; that's it.
That's as much code as you got.
It just restarts it and lets it rerun.
So, I'm gonna stop now, and
I'm going to start a new video
where I talk about this phase here
where we're actually gonna
visualize the page-ranked data.
(relaxing jazz music)