(piano jazz music)
- [Charles] Welcome to
Python for Everybody.
We're doing some code, sample code.
We're playing through with
some sample code samples
and you can get this by downloading it.
I've got this whole thing downloaded
and I've got all the files here
and these are the files we're
going to play with today.
Today, what we're going to do
is talk about the Twitter API
and the one thing we gotta
learn about the Twitter API
is we have to authorize ourselves
and so we have to make sure
that we have a Twitter account
and then we get some keys.
In this particular application,
if you want to duplicate what I'm doing,
you have to go to apps.twitter.com,
click this create new application button
and then get some codes.
And the codes show up as
soon as you hit this button
and then one more button,
which I'm not going to do on screen.
And so, what happens is,
there are four codes that you got
to put in this file, hidden.py.
Consumer_key, the consumer_secret,
token_key, and token_secret.
These are just messed up,
so I'll show you how this works
and blows up if, first.
And then I'll put my keys in here,
without showing you.
But basically, this is the
little file you gotta edit
or these Twitter ones don't work.
You'll see what happens.
So, the first one I'm gonna
do, is the simplest one of all
and that is, I call
this thing Twitter test
and it's going to go ask
for the user timeline
and we can take a look at this
and we're gonna take the URL
and we're going to augment the URL.
This is the base, we
found this looking at the
Twitter API documentation.
We're going to pass the parameter of
screen_name, drchuck, and a count of two.
So, this is just a Python dictionary
and augment comes from this
little bit of code called twurl
and this uses a bit of code called oauth,
which is built into Python as well
and it augments the URL and
it takes the key, the secret,
the token key and does a thing
and assigns it and makes
this big, long, ugly, URL,
which you will soon see.
It's a signature of the URL.
So, we pass this data
back and forth to Twitter
with a signature and then
they recheck the signature
and it's a digital signature
that this URL came from
a program that knows the
key, secret, token, and token secret.
And so this augment basically,
is something I wrote, twurl, augment,
is something I wrote to
make it easier to add
all these oauth parameters
and you feed this code by
putting your data into hidden.py.
Lots of people get this to work,
so don't worry, it's kinda cool
when you finally get it to work.
So, let's take a look at what it does,
just know that this makes an awesome URL
that does all the security
and we'll see one of those URLs.
Ignore the certificate errors,
this has to do with the fact that
we're using https and
Python doesn't have enough
certificates to put into by default,
for a lot of reasons, but
our quick and dirty way
is to turn them off.
Thank you Python for reducing
security by teaching us,
so this is the best way to do it.
That's a crumpium moment on my part.
So, what we're going to do,
we're going to do a URL open,
this is to shut off the security checking
for the ssl certificate.
We're going to read all the data
and then we're going to print it out
and we're also going
to ask the connection.
Remember, I told you a long time ago
that urllib eats the headers
but you can get them back
and now we're going to ask to get
a dictionary of the headers back.
So, we'll print those out.
This is really kinda just testing
the body and the headers
and printing them out
sort of in as raw a way we can do.
So, let's go run this.
Now this is going to fail
the first time we do it
because we haven't put the
hidden variables in there.
So, if I say python3 twtest.py,
it's going to run and blow up
and give you this 401
authorization required.
That's a good sign because that means you
haven't yet updated your
values in hidden.py.
This is that augmented
URL and you can see the
consumer_key, then consumer_secret,
and the oauth_token and whatever.
Okay, so these tokens are like, wrong.
Oops, control C.
They aren't real, but you'll notice that
key and the secret, the
token_key and the token_secret,
and the secret and that's
all actually encoded
in this signature.
Turns out that you need to have the
secret and the token_secret
to generate the signature
and where is the signature,
oh there's the signature,
right, there's the signature.
And so, this signature
combined with nonce,
the signature has time and
includes all kinds of things,
so even if you type this in,
you'll see these go by
and it's not really breaking
my security too much
when you see these afterwards.
So, don't get all excited when you say,
oh, you revealed your token and your key.
Well I can reveal my token_key
but I'm not gonna reveal the secret.
This adds all this oauth stuff.
Oauth_nonce, oauth_timestamp,
and these timestamps and nonces are made
so you can't replay my URL,
even if you see the exact URL.
Once I hit it, then you can't hit it again
and so that's what the nonce does.
So, I'm gonna close hidden.py here
and I'm going to update
hidden.py in another window.
So, in another window,
I updated hidden.py,
I'm not going to show you that,
but now I'm going to
run python3 twtest.py.
So, twurl is going to read hidden
and now these keys and
secrets are my real ones,
that I haven't shown you.
So, this should work, fingers crossed.
Yay, it worked.
So, it worked, so I'm calling Twitter.
Here's the URL, now don't worry,
the token and the
consumer_key are not enough
to break into my account
and neither is the signature
because you can't replay this,
in about five minutes, you
can't replay this anymore.
You can't generate the signature,
the signature includes the time and date,
so you can't, trust me.
Go read up on oauth, don't worry.
I haven't really revealed anything,
but the first thing we see is this.
We should part like the
line of dashes here.
This is the JSON, it ain't very pretty,
it's not very pretty.
So, that's the JSON, from there to there.
It's just what most APIs give us back,
it's really dense JSON, right.
And so, this is a byte array.
Remember how you have to do a .decode?
I didn't do a .decode here
and so Python is telling
us this is a byte array.
Which it's a raw set of bytes
that came from the internet,
which probably are UTFA
and if I put a decode here,
then it would decode, if
I say .data.decode there,
then it would be fine,
but we don't care, this is just
a dump, do we get anything?
Let's do this, print, I'll
just make this code different,
put some equal signs here,
a lot of equal signs.
So we can easily see
where the thing starts and stops.
So we'll run that again,
if you look at those URLs.
That was all of that stuff and then
this is the headers.
So, the headers, again, are not pretty.
You get the headers, it's a dictionary.
You got cache-control,
no-cache, this is the string.
Key value, you got to find
your commas key value.
But the one that's really
interesting here is,
which one is it?
X-rate-limit-remaining,
so that means for this particular API,
this header tells me
that I got 898 calls left
and this is when I'll get more calls.
So watch, I'm going to do this again
and you will see that I can
only do this 897 more times now.
Run it, I can only do the 897.
So, I am being tracked at this point.
I am being tracked by Twitter.
Twitter knows that it's drchuck doing this
and drchuck had done
900, he's done 899, 897,
and if I keep running this,
eventually Twitter will tell
me, you gotta wait for awhile
and that's because
Twitter doesn't want me,
under my drchuck account,
pulling out lots and
lots of stuff out Twitter
and making my own website.
I do actually have my own Twitter website,
using some cool software.
Www.dr-chuck.com/twitter.
And this I have to run
and rate limits cause
all kinds of whatever.
So, I'll save that.
So, this is just a test.
I want to do something interesting.
So we're not parsing the
JSON that comes back,
we're not doing anything tricky with this
and away we go.
Let's take a look at some more code.
I think I don't need this anymore.
I am going to parse this.
So, most of this looks the same.
I've got that same user_timeline.json,
I'm going to ignore the ssl
certificates, write a loop.
I'm going to print.
I'm going get a Twitter account
and quit if it's a blank line (inaudible).
I'm going to use the
twurl.augment the same way.
That's going to do all the
signing using from hidden.py,
I'll retrieve it and I'm
going to retrieve it,
ignoring the ssl errors and
them I'm going to decode it,
so I get a real unicode string
and I'll print the first
250 characters of it.
I'm gonna grab the headers
and I'm going to print
the remaining rate limit.
This is sort of a very simple
version this, same thing,
it really is decoding the data
and only printing the
first 250 characters,
so let's run that.
Drchuck, boom and it's got 896.
So this just a little simpler version,
a little less brutal debugging.
So, now let's do something even more fun.
Let's go to twitter2.py and tear it apart.
So again, we're going to
look at my friends list,
or anybody's friends list.
We're going to ask for the friends
and ask for the screen_name,
ask for the first five friends
and then look at their statuses.
Open it, decode it, get the headers,
print the rate limit remaining.
All this stuff is the same as in twitter1
and now we're going to
parse the javascript.
I'm not even putting
this in a try and accept
because, hey, I'm talking to Twitter.
I'm gonna guess that Twitter's
gonna give me the right stuff.
You'll probably want to
put a try and accept here.
Then I'm gonna do a debug print.
I'm gonna do a JSON pretty print,
let's make that be 2, so
it looks a little better.
And then, I'll run it
and then you're gonna see
how we have to parse this.
We're gonna see that it's a list.
We're done with that
and now we're running twitter2.py.
So, I'm gonna go to drchuck
and this is going to ask the question,
who drchuck's friends are.
Okay, let's go to top.
It hit this API
and it has the screen
name, drchuck equals five
and all the oauth stuff.
Again, this is not a security breach
by showing you all of this.
Because the signature,
the secrets aren't there.
If we look at it,
it's an outer object or dictionary
and then outer has a users which is a list
and then each user has some stuff in it.
This one is Stephanie Teasley.
It's got her screen name and
it's got some descriptions.
Keep on going, it's got her status,
her latest status.
For my friend, her status,
her source, where she's at.
Man oh man, she's got a lot of stuff here.
Okay, there we go, that was the first one.
Then the next one I'm following
is LiveEdu, et cetera.
Som you'll see that this an array.
So that outer thing is an array of users.
Now, js here is a dictionary.
So I can say for U in js sub users,
while js sub users is a list.
So the first U is gonna be
this Stephanie Teasley U
and the second U is gonna be LiveEdu.
That's all it took to get
through all that stuff
and figure that out.
Then I'm gonna say, get me
the screen name of my person.
So that's gonna pull Stephanie Teasley
as stephteasley out.
Then I'm gonna go find her status.
Lets find her somewhere in here.
The U of status sub text.
Come on, there's sub status.
Sub status is all this stuff.
More, more, more, more, more, more.
Right there, that's status,
that's U of status is that
and then U of status
sub text, is this stuff.
So it's gonna extract this bit right here.
and so, U status text
and I print out the first 50 characters
of the screen name status.
And I do that for the first five
because I told it, I only wanted five.
And then of course, I get
to see the rate limit.
So, let's go down to the bottom.
All of this is the debug
print of the JSON I got back.
Here is the program starting to print.
Here is the screen name of my first friend
and here's the first 50 characters
of her most recent status.
Here is the screen name of my,
and these are in reverse
order who I've been following.
So I've been playing with
this live coding stuff.
So I'm following them.
What?
KeyError status, that didn't work.
Why not?
Oh that's because Livecodingtv,
somehow doesn't have a status.
So, most of these work.
So now you'll get to see me fix something.
When you download it, it'll be fixed.
And so it says KeyError status,
so that means I've gotta
do a thing that says,
if status not in u,
print no status found, continue.
Since sometimes, there's no statuses,
who would have thought?
I did not know that.
Okay, let's run this again.
Did I get to see my remaining?
Actually, let me change the order of this.
Let me put this down here.
That'll be wrong from the slides
but it'll be prettier now.
Let's put the headers
after the dump of the data.
Okay, let's run it again.
Did I save it, yeah.
Drchuck, blah, a whole bunch of stuff.
So, I got 13 remaining calls on this one.
So, it's not the same as the other one.
I don't get to call this
too many more times,
so hopefully I'll get
debugging to work, sort of.
I got a bad space here.
Not status found, no status found.
And I need to put three spaces there.
No status found, I'll make an asterisk.
So, let's run it again
and see I got 13 remaining.
It's important write code
that's aware of your remaining,
that's why I made so obvious about that.
It'll retrieve all of that.
I got 12 remaining, but
my code starts to look,
ah dang it, I need another space here.
Hang on, gotta fix that.
I need yet another space.
Hopefully, I can make this as
pretty as I want it to work.
Oh wait a sec (laughs),
I didn't even do drchuck,
are you that wrong?
Type my name wrong.
Okay, so now it works (laughs).
Oh well, so now I have my
first most five recent friends are this,
stephteasley,
liveeduofficial, livecodingtv,
nancygilby, and greggykrueger.
And so there are their statuses
and I tore all this JSON apart
using twitter2.py.
Of course, after fixing hidden.py,
which I'm not going to show you,
'cause it actually contains my real
consumer_key and consumer_secret.
You're seeing the
consumer_key and the token_key
go by on each of these URLs,
but what you're not seeing
is these two things,
which are the thing I'm protecting.
So, that it's not a problem.
Okay, I will send that up.
There you go.
I hope you found this useful.
The code will be fixed
when you take a look at it
and download it here from samplecode.zip.
(piano jazz music)