- [Narrator] Hello everybody, welcome to
Python for everybody.
This is another worked coding sample,
you can download the sample code zip file,
if you want to follow along.
And the code that we're working on today
is what I call the "Geodata Code"
and that is a code that
is going to pull some
some locations from this file,
we're simulating or using
the Google Places API
to look places up and so we
can visualize them on a map.
And so this is the basic picture,
if we take a look at this where.data file,
it's just a flat file that
has a list of organizations,
and this actually was pulled
from one of my moot surveys,
we just let people type in
where they went to school,
and this is just a sample of them.
So this data is read in
by this program geoload.py
and if you recall, this Google
geodata has rate limits,
it also has API keys which
we'll talk about in a bit too.
And so the idea is this is a
restartable, spider-like process.
And so we want to be able to run this
and have it blow up,
and run it and start it
and not lose what we've got, right?
And so this is unlike, so we're now using
a database as well as an API,
but in order to work around
the rate limits of this API,
we're going to use the database
with a restartable process.
And then we'll make some sense of this,
and then we'll visualize this,
but in the short term,
let's start with the geoload.py code.
Geoload.py, take a look here.
So, a lot of this hopefully, by now,
is somewhat familiar to you,
urllib, json, sqlite,
and so I mentioned that the Google APIs,
these used to be free,
and did not require an API key,
but increasingly they're
making you do API keys
for, especially, new ones.
So what happens, you can
go to your Google Places,
I mean, go to Google
APIs and get an API key
and you can put it in here,
it'll be this long, big long
thing that looks like that.
And then if you have an API key,
you can use the Places API
and I've got a copy of a subset,
not all of it, a subset,
of it here at this url.
As a matter of fact, you can
just go to this url in a browser,
and it will tell you a list
of the data it knows about.
'Kay?
And I made it so that that does
the same basic protocol with the address,
you know, address equals
as the Google Place's API.
So this will just change
how we retrieve the data,
either retrieve it from myserver,
the nice thing about myserver,
it's got no rate limit, it's really fast,
and you're not fighting
with Google all the time,
and it means that, perhaps,
if you're in a country
that Google is not well supported,
you can use my API,
I mean, that's really strange that somehow
my API is more reliable and
available than the Google one,
but it's true.
So we're gonna make a database,
we're gonna do a create
table if not exists
and we'll have some address,
and we're really just caching
the geographical data,
we're gonna cache the json.
One of the things we do when
we build these processes
is we tend to simplify these things
and not do all the calculation
in parsing the json
just load it and get it in
and load it and get it in
and fill the data up in this database,
and so that's what we're going to do.
Because Python doesn't ship
with any legitimate certificates,
we have to sort of ignore
certificate errors.
We're gonna open the file,
and we're gonna loop through it
and pull out the address from the file,
and we're going to select from the geodata
where that address is the address.
Let's move this in a bit.
And so we're gonna do a select,
and pull out that address,
and the idea is is if it's
already in the database,
we don't want to do it,
so we do fetchone and
pull out that first thing
which is, that will be
the json right there.
If we get that we'll continue up,
otherwise we'll keep going.
Pass just means "don't blow up"
so we accept and we just do a pass,
that's like a no-op.
And we're going to make a dictionary
because that's what we do
for the key value pairs,
everything you've seen so far,
I've used constants here,
but because we may or
may not have an API key
query equals and then that's the address,
and then the key equals
and then the API key,
if you you recall
urlencode adds the pluses
and question marks and
all that nice stuff.
We're gonna retrieve it,
we're gonna read it and decode it,
print out how much data we've got,
and add a count,
and then we're gonna try
to parse that json data
and print it if something goes wrong.
And as we've seen at this top level
of this json data from this
geocoding API is an object,
which we'll see a little
bit of it in a bit.
And it has a status field in it,
and the status is OK if things went well,
so if the status is not there,
that means our JavaScript
is not well formed
or not how we expected,
if the status is not okay
or not equal to ZERO RESULTS,
then print out failure to
retrieve and then quit,
and then we're simply going to insert
this new data that we just put in,
and then we're gonna commit it,
and every tenth one, this is count mod 10,
we're gonna pause for five seconds
and we can hit control C here,
and then we're going to do the geodump.
'Kay?
So let's just run this.
Geodata.
Python, so let's do an ls,
so we don't have, oh we do have.
Let's get rid of from a previous test,
geodata.sqlite,
so we'll start with a fresh,
a fresh set of data and
run Python geoload.py.
Of course, I'm always
forever making the mistake
of forgetting Python 3,
so you can see that it's running
and it's adding the query
and in this case I don't have the API key,
and it's putting the pluses in,
and that's this part
here with all the pluses
that's the urlencode,
and you notice it's pausing a bit,
now depends on how fast
your net connection,
this may or may not go so fast,
but this is not that much data,
so it should, it's like
only 2000-3000 characters,
and so it's working,
and talking to my myserver.
And the interesting thing
here is I can blow this up,
I'm gonna hit control C,
in Windows you'd hit control,
in Linux you'd hit control C,
and in Windows I think
you'd hit control Z,
depending on what shell you're working in,
but I'm gonna hit control C,
and you see I sort of blew it up, right?
And that's, causes a trace back
at KeyboardInterrupt trace back.
We'll do an ls minus l,
you can see that now
this geodata is there,
now, in the name of restarting,
I will restart this and you will see
that it checks and skips,
and so all, it runs this
code here where it's...
Right here, it grabs it and
finds it in the database,
so you'll see it say found in the database
really quick, chop, chop, chop.
And go really fast and then it'll go back
to catching up where it left off.
And so all those up there,
they did not actually re-retrieve it,
'cause it knew about those things.
And so now it's catching
up, and doing some more,
and doing some more, and doing some more.
And then I'll hit control C,
it has a little counter
in here that basically,
if it hits 200 it stops
and you have to restart it.
You could obviously change this code,
you could make it so it didn't sleep,
doesn't hurt to sleep for like a second
after every 100 or so
if you want you can change that code,
and now let's just hit control C
and blow it up, ls minus l,
and there is another bit of code,
and this code, it's always good
to write these really simple things,
and so we're gonna, now
we're going to import
sqlite and json, we're
gonna connect ourselves up,
we're goin to open,
except this is a utf-8,
because it's a utf we're
gonna open this with utf-8
and we're going to read through,
and in this case we're going to decode.
Select star from locations,
and if you recall, locations
has a location and a geodata.
And so the sub 0 will be the location
and the sub 1 will be the geodata
and we're going to parse it.
Convert it to a string and then parse it,
if something goes wrong with a json
we'll just keep skipping it.
We'll check to see if we
have the status in our json.
Lemme run the sqlite browser here.
File, open databases, take a look
at what's in this database.
Oh, where are we, code3,
geodata, geodata sqlite.
So this is our, the data we've got,
so if you, I'll make this
a little bigger if I can.
Can I make that bigger?
Yeah, it's not gonna show us much.
So you can see that these are
the addresses and the geodata,
that's just the json,
so that's the json that we've got,
and it retrieves it,
and so this is a really simple database,
that's just a sort spidering process,
run, run, run.
But now we're gonna run the geodump code,
which is gonna read this
and dump this stuff out,
and print where.js,
so it's gonna actually parse this stuff.
And that's a code we've seen before,
and so we're actually reading it,
and this line goes into the results,
results is an array,
so if we go into results,
we're gonna go grab the
0th item in that array,
and then we're gonna go find geometry
and then location and then lat and long
for the latitude and longitude,
and then we're also gonna
take the actual address
out of the formatted address right here.
So in this, in this bit of code,
we're actually parsing the json
and we're gonna clean things up,
get rid of some single quotes,
this kind of data cleaning is just stuff
after you play with it for a while,
you realize, "Oh, my
data's ugly or does this."
I'm gonna print it out, and
I'm gonna write this out,
and I'm gonna write it
into a JavaScript file,
and so the JavaScript
file is this where.js
and this, I'll show
you what it looks like,
it's gonna be overwritten,
this is the one that
came out of the zip file.
It'll have the latitude, the longitude,
and we're gonna use
JavaScript to read this
in this where.html file.
It's going to actually
read this right there,
and pull that data in and that's
how we're gonna visualize,
I'm not gonna go into great detail
on how the visualization happens,
but that's what's happening,
and so we're gonna write that.
We're gonna actually write this to a file,
so let's go ahead and run this code
and say python3 geodump.
Okay, so it wrote 120 records to where.js
so if we look at where.js
this is now the new data
that I just downloaded moments ago
and it says open where.html in a browser.
Now this way you'll need
the Google Maps API,
and you might not be able to see this
depending on where you're at,
but here you go with Google Maps locations
and I think if you hover over this,
you can see and you see the utf,
why we bear in that particular thing
why we had to use the utf-8
when we wrote the file so
we that we didn't end up
with trouble writing the file out.
And so there you go.
And so that is a simple visualization
and just a simple visualization
it wrote this where.js
if you are smart with html and JavaScript,
you can look at this where.html file,
it's really just reading
through a bunch of data
and putting the points.
That's all there is,
but I'm not going to go through that.
So at least not in this.
And so I hope that this was useful to you,
and thanks for watching.