(soft piano music)
- [Narrator] Hello and welcome
to Python for Everybody,
I'm Charles Severance, I'm
the author of the textbook
and we're going to do
a little bit of code,
if you want to get your hands on the code,
go to the materials
website materials dot php,
actually materials dot php
and download the sample code.
The code that we're going to work on today
is the xml code and we
need to be able to talk xml
to work with web services and so
here's one of the examples from the book.
It's xml one dot py and
so later we'll be pulling
xml and json from the web but for now
we're just gonna put it in a
triple coded string, so data.
And we're going to use
a built in xml parser
in Python called Element Tree
and when we say import
xml etree element tree
as ET, this as ET gives us basically
a shortcut handle for it.
And so the idea, this is a string
it has less thans and greater thans
it looks like structured information
and it is but really at this
point it's only a string.
Now we have to call this ET from string
to read this and give
us back a tree object.
And what it does is this might blow up,
this code might blow up right here
if there was a mistake in it.
Okay, and a matter of fact, I
can probably put a mistake in.
Let's see if I can delete this
and save it and run this code
and we'll see that it will blow up.
Right, and so it blew
up here in line eight
element tree blew up, it blew
up in line 12 of the code
which is right here.
This failed because the line eight
of the xml string was wrong.
So let's put that back in.
So now it's properly formed xml.
So this tree we get back, I name it tree
just because I always name it tree
but you could name it x, so the key is
tree dot find goes and
looks for a tag named find.
Tree has no longer got less thans
and greater thans in it.
It has went and turned these into
objects within objects within objects.
So tree find name says I would
like to find the tag name
and that's what this bit is right here.
And then dot tx dot text
is going within that
and grabbing that text, okay?
And if we say tree find dot email
then that's going to give us this.
And then that's that
object, and then dot get
asks for the contents
of the hide attribute
which is the string yes.
And so if we run this, now that it's fixed
python three xml one
dot py, it will pull in
and get the name and the attribute.
So it pulled the Chuck out.
So you get this object and then
you kind of dive into that object.
And so that's xml one dot py
if you've got a tag, you can either
get the text out of the tag or
you can get an attribute out of the tag.
So now let's take a
look at xml two dot py.
Again we import element
tree and we have a tag.
And xml's always gotta
have a single outter tag.
But this time we're gonna
have it affect a list.
Now let's line this up a little better.
There we go, that looks a little prettier.
And so users, the fact that it's users
doesn't mean anything
but we often come up with
semantically meaningful
names for these things.
Users is gonna have as its children
as a list of user tags.
So the children under
user, users under users
and then this has each of these as a tag.
So we wanna parse this, and this is a
common thing we wanna do.
So again the first thing
we do is we read the string
to just take this, it's
a triple coded string
going from here to here.
And then we're gonna
instead of doing find,
which gives us one tag,
we're going to do find
all with the users tag,
the user tag that is a child of users.
And we get back a python list of the tags
not of the text but of the tags.
So there's one tag, and
there is another tag.
And so you can do len of that
so we can see that we got two.
And then we can write a four loop
and this item is gonna iterate through the
user tags that are children of users.
So the first time item
is gonna be this tag,
a tag remember, and then the second time
is gonna be this tag.
And so we can do things like find and get
just like we did with the in xml one
so running this is not too exciting.
Python three xml two dot py,
you see that there are two users
that comes from this print right here.
There are two users in
there and the first one
if we go into name and we go find the text
within the name tag within user
then we get Chuck and then we get the id
which is zero zero one, so we find the id
within that item and then we get the text.
And then we look and we grab
the x attribute off of that
and so we see Chuck
Chuck zero zero one and two
and then the next tag we
get a four loop continues
and we print that out, okay?
So that's just a basic run through
of the xml from the
chapter in the python book.
Okay? Thanks
(soothing piano music)