(ambient music)
- Hello everybody.
Welcome to Python for Everybody,
We're doing a bit of code walk through.
If you wanna follow along,
you can download the
zip file for the code,
from our website.
We are in the process of retrieving data
from this gmane server, one
that I've made a copy of.
And we have so far spider-ed it all,
ended up with 600 megabytes
of spider-ed information.
We have ran a rather
complex clean up process
that you probably don't
need to fully understand.
You can look at it for patterns,
but, in general, the clean up process
will be very sensitive to the data.
And then we have this index.sqlite,
which is 260 megabytes right now.
And we are going to now do a--
the easy, the fun, easy, bits here.
Where we're gonna run little queries
that just pull data out.
So these are much simpler.
So part of what I wrote
when I was doing this,
is I wanted to do some simple,
basic calculations on the data, to make--
I really was sort of looking
for anomalies, right?
What was working, what wasn't working.
So I wrote a series of
really simple things,
like this gbasic.
A gbasic code, just to give
me some basic data, right?
So I wrote things down,
and I counted things.
And so, do I need urllib
request in this one?
I don't think so.
Let's fix that bug, it's not there.
No reason to put any
of that stuff in there.
So, it just, it reads that index.sqlite,
which is our cleaned up data.
It reads through and makes it dictionary.
This pattern you're gonna see a lot,
where I'm gonna make a
dictionary of id to senders.
Save myself repeatedly looking at things.
I'm gonna grab the subjects,
I've cashed them all.
I could've done this all with sql,
but I just wanted to do things faster.
And now I'm gonna go through
each of these messages,
and make a dictionary of them.
Gonna put a lot of stuff in memory.
And then I'm going to do some counts.
I'm gonna see who has
sent the most, right?
The organizations, and so
now I've gotta re-go through
all the messages.
So you'll notice that I'm
not selecting the body,
or the headers here, I am
just getting sender id,
subject id, I probably
could've done this with a join,
it would have been cleaner.
You can do that, you can make that change.
Do that with a join so it's cleaner.
So I'm going through all the messages,
except not the bodies.
So this is going to be really quick.
And I'm pulling out the sender's id,
I'm breaking the sender into pieces.
See, my data's clean now.
I cleaned it all up in
the previous processes.
And if I don't have two pieces,
I continue, and I get the domain name.
So I have the person, I'm doing a basic
dictionary histogram for
the people and the domains.
And then I'm going to sort them.
Alright.
With a sorted.
And we're gonna grab the key,
we're gonna sort it by the
how many there are, reverse.
And then print out the top
few of the organizations,
and the top few of the people.
Kay, so we'll just run that code.
Python gbasic.py, P Y.
Let's type the, dump out the top 10.
So we loaded 59,000 messages,
29,000 subjects, and 1,800 senders.
And figured out the top 10 people,
and the top 10 organizations.
And you can write
various things like that,
that just sort of,
scream through your data,
and it's good to get sanity
checking on your data.
Okay, so that's gbasic.
Now I wanna do gword.py.
So that's kinda fun.
Gword.py, I don't need urllib,
why do I keep putting
urllib in all these things?
So we'll get rid of that.
So this is really simple
because I'm just gonna
go for the words and the subject line.
And so I go through index.sqlite,
I read in all of the subjects.
And I make a dictionary of those.
And then I go and find
all of the subjects.
And then I'm doing this code right here,
I'm pulling out the subject
based on the message.
And I'm doing this so
that when the subjects
are used more than once I
count the words more than once.
This str.maketrans,
I talked about that in a earlier chapter.
This basically throws away
punctuation and numbers,
so that when I make my words,
I don't end up with words
that are like dashes,
it compresses them down.
Then I strip it, I convert
everything to lowercase.
This is basically just to keep
too many words from showing
up, and I do a split.
And then I got a counts, a dictionary.
So this is a no punctuation,
no numbers, dictionary count.
And then I just take
the, and do a dictionary.
And then I sort them in reverse order.
And then I figure out what
the highest and lowest is,
by running through a--
I could have probably done
this with a max and a min,
if I felt like it.
And so now I have the
highest and the lowest.
You know, I should've done
a max and a min on that one.
Why'd I do that?
But oh well.
And now I've got to spread out the size,
and so I'm gonna produce
this file gword.js,
which is to needed by the visualization,
cause it's gonna use d3.js, a
word visualizer, and gword.js.
I have to tell it how big the text is,
and so I'm doing some text normalization,
took me a little experimentation.
So if I run this now, and
I say python gword.js.
And I say python3 gword.js,
which is a lot better.
Oh, not--
Python.
Okay, so now I can go
look at the gword.js,
wherever that is.
Gword.js, yep.
And so this is basically,
it normalized all the frequencies,
and made it font size,
these are font sizes now.
Okay, and so this is just
the data that's needed
by this gword.jm, which uses
this d3 visualization, word cloud code.
So this pulls in all my data,
and then this is just some java script
that draws the picture
in on the page, okay?
And so the easy part now is to just
open gword.htm in a browser,
it just so happens on
a Mac, I can do this.
And so that gives me a word
cloud based on that data.
And it kinda randomizes it,
it shows different stuff,
but it's using this.
It's using this data to generate
how big those things are,
and then using a bit of
randomness and simulating
the kneeling to lay it out.
That's not stuff that we
actually have to worry about.
Okay?
So that's how we get to the point
where we're seeing a word cloud from this.
Now we're gonna do another visualization.
And this time we're gonna
do a line visualization.
And we're gonna create
a thing called gline.js
and produce with another html file.
We're gonna use d3, and
produce that output.
So let's say goodbye here,
bye, goodbye, goodbye, goodbye.
So gline.py, get rid of that file.
So again, I'm gonna
preload all of the senders.
In this case, and again, I
could've done this with a join,
probably should have
done this with a join.
I'm going to preload all the messages.
The sender id, subject id, et cetera.
And I'll load those up.
And now I'm going to read through,
I'm going to have the sending
organizations and the senders.
And I'm going to split the senders,
and I'm gonna have the
sending organizations,
and then I'm going to
do a simple dictionary,
as I accumulate the sending organizations
by splitting the person's
name into "at" signs,
and then based on the organization,
I accumulate it.
And then I sort them,
and I pull out the top 10
organizations, print those out.
And now I'm going to
produce, break this down,
into months and I'll show
you what this looks like,
in a second.
Let's go to the gline.js.
So the month looks like this.
Okay, so the month looks like that,
so that's the first seven
characters of the date.
So if we look at the date.
The date looks like that,
and the month is the
first seven characters.
And this is the data
that I've gotta give it.
I'll clean that up in a second,
that data will look better in a moment.
Go back to gline.py, and so this is,
we're doing a, the key is a topple,
which is the month, and
which organization it is,
that did it.
And it's only in the
top ten organizations,
and then we're gonna do a,
we're going to basically do a dictionary,
where the key is a topple.
And then we're gonna sort it.
Sort by key in this case, not by value.
That's in the months,
it's gonna sort that.
And then we're going to
write all this data out
into gline.js.
So let's go ahead and run this,
and again, this is just the data
that has to be written in a way that
the Java Script can understand it.
Python gline, python3 giline.py.
Okay, so top 10 organizations.
So now let's take a
look at the java script.
So this is what it looks like.
So it just so happens
that you gotta tell it,
these are the data points,
these are the lines.
This is the year, the line
for University of Michigan,
gmail.com, swinsborg.com,
so this, this first
column is that line point.
So the next line points.
So all this code was to get the data,
in such a way that I could
produce this java script file.
Because, if I look at
gline.htm, I need that data.
In that particular format.
And I've got all this stuff,
I'll make a line chart.
And I draw with this data,
that data, I had to go
read all the documentation
on how to figure this stuff out.
Alright, and now that's the data
that I'm going to use.
And I had to figure this out,
and I can transform
it, and make it pretty.
It took me quite a while
to get this to work,
and this is not a Java Script class,
nor a "How to Visualize in d3",
but basically we pulled all that stuff in,
and there's the gline that
came from the Java Script,
and then it makes a arrayToDataTable,
and then that data table
is what gline draws.
So, with no further adieu,
let's open gline.htm to show that data.
So there you go.
That's the Sakai Developer Participation
from 2015 through 2000, uh,
2005 through 2015, based
on which organizations
did the most commits in Sakai.
And so I know that I
haven't done all this code
full justice, there's a lot of code here.
The fun is just to kinda
run it, and see it.
And then when the time comes,
to come back and see the techniques
that are used when you're trying
to build your own visualization pipeline.
So I hope that you found this useful.
You know, this is a lot of code,
hard to explain in 15-20 minutes,
but I hope you take some
time and look it over.
And I hope you found all these videos,
this is kinda the last walk-through video
for chapter 16 of the book.
And so I hope that I
will see you on the net.
(ambient music)