[MUSIC PLAYING]
So JSON is the world's best
loved data interchange format.
I discovered it in 2001.
I don't claim to have
invented it because it already
existed in nature.
I just saw it, recognized
the value of it,
and gave it a name
and description,
and showed its benefits,
but I did not invent it.
I don't claim to be the first
person to have discovered it.
There were other people
who, I later found out,
had come along the
same idea in 2000.
The earliest instance
I found of JavaScript
being used as a data interchange
format was at Netscape in 1996.
So it's an idea that's
been around for a while.
And if you look at other
data representations
like the property lists that
were used at NeXT, and then
later at Apple.
Except for a couple
of cosmetic changes,
it's the JSON notation as well.
So it seems like it's
an inevitable sort
of representation for
data, at least data
that is intended to be consumed
by programming languages.
And ultimately, that's all data.
I started with JavaScript
but my first application
was facilitating
communication between programs
written in JavaScript and
servers is written in Java.
So I recognize that even though
it was born out of JavaScript,
it could be and should
be language independent.
So I simplified it
as much as possible.
Took as much out, tried
to make the simplest
possible specification for how
to structure data and put it
on the wire.
And that ultimately
became called JSON.
In 2001, I was in a
company I had started
called State Software, and we
developed a platform for doing
applications which
could be delivered
through unmodified web browsers,
what today is called AJAX
But in 2001, that was
kind of a radical idea,
and not many people would
believe that was even possible,
or if it were, that
it was a good idea.
But we produced some
brilliant demonstrations
and we were starting
to make some progress
in trying to convince, you
know, potential customers
that they should adopt the style
of application development.
And as part of the
description, we'd say,
and then we use this JSON idea
for communicating the stuff
back and forth.
And they'd say
JSON, what's that?
It's this thing we
found in JavaScript
and it's really great.
And they'd say oh we can't use
that, we just committed to XML,
so no we can't.
But XML was wrong for
all of these reasons.
It's hugely expensive, much
harder to use, all that.
Well, we can't use
that thing you did
because it's not a standard.
I said, it is a standard.
It's a proper subset of ECMA
262, which is a standard.
They say no that--
that's not standard.
So I decided if I want to
be able to use this thing,
I need to make it a standard.
So I bought JSON.org
and put up a web page
and sort of declared
it's a standard.
That's it.
That's all I did.
I didn't go around trying
to convince industry
and government and
everybody that this
is what they should do.
I just put up a website.
Basically, a one page website.
And over the years, people
discovered it and realized,
oh yeah, this is so much easier.
I'm just going to do that.
I
The thing I never
understood about XML
for data interchange,
OK so basic-- generally,
the pattern is
you've got a query,
you send it to the server,
it gives it to the database,
and you get back this
XML thing, but then you
have to send queries
to that in order
to get the data out of it.
Why can't you just
give it to me in a form
where I know what it is and
I can use it immediately.
And so that was the main
benefit of JSON, I think.
It wasn't that curly
braces are so much
better than angle brackets.
I mean ultimately
none of that matters.
The thing that mattered was that
the data structures that JSON
likes to represent are
exactly the same data
structures that programming
languages represent.
You know when Ajax was
formulated, the X in AJAX
was supposed to be for XML,
and the smart kids right away
realized, well this is too hard.
We don't want to
be doing XML here.
And some of them discovered hey,
you can use JSON here instead.
And It is so much
easier, so much faster.
So they started doing that and
for while, there was a debate.
Some people were arguing
Jesse James Garrett
said the X stands for XML.
So you can't use
anything but XML.
That didn't last very long.
There were a number of
other alternatives to XML
that were being considered
around those times,
but JSON was the only one
that was designed specifically
for AJAX.
Probably the boldest
design decision
I made in designing JSON was to
not put a version number on it.
So there is no mechanism
for revising it.
So JSON, we're stuck with it.
Whatever it is in its
current form, that's it.
And that turns out to be
it's best feature because it
wants to be a low level thing.
In its basic infrastructure,
its the thing
that you pile
everything else on.
And it's sort of the equivalent
of alphabet in a language.
And we might make
up lots of words
in lots of ways of
having sentences,
but it's very uncommon
to make up new letters.
And that's sort of the
place where JSON lives.
So it's good that it's
not going to change.
I expect maybe
someday, we'll find
that there are really important
things that JSON doesn't
do like cyclical structures.
Graphs are not easily
represented in JSON.
They can be, but it requires
a level of interaction,
a little bit more work.
Someday, we might decide we
don't want to do that work
and then we replace JSON
with something else.
We will not extend
JSON to do that.
We will replace JSON.
And even after we
do that replacement,
everything that was ever
developed that still uses JSON
will still work because
JSON will never change.
[MUSIC PLAYING]