Hi, I'm Arnold from
Manila in the Philippines.
And I'm first got
into MOOCs because I
wanted to learn some
college-level math--
specifically probability, linear
algebra, calculus, statistics,
that kind of thing.
It's true that a MOOC
class can't replace
a class in a real
college, but in my case
I already have a
college education
and I'm actually using MOOCs
to fill in the gaps left behind
by my very qualitative degree
in the social sciences.
Along the way, I discovered
IHDS, which looked interesting,
and it was interesting.
It was basic enough for
me to be able to learn
a little bit about
computers and the internet,
and it was actually
interesting enough
for me to want to take a
course in programming Python
afterwards.
That was six months ago.
In a span of six months, I
think I've come pretty far.
I've learned enough to be
able to attend my local Python
conference and be able to
follow along with what everyone
was talking about.
These are all computer science
graduates are professionals,
and I consider it an achievement
that in the span of six months
I could go there and be
able to mix with the crowd.
MOOCs to me are an investment.
I'm taking a lot of them right
now, math and computer science
and programming.
I actually left my job two
months ago to focus on MOOCs,
and that's because
it's actually hoping
to make a little bit
of a career change.
Well, more of a shift
in career trajectory
towards more quantitatively
oriented side of things.
I actually hope to work
in the development sector.
I admire the work of
organizations like the Abdul
Latif Jameel Poverty Action Lab,
those randomized control trials
in developing countries to see
the impact of social programs.
And I think it's fair to say
that without MOOCs I wouldn't
have had the opportunity
to learn to kind
of quantitative skills
I need to even consider
working in a setting like that.
So that's my story.