The service-oriented approach
to linking software systems
and applications is transforming
the way many organizations
share data.
This approach improves
existing methods
of data sharing by providing a
service layer between systems.
Sharing data
between applications
is a well-established principle
that works on a simple level.
As systems expand,
the solution that
connects two
software applications
will often not work for a third.
What began as a
workable system then
locks valuable data in a silo.
Sharing the data is still
possible but requires
adaptations and tweaks.
The process is laborious
and time-consuming,
leading to bottlenecks
and overload.
The reality of this world is
unnecessary effort expended
in duplication of data.
By applying a service
layer to the applications
you wish to connect
up, data is offered out
in a common format
for reuse elsewhere.
The service-oriented approach
works with existing software
systems and does not
require you to remove
the monolithic application.
Placement applications
reuse the links already
made and can plug
into the service layer
without affecting
other users of data.
New applications can be
added to grow overall system
architectures in the same way.
The data in each
application is offered up
as a service, which any other
application can consume.
When the
service-oriented approach
has evolved into a
system-wide architecture,
it allows connections and
service sharing opportunities
between organizations
nationally and globally.
Take monitoring of student
progress, for example.
Results are locked by a
virtual learning environment,
but how much of that data is
shared with the management
system that is tracking
progression against funding?
If the motivation and commitment
of struggling students
is not addressed, and
they decide to walk away,
there is a direct
impact on funding.
If the data is freed up and
shared across a system using
a service-oriented
approach, it could
contribute to retaining
student motivation,
and thereby maximizing income.
And what if across the
education community
there was one standard
and agreed way
to describe a course?
It would allow
course information
to be made available
as a consumable service
both internally and externally.
This is the subject of
a current project called
exchanging course-related
information,
or XCII, encompassing course
marketing, quality assurance,
enrollment, and
reporting requirements.
This service-oriented
approach enables
aggregated organizations like
UCast to gather the standard
and agreed descriptions of
courses from each provider.
Comprehensive details
of approved enrollment
opportunities are then returned
to a prospective student
for easy and
accurate comparison.
Amongst the research community,
it is the same principle.
Here, the
service-oriented approach
is enabling researchers to
work across institutions
in virtual organizations.
myGrid is a project that
provides a shared tool
kit for creating experiments
by coordinating the information
flow between distributed
resources and services.
Workflows and query
specifications
link together remote
and local resources
using web service protocols.
Workflows created
by myGrid represent
the scientific process of
the experiments they enact,
making them a rich resource
for scientists creating
their own new experiments.
The service lab to
this data enables
users to share, reuse,
and repurpose experiments
within the myGrid community.
Many education and
research services
are already developing a
service-oriented approach,
taking their lead from
the business world
and major software developers.
It is in this context
that the e-Framework,
a successful and expanding
international initiative,
works to make sense of the
service-oriented approach
for the education and
research community.
The e-Framework website
identifies and describes
the service components needed.
It provides the blueprints
and reference examples
for those in the community
who want to gain a greater
understanding and knowledge
of how to implement
a service-oriented approach.
The e-Framework website is
thus becoming a knowledge base
that is developing
a shared vocabulary
and way of thinking for all
in education and research.