Hello.
Welcome to running Python
programs with TextWrangler
on the Macintosh.
So, I'm here on Google and
I've typed TextWrangler
and I can just go to the
TextWrangler website.
And we're going to
download TextWrangler.
and we're playing
with usability.
I guess we've got a nice
little download button here;
download now.
OK, so we're going to download.
Right there.
That made that work.
So here we come.
OK, so now it's downloaded
and is mounting up the image.
And so I'll come
over here and all
we do is we drag the
TextWrangler into applications.
And then since I'm not a
super user on this account,
I have to authenticate,
which means
I have to type an
account and a password.
And I've already done
this once, and so I'm not
going to bother copying it.
So we'll cancel this.
But it will copy
in and then you'll
have TextWrangler installed.
And I can close
all these windows.
And you have TextWrangler.
And I'm going to unmount
this TextWrangler drive.
So I have a nice clean desktop.
So I want to run TextWrangler.
And the easiest way is to
start in with Spotlight
and do TextWrangler and click on
TextWrangler when it comes up.
And so it's going to ask me
a few questions when we first
start out.
And it's got this cool
little window here,
which I'm going to close.
That shows us recently
opened documents.
And so I'm going to write
some Python code here.
And I'm going to say
print hello world.
Oops.
I want to say hello world.
And I'm going to save this
by saying File save as
and I'm going to instead of
going straight to my desktop,
you might have to push this
little button to see these,
I'm going to make a
folder called assign0.
And then inside
assign0 I'm going
to name my file firstprog.py.
Now you'll notice that this
assign0 appeared as soon
as I made it in the
desktop, because this folder
desktop under places is
the same as my desktop.
So now I'm going
to save my file.
And so you'll
notice that it does
what's called syntax coloring.
And shows me the fact that
it's now got a double quoted
string in Hello world.
So now I'm going to run Python.
Now there's a couple
ways to do it.
First I'll show you the
built in one in TextWrangler.
You go up to here,
pound exclamation
and say run in terminal.
And this will
start up a terminal
and then run the Python
command interpreter and feed it
our program.
So we say run in terminal.
And so there's some stuff here.
This is just sort
of cruddy overhead.
But right here it basically
is my output for my program.
And it says, oh, in the
file users demo desktop,
we've got a syntax error
on line one, hello world.
Invalid syntax.
Now it doesn't tell
us much about how
we might fix this showing
just how not clever Python is,
but it certainly knows
it we've made a mistake.
But we know it's in line
one so let's go back
and take a little more
closer, we meant to say print.
So I forgot the t.
So let's go ahead and say t.
And we'll save it.
I didn't mean to lock it.
I'll just save it.
File, save.
And then I'll run
it in Python again.
Run in terminal.
And then I see my
little Python output.
So you've got to realize that
everything other than this bit
here is the Python output.
And I can make changes.
I close each time.
Hello there world.
Oops.
And I will use a shortcut.
Now this command ask.
There's little apple symbol.
Apple s will save it.
So I'm not going to
actually save it.
I'm just going to save
it with Command s.
And then I'm going to run it.
Oops, I didn't mean
to run a debugger.
No I do not want to do that.
Close.
Die.
Again, I'm going to
run it in terminal.
And then away we go.
And you'll see that my
program has changed.
And so we can see that
I can run this program
and change it over and over.
Now after a while this
will get kind of tiring.
I'll hide the terminal.
Get rid of it.
And especially when you need
to be in a particular directory
and if you're opening
files, and so you're
going to want to run
the terminal by hand
and learn a few
terminal commands.
And so I'm going
to type terminal.
Terminal is, we've
actually been using this
but now I'm going to
open a separate one.
And now I'm at this
command prompt where
I can type commands.
Let me make that a
little bit bigger.
So you can see it better.
And one of the commands
is ls, which stands for;
I don't know, list all
my files or something.
In Windows this'd be
Derby, but in Unix it's ls.
And one of the
folders that I see
is the desktop folder there.
So I'm going to say cd desktop.
And then I'm going to say ls.
And you'll see that I have
effectively this little
folder I've got
there, is shown as one
of the folders in
my desktop folder.
So it's a subfolder.
So I'm going to go into a SS,
and zero, and do another ls.
If you're wondering
where you're at you
can always type this
command PWD, which stands
for print working directory.
So I'm in the main hard drive
under users, demo, desktop,
assign0.
And then within assign0, I've
got one file; firstprog.py.
If I want a little more
detail, I add minus l to my ls.
And it can tell me that
it's a file, how big it
is, when it was created etc.
Now if want to run this, I
simply type the command Python
firstprog.py.
And Python says start
the Python interpreter
and then feed it firstprog.py.
And then Python runs my little
program and gives me output.
Now a couple of shortcuts.
First shortcut.
Hit the up arrow,
and you can hit
the up arrow a couple of times.
You can hit it couple times.
I'm hitting up arrow,
then I'll hit down arrow.
I can run previous commands.
OK?
I can also type part of a
file name like Python fur
and then hit Tab,
and it actually
auto completes because
it knows the file name.
It looks at the file
name and says oh, fur
is the beginning of,
there's only one file
that begins with fur so
I'll finish it for you.
And so the command
line is pretty easy.
So if you want to
make a change, you
can just have the command line
sitting there in one window,
and make a change.
And I'm going to just
hit Command s to save it.
And then I'm going to
come here and hit up arrow
and I'm going to hit enter.
So now I can make a mistake,
like a syntax error.
I can hit Command s to save it.
And I can go over here in an
up arrow and run it again.
And it tells me whoa, line
two you've got a syntax error.
And then I'll go ahead and
fix this, print, sorry.
And so now I've got valid
Python and if I hit up
arrow, hit Enter.
It says two lines; print, sorry.
Now you'll also
notice that it's doing
what's called syntax coloring.
It's showing us what part's
key words, what part's not
a key word.
And I don't know if
you noticed but when
I had the mistake it was
black because blue means
it's a Python keyword,
print is just text
so it doesn't really know
what we meant by that.
And then when I get the
syntax right turns blue.
It's not really
critical, it just
helps you understand
what's going on.
Syntax coloring
gives you good clues.
You can see what line you're on.
Down here in the lower left
hand corner, what line your on,
what column your in.
And that can actually help you
as you look at syntax errors
when it tells you, ah.
The syntax error is on line two.
So that gives you a good
start using, downloading,
and installing,
text edit and using
it to do Python on Macintosh.
Thank you.