Most of the skills
that companies
are looking to hire for, they
don't actually even teach
you in college these days.
One Month is an online
learning platform
with a very simple idea.
What if you could learn
anything in one month?
I tried to learn how to
code using online resources,
and I found that almost all
of the resources I found
were so complicated and were
just not made for beginners.
So One Month it's a simple
approach to that problem.
Every single month you
can decide, what do I
want to tackle this month.
How do I want to
level myself up?
So right now you can
learn how to code.
You can learn growth
hacking, content marketing,
web security.
You can learn how to
build mobile apps.
And that's just beginning.
We're constantly
releasing new classes
based on what the
students are asking for.
One Month is about
real results that
will impact your career,
your skills, your abilities,
your future.