Hello and welcome to yet another
worked exercise for Python
for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
I'm Charles Severance.
I am your tour guide to this
particular worked example.
And this material is
Creative Commons attribution.
And I hope to see the
clever and cool things
that you can do with it.
This is part of my
www.PythonLearn.com website
that helps you to learn Python,
from the very beginning,
with videos and other
materials to help you go along
with the book.
Of course, the book is
Creative Commons attribution.
So pretty much everything
here is free for you
to use and adapt as you see fit.
So we're taking a sort
of a working example
from the tuples chapter.
And the task that we're given
is find the 10 most common words
in a file.
And we will do that.
So if we take a look at the
basic overall structure,
we're going to read a file.
We're going to
make a dictionary--
an empty dictionary--
and we're going
to read the file line by line.
We're going to split each line.
Then we're going to
loop through the line,
using the dictionary pattern
from the dictionaries chapter
using get, so that
we can both access
and initialize new words that we
haven't seen at the same time.
And then we need to sort.
But we need to sort by the
value instead of the key.
So we're going to make a list.
And then we're going to
loop through the results
of the dictionary.
And we're going to
make a new tuple.
But instead of being
key-value-- which
is what you get from items--
we're going to do value-key.
And then we'll sort
that in reverse order.
And then we'll simply print
the first 10 elements of that
sorted in reverse order.
And because we're constructing
carefully this new tuple--
value-key-- in the
right order, value
will be what's sorted on first.
And then in cases where value
matches, it will sort on key.
Whereas if we just took items--
which is key-value tuples--
then it would sort on the key.
And that's quite easy.
So that's the basic idea.
So let's go ahead
and get started.
So I'm going to
grab some of this
and save myself a little bit
of time and paste that in.
I'm going to use
actually romeo-short,
because I don't want
to mess with-- romeo
has punctuation in it.
So I'll call this under tuples.
I'm going to call
this guy, topten.py.
And see if it's in
my tuples folder.
Yup.
Just always sanity checking.
So let's go ahead to PythonLearn
and grab that romeo-short file.
So I'm going to
grab romeo-short.
If I look at romeo--
romeo-short conveniently
has the-- or just
romeo conveniently
has the punctuation
moved, and it's small.
So we can do debugging.
Romeo-full is a little harder.
And I cover that in the
book in some more detail
to get rid of
punctuation and stuff.
Not too bad.
But we won't talk about here.
So I'm going to grab romeo.txt.
And I'll save this to my
tuples folder as romeo.txt.
And I should be done that now.
And I'm done with that.
So if I take a look
at tuples again,
I've got romeo.txt in
this file, topten.py.
And it's not romeo.
It's romeo.txt.
And I'm just going to split.
And I hope by now you can
read a text file and split it
into words and count those
words in a dictionary.
So I'm just going to print
out the dictionary, the counts
dictionary that
we've got at the end.
And let's see how that works.
So I'll go onto my desktop.
And this is under tuples.
And so there's
romeo.txt and topten.py.
So let's go ahead
and run topten.py.
And so there we go.
We have just sort
of roared through,
broken into words,
broken into lines.
We have a nice, convenient,
little thing here.
Now, you know what?
I'm going to do one thing
that's not in the example.
The fact that these
are upper case-- I
don't know if it's going
to cause a problem or not.
This bothers me.
And so I'm going to force all
the words to be lowercase.
And so I'm going to call--
I'm going to make a thing,
word equals word dot lower.
I think it's lower.
We'll find out fast enough.
So I'm going to just grab
a lowercase version of word
and make it be W-R-D.
And that's what
I'm going to put
into my dictionary.
So let me run this again.
See if I got it right.
Yeah.
So now we see things
like "who" is lowercase.
I don't think it changed
any of the numbers.
It may have.
But I think we shouldn't
treat uppercase--
we should make this
case insensitive,
so we'll map everything
to lowercase.
So I just did that by
mapping it to lower
and then using W-R-D instead
of word after I made a copy.
So here we go.
So then what I'm going to
do is I've got my counts.
And I'm going to print
the results of the items.
So that gives us a list.
Instead of just showing it,
it gives us a list of tuples.
So there's a tuple.
It's a two item tuple.
Tuple.
And it's key-value pairs.
And this is useful
now, in particular
because we can construct a
for loop that goes through.
For kie, vaal-- key and value.
Kie, vaal equals-- I'm sorry.
In count dot items.
I get all confused
trying to create
really non-numonic variables.
So we got kie and vaal.
And it's two
iteration variables.
And the way it works
is these will iterate
through each tuple--
tuple, tuple-- and then kie
will be the first thing in
a tuple-- which is the key--
and the value will be the
second thing in the tuple.
Kie, vaal.
And so kie will bounce
through these at the same time
as vaal's going to bounce
to the corresponding values.
So that's quite nice.
I always love sanity
checks, so I'm
going to print out kie and vaal.
Just print them out.
Yeah, something's wrong.
Kie, vaal, and-- oh.
Counts.
So here we go.
Trace back.
Line 11.
The name count is not defined.
I was so quick, I didn't
even read what it told me.
So look at line 11.
Go down to line 11.
And then I forgot my S.
Once you get used to this,
it's pretty much telling
me what it wants to do.
So now I'm going
through my tuples.
Here's my tuples.
And now I'm going through
the tuples one at a time,
just dumping them out in
a loop, and away we go.
Now, the whole problem is is
we want to make a new tuple.
And I'm going to
call this newtup.
Newtup.
And I'm going to
create a tuple--
and I can do this by
just putting these two
things in parentheses-- except
that I want vaal first, and kie
second.
So I want vaal first
and kie second.
And so now I'm going
to print out newtup.
Now you'll see that as
I will loop through each
of the key-value pairs, I'm
just making a new tuple where
they're reversed, where
the value is first
and the key is second.
All right.
So value-key.
Value-key.
And now I'm going to
stick this in a list.
And I'm going to
call my list flipped.
And I'm going to say,
give me an empty list.
So I'm starting an empty
list called flipped.
And I am going to tell
flipped to append to itself--
so now I'm extending
this list each time
through the loop-- take that
newtup that I just made.
So we got newtup.
And I'll take my
print statement out,
because that'll be obvious.
So I'm going to append newtup
to the end of my flipped list.
And then I'll print at the
end of this print flipped.
So I make a tuple, and
instead of printing it,
I just append it to this list.
And then I print the
whole list out afterwards.
This is a little messy,
but here is the first list.
It's got key-value.
And here's the second list.
It's the exact same list as
before, except it's value-key.
Now it's the exact same list.
We didn't take anything out.
We didn't add anything.
We didn't sum anything.
We didn't do anything.
So then what is it that we're
going to do with this list?
Well, we can use the totally--
well, we could use sorted,
but we're not going to do that.
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to say, I want
to take that flipped list,
and I want to sort it.
Sort.
And then print flipped.
Just sort it.
Now the key is sorting.
The awesomeness of
sorting is that sorting
is done by repeated comparison.
And it's comparing this
tuple to this tuple.
But the rules of
tuple comparison
is it first checks
the first pair,
and then it checks
the second pair.
It only checks the second
pair if the first pair
doesn't match.
So 3, 1 doesn't match.
And so it sorts it
based on the 3 and the 1
without even looking.
But then when there
is two 3's that match,
it actually does check
the second two words.
So 3, "and" will sort.
The "and" and the
"the" will decide
where the 3, "and" and
the 3, "the" tuples
end up sorting, if
that makes any sense.
So let's just print this out.
Actually let's print flipped.
Not clipped.
We could make a
clipped one too later.
And I'm actually going
to get rid of this print.
So it's going to print
flipped before and after.
So watch this.
So here's flipped before.
It's been sorted,
in whatever order
it was in the dictionary
in the first place.
And now here's flipped
in the final order.
And you see that it's in
sort of reverse order,
where 3, "and," "is," and
"the" are here at the end.
The ones are in alphabetical
order within the ones,
because tuples check--
oops, don't do that.
Don't do that.
That was nasty.
Ah, and that was nasty.
That's because I was
copying and pasting.
So within all the
ones, it actually
sorted based on the alphabetic
sort of the second parameter
or the second item in the tuple.
Whereas the twos
all sorted later.
So this actually isn't
quite what I wanted.
And so I'm going to say,
reverse equals true.
Because I actually want it
sorted so the big numbers
are at the front.
So let's run that little bit.
So check that, right?
So now I got my same sort.
It's got the unsorted--
now it's got the sorted.
But the big numbers
are at the beginning.
You'll notice it's in
reverse alphabetical order,
because the big words are at
the beginning among the threes.
But, eh, whatever.
We're close enough
for government work.
So now I want to
print out the top 10.
Oops.
I did that again.
I want to print out the top 10.
I'll just do the top five.
Top five.
So I could do something simple.
We'll get rid of this.
We trust that it's
now properly sorted.
I could say, print this list
up to but not including five,
by using list slicing.
So there we go.
There's the top five.
But that looks kind of ugly.
Maybe it does.
Maybe it doesn't.
So I'm going to write
a super cool for loop.
But again, simple, right?
Just for me to
check it, I can say,
print the first five of flipped.
This little list
slicing is a great way
if you're using a lot of data
to keep your data from being
totally insane.
So I'm going to
write a for loop.
For key and value in, flipped.
So I'm going to say, only
go through the first five.
So this loop will only
run for the first five.
Just like this only
prints the first five,
this is going to iterate
only through the first five.
And key and value will go
through the keys and values
of these first five.
3, "the."
Key-value.
3, "is."
And now I'm just going to print
a sweet, cool message out.
And I'm just printing completely
insane, partially mnemonic
things.
So I print out my top
five keys and values.
So let's take a look at that.
Let's go ahead
and run that baby.
Winner, 3 is "the."
3, "is."
3, "and."
So we saw five of these things.
Five of them.
And we're seeing the
key and the value.
It would probably be more
easily read if I just did that.
So 3, "the."
3, "is."
Those are the top five
words in my little program.
So let's take a look
at this and review.
We open the file.
We make an empty dictionary.
We do our standard file
loop, splitting each line.
New lines are kind of
chomped up in the split,
so we don't have to
worry too much about it.
We looped through the words.
We changed it to make it
go lowercase for each word.
We used the get pattern to both
initialize new words to one
and add one to existing words,
by using this awesome get-ness.
Now we want to flip.
We want to flip the
order in each tuple.
We want to make the tuples
from key-value tuples-- which
we get from items--
to value-key tuples.
We append each of
those tuples to a list.
Then with the tuples that have
the vaal and the kie in them--
I can't write with
this very well--
we sort them in reverse order.
But the vaal is going to
be the most important thing
it gets sorted on, because
it's the leftmost thing
in the tuple.
And then we simply
print out the last five.
Or the top five of this
tuples after the sort.
And so that, pretty simple.
Print out the top five words,
in this particular file.
OK?
Simple enough.
Thanks a lot and see you--