Welcome to our worked exercise.
This is Dr. Charles Severence
and worked exercises
from Python for Informatics.
This material copyright Creative
Commons attribution 3.0.
And if you need basic guidance
on how to install Python or use
a text editor in general or
how to use the command line,
stuff that we'll be
using in this exercise,
go back to
pythonlearn.com and work
through the
introductory materials.
So here's our exercise.
We're supposed to
rewrite our pay program.
And we're going to use try
and except in this situation
so we can handle non
numeric input gracefully.
And we're supposed to print
out an error if there's
any non numeric input
and otherwise print out
the right thing.
So let's get started.
Let's go ahead and
start Text Wrangler.
And start terminal program.
And make it a little smaller.
Move it to the bottom.
Make this a little smaller.
Get rid of the-- So I'm going
to start with the program
that I've already got written.
And so I'll open the last one
I worked with, which is hours2.
And I'm going to save
this quickly as hours3.
We programmers do
this all the time.
I mean, why waste typing if
i just got done typing it?
There we go.
That's why these
exercises build on it
so you get used to this notion
of just kind of hack and code
that you had before.
OK, so I'll put the print
of rate and hours back in.
This part from here
down is pretty safe.
So I'll go into my desktop, go
into Python for Informatics,
and say python hours3.
And I'll say 40,
10-- super duper.
And I say glug, glug, crash.
So where is it blowing up?
Well it's blowing
up on the float.
So the float is the
dangerous thing.
And this is-- this float is
the dangerous thing too, right?
And so this is where
it's going to blow up.
And now because of this, the
rest of the program hasn't run.
And this is exactly
the situation
we're going to use a
try and except for.
OK, so let's do try.
And we're going to
just-- we're going to use
a sledgehammer on this one.
We're going to put all four
of these statements in a try
block.
But only two of the
statements are in some danger.
And in a second, I'll
show you what can go wrong
with this approach.
But for now, we're
in the beginning.
It'd be E-X-C-E-P-T colon.
And this is where we
put our error message,
where we go to print, and
what we're supposed to print.
Let's just kind of steal that.
Error, error-- please
enter a numeric input.
So I just cut and paste that.
So now we take an insurance out.
If everything goes well,
this except is ignored.
If anything goes
wrong, and really it's
going to be the floats--
one of the two floats
is going to go
wrong-- away it goes.
So let's go ahead and run this.
Make this a little bigger.
And I will save it.
OK, python hours3.
Let's do it right first.
Looking good-- now
let's do it wrong.
Now, I typed in a bad number.
And it said, error, please
enter numeric input.
But then blew up--
trace back to line nine.
This is line nine right here.
Oops-- well, that's because
I didn't tell it to stop.
It just kept on going, right?
And so there's a couple
ways we can solve this.
We could solve it cleanly.
But I'm just going to
be crude at this point.
And I'm going to put all
this stuff in the except.
Because that way-- oops-- if it
dies, it's going to run this.
And then the program's
going to be done.
And if it succeeds, it's
going to fall through.
And it's only going to do this
code if that other code worked.
And I will show you in
a moment the fallacy
and why this isn't the best way.
But this is crude
but effect, right?
We're early on so.
So all we have to do
is find a solution.
You bet we'll talk about
what the better solution is.
So here we go-- python hours3.
So we type Fred.
Kaboom, it dies.
So it died on this
line right here.
And then it transferred to
the except and ran this.
And the program was over.
And if we go give a good
one and then something bad,
this line dies and
then it continues on.
So let me show you a
couple of fallacies
or some mistakes in this.
So watch this.
I'm going to make
a mistake here.
Print-- I'll say print r,h.
So I'll print r,h.
So I'll type python
hours 40 10-- error,
please enter numeric input.
So what in the
heck was happening?
It's like, it is numeric input.
Where did it die?
So what-- I'll tell you what.
I'll just show you
what happened here.
We won't worry too
much about this.
It came into the try.
It did this.
The 40 is good, so that worked.
The rate is good,
so that worked.
What worked was,
r is not defined.
But it turns out that
this is another error.
It's just a different error.
It's not the same as this one.
And we just didn't
type it right.
And so it jumps to the except.
It doesn't do any of this code,
but it jumps to the except.
So that's why-- it
was numeric input.
But away we go, OK?
So that's not so good.
You don't really want to put
too much code inside your try
and except.
So let's take a look and do
this one a little better.
I'm going to cut this back out.
I'll move it down to
the bottom and now I've
got to deindent it.
I'll fix this rate and hours.
Deindent-- I didn't
get my indents right.
OK, so now my indents are right.
So let me go ahead and
run the program just
to make sure I'm not crazy.
40, 10-- that's good.
50, 10-- that's good.
So I'm good.
OK, so the problem now is I've
reintroduced my error that if I
give it a bad thing--
OK, so let's take a look
at the kinds of
things that we can
do to make this a
little more elegant.
So we're right here.
This is the problem.
We need to stop.
We don't want to
continue at this point.
If there was the thing that
we could say, just stop here.
If there was such a thing
in Python, we'd be fine.
But that would be
bad Python syntax.
But there is such
a thing in Python.
If you want to quit your
program, you type quit.
It's a function.
We haven't covered
functions yet.
We will soon.
It's a function that
never comes back.
Most functions come back.
But the quit function
does not come back.
So when it comes down
here and it prints this,
the next thing-- and
that doesn't continue.
So this is a way of
saying we are done.
So now let's run this and
put in some bad information.
And it indeed quits.
And so it doesn't
continue down here.
Let's make sure it
works with good data.
Oh, four hours-- well, OK.
I guess that's right.
So let me comment out my
debug print statement here
and finish it up.
We're going to run
it one last time.
Error, please numeric
input-- good hours, bad rate.
That's good.
And good hours, good
rate, and that's good.
So we've accomplished this one.