Hello and welcome to yet another
worked exercise for Python
for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
I am your exercise
worker, Charles Severance.
I'm the author of the book.
And as always, this
material, as well as the book
itself, is Creative
Commons Attribution.
So this exercise assumes
that you sort of know
how to edit files and
have things set up.
If you need more help go to
www.pythonlearn.com and go
through the
installation process.
So the exercise we're
contemplating right now
is exercise 5.1.
We're going to read a
list of numbers and deal
with some bad data, and
ultimately compute the average
and finish when we're done.
And so we're going to do this
stepwise like we always do.
We're not going to just
write this and try to imagine
what the ultimate thing is.
So the first thing that
I'm going to try to write
is-- so the first thing that
is the enter a number, convert
the number to a floating point,
and then print it out.
Just [INAUDIBLE].
So let's go ahead and
get started on that.
Keep a copy of that.
I've got a nice
copy on paper here.
I'll refer back to
my specifications.
So here I have Text Wrangler up.
I will go into my desktop.
I've got this folder called
Python for Informatics here.
So I'll go on my desktop.
Desktop.
cd Python for Informatics.
I do an ls and there's the
sum of the other exercises
that I played with before.
So I'm going to make a new file.
I'll just say print hello.
Just I always start this way.
It's how I do it.
Save as.
I'm just making sure.
It looks like I'm
in the right folder.
And I'll call this
one numlist.py.
If all goes well, you'll
notice that now it
has python suffix
it's properly colored.
And son of a gun, if I'm not
in the correct directory.
So let's go ahead
and run this thing.
numlist.py hello.
So it's good stuff.
I'll make this a little smaller.
So there we go.
So let's get started.
So instead of saying hello,
I'm going to just say--
I'm going to get a
string variable inp,
and say raw input,
enter a number, colon.
And then I'm going
to add a space just
to make it look a
little prettier.
Then I'm going to Convert that
to a floating point number.
I'll call this thing
num and I'll call float,
because int is a string.
And I want floating point
number so I can add them up.
And I'm just going to print num
out just to sort of be cool.
So on my Mac I use
Command S instead
of all the clicky stuff.
So Command S. In my
terminal I hit up arrow,
so I can run it again.
Enter a number.
789.
That's looking pretty good.
Enter a number.
That's looking pretty
bad, but, frankly,
that's exactly what
we would expect.
If we're going to
type garbage in,
we're going to get a trace back.
We'll deal one out in a minute.
OK, so.
So it looks like that
part's pretty cool.
So our problem now is we
want to take this-- let's put
that back in.
Let's put this in a loop.
So how do we make a loop?
Well, I'll just make an
infinite loop for now.
And I'm going to indent
these four spaces.
Make sure you have tabs
turned into spaces,
or you'll just be--
And so I'm going
to write this loop.
Right now I'm writing
an infinite loop
because it's always
going to be true.
So let's go ahead
and save this one.
Python numlist.py.
123, 456, collect
another number.
Now we're supposed to
be able to type done.
Well, our program ended
because the float crashed.
The float crashed on line
three, and so at least we
killed our program.
Because we wrote
an infinite loop.
It would have been prompting
us for numbers forever.
It would have never been done.
So the next thing we're
going to need to do
is we're going to need
to get out of the loop.
OK?
So I'm going to
get out of the loop
by checking to see if inp
is equal to done, break.
So that just basically says
if the input the user types,
I'm going to break out.
So let's run this again.
123.
Done.
Now, at least it runs.
And it gets out of the loop.
The break comes down here.
[INAUDIBLE] just pretty good.
Let me just add a quick feature
to this not specification list.
We'll see if we get in
trouble for this one.
I'm going to say if len of
inp is less than one, break.
This is actually kind
of an idiom here.
Check for empty line.
It's a bit of an idiom.
So basically maybe the
poor user would not
think to type done because they
didn't read the specifications.
So we'll save that one.
And you'll see now that
I can just hit Enter key,
and it sees that
as done as well.
And that's probably a
more clever way to do it,
and a more user
friendly way to do it.
Or maybe it's a violation
of the specifications,
but we're just going
to treat that as vague.
We'll leave it in there for now.
But that's kind
of a Python idiom,
that ending on an empty line.
Just because it's
natural for the user
to just hit enter and think
is this thing going to stop.
OK, so now our
problem is, is we've
got to count these things.
So we've got this loop body, and
it's running a bunch of times.
And we want to count
how many times it runs.
So we'll make a variable
called count, set to 0.
And then each time
we count through,
we're going to add count
equals count plus 1.
Now, I did not put
the count here.
And that's because I only want
to count the numbers that I've
actually read.
So I've read a number.
Because if I increment my
count here, and I break,
it'll be one too many.
Well, let's just go ahead and
do that-- just say count equals
and make that mistake.
So I'm going to get rid of this.
And I'll put it here, exactly
where I say don't count here.
All right?
So I'm going to count here.
And this is a bad
place to count.
So I'm going to save that.
And this loop is going
to go until it's done,
and then it's going to print
out how many numbers we've got.
So you see here
it's got a mistake.
It's not a syntax error,
it's a logic error.
Because we've got
to count up to 3.
But that's because the last time
through the code-- count was 0.
We read a number.
We added 1 to the count.
Read another number.
Added 1 to the count.
And then we wrote
another bad number,
we added a number the count.
And then we end up
with this break.
So the account is
wrong, basically.
OK?
And so the key is
that we got to move--
you got to move the count down.
We only want to
count valid data.
We don't want to
count invalid data.
So what we were doing is we were
counting the last non data bit.
So that's just another
thing to look for.
The pattern here
is read your data,
decide if you've got bad data
or good data or you want to stop
or whatever, and
then do the work.
So I'll put a comment in
here called do the work.
So this is the work.
And this is kind of--
handle the edge cases.
And this is get the data,
handle the edge cases,
then do the work.
And incrementing count
is just part of the work.
OK?
So let's keep going.
Now we've got to
make our average.
So average of course
means the total.
And that's pretty
easy because we
want to-- so total
equals total plus num.
Simple enough.
So I'm going to print out
num, total, and count.
So now 12, 14-- so you see our
number is 12, our total is 12,
and our count's 1.
Number's 14, total 26, count 2.
Looking pretty good.
Let's just hit enter,
and count is 2.
So we got count.
So let's change this to be what
we're supposed to change to,
say average.
Colon.
No space because the
comma adds a space.
And we're going to just
say total over count.
So let's run that.
Write 10, 11, 10.5.
So our numbers are working.
So we're getting pretty close.
We really have one
more problem to solve.
And that is that
problem-- the problem
when we got crappy data.
And we don't want to use
trace back as our mechanism.
We just want to
reprompt the user.
So the key thing
when you're dealing
with this, is the first
thing to take a look at
is the actual line question--
the line that caused the error.
The line that caused
the error is line 11.
And it's this line right here.
So we can't control
what the user types.
The simplest thing to
do is to the tracks out,
to take out some insurance
on this particular line.
Like that's a dangerous line.
And then except
tells us what to do.
So now the question
is-- now let's
put out a print statement.
Print what we're supposed
to say-- invalid input.
OK.
So here we go.
We've got invalid input, and
so we got an accept state.
I've made a mistake on purpose.
You can pause and try to
figure out what the mistake is.
OK, you had your
chance to pause,
so let's go take a look
at what the mistake is.
Let's come up with some evil
data that causes the problem.
So 10 is our first number.
12 is our second number.
And now I'm going to say Fred.
So now you should be able
to see what's wrong here.
The problem is that
basically Fred, indeed,
says invalid input.
That works because it runs
down this line of code,
and it says invalid input.
The problem is it still is
executing this code right here.
So the number-- actually
the float-- failed.
We said Fred, but
the number's 12,
and that's because it's 12 from
the last time through the loop.
The last time through the loop.
So it ends up
adding 12 again, 22.
And we have three numbers.
And then we finish it.
That was in the
wrong window there.
And then when we finish,
the average is not 11,
but it is indeed 11.3.
So the problem is when
we have this exception,
we can't run this code.
Of course, there's a
lovely, lovely bit of python
that solves this for us.
And that is the
continue statement.
The continue statement says
I'm done with this iteration.
You entered a number.
It's crappy.
I'm just not going
to do anything.
So effectively, instead of
going down here to continue,
goes up to here and
prompts for the next one.
So it doesn't do this code.
It does not do that code.
And everything's cool.
And so that's the key.
When we say invalid input, we
do not want to run this code.
So let's save this.
So it continues our
friend on this one.
So 10, 12-- I'm doing these
just so I can know the average
should be 11.
And then Fred.
You'll notice it
says invalid input.
But because of continue, it
doesn't follow through and do
all the rest of that stuff.
And then let's hit
Enter to finish.
And the average is indeed 11.0.
OK?
So again, I think
that's pretty much it.
Thanks for listening.
For more information Python for
Informatics, www.py4inf.com.