Hello and welcome
to my short video
on using the AutoGrader that
I built for Python associated
with my pythonlearn.com.
That's my free and
open book-- Python
for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
Of course, the book is available
in PDF and EPUB and iBooks
and HTML.
And it's a free book.
That's how these things work.
So let me go back here.
I'm here to talk
about the AutoGrader.
The AutoGrader is open source.
If you're a teacher
yourself, you
can download a copy
of the AutoGrader
and use it in your own course.
You'd have to configure
it to teach it
the questions that you want
and the answers that you want.
I haven't got that
documented yet
but the source code is
pretty straightforward
if you're a teacher.
So there's a couple
ways you can do it.
If you just go to it as a
website-- as a hosted website--
it does great.
So here's just a few that
I've got all put up some
more pretty soon I'll start
with just the hello world
assignment.
And so the basic idea is you've
got a problem statement here.
I want to change that
color to make it green
or something so it's
a little more obvious.
Write a program that uses
a print statement to say
"hello world," as shown below.
So here's the desired
output that we have.
And here is the output
of your program.
And this window here
is a text window
that you can type whatever
it is that you want to type
and then run the Python.
So if you press the
Check Code button,
it compiles it and runs it.
But this is complaining
because I have a syntax error.
And so if you look, this
sample code has a mistake.
It should be print
"hello world."
And then when I
check it, it works.
And part of it, it
checks to make sure
that the output of your
program matches the output
of the other program.
I could make a
successful program
and it would show you that there
was a mismatch on that line.
And so it's pretty smart.
Now, this Done
button may or may not
appear whoever's calling it.
If you embed it in
your own website,
you can control where this
Done button goes back to
or if it even appears
or not, but I've
got to go back in this
thing to go back to my list.
So here's one that it
also can open files.
I've got it to the point where
it always opens the files
unbox-short.txt.
If you're doing it
yourself, you can
teach it to open more files.
This one will run.
The desired output
is 1910 Lines.
Here's an open and a
read loop and a print.
So if you run it, it runs
it and you can finish it.
So you can put things in.
It is not my goal to have
this be your development
environment.
I want you to develop
on your own computer,
but this is really
for turning it in.
Now, I want to show you how this
can also be used in a course.
This is my online
course, and I'm
going to go into my
Python playground, which
is an instance of Moodle.
And so here's Moodle.
It's based on this same book.
It's got some YouTube
lectures and discussion forums
in the textbook.
And then I have some
assignments that can be graded.
So I'm going to say, turn in
the hello world assignment.
And so here we go.
We're back into
this user interface.
And if I check my code again,
it says bad input on line one
and it's made the
same mistake just
to sort of the teaching thing.
So check the code.
Now, you see
something different.
Because it's been launched
with IMS Learning Tools
interoperability,
it has the ability
to send a grade back to
Moodle-- the Moodle that I'm
logged in from.
And so it is allowing me as a
student to send a grade back,
and so it just sent a
grade back to Moodle.
It gives the student the
option to submit the grade.
And then if I go
back into Moodle,
you will see that I now
have a grade for that one.
Let's go see if a
can do problem 2.2.
I hope it's really problem
2.2 Go to problem 2.2.
What is this?
Oh, prompt the user that
uses raw input-- write
a program that uses raw
input to prompt the user
and welcome them.
OK, let's check it.
So let's check it.
Now, this raw input is actually
popping up the alert box here.
So I'll type Sarah and
it got data mismatched.
So that's not good.
Sarah.
Oh, I can't even type Sarah.
There we go.
Oh, but I need to say-- I
need to print "hello Sarah."
Check code.
Oh, that's going
to blow up again.
Sarah is not defined.
And it's got a mismatch.
All kinds of bad things
are happening here.
Hello name.
Sarah.
Now it should work.
Now I can submit the grade.
So before I submit the grade,
let me show you something
that it does.
I could possibly try to trick
this by saying "hello Sarah"
and only producing this output.
So here, we're
going to finish it.
And at the output's going
to match, but it's saying,
you've got to use
the raw input here
because that's part of the
program specifications.
So that sort of complains.
So there are some sanity
checks on the code
you write to make
sure that you're
at least doing some
basic things according
to the specifications.
So let me do it one more time.
Sarah.
And now it works, and now
I can submit my grade.
So I submit my grade
back to Moodle.
I go back to Moodle and I go
down and I check my grades.
And now I've got two of
the assignments completed.
So that gives you a
sense of the AutoGrader.
If you go to pythonlearn.com,
the source code
is available to this.
And so people who actually
want to use it in their classes
can adapt this AutoGrader
for themselves.
And I really need
to give a shout out
to SKULPT, which
is the thing that
really makes this practical.
It's a Python
in-browser compiler,
which means I don't have
to use a server at all.
These pages are
just PHP pages that
do all the work in JavaScript.
And so you don't need a lot
of server infrastructure
to do this.
And so that is really
quite exciting.
And so thank you for listening.
And I hope you can either
make use of these things
in PythonLearn or
my online courses
that I'll be teaching
using this technique.
Thanks.