Hello and welcome to
chapter eight, Python Lists.
So now we're sort of going to
start taking care of business.
We are [? going ?] to make lists
and dictionaries and tuples
and really start
manipulating this data
and doing real data analysis--
laying the ground work
real data analysis.
As always, these lectures,
audio, video, slides,
and even book are copyright
Creative Commons attribution.
So lists, dictionaries
and tuples,
the next real three big
topics we're going talk about,
are collections.
And we've been doing
lists already, right?
We've been doing lists when
we were doing for loops.
A list in Python is something
that has square braces.
This is a constant list.
Now when I first talked
to you about variables,
I sort of oversimplified things.
I said if you put
x equals 2 and then
put x equals 4, the 2 and
the 4 override each other.
A collection is where you
can put a bunch of things
in the same variable.
Now I have to have a way
to find those things,
but it allows us to put more
than one thing in a variable.
And so here we have friends,
that has three strings, Joseph,
Glenn and Sally and
we have carryon,
it has socks, shirt and perfume.
So that's the basic idea.
So what's not a collection?
Well, simple variables.
Simple variables
are not collections.
Just like this example,
I say, x equals
2 x equals 4 and print
x and the 4 is in there
and the 2 is somehow gone.
It was there for a moment
and then it's gone.
And so that's a normal variable,
they're not collections,
you can't put more
than one thing in it.
But when you put more
than one thing in it,
then you have to
have a way to find
the things that are in there.
We'll get to that.
So we've been using
list constants
for the last couple
of chapters just
because we have to use
list constants, you know?
So we used it in the
For loop chapter,
we did list of numbers.
We have done lists
of strings, t that's
strings red, yellow and blue.
And you don't have
to necessarily have
to have things all
of the same type.
This is three item list
that has a string red,
the number integer
24 and 98.6 which
is a floating point number.
Here's an interesting
thing just as a side note,
this shows that floating
point numbers are not always
perfectly represented
inside of the computer,
it's sort of an artifact
of how they work.
And this is an example of
98.6 is really 98 point
na-na-na-na-na.
So when you see something
like that, don't freak out.
Floating point numbers are the
ones that show this behavior.
So interestingly,
you can always--
although we won't
put a lot of energy
into this-- you can also
have an element of a list,
be a list itself.
So this is a outer list that's
got three elements: 1, 7
and then a list that's 5 and 6.
So if you look at
the length of this,
there is three things in it.
Not four, three, because the
outer list has one, two, three,
things in it.
An empty list is
bracket, bracket, OK?
Like I said, we have been
going through lists all along,
we have iteration variables
For i in, this is a list,
we've been using it all along.
Similarly, we've
been using lists,
indefinite loops are a great way
to go through lists for friend
in friends, there we have goes
through three times, outcome
three lines with the
variable friend advancing
through the three
successive items in the list
and away we go.
So again, lists are not
completely foreign to us.
Now just like in
a string, we can
use the index operator, the
square bracket operator,
and we can look up items in
the list-- Sub 1, friend sub 1.
Not surprisingly, using
the European elevator rule,
the first item in
a list is sub 0.
The second item is sub 1,
and the third one is sub 2.
So here when I
print friend sub 1,
I get Glenn, which is
the second element.
Just like strings-- so once you
kind of know it for strings,
lists and the rest of these
things make a lot more sense.
Just remember that
we're in Europe,
and things start with 0.
Some things in these data
items that we work with
are not mutable, so
for example, strings:
When we ask for a lowercase
version of a string,
we're given a copy
of that string
and that's because
strings are not mutable.
And we can see this by doing
something like saying, fruits
sub 0 equals lowercase b.
Now you'd think
that, that would just
change this to be a lowercase
b but it doesn't, OK?
It says string object
does not support
item assignment, which
means that you're not
allowed to reassign.
You can make a new string
and put different things
in that string but once
the strings are made,
they're not changeable and
that's why we call fruit.lower,
we get a copy of
it in lowercase.
And so x is a copy of
the original string
but the original string,
once we assign it into fruit,
is unchanged-- can't be changed.
This on the other
hand, can be changed
and we can change
them in the middle.
This is one of the things
we like about them.
So here we have a list:
2, 14, 26, 41 and 63.
Then we say lotto
sub 2, of course
that is going to
be the third item,
lotto sub 2 is equal to 28.
Then we print it and we
see the new number there.
So all this is saying, is that
we can change them, right?
Strings no, and lists yes.
You can change lists but
you can't change strings.
So the lend function, we've
used it for several things--
we can say lend is
used for strings
and it's used for lists as well.
So the same function knows
when its parameter is a string
and when its
parameter is a string,
it gives us the number of
characters in the string
and when it is a list, it
gives us the number of elements
in the list.
And just because one
of them is a string,
it's still one element from
the point of view of this list
so it has one, two, three, four,
four items in the list, OK?
So the range function
is a special function,
it's probably about time to
talk about the range function.
The range function
is a function that
generates a list, that produces
a list and gives it back to us.
And so you give
the range function
a parameter, how
many items you want,
and the range function
creates and gives us
back a list that is four numbers
starting at 0, which is 0 up to
but not including, 3.
Sound familiar?
Yeah.
0 up to but not including 4.
And so the same
thing is true here.
So we can combine the
lend and the range
to say OK, we'll lend
friends, that's three items
and range lend
friends is 0, 1, 2.
And it also corresponds
exactly to these items.
So we can actually
use this to construct
loops to go through a list.
We already have a
basic For loop, right?
We basically have a For
loop for each friend
and friends and outcomes, Happy
New Year Glenn and Joseph.
If we also want to know
what position we're at
as the loop progresses,
we can rewrite
the exact same loop
a different way
and make i be our iteration
variable and say i in range
lend friends, that turns this
into 0, 1, 2, and then i goes
0, 1, 2, and then
we can in the loop,
look up the
particular friend that
is the particular one
we're interested in,
using the index
operator, friends sub i
and then print Happy New Year.
So these two loops
are equivalent.
This loop and this loop.
This loop is preferred unless
you happen to need this value
i, which tells you where you're
at, in case maybe you're going
to change something, you're
going to look through something
and then change it.
So for what I've written here,
they're exactly equivalent.
Prefer the simpler one unless
you need the more complex one,
they both produce the
same kind of output.
We can concatenate lists much
like we concatenate strings
with a plus.
And you can think of the Python
operators looking to its right
and to its left and saying,
oh, those are both lists,
I know what to do with lists,
I'm going to put those together
and so that produces a two,
three long lists become a six
long list, with the first one
followed by the second one,
concatenated.
It didn't hurt the original,
a, c is a new list basically.
We can also slice lists.
Feels a lot like strings, right?
Everything's kind of like
strings, For loop like strings,
concatenation like strings and
now slicing like strings and it
is exactly the same.
So 1, up to but not including--
just remember, up to
but not including,
the second parameter
is up to but not including--
so that starts at the sub
1 which is the second one.
Up to but not including
3, the third one so this
is 1, 2, and 3.
So that's 41, comma 2.
Starting at the first one,
up to but not including
the third one.
We can similarly
eliminate the first one
so that's up to but not
including fourth one,
is starting at 0 1, 2,
3, but not including 4,
so that's this one.
If we go 3 to the end,
and again remember
the they're starting at
0, so three to the end
is 0, 1, 2, 3, to the end, the
number three doesn't matter.
So that's 374.15
and the whole thing,
that's the whole thing so
these two things are the same.
So slicing works like
strings, starting and up to,
but not including is
the second parameter.
There are some methods and you
can read about these online
in the Python documentation.
We can use the
built in function,
doesn't have a lot of use
when we're running programs
but it's kind of
useful, I like it
when I'm typing interactively
like, what can this thing do?
So I make a list, a
list is a unique type
and I say with dir, I say,
what can we do with it?
Well, we can append, we can
count, extend, index, insert,
pop, remove, reverse and sort.
And then you can sort of
read up on all these things.
I'll show you just a couple.
We can build a list
with the append.
So this syntax
here, stuff equals
list-- that's called
a constructor, which
says give me an empty list.
You could also say bracket,
bracket, for an empty list.
Whatever, you've got
to make an empty list
and then you call the append.
Remember that lists are mutable,
so it's OK to change it.
So we're saying, OK, we
start with an empty list
and now append to the end
of that the word book,
and then append to that, 99.
Wait a sec.
That's a mistake.
So I have to fix this mistake,
so watch me fix the mistake.
Poof!
Now my thing is magically
fixed, isn't that amazing?
I have magic powers when
it comes to slide fixing,
I just snap my fingers
and the slides are fixed.
So here we go.
We append a 99 and
we print it out
and it's got book and 99,
emphasizing the fact that they
don't have to be the exact
same kind of thing in a list.
Then later, we append cookie
and then it's book 99 cookie.
OK?
So this append, we won't
do it in line like this
so often, we'll tend
to do it in a loop
as we're building up
a list, but that's
a way you start
with an empty list
and then
programmatically grow it.
We can ask-- much like
we do in a string-- we
can ask if an item is in a
list, so here's a list called
some with these numbers in it,
it's got five numbers in it.
Is 9 in some?
True, yes it is.
Is 15 in some?
False.
Is 20 not in, that is legal
syntax, is 20 not in some?
Yes, it's not there, OK?
They don't modify the list,
they're just asking questions.
These are logical
operations often used
in If statements or
while, some kind of logic
that you might be building, OK?
So lists have order.
So when we were pending them,
the first thing went it first,
the second thing went in
second, et cetera, et cetera.
And we can also tell
the list to sort itself.
So one of the things that
we can do with a list,
now we're starting to
see some power here,
is say, sort yourself.
This is a list of strings,
it can sort numbers,
it can sort lots of things.
Friends.sort That says,
hey, there dear friends,
sort yourself.
This makes a change.
It alters the list and
puts it in this case,
in alphabetical order:
Glenn, Joseph and Sally.
It's been modified
and so friend sub
1 is now Joseph because
that's the second one, OK?
So the sort method
says, sort yourself now
sort yourself and it sorts
and then it stays sorted.
So again, you're going
to be kind of ticked
about this particular
slide because there's
a whole bunch of built in
functions that help with lists
and there's max, there's min,
there's lend, various things.
All those loops that
I told you how to do,
I was just showing you
that stuff because I
thought it was important.
This is the simplest way to go
through and find the largest,
smallest n, sum, et cetera.
So here's a list of numbers.
We can say how many are
there, that's the count.
We can say, what's the largest?
It's 74.
What's the smallest?
That'd be 3.
What is the sum, the
running total of them all,
154, if you remember
from a few lectures ago
these are the same numbers.
And what is the average?
Which is sum of them over
the length of them, OK?
So this makes a lot
more sense and if you
had a list of numbers
like this, you
would simply say what's the max,
you wouldn't write a max loop,
I just did that to
demonstrate how loops work.
So here is a way that you
can sort of change those kind
of programs that we wrote.
So there's two ways to
write a summing program.
Let's just say instead of
the data being in a list,
we're going to write
a While loop that's
going to read a set of
numbers until we say done,
and then compute the average
of those numbers, OK?
So let's say this is our
problem: Read a list of numbers
and wait until the word done
comes in and then average them.
So here's a little
program that does that.
We create total equal
0 count equal 0,
making an infinite
loop with while true,
and then we ask
to enter a number,
we get a string back from
this-- remember raw input always
gives us strings back--
and then if it's done,
we're going to break.
This is the version
of an If that does not
require an indent, we just put
the break up there and so that
gets us out of the loop
when the time is right
so when the time
is right over here,
and then we convert
the value to float,
we use float to convert the
input to a floating point
number and then we do
our accumulation pattern,
total equals total plus value,
count equals count plus 1.
So this is going to
run, these numbers
are going to go up
and up and up and up
and then we're going
to break out of it,
calculate the average and
then print the average.
Because that's a floating
point number so now
the average is a
floating point number.
So that's one way
to do it, right?
That would be one way
to write a program that
does an average, is
keep a running average
as you're reading the numbers.
But there's another
way to do it that would
work exactly the
same way, and this is
when you can start using lists.
So come in, you say I'm going
to make a list of numbers
just a mnemonic name number
list is an empty list.
Then I create
another infinite loop
that's going to read
for enter a number,
and if it's done break that
kind of gets us out of it.
Convert the input
value to a float
and then append it to the list.
So now the list is going to
grow each time we read a number,
the list is going to grow.
However many times we add
the numbers, how many things
are going to be in the list.
So in this case when we're
at this and we type done,
there'll be three
numbers in the list
because we will have
run append three times,
we'll have appended
3, 9, and 5 we'll
have them sitting in a list, and
we will have exited the loop.
So now you say oh, add up
all the numbers in that list
and then divide it by
the length of the list
and print the average.
So these two programs
are basically
equivalent-- the only time that
they might not be equivalent
was if there was
ten million numbers,
this would use up 40 megabytes
of your memory, which
is actually not a lot of
memory on some computers,
but if memory mattered this
does store all those numbers--
this one actually just
runs the calculation
so if there's a really
large number of numbers,
this would make a difference
because the list is growing
and keeping them all,
summing them all at the end,
this is actually storing
very little data.
But for reasonably sized
numbers like thousands or even
hundreds of
thousands of numbers,
these two approaches
are kind of equivalent
and then sometimes
you actually want
to accumulate something a
little more complex than this,
you want to sort them,
or look for the maximum
and look for something
else, who knows what.
But the notion of make a list
and then append something
to the list each time
through the iteration
and then do something
with a list at the end,
is a rather powerful pattern.
So this is also a
powerful pattern,
this is accumulator
pattern we just
have variables
accumulating in the loop,
this one is one where we
accumulate the data in the loop
and then do the
computations all at the end.
Certain situations will make use
of these different techniques.
OK so.
Connecting strings and lists.
So there's a method, a
capability of strings,
that is really powerful when
it comes to tearing data apart.
It's called the split.
So here is a string
with three words
and has blanks in between
here and abc.split
says parse this string,
look for the blanks,
break the string into
pieces, and give me
back a list with one item for
each of the words in the list
as defined by the spaces, OK?
So it breaks it
into three pieces
and gives us that back in the
list, it's very powerful, OK?
So we're going to split
it and we get back a list.
There are three words
and the first word,
stuff sub 0 is With.
So there's a lot of
parsing going on here.
We could do this with For
loops and a lot of other things
but there would be a lot
of work in the split.
Given that this is a
really common task,
it's really great that this has
been put into Python for us,
OK?
So split breaks a
string into parts
and produce a list of strings,
we think of these as words
and we can access
a particular word
or we can loop
through all the words.
So here we have
stuff again and now
we have a For loop that's going
to go through each of the three
words and then it's
going to run three times.
Now chances are good we're going
to do something different other
than just print
them out, but you
see how you quickly can take
us split followed by a For
and then write a loop that's
going to go through each
of the words without working
too hard to find the spaces,
you let Python do all the hard
work of finding the spaces, OK?
So let's take a look
at a couple of samples,
just a couple things to teach
you a little more about split.
Split looks at many spaces as
equal to one space so if you
split a lot of spaces,
it's still just
throws away all those spaces
and gives us four words.
One, two, three, four and
throws away all the spaces
because it assumes that's what
we want done, so that's nice.
You can also have split
on some other characters.
Sometimes you'll be
getting data and they'll
have used a
semicolon, or a comma,
or a colon, or a tab character,
who knows what they've used,
and your job is to
dig that data out.
So you can split based
on a different character.
Here, if we're
splitting normally,
this is a normal split, it's
not going to see the semicolons,
it's looking for
a space and so all
we get back is one item in
the string with a semicolon.
But if we switch and we pass
semicolon in as a parameter
to split, then it will know to
split it based on semicolons
and gives us first,
second and third back.
OK?
And then it gives
us three words.
So you can split
either on spaces
or you can split on a character
other than a space, OK?
So let's take a look at
how we might turn this
into some of our
common assignments
that we have this
chapter, we're going
to read some of
the mailbox data.
So here we go with
a little program.
First three lines,
we write these a lot.
Open the file, write
a For loop to loop
through each line in
the file, then we're
going to strip off the white
space at the end the line.
One, two, three, do
those all the time.
And we're looking for lines,
if you look at the whole file,
we're looking at
lines that start
with from followed by a space.
So if the line does
not start with from
followed by a space, that's a
space right there, continue.
So that's a way to skip all the
lines the don't look like this.
There are thousands
of lines in this file
and just a few that
look like this, OK?
And so we're going
to look and we're
going to try to find what
day of the week this thing
happened on.
So we're throwing
away all the lines
with this little bit of code.
Then what we do is we
take the line, which
is all of this text,
and then we split it.
And we know that the day
of the week is word sub 2.
So this is word sub
0, this is word sub 1,
and this is word sub 2.
So this is word sub
0, sub 1, and sub 2.
And so all we have to do
is print out the sub 2
and we throw away all the
lines except the from lines,
we split them and take the
third word or word sub 2,
and we can quickly
create something
that's extracting the
data week out of these.
OK?
So it's quick because
split does the tricky work.
If you go back to
the strings chapter,
you saw that we did a lot of
work to get this to happen.
So here's even another
tricky pattern.
So let's say we want to do what
we did at the end of chapter
six, the string chapter, let's
say we wanted to get back
this little bit of data, OK?
So we can look at
this and say, OK,
let's split this-- and this will
be 0, 1, and 2, and 3, and 4,
5, and 6.
We're splitting it
based on spaces then
that email address is
words sub 1, right?
So that email address
is this little bit
of stuff because it's in
between spaces, right?
So that's what we pull out, the
email address is words sub 1,
and we've got that.
So that's sitting in this
email address variable.
Then all we want, we don't
really want the whole thing,
we just want the
part after the @,
and we could do a
look up of the @,
but you can also do
a second split, OK?
So we're taking
this variable here,
email, which is merely this
little part right here,
and we are splitting it
again except this time
we're splitting it
based on an @ which
means it's going to
bust it right here
and find us two pieces.
So pieces now is a list where
the sub 0 item is the person's
name and the sub 1 item is the
host that their mail address is
held from, OK?
And so then, all
we need to know is
pieces sub 1 and pieces sub
1 is this guy right here.
So that's pieces sub 1
and so we pulled it out.
So if you go back to
how we did it before,
we were doing searching
and we were searching some
and then we're
taking slices-- this
is a little more elegant, OK?
Because really, we split
it and then we split it,
and we knew what piece
we were looking at.
So this is what I call
the double split pattern,
where you split a
string into a list,
then you take the
thing out and then
you split it again, depending
on what data you're looking for.
This is just a technique,
it's not the only technique.
OK so that's lists, we
talked about the concept
of a collection where lists
have multiple things in it,
indefinite loops, again
we've seen these things,
it looks a lot like
strings except the elements
are more powerful and
they're more mutable.
We still use the
bracket operator
and we re-did the
max, min and sum
except we did it in one line,
rather than a whole loop.
And something we're
going to play with a lot,
is using split to parse strings,
the single split and then
the double split is a natural
extension of the single split.
So, see you in the next
lecture, looking forward
to talking about dictionaries.