Hello, and welcome back
to our continuing episodes
of worked exercises for the
book Python for Informatics
Exploring Information.
I'm your author and tour
guide, Dr. Charles Severance.
As always, these materials
are Copyright Creative Commons
Attribution.
I look forward to ways that
you can improve on this work.
This material is a supplement
to my www.pythonlearn.com,
which is my supporting website
for Python for Informatics.
It has installation and
other kinds of support
that can help you get started.
So for this particular
exercise, it really
comes from our
dictionaries example,
and we're going to try to
figure out the most common word.
And in this one
we're going to deal
with some really simple text
files, where the words are just
words, and we're not going
to worry about lines,
or skipping lines, or anything.
So we're just going to do words,
and so we'll do this thing.
So if we look at
this program, there's
really four basic
parts to the program.
One is-- the first part-- is
actually reading the program,
and this is a little different
pattern than other things
that we've done.
And we're going to
read the whole file.
And so this is-- instead
of doing a for loop here,
we are going to read
the entire file.
So we're going to ask the
user for the file name,
and then open the
file name to type in.
So here, we're asking
the user for a file name.
Open the file.
But then we're going
to do a handle.read.
Now if you recall,
handle.read, normally we
would write a for
loop that would
loop through each line, and
strip, and split, and whatever.
What we're going
to do here is say,
you don't read this whole thing.
We know that these
files are pretty small.
Read the whole thing
in into a string.
Now the key thing
is that will read
all the lines in, and
the new lines at end
of the-- at the line,
there's a new line.
But all this will be
read in, all the lines
and the new lines.
And the nice thing about this is
the new lines form white space,
and so they will give
a word break before
the-- between the last
word on the one line,
and the first wore
on the next line.
I'll talk about that a bit
more When we're actually
looking at some stuff.
We're going to
split it into words,
which means we're going to
make a very long list, which
is all the words
in the entire file,
not just the words
on a line, which
is some of the other
examples that we've used.
But again, we know
these files that we're
playing with are
relatively small,
and they fit in the
memory of Python.
So we're just going
to do a simple,
crude-- read the whole thing
in as a string, split it
on white space,
new lines included.
And now we're going to write
a very simple dictionary
loop, that we're going
to create dictionary,
and we're going to
go through the word.
Now this word is our
iteration variable, of course,
and words is all the words
in all the lines of text.
We're going to use
the get pattern.
So if the word exists,
whatever word we're looking at,
we will get it and add 1 to it.
And if it doesn't, we'll
just use the default value
and add 1.
So this is effectively the
same as setting it to one
the first time we see a word.
Then I'm going to write
a simple maximum list.
And so what we're
going to do is we're
going to create a big
word variable that we're
going to start as none, which
is the word that is the largest,
and how many there are.
And then we're going to do
a loop with two iteration
variables.
We're going to go through
our-- our dictionary
will be word, comma, count.
The word will map to the count.
The word will be the key,
count will be the value.
So we use counts.items to
get that list of tuples back.
And basically, if we're on
the first one, big count
being none, or if the count
is greater than big count,
then we're going to
remember the word
and we're going to
remember the count.
And then this loop will
go through all the words,
and at the end, we just print
out big work and big out.
So that basically is the outline
of what we're going to do.
And when we run it, we'll run it
with a couple different files,
words.txt and clown.txt.
OK, so I'm going to
clear this and get out.
And so I'm just going to cheat
and put a few of the lines in.
We'll actually write
the whole thing.
So we can say
goodbye to that now.
So I'm going to
get my data files,
and I will go to
pythonlearn.com,
go under the book.
The code samples, actually
is just files, mostly.
Maybe I shouldn't call it code.
And I'm going to
grab the clown file.
So the clown file is going
to be from the lecture,
the cloud ran after a car.
I'm going to save this file.
I'm going to put it in my
folder called dictionaries.
And then I'll hit
back, and I'll go down
to the file called words.txt.
And this is the first three
paragraphs of the book.
And we're going to count
the most common word there,
and I'll do a File, Save As,
and put words there right
in the dictionaries folder.
So now I've got my data.
And I can get rid of this.
And so if I take a look
at my dictionaries folder,
I see that I've got
clown.txt and words.txt.
And so now I'm going
to say, I'll save this.
And I'll call this
thing common word.
I'll call it common.py.
What the heck?
Keep these things short.
So if I take a look in
here now, I've got-- oops,
I saved it to the wrong place.
File, come back.
File, Save As.
Where did I save it?
I have no idea where I saved it.
But I will save where
it's supposed to be.
It's supposed to
be in dictionaries,
and we'll call it common.py.
That's why I always
check, right?
There it is, common.py.
And now I'm going
to go into that,
go into my Desktop,
dictionaries,
and there I've got
common.py and words.txt,
and we'll just run it.
And I'll tell it
to do clown.txt.
Now it didn't do
anything, because I
haven't printed anything out.
It actually did read it.
So let's take a look here.
I'm going to print len of text.
And I'm going to print
the first 40 characters.
text up to but not including 40.
So that's what I'm going to
do here, just to see this.
And I'll do clown again.
So the length of text
is 106 characters,
and that is exactly
the size of the file.
It read the whole file.
If I do ls minus l,
it shows clown.txt
having 106 characters.
So it read into-- handle.read
read into the variable text 106
characters, and the first
40 are just those things,
the clown ran after the
car, blah, blah, blah.
OK?
So now this entire file,
clown.txt, has been split.
So I'm going to
print len of words.
So how many words did
I get in that split?
And then I'll print
the words themselves.
Oops.
clown.txt.
So I a read in 106 characters,
but then I broke it into words,
and there's 24 words.
And then here is
my list of words.
OK?
So I split the entire file
into words at this point,
and now I have a big list.
Now if I do the same
thing with words.txt,
it read 1,170 characters, and
here's the first characters,
and then it broke it into
words, and it was 210 words.
Now let me change
this ever so slightly,
so it prints the
first 100 characters.
And I'll show you something.
words.txt.
So it printed the
first 100 characters.
Let me split this
into print statements
to make it even clearer.
We run again, words.txt.
I clear my screen.
So the first print, this
print right here, is 1,170.
And then I print the
first 100 characters.
This is that first
100 characters.
What you're sort
of not seeing here
is there's a new line here.
OK?
And that's why it
prints on two lines.
So blah, blah, blah,
blah, blah, new line.
It read new lines in all.
Now it didn't do the
second one, because that
was where my print stopped.
The key thing is, it knows
that when split works,
this is white space, that
space is white space,
and the /n is white space.
So it knows that creative and
and are two separate words,
and it doesn't somehow
put them together.
So that's the nice
thing about the split
with no parameter doing what
it knows to be white space.
It will use new lines
as white space, as well.
And that's quite nice.
And if there's extra spaces,
it just throws those away.
All of the features of sort
of split with no parameter
are very intelligent
and very clever.
And so it works very
nicely in this situation,
because new lines are
thought of as white space,
and blanks are thought
of as white space.
And it really is exactly
what you would want.
I mean it's exactly
what you want.
I mean that's because
humans wrote this stuff,
and they thought,
what would I want?
So they wrote something
that's what you want.
So now we have, in effect,
a whole file and a list
of all the words in that file.
OK?
So I'm going to take
all this stuff out.
I'm going to take
So now words is a list.
And I'm going to say
for wrd in words.
I'm using word on purpose.
Print wrd, right?
So that's a slightly
less mnemonic word.
So I'll go back
to the clown.txt.
And now I'm going to
print out the words.
So now my loop is going
through the list one at a time
and printing them out.
OK?
So I am now going to
make a dictionary.
I'm going to call this cou=dict
to make an empty dictionary.
So cou is a really
un-mnemonic version of counts.
So we'll call him cou.
OK?
So cou is our dictionary.
And I'm going to do
this the hard way first.
I'm going to say if wrd-- word
up-- in cou, then cou sub wrd
is equal to cou sub wrd plus 1.
So if it's already
there, we're going
to add 1 to whatever is stored
in the thing marked with wrd.
Now wrd is not wrd, it's the
and on and down, and whatever.
wrd is a variable that
contains these strings.
OK?
But if it's not in there, else
cou sub wrd is equal to 1.
So that's like when
we've seen the new person
for the first time, we say,
oh, we haven't seen you before,
so we're going to set you to 1.
OK?
And then I'm going
to-- just for yucks,
I'm going to print
wrd, comma, cou of wrd.
So I'm going to-- as
we go through the loop,
for each word we're going
to do this add or set to 1.
And then we'll just print
it at the end of the loop,
how many we've got so far.
So let's run this now.
clown.txt.
That didn't work so well,
because I didn't save it.
So let's try that again.
Let me clear my
screen I like Macs
because I can clear
my screen so nicely.
It keeps my brain organized.
So what we see here is we saw
the word the, and we put it
in the dictionary with 1.
clown 1, ran 1, after 1.
Now we've seen the-- Ooh,
ooh, let's make another thing
to make this even clearer.
Hang on.
print, adding, print, New Word.
Good thing I-- actually, I'm
going to call this Word up.
So when I'm incrementing,
I'm going to say Word up,
and then I'm going to say new
word when I'm creating it.
So I just added a
print in each of these,
just to really clarify
what's going on, right?
Word up, that means
I'm incrementing it.
I'm adding 1 to it,
that's what Word up means.
clown.txt.
So here we go.
So let's make this even cooler.
Word up, comma, wrd.
And now I can say, comma, wrd.
So it saw the, did a new
word, its count is 1.
It saw clown and it's
new, so it got a 1.
It saw ran.
Ran's a 1.
After's a 1.
Ooh, now the.
The is a Word up.
So we add 1 to it.
So it's now a 2, right?
Car's brand new.
And is new.
We see the again, so
now the goes to 3.
So you're incrementing
when I say Word up,
and you're setting to
one when I say New Word.
Yeah.
So you get the picture.
So by now we've seen
the a bunch of times.
We're adding 1 to
the, and it's now 5.
So at the end of this
we're going to present cou.
I'm going to do this cooler.
Watch this.
wrd, comma-- now I'm actually
going to put the count on here,
cou wrd.
And I'm going to put it
after I set the count, so it
looks a little prettier.
Check this out.
It's going to be awesome.
Word up.
And then I'm going to change
this to just see Word.
And now I've got the print
inside [? my ?] if, then, else.
I'm going to say cou, sub word.
It's OK to make your debug
output a little bit fun.
So now, here we go.
So I moved my print
into the if, then, else,
and I print the word,
whether I'm increasing it
or not, and then
how many it's after.
And I do this after this line,
so it's the word afterwards.
And then I print the
whole dictionary out.
So this is going to
be even awesomer.
The, Word.
The count is 1.
Clown, first word.
Word, Word, Word.
Now, here we saw the,
and we did Word up.
So now it's 2.
Car, word is 1.
The, Word up, now 3.
You get the picture?
So every time we hit this
if part, we do Word up.
If we hit the else
part, we do Word.
OK?
And at the end we have all
the words that have been upped
and added, et cetera.
OK?
So enough of this
debugging print.
We don't need that.
It was just fun.
But just let's make sure
that it still works.
It does.
Now, after all that, we are
going to say, you know what?
We don't actually
need any of this crap.
Because there is an
idiom that basically
deals with the fact that,
instead of a lookup-- so let's
run this one real quick.
Right?
It's like, hey, I want
to just add 1 to it.
And we will watch just
how fast this blows up.
And that's because
the-- see, we're
doing count word equal
count word plus 1.
It's this count
on the left side.
It's blowing up.
Right?
It's blowing up right here,
because the is not yet there.
Well, that is why they
made the get function.
So it has this cool get.
Now that's a method, so we're
going to use parentheses.
And we have to give
it a default value.
Get says look up word--
whatever's in word,
the, clown, whatever--
and if it's not there,
give me back a number.
Well, we want to set
it to 1 the first time.
So if I return the number
0, then adding 1 to it
will make it be 1.
And so I can capture
all of that if,
then, else in one statement now.
Clown.txt.
Word up.
OK?
So we use the get
to do the lookup.
It encapsulates that if,
then, else that we just
got done rewriting.
It is the, if this exists,
else, give me back a 0.
OK?
So here we go.
We've got ourselves a
nice little happy guy.
Right?
So now we want to
find the biggest one.
Well, we're going to
do a maximum loop.
And so let's start by
this, in saying lrg=None.
We're going to use
the None pattern.
And so now what
I'm going to do is
I'm going to write a for
loop that goes through.
Well let's not--
let's get rid of that.
We'll come back to that.
We're going to do kyy.
Maybe not.
We might do kee and
val in cou.items.
So I'm going to go
through the items.
Remember that-- OK let's just
do cou-- let's print cou.items
here for [? yuckomatic. ?]
Let me comment this
out for a second.
Ah, don't do that.
There we go.
So let's run this one now.
clown.txt.
So now we're printing
a list of tuples.
So each one is a tuple.
And the way-- we can
then write this for loop
to get this cou item.
So this whole thing
here is cou items.
It's a list of tuples.
And we can basically make it
so that the kee and the val
move through the list
of items, where kee is
and, val is 3, then next
iteration, kee is on, val is 1.
Next iteration, kee
is ran, val is 2.
Dot, dot, dot, dot.
OK?
And so that's cool.
I mean it says,
this cou items is
a list of two tuples,
tuples with two items in it,
two things in it.
And we're going to give
ourselves two iteration values.
So just for [? yuckomatic, ?]
we're just going to first,
as we would, print out kee
and val, and then run that.
So here we go.
We've got kee and val,
kee and val, kee and val.
And it's in whatever
order it feels
like having this come out in.
OK?
So then what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to create a
variable called maxval.
I'm going to set it to None.
And I will say, if
maxval is equal to None,
maxval maxval=val.
Now, I'm using this--
don't get too crazy.
I am using the contraction
form of if here.
So I'm not indenting.
I'm just putting the one line.
Because if maxval is None,
maxval is the current value.
And then I'm going to say
if maxval is less than val--
and again, I'm
doing this in order.
I'm doing the check
for None first.
But once I've got
it, maxval=val.
OK?
So this is, in a
sense, my priming.
We call the sort
of a priming thing.
So first time through
the loop, we're
going to grab the first
value that we see.
And then we're going
to print maxval.
We're going to check to see
if we're going up basically.
If the current maximum is less
than what we're looking at,
let's grab it.
And I'll just print out
maxval here, just for yucks.
OK?
clown.txt.
So we see and.
And the first maxval is 3, which
kind of makes the thing boring.
On is only 1, which
is not-- so ran is 2.
Nobody seems to
be better than 3.
Down is 1.
Fell is 1.
The, ooh, the is
7, so we grab it.
Tent is 2.
So then we're all done.
OK?
So then I'll just print out
at the end, print out maxval.
So if I do this and
type clown.txt cou,
we know that the
best number is 7.
But now what we want is we
want to know what word it was.
What is our best word?
So I'm just going to make
another variable called maxwrd.
And I'm going to make it None
at the beginning of the loop.
And I'm going to make
that be an indent.
And at this moment where I'm
capturing the maximum value,
I'm just going to capture
the maximum word, as well.
maxwrd=kee.
Oh, wait a sec.
I want to call this maxkee.
So we have a really
stupid, funny maxkee.
So we've got kee, which is
the key, and then maxkee.
And I'm going to print out
maxval and maxkee as well.
And then I'm going to print
out maxkee, comma, maxval.
I'll put maxkee over here.
And you'll see-- maxval.
Ooh, that's not
going to quite work.
It's not going to quite work.
But let's let it not
work, and then we'll
see what we did wrong.
It'll ultimately work, but
it'll kind of be flawed.
clown.txt.
So let me get rid of
this count items line.
Get rid of that, make it clear.
So here we go.
We've got-- first time through
the word we're looking at
is and, and the value for
and is 3, and maxkee is None.
That's the maximum
kee we've seen.
But we do have a maximum
value, which means
we've seen the largest is 3.
Now why is that?
Wait a sec.
If the 3 is the largest,
and we just saw 3,
shouldn't this be
and instead of None?
And the problem is, when
we came through here
and we hit this maxval None,
we set maxval equal to val.
And then we checked if
maxval was less than value
to capture the kee.
So we weren't capturing the kee.
So quick hack on this.
And what the heck?
We're not above quick hacks.
So if I change this to
less than or equal to,
that when I set
maxval to val, it'll
at least run this bit of code,
and then capture the key.
So that's a quick way to do it.
Close enough for
government work.
So now we've fixed the bug.
Right?
The bug is that we were
capturing the max number,
but we weren't
capturing the maxkee.
But now we're also
Now in general a slightly
more elegant way to do this
is actually to just make
this a guardian pattern
with an or clause.
If maxval is equal to
None, or-- and I'll
put this back to a less than,
maxval is less than val,
then capture them.
Right?
So if we're in the-- get
rid of the equal sign.
Right?
If maxval is equal to None,
or maxval is less than value,
capture them.
Grab them.
Now the output's going to be
the same, but it will be pretty.
It's more elegant code,
partly because we did it
all in one if, and
partly because we just
don't have to look at
our code to decide, oh,
when that first
thing runs, we've
got to get the
second thing right.
And so now at the
end, we see the and 7,
and we are as good
to go as you can be.
And all we have to do before
we turn in our assignment
is comment on that a little
bit a debug, and away we go.
Clown.txt.
The, 7.
And what's my other file?
words.txt.
We just try to run it
on a bigger file now.
words.txt, it's always safe.
And it shows us 216.
So here's our happy
little program at the end.
Let's take a look at this.
We read the file--
we open the file.
We read the entire
file, line after line,
all the lines,
including new lines.
We split it into words.
Conveniently, the new
line counts as a space,
because it's white space.
Then we make a simple
dictionary counting loop to loop
through the words we just split.
And then we have a
real simple maximum
loop, where we capture
both the maximum value
and the maximum kee.
And then we simply print
the maximum kee out
at the very end.
OK?
So I hope you found this useful,
and see you in the next exer--