Hello and welcome to yet
another worked exercise.
I'm the author of the book
Python for Informatics,
Exploring Information,
as well as
your host for this
particular worked exercise.
As always, the book, this audio
and video, and these slides
are copyright Creative
Commons Attribution,
and I hope you find exciting and
interesting ways to reuse them
and repurpose them
and add to them.
So PythonLearn.com
is my support website
for the Python for
Informatics book.
And hopefully by now you've
got all this worked out,
but it does teach you
how to get started,
all the things that you need
to know to edit files and use
the command line to run
Python programs, you've got
figured it.
So our program for today
is from the List chapter.
And our program is actually
we're going to debug a program
rather than just writing
a program from scratch.
And so what our task
is in this program
is we are looking for
words that start with from.
We're looking for lines
that start with from.
And on the lines
that start with from,
we're going to pull
out the day of the week
that this particular
email message was sent,
Saturday, Friday, whatever.
And so the structure of the
program is pretty standard.
We're going to open
a file at the top.
We're going to loop
through the file.
Strip the new lines
at the end, right.
There's a little new line
at the end of each line.
And then we're
going to use split
to split it into
words, which means
that will make this the 0 word,
the 1 word, and the 2 word.
And then we're going to check
the 0 word to see if it's from.
And if the 0 word's
not from, we're
uninterested in that line, so
we're going to skip back up.
And if it is, good.
If we find a line
we're interested in.
We're going to skip the majority
of the lines of this file.
Less than 1 in
100 of these lines
actually have from
as the first word.
And then the second word is
what we're interested in.
So we're going to print
the day of the week.
So this program,
as we type it in,
is going to have a trace back.
And as soon as you
see trace back,
you immediately are drawn
to the word traceback.
And maybe you've
got to the point
where you start to read the
y list index out of range.
And then it says line
five, so that's helpful.
But the first thing to not
get distracted about is this.
Our program actually
ran a little bit.
So when you look at a
traceback, look right above it
and make sure-- and maybe
you won't see any output--
but maybe your program
will look partially run.
And so don't immediately assume
the program is totally broken.
So this is actually
successful output of one
of the many from lines.
And it dies later.
So as we debug it, we'll
come up with techniques
to figure out how
much your program has
done before it
died, because that
might be an important
question to answer.
How far did your program get?
Because if it dies
before the first line
or on the first line,
that's something
different than if it goes
like, 300 lines and then dies.
If it goes a long ways,
300 lines and then dies,
maybe there's something
subtle or weird about the line
it's dying on rather than just
your program is totally broken.
So look for this.
Look for something where your
program actually partially
worked, and it helps you narrow
down your suspicions as to what
might be wrong with it.
So let's get on with
the programming.
And so I will simply steal this.
I'll cut and paste it.
And that'll be that.
So I'm going to cut and paste
this into my Text Wrangler.
Now, it's always dangerous
cutting and pasting.
But I'm cutting and
pasting from a slide which
seems to work a little better
than cutting and pasting
from PDFs.
You can even get away with
cutting and pasting with PDFs
as long as you don't freak out
when the first thing you see
is a bunch crazy syntax
errors because of characters
being coded improperly.
Synonymous file.
And I'm going to save this.
Save As.
And I'll put this on my
Desktop in the Lists folder.
And we'll call this
day of the week dot py
in the Lists folder.
Of course, it's sync
text colored it,
which makes my Text Wrangler
sync text colored it.
And so sitting in
this Lists folder,
I've got the data
of the week dot py.
And one of the things
that we've got to do
is we've actually got
to get our data files.
See this mbox.short.txt?
So the mbox.short.txt is
sitting here on PythonLearn.com.
I'll go to the Book page.
And you'll see this, all
the stuff in code samples,
including maybe a worked
version of this example.
You just never know.
It doesn't look like
this one's here.
But the file I'm looking
for is mbox.short.txt.
So there it is.
It's a mailing thing.
And here's one of those
lines that we're looking at.
And there's many of them.
This happens to be the
first line in the file.
So I'm going to make sure that
I save this into the folder.
Go back to my desktop.
And put it in Lists
and then Save it.
And so at that point, I should
be able to go back and see,
ah ha.
I have mbox.short.txt.
Now, the interesting thing
is if you read this file--
if you open this file-- Text
Wrangler's perfectly happy.
So we see from.
So if I was to do
a search, and I'm
going to search for the
string capital From space.
And then I'm going
to search next.
Oh, there's lots of them.
I'm going to make
them case sensitive.
So get only the Froms
that are case sensitive.
Oh.
There we go.
And so in a sense, our
program is doing this little
from where it's looking.
It's throwing away all
the lines except those
that start with
From and a space,
because the way the split
works, and then it's
going to pull these days
of the week, these Fridays.
If I was doing it by
hand, I'd be like,
find the line that
starts with From blank
and then grab this little text.
And that's what
I'm interested in.
Maybe I'm curious
as to whether or not
these folks work on the
weekends or on the weekdays,
and that's the purpose of this.
So I'll close this.
Close document.
There we go.
So here's my little program.
I can get rid of this now.
So now I'm going to
go to my desktop.
I'm in my home
directory, cd Desktop.
cd lists.
If I do ls, there I am.
I've got this day
of the week Python
program and mbox.short.txt
sitting here.
So I'm going to run it.
And there it works.
Well, works.
For some value of work.
So we get the same
traceback the lecture
slide suggested we would.
And thankfully,
that probably means
the lecture slide is right.
So here we go.
We got this one thing where the
day of the week is coming out
and then it dies on line five.
And it even gives us
the line it's dying on.
So it's complaining about
list index out of range.
And you might be
able stare at this,
and maybe you have
enough skill already
that you're seeing
these kinds of errors
and you just right away
know what the problem is.
But that's not so much fun.
So here I am in
line five, right?
I'm going to go
right to line five.
And so the first thing I
want to do on line five
is I often add a
print statement right
before the line that's dying.
And I'll just print
out something.
Something random.
Sometimes I'll print
the letter A out.
And so now I'll save this.
And now I'm going
to run it again.
And this tells me just by
putting a print statement
in what's going on here.
It's like, OK.
Wait a sec.
This is the good line.
I mean, this is the
line I'm interested in.
As a matter of fact, I'm going
to make another change just
to help me visually
see what's going on.
I'm going put a
bunch of equal signs
at the beginning of
this line and now I'm
going to run it again.
And so if I look,
it's like, oh, dude.
That's the good line.
That's the line I'm liking.
And here's my debugging.
Something random.
So a lot of stuff
is going on here.
And then finally, it dies.
So finally it dies here.
Now, it's line six
because I added a line.
So perhaps instead of
printing out something random,
I'll print something useful.
So the first thing
to do is to look
at this statement,
the one that's dying,
and say what is the most
suspicious thing in here?
And so something's going
wrong with this word subzero.
It's saying index out of range.
Something's gone wrong
with the word subzero.
So what's the deal?
So I'm not going to
print out word subzero.
I'm going to print out words.
I'm going say, what is in
this words list at this point?
So now let me Save that.
So instead of me printing
something random,
we'll see a bunch
of words go by.
And so here's that
first line broken
into words, where, from,
Stephen Marquard, Saturday.
And here's our good line.
And then here's one that doesn't
have from as the first word,
so we skip it.
Here's one that doesn't.
So let's continue on.
We see lots of lines.
Everything's cruising along.
We actually see one
that says From colon,
but that's not what
we're looking for,
so that one gets skipped, too.
So make sure you skip that.
Now here we are.
Here's the words.
Here's that list of
words that we've split.
Now, this was line before.
Here's the next line.
It's like, OK.
Now what's going on here?
That looks like an empty list.
So I'm a little more curious.
I'm going to print
line out, too.
And just so I know
what's going on,
I'll stick a couple
pluses in front of that.
So the line will have pluses
on it and it'll print the word.
So let's run this again.
So I'm adding junk
to this, right?
So now if I look at
my things, the pluses
mean that's the line I'm seeing.
I just put those pluses
in so I can visually
see it more naturally.
That's the line.
And you can see how nicely
it breaks it into words.
So it breaks this
line at the space.
Sorry.
That was not so good.
It breaks this line, spam
probability line, at the space
and gives me two words.
So here we go.
Two.
There we go.
Here's the space.
And then it breaks into
one word and another word.
And so that's working.
But if I look here, that's
the line that I'm on.
Oh, well, that's a blank line.
Hang on a sec.
So let's just real quick take
a look at that file again.
Let's look at that file.
And so here we go.
Here we go.
So that's cool.
That's cool.
Let's look at the line.
And here we go.
So if you look, the last thing
that we read successfully
was this line right here.
This line is a blank line.
So our program is
choking on blank lines.
It's not failing on
lines that work right
and it's not failing on lines
that don't have From in them.
It can handle the
From line fine.
It can handle any
other line fine.
But it freaks out
on the simplest
of things, blank lines.
So the question is,
how do we fix this?
How do we deal with this fact
that this bit of code right
here is dying whenever
there's a blank line?
So the way we do this is what's
called the guardian pattern.
I'm going to get rid of this.
So one of the guardian
patterns looks like this.
So we don't want to get to this.
So we want to put
something in front of it
to make sure we never hit it
in the dangerous situation.
So it's if hm hm hm
something continue.
We'll call this thing
the safety check.
If some safety check continue.
So that means that if
the safety check matches,
we're going to not fall through
and not do this dangerous line.
So the question is what would we
put in as the safety check here
to protect?
This line is guarding this line.
That's what the
guardian pattern means
is do something before the
scary thing that hurts you.
So one thing we can do is we
can say, OK, well, what's words?
Well, words is an empty list.
You know what?
If I got an empty list of words,
I have no interest in this.
So if I say words is equal
to an empty list, continue.
So what this basically
says is read the line,
strip it, split it into
words, we'll print it.
If it's an empty list, continue
and go up to the next line.
And then if it is
a nonempty list,
it continues here and checks to
see if the first word is From.
And if it is not, it continues.
And then if it works, it works.
So this line here is
the guardian line.
It's guarding this other line.
And you got to do it in
order if you do the guardian.
You have to have
the guardian happen
before the line in question.
So now let's run it.
Oops.
Let's run it.
And now it works great.
We got a little too much
crap, so we better get rid
of this print statement.
It didn't give me
a traceback, right?
So now I'm going to get rid
of that print statement.
And look at that.
I'm getting the line.
Saturday.
Friday.
Thursday.
So it doesn't look like
these people work weekends,
but it does look like they
like finishing up stuff
toward the end of the week.
So there we go.
I mean, it's not much data
to conclude anything solidly.
Maybe if we look at the
bigger mailbox file,
we can find something else.
So now it works.
Let me show you a
couple of other things
that you could have used
as a guardian pattern.
So we could say if the words
we got back as an empty list,
I could say if the number
of elements in words
is less than 1, continue.
So that basically says, look,
if the words that I got,
if I got fewer than
one word, then I'm
not going to look
for the first word
because that's quite dangerous.
So if I run that,
it again works.
Another more direct, even
potentially more direct,
would be-- let's
move this up-- I
could say if line is equal
to empty string, continue.
So now what it says is if
I'm going a blank line,
I'm not even going to
bother splitting it
because I know exactly
what's going to happen.
So let's see if this works.
So this one works as well.
So now I've got a couple
of code pass-through here.
If the blank line.
I do it after the strip to
make sure it is really empty.
I skip blank lines this way.
I come all the way
down and split,
and then skip lines that don't
start with From this way.
And the only way I make it
all the way down to here
is if it is a non-blank line
and if the first word is a From.
And then I do my thing.
And so that basically is the
notion of the guardian pattern.
And the pattern
is simply if there
is some code that might have a
problem depending on, perhaps,
user input, put
something in before it
that makes sure that you never
get to the dangerous code.
And don't use a try
except for this.
That just would be tacky,
tacky, tacky, tacky.
So that's the end of
this presentation.
So thanks a lot.
And see you on the--