Hello, welcome to one
of our Worked Exercises
for the Python for Informatics
Exploring Information book.
I'm Charles Severance,
and I'm your host
for this Worked Exercise.
As always, this material is
copyright Creative Commons
Attribution and you're
welcome to use it.
So in using these
exercises, don't just
start using these
exercises because they
make everything too easy.
Part of the idea of
a book is that we
start with some easy exercises
and you stretch your skills
with those easy exercises, and
then the exercises get harder.
And if you take all of
the scaffolding, all
of he supporting materials
that we give you,
and take the easy way through
the exercises at the beginning,
then the harder exercises
will be so much harder
that you'll have less
of a chance to make it.
So these early exercises
are designed to be easy.
Try to use these exercise
videos as the last way out.
OK?
This exercise assumes that
you have Python installed,
that you've installed your
text editor, your NotePad
or TextWrangler, or
whatever one you like.
Please set tab expansion,
that's my little advertisement.
You learned a little bit about
how to use the Command Line
Interface, how to
create directories,
how to navigate
directories, and then
how to run Python in the
Command Line Interface,
interactively and interactively.
And then how to use
your text editor
to edit and run Python program.
So if you haven't
done that, please
go to www.pythonlearn.com and
click on the appropriate links
to get that all taken care.
So this is the first exercise
that we are going to do.
In this particular
exercise, and it's
a variation on the classic
first program, where
we ask the user for their
name and we print out
a simple welcome.
So let's go ahead and
get started on that.
So I've got some
things in my dock
to quickly start Text
Wrangler, and let
me make this size a
little bit different,
and also a terminal window
and I'll do my Python running
in this terminal window.
Of course I'm doing
this on a Macintosh
and I'm sorry about that.
Hopefully you'll be
able to translate,
and then in those
first exercises,
I'll try to tell you what would
be different on a Windows box.
So of course on Windows, this
terminal is your command line.
Many of the commands are
different, some are similar,
I'll tell you about them.
And here's Text Wrangler and so
the first thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to make a
folder on my desktop.
I'm going to call that
folder py4inf and then I'm
going to make in
that folder, I'm
going to make another
folder called, let's not,
I'm not going to
make this folder.
So I'm going to make
a Python program
in py4inf called welcome.
So I'm not going to write
the program even though it's
only two lines long.
I'm going to write the
program that I know works
and I'm going to make sure that
I can get my Python to work.
And so this is sort
of inner development,
even if this is a
simple two line program,
I'm going to start with
a one line program.
And I will go into my desktop
and find the folder py4inf.
And I'm going to save this
file as howdy, howdy.py.
Also the thing
that you'll notice
is that now that I've
saved it with a py suffix,
my text editor is smart
enough to detect coloring,
so note that print
is a reserved word,
and hello world is a string.
So if I, for example,
just made a mistake
and I said hello
space world, it would
notice that the string stopped
and so this is helping me
with the pink to
know what's going on.
So let me save this,
I just saved it.
So I'll do a File, Save, command
S is my shortcut for that.
And if I look at my
py4inf it's sitting there.
Now in my command line, I have
to go into the desktop folder,
I did that cdd tab,
and then to py4
and then tab because
it does tab completion.
And then in Windows
you would type dur,
but in Unix we will type lx.ls.
Now to run it in Windows, you
would do something like c:/
Python two five Python.
OK, this is not Windows so I'm
just going to type Python howdy
and I'm typing how Tab.
You get used to these things.
So now I'm going to run it
and it says hello world.
So here's the output
of my application.
Another quick thing
in terminals is
you can hit the up arrow,
watch and I'll run it again
by hitting Enter.
So that you don't have to
keep typing over and over,
even in Windows it's a
little yucky type this thing,
but you just type it once and
then hit up arrow and enter, up
arrow and enter, you can
do it over and over again.
OK so now let's write our
first program and, what's
that program supposed to look
like again, enter your name.
OK.
So we are going to use
the raw input function.
I'm going to put my
variable called lmnop.
That Is a very
bad variable name,
it's a very non-numeric
name but it's
to emphasize that
it's a variable.
Raw input is the
function that takes
as its parameter,
as an argument,
enter your name
close parentheses.
So now I'm going
to save this file,
I'll just leave the Hello
World in here, save the file,
also I'll be sure
to cut save, and now
I'm going to run it again.
Just say Python, howdy.py.
Oops, that's not
what I was expecting.
It's complaining that I have
an end of line, well, EOL,
end of line, while
scanning string letter.
Boy, this is turning out to
be harder than I thought.
Oh but look here, to
the pink parentheses?
I forgot my quote, close
quote and I'll save that.
I'll use cursor up
to run it again.
Enter your name.
Now that doesn't look so good.
See how it's jamming to
enter your name there?
Was I supposed to
put a colon there?
I was supposed to put
a colon and a space.
OK, so let's take a look.
I need to put a
colon in the space
there so let's go back
here, colon and a space
and that will make this look
a little prettier when I save
the file, and I run it again.
Enter your name, Chuck.
Now it works, OK.
Let's make this a little bit
bigger so we're seeing it.
OK but now it's not
saying Hello World,
it needs to say Hello Chuck.
Now Python when you're
putting things together
with a comma on
a print statement
it actually adds the
space for you, so.
We won't add space
inside the string,
we could add a space
inside the string
but then we'd get two spaces.
And I'm just going to put
the variable named lmnop.
Now I'll save that.
There we go and it works.
Now what if I made
a mistake here?
Let's just make another
mistake, I should probably
make more mistakes.
I'm going to call it
lmnoq instead of lmnop.
So if kind of works,
but blammo, in line two,
lmnoq is not defined
because this variable,
I put it in lmnop as
the variable name,
but then I pulled it back out,
of lmnoq is the variable name.
I can look at the line numbers.
Look down here--
this is the line m
and then I can quickly
go find the line.
OK?
So let's go fix that lmnop, save
it again, cursor up, run it,
enter your name, Chuck, works.
So now I've got this
particular sign.