Hello.
And welcome to yet another
worked exercise from Python
for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
My name is Charles Severance.
And I'm your exercise coach.
I'm your personal trainer,
your personal assistant.
Welcome to the software
development gym.
This material, of course, is
copyright Creative Commons
as is the textbook as well.
So just make sure when
you're using these exercises
that you're using them properly.
Particularly if you've
taken this class
and you have an assignment
that includes this exercise,
you probably should
try it first.
I mean, these
exercises are there so
that you learn the material.
And if you just sort of take
the crutch every time then
you won't learn to do
things on your own.
So enough of that lecturing.
Other details you can
get from Pythonlearn.com.
So today, we're
contemplating exercise 6.9.
And our goal is
to write some code
to parse lines that start with
this something blah, blah,
blah, blah, colon.
And then we're going to
chop off the second half
and convert to
floating point number.
In a later chapter
we'll do this in a loop.
But for now, we're just
going to like hack one line
and just see what it looks like.
OK.
And so this one's
kind of a silly one,
but we'll do it anyway.
So this one, let's grab this
string while we're at it
and start up TextWrangler.
The last exercise
is still there.
I started TextWrangler and I'll
start the terminal program.
From the terminal program,
I'll go to my desktop.
I'll go to Python for
Informatics folder.
And I'll paste that string in.
And I'm just going to
call my string x for now.
And I'll put this in a string.
Later, you'll be reading
this from a file.
But this exercise is not to
read anything from a file.
This exercise is just
parse to that string.
So it's going pretty simple.
We'll print x just for yucks.
We could make it
so it would prompt
for this string in a loop
or something like that,
but we'll leave that for now.
We're just going to-- our job
is just hackin' and slashin'.
So the first thing
we're going to do
is we're going to use the find
function in the string library.
Great.
Make a variable call position.
And we're going to
say x dot find colon.
It's like where
is that colon at?
Print position.
And we're going to save
this guy as spamchop.py.
And of course,
the colors change.
And we do it in a list.
And here's spamchop.py.
So I say Python spamchop.py.
An again, there's no input here.
Let's run that again.
Python spamchop.py.
So there we go.
So that basically says that
the position of this letter
is the position 18.
So the next thing
we're going to do
is we're going to
just sort of say OK.
Let's chop off the first part.
Print x.
We're going to use string
slicing, pos colon, which
says start at position
and move to the end.
So I'll save that
one and I'll run it.
And that looks pretty close.
We got rid of most of it, but
we still don't have the colon.
So we got to chop off one after
the position of the colon.
We actually are not
interested in the colon.
So we just add one here.
And then go, spamchop.
Now, we're going to see if
the float cares about this.
I don't think so,
but we'll find out.
num equals float.
And I'm just going to
say x of position plus 1
because I can give it an
expression here to the end.
And see what happens.
Print num.
So what do you think
is going to happen?
Think it's going to work?
Think it's going to blow up?
Think these spaces at the front
are going to freak it out?
Let's find out.
No.
The spaces don't freak it out.
So we now have a number.
And if I did a
print of type, just
to be sort of like
obsessively compulsive,
you could say num
comma type of num.
And so proven to me, and I
can comment these guys out.
We don't really need
those guys anymore.
And that is a
floating point number.
And it's all parsed,
and it's cool.
I mean, it's pretty simple.
Right?
You go find where this thing
is, advance one character
beyond it, and
then slice it out.
Simple enough.
Thanks for your time.