Hello and welcome to Chapter 6.
This chapter, we're going
to talk about strings.
And stuff is going to
start to get real now.
So as always, this material,
this video, these slides,
and what are copyright
Creative Commons attribution.
I want you to use
these materials.
I want to make more teachers.
So everyone can
teach this stuff.
Use it however you like.
OK, so we've been playing with
strings from the beginning.
I mean, literally, if we
didn't work with strings,
we could have never
printed "Hello, World."
And Lord knows we need
to print Hello, World
in a programming language.
And so, we've been using
them, especially constants.
Now in this chapter,
we're going to dig in.
Oops.
So a string is a
sequence of characters.
You can either use single quotes
or double quotes in Python
to delimit a string.
And so, here's two string
constants, hello and there,
and stuck into the variables
stir one and stir two.
We can concatenate them
together with a plus sign.
Python is smart enough to look
and say, oh, those are strings.
I know what to do with those.
And you'll notice that the plus
doesn't add any space here.
Because when we print
"Bob" out, hello and there
are right next to one another.
If for example, when
we're, like, reading
pay and rate and
hours and stuff,
we've done some conversions.
So this an example of a string
1-2-3, not 123, but the string,
quote, "123," quote.
And we can't add 1 to this.
We get a traceback.
We're kind of at this
point, as we expected.
And we would convert
that to an integer,
using the INT function
that's built in.
See how much Python
you already know?
I mean, this is awesome, right?
I can just say, oh, you
call the INT function,
and you know what that is.
Sorry, I'm just awesomed out.
So you convert
this to an integer.
And then, you add 1 to it.
And then, we get 124.
So there you go.
We've been doing strings
all along, had to.
I mean, literally,
strings and numeric data
are the two things that
programs deal with.
So we've been reading
and converting.
Again, this is a pattern from
some of the earlier programs
where we do a raw input.
And the raw input
just takes a string
and puts it in a variable.
So if I take "Chuck," then the
variable contains the string
C-H-U-C-K. Even if we type
numbers, that is a string.
Just because I put 1-0-0 in,
I still can't subtract 10.
We get a happy little traceback.
Oh, happy, little,
sad faced traceback.
But of course, if we convert
it INT or Float or something
like that, we can do
that and subtract 10.
And we can do that.
So we've been doing
this for a while.
We've been doing strings
and manipulating strings
and converting
strings all along.
So the thing we're
going to start doing now
is we're going to
dive into strings.
We realize that strings
are addressable at
a character-by-character basis.
And we can do all kind
of cool things with that.
And so, a string is a
sequence of characters.
And we can look inside them,
using what we call the index
operator, the square brackets.
And we've seen square
brackets in lists.
And you'll see that
they're similarities
between lists of numbers.
And in effect, a string
as a special kind of
list of characters.
So we take the string "banana."
The first character starts at 0.
So we call this operator, "sub."
So letter equals fruit sub 1.
And that is the
second character.
Now, this may seem
a little weird
that the first character is
a 0 and the second character
is a 1.
It actually is similar
to the old elevator thing
where, in Europe, the first
floor is zero, and then
negative one, and the
second floor is one.
All right.
It's kind of the same thing.
Actually, it turns out that
internally 0 is a better way
to start than 1.
You'll get used to it.
And then after a while, there's
some little cool advantages
to it.
But for now, just
beginning at 0.
It is the rule.
Just remember it.
OK, so the 0 is B,
the 1 is A, the 2
is N, et cetera, et cetera.
And we call this
syntax "fruit sub 1."
OK, so that is the sub
1 character of fruit.
And then, that is
an A. So that fruit
sub 1 says, look up in
banana, find the 1 position,
and give me what's
in that 1 position.
That's what the sub.
And what's inside these
brackets can be an expression.
So if we set N to 3, N minus
1, well, that'll compute to 2.
And then, fruit sub
2 is the letter N.
All right?
So that's fruit sub 2.
It's the third
character, fruit sub 2.
So the index starts at 0.
We read the brackets as sub,
fruit sub 1, fruit sub 2.
Now, Python will complain to
you if you use this sub operator
too far down the string.
Here is a character with
3, which is 0, 1, and 2.
And if we go to
sub 5, it blows up.
Now you know, by now, I hope
that you're not freaking out
about traceback errors.
Remember, traceback
errors are just
Python trying to inform you.
And if we just stop looking
at that as mean Python face
and instead look at that
as, oh, index error.
String index out of range.
Oh yeah, I stuck a 5 in there.
And there's only 3.
Ugh, my bad, thank you, Python.
Appreciate it.
Thanks for the help.
So think of this like--
it's not a smiley face.
But it's kind of like
a quizzical face.
Right, it's saying, eh, I
don't So Python is confused,
and it's trying to tell
you what is confused.
OK?
So don't look at
these as sad faces.
Python doesn't hate you.
Python loves you,
and loves me too.
So strings have
individual characters
that we can address
with the index operator.
They also have length.
And there is a built-in
function called Len
that we can call and pass in
as a parameter, the variable,
or a constant.
And it will tell us
how many characters.
Now, this banana has
six characters in it
that are 0 through 5.
So don't get a little confused.
The last character is sub 5, but
it's also the sixth character.
So the length is
really the length.
It's not length minus 1.
So Len is like a
built-in function.
It's not a function
we have to write.
As we talk about in
the functions chapter,
there are things that
are part of Python that
are just sitting there.
And so, we are passing
banana, the variable fruit,
into function, and then
into the Len function.
Then, Len-- shhh--
does magic stuff.
And then, out comes the answer.
And that 6 replaces this.
And then, the 6 goes into the
variable X. And so X is 6.
I sure made that a
messy looking slide.
And so, think of inside
the Len function.
There's a Def Len.
It takes a parameter,
does sound loopy things.
And it does its thing.
So it's a function that we might
write, except we don't have to.
Because it's already written
and built into Python.
OK, so that's length
of the string.
That's getting it
individual characters.
We can also loop
through strings.
Obviously, if we can
use the index operator
and we can put a variable in
there, we can write a loop.
This is an indefinite loop.
So we have this variable fruit.
It has the string banana in it.
We set the variable index to 0.
We make a little wild loop.
And we ask, as long as index is
less than the length of fruit--
now remember, the length
of fruit is going to be 6.
But we don't want to make
that less than or equal to,
because then we would crash.
Because the last character is 5.
We can say, letter is
equal to fruits sub index.
So that's going to start
out, index is going to be 0.
So that's fruit sub 0.
Then, we print index and letter.
So that means the first
time through the loop,
we're going to see 0B.
Then, we increment our iteration
operator, and we go up.
And then, we come up with 1A.
And index advances
until index is 6,
but has printed out
each of the letters.
Now, we're not doing this
just to print them out.
We will do something a little
more valuable inside that loop.
But this gives the sense that
we can work through a loop,
just like we can work
through a string,
just like we work through
a list of numbers.
Now, that was how you do
it with an indefinite loop.
In a definite loop, it's
just far more awesome.
OK, just like we did
with the list of numbers,
Python understands strings and
allows us to write four loops,
using 4 and N that go
through the strings.
So basically, for letter
in fruit-- now remember,
I'm using letter as a
pneumatic variable here.
It's just a wise choice
of a variable name.
So that says, run this
little block of text
once for each letter
in the variable fruit.
Which means that letters are
going to take on the successive
B-A-N-A-N-A. When
I look at that,
I always worry that
I misspelled it.
I think I got these right.
If I rewrite this
book, I'm not going
to use banana as the example.
Because I'm terrified
that I misspelled banana.
Because I don't know how
many N's banana has in it.
But be that as it may,
we are abstracting.
We are letting Python say, run
this little block of text once,
in order for each of the
letters in the variable fruit,
which is B-A-N-A. And so, it
prints out each of the letters.
So this is a much prettier
version of the looping.
So using the definite, the
For keyword instead of the
While keyword.
And so, we can just
compare these two things.
They kind of do the
exact same thing.
And it also gives you a sense
of what the For is doing for us.
The For is setting
up this index.
The For is looking
up inside of fruit.
And the For is
advancing the index.
So the For is doing a
bunch of work for us.
And I've characterize that
in the previous lecture,
how the For is doing a
bunch of things for us.
And it allows our code
to be more expressive.
And so, a lot of this is
just got a bookkeeping crap,
that we don't really need.
And so the For loop
helps us by doing
some of the bookkeeping for us.
OK, so we can do all
those loop idioms.
We can find the largest
letter, the smallest letter,
how many times, how
many N's in this,
or how many A's are in this.
And so, this is a simple
counting pattern and a looking
pattern.
And so, our word is "banana."
Our count is 0.
For the letter in word, again--
boop-boop-boop-boop-boop--
that comes out like that.
So it's going to run
this little block.
If the letter is A,
add 1 to the count.
So this is going to
basically print out,
at the end, the number
of A's in banana.
It would probably be more
useful for me to print out
the number of N's in banana.
Because I never know how
many N's are in banana.
But it looks like there's
supposed to be two.
Or otherwise, I have
a typo on this slide.
So that "In," again,
I love that In.
I just absolutely love this In.
I love this syntax, this For
each letter In the word banana.
Just to me, it
reads very smoothly.
Cognitively, it fits in
my mind what's going on.
For each letter in banana,
run this little indented block
of text.
Again, very pretty.
I love In.
It's one of my favorite
little pieces of Python.
So again, with the For, it
takes care of all the iteration
variables for us.
And it goes through
the sequence.
And so, here's an animation.
Remember that the For is going
to do all this work for us.
Letter is going to advance
through the successive letters
in banana.
So letter is being moved
for us by the For statement.
OK?
So that's looping through.
Now, it turns out there's
a lot of common things
that we want to do
that are already
built into Python for us.
Clear the old screen there.
We call these "slicing."
So the index operator looks
up various things in a string.
But we can also
pull substrings out,
using the colon in addition
to the square brackets.
Again, this is called "slicing."
So the colon
operator, basically,
takes a starting position
and, then, an ending position.
But the ending position
is up-to but not including
the second one.
So it's up-to,
but not including.
Up-to but not including,
just like the 0,
you get used up pretty quick.
But the first time you see
it, it's a little bit wonky.
So if we're going 0 through 4,
that's how I read this print.
S sub 0 through 4, or--
better said-- S, 0, up-to
but not including 4.
That is, print me out
the chunk that is up-to
but not including 4.
So it doesn't include 4.
And so, out comes "mont."
All right?
So the next one is 6
up-to but not including 7.
So it starts at 6, up-to
but not including 7.
So out comes the P. And
even though you might expect
that it would traceback
on this, here's
a moment where Python
is a little forgiving,
saying, I'll give
you a break here.
If you go 6 up-to
but not including 20,
I'll just stop at the
end of the string.
So 6 to the end.
So you can over-reference
here, and you
won't get yourself in trouble.
So that comes out "python."
So again, the second character
is up-to but not including.
And that's the kind
of weird thing there.
Of course, once you remember
that the first character is 0,
0 up-to but not including.
Nice.
If we leave off the first or the
last number, and both of them,
they mean the beginning and
end of the string respectively.
And so, up-to but
not including 2,
is M-O. 8 colon means starting
at 8 to the end of the string.
So that's "thon."
And then, that means the
beginning to the end.
And so, it's just the whole
string, "monty python."
Now, we've already played
with string concatenation.
Just the thing to emphasize here
is the concatenation operator
does not add a space.
If you want a space,
you explicitly add it.
So here, there's no space
in between the O and the T.
But here, there is a space
between the O and the T,
because we explicitly added it.
So you can concatenate
more than one thing.
And you add your
spaces as you want.
Another thing you can do
is you can ask questions
about a string.
It's sort of like doing a string
look up, using the In operator.
This a little different than how
we use it inside of a For loop.
This is a logical
operation asking
a question like less-than
or greater-than or whatever.
So here's an expression.
So fruit is banana as always.
Is N in fruit?
And the answer is, yes, it is.
True.
So this is a logical operation.
It's a question.
It's like True or False.
Is M in fruit?
No, False.
And this can be a string,
not just a single character.
Is N-A-N in fruit?
The answer is True.
And you can put parts of
Ifs, et cetera, et cetera.
So this is a logical expression
that can be on an If.
You can have a While,
et cetera, et cetera.
So it's a logical expression
and it returns True or False.
You can also do comparisons.
Now, the comparison operations--
Equals makes a lot of sense.
Less-than and Greater-than
depend on the language
that you're using, Python.
And so, if you're using a
Latin character set, then
alphabetical matters, the
way the Latin character set
would do.
But if you're in a
different character set,
Python is aware of
multiple character sets
and will sort strings based
on the sorting algorithm
of a particular character set.
So you can do comparisons
like Equality, Less-than,
and Greater-than.
And we've seen some things in
previous lectures actually.
We've had to use them.
So in addition to these
fundamental operations that we
can do on strings, there's
an extensive library
of built-in
capabilities in Python.
And so, the way we see these
built-in capabilities are
they're actually
built into strings.
So let's go real slow here.
Here, we have a
variable called "greet,"
and we're sticking the
string "Hello, Bob" into it.
Now Greet is of type
string, as a result of this.
And it contains Hello,
Bob as its value.
But we can actually
access capabilities inside
of this value.
So we can say Greet
dot lower parentheses.
This is calling something
that's part of Greet itself.
It's a part of all strings.
The fact that Greet
contains a string means
that we can ask
for, hey, give me
Greet, which just gives you
back what you're looking for.
Like here, print
Greet as Hello, Bob.
Or you could say,
give me Greet lower.
So this doesn't convert
it to lowercase.
It gives me a lowercase
copy of Hello, Bob.
So Zap is hello,
bob, all lowercase.
Now, it didn't change Greet.
Right?
And you could even put this Dot
Lower on the end of constants.
Why you'd do this, I don't know.
But Hi There, with H and
T capitalized, dot lower
comes out as hi there.
So this bit is part
of all strings.
Both variables and constants
have these string functions
built into them.
And every instance of
a string-- whether it
be a variable or a constant--
has these capabilities.
They don't modify it.
They just give you back a copy.
Now, it turns out there is a
command inside Python called
Dir to ask questions like, hey!
Well, here's stuff.
We got Hello, World.
We can say-- oh, I
want to redo this,
come here-- stuff as a string.
We can ask, hey, what are you?
I am a string.
Dir is another built in Python
that asks the question, hey,
what are all the things that
are built into this that I
can make use of?
And here they are.
That's kind of a
raw dump of them.
You can also go look at the
online documentation of Python.
And at the Python
website, you can see
a whole bunch of these things.
And they have the
calling sequence, what
the parameters are, et cetera.
So when you're looking
these things up,
you can go read about them.
Here's just a few
that I pulled out,
Capitalize-- which upper case
is the first characters--
Center, Endswith, Find.
There's Stripping.
So I'll look through a couple of
these, just the kind of things
to be looking for.
It would be a good
idea to take a look
and read through
some of the things.
Here's a couple that we'll
probably be using early on.
The Find function,
it's similar to In.
But it tells you where it finds
the particular thing that's
looking for.
And so, we'll put
fruit is banana.
And I'm going to
say, Pause-- which
is going to be integer
variable-- equals fruit
dot Find N-A. So
what it's saying is,
go look inside this
variable fruit.
Hunt until you find the first
occurrence of the string N-A.
Hunt-hunt-hunt-hunt, whoop!
Got it.
--and then, return it to me.
So that's going
to give me back 2.
2 is where it found it, right?
So where is it in the string?
That's what Find does.
And if you don't find anything--
like, you're looking for Z.
Nn-nn-nn-nn-na, I
didn't find a Z. Then,
it gives me back negative 1.
So again, this is just one
of many built-in functions
in string, the ability
to find a substring
or find a character or
string within another string.
There's a lowercase.
There's also an uppercase.
This might be better
named "Shouting."
Upper means, give
me an uppercase copy
of this variable.
So Hello Bob, becomes HELLO BOB!
And then lower is hello, bob.
Right?
So these are both
ways to get copies
of uppercase and
lowercase versions.
You might think these
are kind of silly.
But one of the things
we tend to use lower for
is if you're doing searching
and you want to ignore case,
you convert the whole
thing to lowercase.
And then, you switch
for a lowercase string.
So it depends if you want
to ignore case or not.
So that's one of the reasons
that you have things like this.
There is a Replace function.
Again, it doesn't
change the value.
Greet is going to
have Hello, Bob.
And I'm going to say, Greet dot
Replace all occurrences of Bob
with Jane.
That gives me back a copy and
End STIR says, Hello, Jane.
So Greet is unchanged.
This Replace says, make a copy.
And then, make that following
edit that we requested.
Now, the replace is going
to do all occurrences.
So Greet is still Hello, Bob.
This is kind of redundant here.
I'm just doing it so
you remember what it is.
Greet is still Hello, Bob.
I put Hello, Bob back in it.
And Replace all the
occurrences of lowercase
O with uppercase X.
And then, that happens.
So this says, go through
the whole string--
tch-tch-tch-tch-tch--
doing all those Replace.
OK?
Now, another common thing
that we're going to have to do
is we're going to have to
throw away white space.
Sometimes, you
have a string that
has blank characters or other
characters at the beginning
and the end,
non-printable characters.
And we can strip them.
And there's three
functions that are
built into Python strings
that do this for us.
There is Lstrip, which
strips from the left.
There is Rstrip, which
strips from the right--
so throws away
these white spaces.
So Hello, Bob is gone.
So it gets rid of
these characters.
Oops.
These are the ones that
are gotten rid of there.
I need an eraser.
Oh, let's use white.
And then, Strip basically gets
rid of all the white space,
both on the left and the right
side and gets rid of that.
So we're going to be
using these a lot.
One of the things you tend to do
in Python is cleaning up data.
Sometimes, if you have spaces
at the beginning or the end,
you just want to ignore them.
So you strip them off.
You throw them away.
When we're looking
for data, we sometimes
are looking for a prefix.
And there is a
Startswith function that
gives you a True or a False.
We're asking here,
does this variable line
start with the string "please?"
And the answer is True.
Yes, it does start
with the string please.
Or in the next, we ask, does
this start with the letter P?
And the answer is False.
It does not start
with the letter P. OK?
So there's lots more
of these things.
And reading data and tearing
it apart is one of the things
that we're going
to really focus on
for the rest of these first
few chapters of the book.
Because that's one thing
that Python's really good at
is tearing data into pieces
and pulling the pieces
that you want.
So let's take a
look at this line.
So this line that we've got here
is a line from an actual email
box.
If you looked at your
email on your hard drive,
email boxes would have
this kind of a format.
And there's actually many lines.
And soon, we'll be reading
whole files full of email.
But for now, let's
just say we've
got this one line somehow.
And we don't know how long
these things are going to be.
The first thing is From, then
there's an email address.
Then, there's some detail
about when the mail was sent.
But what we actually want
is this part right here.
And that's the domain
name of the mail address.
Right?
We want to extract this out.
We're faced with this
line in a variable.
And we want to extract that out.
So this is kind of putting
all these things together.
So let's walk through
how we do this.
So here's this line.
And it's a big long string.
Mostly, we would have
read this from a file
rather than just put
it in a constant.
But for now, we put
it in a constant,
because Files is
the next chapter.
And so, what we're going to
do is we're going to say,
you know what?
I'm going to look at this line.
And then, I'm going to
go find the At sign.
And I want to know
where the At sign is.
So I called Data
dot Find At sign,
and put the
resultant in At Pose.
And that gives me 21.
It hunts until it
finds the At sign,
and then tells me
where it found it.
Then, what I want to
look at is, starting here
for the rest of the string, I
want to find the first place
afterwards.
So what I say is this
SP pose is my variable
for the position of the space.
Data dot Find a blank
starting at the At.
So this is starting at 21.
So it says, I'll
start at 21, and I'll
look for the next blank.
And I find that at 31.
So now, I know where
the At sign is.
And I know where the space is.
And so, what I'm
looking at is I want
the stuff one beyond the At
sign, up-to but not including
the space.
So then, I can use
a slicing operation.
I can start at the At
position, add 1 to it.
So it advanced one.
That's going to be the letter U.
And then, a slicing operation--
up-to but not including space.
Up to-- this is going to work
out nicely all of a sudden--
but not including.
And then, I'm going to take
that slice-- which is really
this little bit of data
right here-- take that slice
and put it in the variable host.
Then, we print that out,
and we get the piece.
OK?
And so, here we have some
data we want to tear apart.
We hunt for the At.
We find it at position 21.
We start at 21.
And we look for the
space after that, 31.
And then, we pull from 22,
up-to but not including 31.
And it wouldn't matter
where this thing was.
Because these aren't
all the same length
when we start looking
at them in files.
But it would have found the At
sign and the space after the
At sign.
And it would have reliably
pulled out the host.
OK?
So this is a basic pattern
we call parsing text.
Like, find this, find
that other thing.
Grab this thing out.
Then, look inside that thing
and-- phl-sl-sl-fl-fl--
it does all these things.
So that's strings.
Up next, we have files.
Files are going to
be lots of strings.
So we're going to start putting
all these things together.
And so, the next chapter is
a really, really important
chapter where it starts to
really start coming together.
So see you soon.