Hello, and welcome to chapter
five, loops and iteration.
As always, this lecture is
copyright Creative Commons
attribution, including
the audio, and the video,
and the slides,
and the book, even.
So now we're getting to
our fourth basic pattern.
We've talked about
sequential, where
steps happen one after another.
We've talked about conditional,
where steps may or may not
happen.
In chapter four, we talked about
the store and retrieve pattern,
and now we're going to talk
about the looping pattern.
And the looping pattern is the
last of our really foundational
ones.
And it potentially is
the most important one,
because it's the thing that
allows us to get computers
to do lots of things that,
say, humans might get tired of,
but computers don't tire of.
And so after this,
we'll start becoming
a little more skilled in the
basic language capabilities.
We'll talk about strings, and
then start talking about files,
and start doing some real work
after we get done with this.
So bear with us, it's
going to be a while,
but we'll get there.
So welcome to repeated steps.
This is the example that I had
in the first lecture, chapter
one.
And the basic idea,
just to review,
is that you have
this while keyword.
The while keyword functions
like an if in that it implicitly
has a decision
that's going to make.
And it's either going to do
the code in the indented block
or or skip it, basically.
So you either do
it, or you skip it.
The difference between
the while and the if
is that it's going to do it many
times as long as this question
that we have remains true.
And so in this case, n is 5.
While n greater than zero,
functions like an if.
So yes, it's going to run it.
Prints out 5, subtracts
one, so it's four.
Goes back up and asks
the question again.
Is n still greater than zero?
Well, since it's four,
yes, we'll continue on.
Out comes four, then
n gets subtracted.
Three, two.
And then we come
through, we print one.
We subtract n to zero.
We go back up.
n is now not greater
than zero, so we come up
and we execute outside the loop.
We leave the loop.
And that really means
in the Python code,
we skip to whatever's lined
up with the while statement.
The in same indent level
as the while statement.
And so that's how it works.
And I just print n at the
end here to remind ourselves
that n ended up at zero.
Not at one.
The last thing we printed
out in the loop was the one,
but n ended up at 0.
Because this loop was
going to run as long as n
was greater than zero, so it
had to be not greater than zero
to get out the loop.
So that's basically a
review of what we've done.
Now-- oh, wait, something else.
Iteration variables.
So the key to this is these
loops can't run forever.
We don't want them
to run forever.
We want them to run as long
as we want them to run,
they may run a very long
time, but not forever.
There's got to be a
way to get out of them,
otherwise we call them
infinite loops, which we'll
talk about in the next slide.
So the iteration
variable is generally
some variable that is changing
each time through the loop,
and we are changing it by
subtracting one from it.
And so this thing is
going to keep running,
and we can pretty
much see that, oh,
this is going to exit, right?
Whatever n is.
It could be a large
number, but eventually it's
going to get to zero.
So the iteration variable
controls how many times
the loop runs,
and it also allows
us to do something
different inside the loop.
And of course, this
is like a trivia loop,
where we're just printing
the iteration variable.
But it just means that this
loop is going to run five times,
and it's going to do something
potentially different
each time.
If you just ran the loop
that did the same thing over,
and over, and over again
with no data changing,
that's dull and pointless.
So just because you have
an iteration variable
doesn't mean that you've
properly constructed your loop.
It's a common problem, or
something we want to avoid,
is an infinite loop.
And here is a carefully
constructed loop.
We start n at five
at the beginning.
We have a good question at the
end, while n greater than zero,
it's going to run this as long
as n is greater than zero.
But the problem is, we don't
change in the little block,
we don't change the n.
Which means it's
going to come back,
and n is going to be five.
And that's going to run this,
and n's going to be five.
And it's going to run this,
and it's going to be five.
And so this an infinite
loop, which means this loop
will never exit.
It will never get out.
It's just going to
run forever in here,
because n's not changing.
Neither of these
statements change n.
So part of the
iteration variable
is there needs to
be something that
changes so that the loop
will ultimately make progress
to accomplish what it is
and know when to stop.
So this is an infinite loop.
And, of course, lather,
rinse, repeat is commonly
put on shampoo and conditioner.
And so you can next time
you're in the shower
take a look at your
shampoo and conditioner
and find the
infinite loop that's
on most bottles of
shampoo and conditioner.
Now here's another
loop just to emphasize
that it's possible to
structure these loops in a way
that they never run.
So this function is an if.
The while functions as an if.
And so when n is set to zero
and we ask the question,
it is literally going
to make the decision
based on n greater than zero.
Well, it is not
greater than zero,
so it's going to go
right by it over here.
It's going to come here
and go right to there,
and never run these
lines of code.
And we call this a zero
trip loop, and that's OK.
I mean, this is a
silly one, of course.
It just shows that the test,
the question that's being asked
is above the lines that make
up the body of the loop.
And if it's false,
the loop never runs.
So it's possible that these
loops have zero trips.
So that's a loop.
Now there are more than one way
to control the flow of a loop.
The basic flow of the loop is
when it gets to the bottom,
it goes back up to the
while and does the check.
This is a different way of
getting out of the loop,
or controlling the
execution of a loop.
There is a key word, or a
part of the Python language,
called-- what color do I got?
Nope, Green's over here.
Called break.
If you looked back
at reserved words,
break is one of
the reserved words.
Break says, hey, if I'm
in a loop, stop the loop.
Get out of this loop,
I'm done with this loop.
And so here's this loop.
Now the interesting
thing we've done
is I just got done talking
to you about infinite loops.
We have just constructed
an infinite loop.
Because the question is right
there, and the answer is yes,
true.
And that's a way to
construct an infinite loop.
We've done this because we have
a different way of getting out
of the loop.
So we've constructed loop
just on the face of it,
just looking at that line,
looks like an infinite loop.
So what this loop does is
it reads a line of input,
checks to see if it's the string
that we've entered as done.
And if it is, we're going
to skip out with this break
and get out of the loop.
Otherwise, we're
going to print it.
So at a high level, what
this loop is going to do
is prompt for strings of
characters until we enter done.
And that's exactly what it does.
It prompts, we say hello
there, it prints that out.
So we say finished,
it prints that out.
We say done, and it's done.
So when we say done, it comes
out and finishes the loop,
and that's the end
of the program.
So to look at this
in some more detail,
the first time it comes
in, does the raw input.
Because true is true,
so it's going to run it.
And then we entered hello there.
It checks to see what we entered
is equal to the string done.
It is not, so it skips
and it does the print.
We do this one more
time, we type finished.
And then the line is not done.
Variable line does not
have the value done in it.
So we print that.
We come in one more time.
But this time this is true.
So it goes and
executes the break,
and then it escapes the loop.
And so you can think of, here
is the body of this loop,
because that's where the
indentation starts and ends.
The break says break me out of
the current loop that I'm in
and get to that
next line that has
the same indent as the while.
So whatever it is, break says
we are done with this loop.
When that statement executes,
we are done with the loop.
We're finished with the loop.
It'll run until that
executes, because we've
got this set to be while true.
OK, so this is a simple
way to draw this.
Break is a jump to the statement
immediately following the loop.
If you really want
to picture this,
I think of this as like
a Star Trek transporter.
Where you come in to break,
and then your molecules
are sent to the four
corners of the universe,
and you reassemble
outside of the loop.
And so if we look at this
outside of my little roadmap
version of these
things, our while loop
is going to run for
awhile, yadda yadda.
There can actually be
more than one break,
as long as they only get this.
But the moment that somehow,
some if for whatever
hits the break, then
it gets out completely.
And so it escapes the loop.
And so it's like you
zoom, zoom, zoom.
You come in here,
and then you're
rematerialized outside the loop.
That's what the break does.
So break is one way to control
the execution of loops.
Now another way to
control the execution
of loops that doesn't
actually exit the loop
is called continue.
Continue basically
says, hey, I'm
done with this
iteration of the loop.
Now, each time through the
loop, we call that an iteration.
Continue says I don't
want to stop the loop,
but I want to stop the
iteration and advance
to the next iteration.
And so what we have
here is we have
the same basic loop,
a while true, which
makes this an infinite loop.
We're going to read
a line prompting
with a less than sign.
And if it's done, we're going to
break, that code is down here.
And we're going to print
it if we fall through.
So normally, we'll be
reading and printing.
And if the line is
done, we're going
to break out, that's what
we just got done doing.
But the new part is right here.
And this is-- we'll learn
this in the next chapter.
If line sub 0, if the first
character of the line,
is a pound sign, we're
going to continue.
And what continue says is it
doesn't actually get us out
of the loop, it jumps back
up to the top of the loop.
Which means that it
ignores, for that iteration,
the rest of the loop.
So if execution comes in
here and hits this line,
it goes back up to the while.
Which means that
whatever this is,
it's not coming out
of this if, it's
going back up to the white.
So continue ends is
the current iteration
and jumps to the
top of the loop,
and starts the next iteration.
And so if we look at how
the code runs, hello there.
Prints.
Pound sign with the first
character doesn't print,
so there is no print
out right here.
Print this is not done,
and we enter done,
and then the loop ends.
Now another way to draw
this is that continue jumps
to the top of the loop.
It does run the question, right?
It does check the question.
So here's another way
to draw that picture.
And so here again we have a
loop, and it's happily running,
and there can be
breaks in there,
and there could be
continues in there.
And as long as we don't
hit a break or continue,
the loop just runs and
goes up to the top.
And at some point, some
if, we hit the continue.
And like a transporter, instead
of going out of the loop,
we go to the top of the loop.
But it's important that we
go and we check the question.
So the continue is
not likely to exit
the loop unless the
question has become false.
So the continue is likely to
come up here, run some more,
then hit the continue,
it comes up here.
Oops, I did that backwards.
Run some more, clear this out.
So the continue
could run many times.
So we have the loop, loop
runs a bunch of times.
And finally we hit the continue.
Continue goes up to the top.
If it's still true, we'll
run the loop some more.
Than you might hit
the continue, then you
might go up to the
top, come down.
Round, and round,
and round, and round.
Hit the continue again, go
up to the top, yada yada.
Now in this particular
loop, this break eventually
is down here, and
that's how we get out.
So the continue goes back
up to the top of the loop.
So these loops that we
construct with the while keyword
are what we call
indefinite loops.
I mean, looking at the
ones that we've written,
which are two
lines, or six lines,
we can inspect
them and understand
when they're going to stop.
And we're going to know that
they're possible to stop them.
A loop that won't stop
as an infinite loop.
Sometimes these can
be rather complex.
And you may not actually
be able to look at them,
because they're many lines
and so we don't know.
So you have to be real
careful when you construct
these to make sure
that they stop
as things get more complicated.
Now the cousin to indefinite
loops are definite loops.
And definite loops is something
where we have a list of things,
or a set of things that
are a known set of things,
a finite set of things.
And we're going to
write a loop that's
going to go through
that set of things
and do something to each
thing in that set of things.
And the key word that we
use for this is the for.
So we use the Python
for keyword that says
we're going to write a loop.
But instead it just running
until some condition becomes
true or false, or
we hit a break,
we're actually going to
know how many times this
is going to run.
Now, you can actually use break
and continue in for loops.
We call these definite
loops, because how long
they're going to run it
is well known, basically.
So here's a simple
definite loop.
And it's like that
while loop that we just
got done looking at,
where it's counting down
and then saying blast off.
And so the way we
construct this loop is we
have the for keyword, it's
part of Python language.
The in keyword, and then we
have an iteration variable.
I've chosen i as my
iteration variable.
And basically what
we're saying is,
dear Python, run
this indented block--
and there's only one line
in the indented block.
Run it once for each of the
values in this little list.
This is a Python list.
Square brackets
make Python lists,
comma separate the values.
So it says, I would like i to
be five, then run this code.
Then I would like i to be
four, then run this code.
three, then run this code.
i should be two,
then run this code.
And i should be one,
And so this is pretty clear,
and I like this word in.
It says, doot, doot,
doot doot doot doot,
and then run this each time.
And so out of that comes
five, four, three, two, one.
And then the loop is done.
Python is doing all
the tricky bits here.
Python's figuring all
these things out for us
and handling all this,
and then we're done.
And so if you look at it, we
have an iteration variable,
but we didn't have
to increment it,
we didn't have to do anything.
Python took care of a
lot of things for us.
And so when we're looping
through known list of things,
or later when we
read a file, we're
going to loop through
the lines in the file.
And so the for loop is
a really nice, powerful,
and its syntactically cleaner.
It's really quite nice.
Now it's important to
realize that you don't have
to just loop through numbers.
I did that one with a set
of descending numbers,
so that was equivalent
to the while loop
that I started at beginning.
But this is a loop where what
it's going to loop through
is a list-- closed square
brackets are a list in Python.
This is a list of three strings,
Joseph, Glenn, and Sally.
They're string constants,
and then commas
are how we make lists.
And so friends is a
mnemonic variable.
Python doesn't know anything
about friends in particular,
but I've chosen this
variable name to be friends.
And it's a list of three
people, Joseph, Glenn and Sally.
And so I have an iteration
variable called friend,
and I'm going to loop
through this set of friends.
Now, Python doesn't know
anything about singular,
Python doesn't know
anything about plural.
I'm just choosing
these variable names
because it makes a lot of sense.
This is a set of friends,
because it has three of minute,
and this is a single friend.
What it's really
going to do is friend
is going to take on the
successive values Joseph, Glenn
and Sally, and this
little block of code
is going to run once for each
of those three items in the set.
And the variable
friend is going to take
on the successive
values of that set.
So out of this comes three lines
of print out, happy new year
Joseph, happy new year
Glenn, happy new year Sally.
Of course, this is the
i bit right over here.
But we just made it so,
hey Python, look, however
many friends there are, run
this code one time for each one.
Change this variable,
friend, to be each
of the success ones in order.
And then we print
that we're done.
OK.
So the for loop, we
go and try to make
a picture of the for loop.
The for loop's kind
of a powerful thing.
It does two things.
It decides if we're
done or not, how
do we keep going in the loop.
And as long as we
keep going, we're
going to advance the i value,
the iteration variable.
It takes care of the
responsibility of changing
the iteration variable, we do
not have to add lines of code
in that change the
iteration variable.
And so if we take a look,
we come in, are we done?
We're not done.
Set i to the right
thing, then print it.
Out comes 5, advanced
i, advance i.
Print it, advance it, print
it, advance it, print it.
Oh, now we're done.
i was not the thing that
decided when we were done.
The for loop just
keeps track internally
as i moves through these things
and goes, oh, I'm all done.
I'll take care of that.
You finished.
So there's no if in here.
It's not like, if
i equals 1, stop.
No, no.
It just says, you told
me to do five things,
I'm going to do five things,
and then we're going to stop.
And so again, the for loop
here has got two functions.
Decides how long the
loop's going to run,
and changes the
iteration variable
based on what you've told
it to in this in clause.
So I think in is a
real elegant construct.
It's just a key word, but
if you think about math,
if you're familiar
with sets, it's
like something inside
of a set of something.
I think it's a real pretty
way to think about it.
And you can think
of a little more
abstractly, that you
say, well, here's
a little indented block of code.
And I want it to run some number
of times, for each of the i
values in the set, five,
four, three, two, one.
That's how I think of it.
So I think this is a
real pretty syntax.
Different languages have
different looping syntax.
I think this is really a very
expressive, very pretty one.
So one way to think about this
picture is that the for loop
causes repeated execution, and
we're driving in this circle.
and then we stop.
The other way to
think about this
is to think about it a
little more abstractly.
To say, hm, at the end of
the day, all I'm really
telling Python is I want to
execute this block of code
five times, and I want
the variable i to change
to these three values.
So in a way, you
could think of this
as expanded is the for
loop sets it to five,
then runs your code.
The for loop then sets it
to four, runs your code.
The for loop sets it to
three, runs your code.
For loop sets it to two, runs
your code, sets it to one,
runs your code.
These two ways of looking
at it are the same
from your perspective,
because you're just
asking Python to do something.
Whether it does it this way or
whether it does it this way,
you hardly can tell
the difference.
It's probably going
to do it this way.
But logically it's
not that different.
It's not different
from doing it this way.
You're saying run
this block of, code
change i in the following way.
Cool.
It's like we don't
have to worry.
I mean, we can use mentally
either model of what's
going on inside, because
it doesn't matter,
because they're the same.
OK, so these definite
loops are really cool.
Starting in a
couple of chapters,
we'll mostly use definite
loops to go through lists,
or dictionaries, or
tuples, or files.
And so it's a finite
set of things.
It can be a large set
of things, but it's
a finite set of things.
OK.
So now I want to talk
about loop idioms.
Loop idioms are how
we construct loops.
And the loops have some
kind of a goal in mind.
Finding the largest,
we've played with that.
Finding the smallest,
counting the number of things.
Looking for lines that
start with pound signs,
something like that.
They have a high level view of
what they're supposed to do,
and then we have to build
a loop to accomplish that.
And and this goes back to how we
have to think like a computer.
We have to say, hey computer,
do this over, and over,
and over again,
and then I'll get
what I want when you've done
that over, and over again.
You have to do something
a million times.
I'm not going to
sit here and wait.
At the end, I'll
get what I want.
So I call these smart loops,
or how to build intelligence
into loops.
So for example, we want
the largest number.
But we have to
construct a loop that
will get us the largest number
thinking like a computer.
Thinking computationally
So idea is that we have
some kind of a loop,
and we're going to through
some list of things,
and this is going to
run a bunch of times.
But the way we're
going to do it is we're
going to set something up
before the loop starts,
we're going to do something
to each of the things that's
being looked at.
And at the end,
we're going to get
the result we're looking for.
And so in the
middle, it's working,
it's in the middle working.
And then here is the payoff.
The payoff is at the end when we
get the information that we're
interested in.
So I will use in the next few
examples this simple loop.
And right now, it
doesn't do much.
It does a print before, and it
has this variable thing that
goes through the successive
values of these numbers,
and it prints it out.
So that middle part says,
run this six times, once
for each of those
values, and then after.
And so we will add some
intelligence at the beginning,
we'll add some
intelligence in the middle,
and we'll add some
intelligence at the end.
And then the whole thing
will accomplish what we want.
Right now this is
not that intelligent.
So now what I want to do is
I want to review the thing
we did, and I want you to
remember what the largest
number is, and I'm
going to show you
a sequence of numbers in order.
Ready?
I'll do it quickly because
you've seen this before.
So I'm only showing you
one number at a time,
so you want to tell me
what the largest number is,
so here we go.
The first number is 9.
The second number is 41.
The third number is 12.
The fourth number is 3.
The fifth number is 74.
And the six number is 15.
So what was the largest number?
Did you have to go back, or
did you remember how to do it?
Well, I will give you a clue.
It was 74.
That's because I know.
Now if you did that,
and you had to do
that for 20 or 30
numbers, you'd have
to create a mental
algorithm in your head
to approach it and
stay concentrated.
Focused.
So you would have create a
variable in your head called
largest so far.
I would show you the first
number, which would be nine.
And you would go, well, nine
is larger than negative one,
so I will keep that.
That's the new largest I've seen
so far, that's pretty awesome.
Because it's way better
than negative one.
41, I thought nine was good.
But 41, that is a lot better.
So I'm going to keep that one.
That's the best.
It's the largest
we've seen so far.
We've only seen two numbers,
but the best we've seen so far
is 41.
So 12.
That's not larger.
Who cares about that?
It's not as big as 41, so we'll
just go right on to the next.
On to the next.
Three.
That's lame when we're
looking for large numbers.
So we skip.
Whoa, 74.
That's a rockingly large number.
So that's actually the
largest we've seen so far.
Because it's bigger than 41,
and 41 was the former champion
largest we've seen so far.
And there's 74, so
we keep that one.
I don't know how many of these
things we're going to see.
We could see lots of them.
But the next one we see 15.
Well, that's no good.
We got 74 already, 74 is,
like, totally awesome.
So now, oh, we're done.
So hey, we're done.
And so 74 is the champion.
That is the largest.
It's not even the
largest so far anymore,
it's actually the largest.
It's the largest.
So again, we had this
thing at the top,
we had this loop in the middle.
At the bottom is where
you get the payoff.
And the payoff is
not in the middle.
While we're largest so far,
largest so far, largest so far.
But at the end, it
turned out once you've
looked at all the
variables, all the values,
the largest so far is,
indeed, the largest.
OK, so here's the
algorithm for this.
I have some variables.
And remember that
underscores are
valid characters in variables.
I'm being a little
over explicit in this.
So I have a variable
called largest so far.
And what I do is I set
it to negative one.
Then I print before, so
we can see that largest
so far is negative one.
Then we have a for loop, and my
iteration variable is the_num.
So that's going to
take on the successive
values 9, 41, 12, 3, 74, 15, and
run this indented loop of code.
And so the_num will be
nine first time through.
If the_num, 9, is greater
than largest so far,
then grab the_num and assign
it into largest so far.
Then print at the end of
each loop largest so far
and the_num.
So in effect, the_num is nine.
We compare it to negative
1, and nine is higher.
So we make largest
so far be nine.
Next time through
the loop, num is 41.
So we compare largest
so far with 41,
and we like it, so we store it.
So we like it, we run
it, and we print out,
41 is the largest
we've seen so far.
Then we run again.
We come in, the_num
points to 12.
The_num, 12, is not greater
than 41, and so we skip.
So the largest so far
stays 41, and we see 12.
Similarly, the_num
advances to three.
We skip.
So we saw three, but the
largest so far is still 41.
Continuing, the_num is now 74.
It runs.
74 is greater than 41.
And so we run this code.
And so we say, 74 is
stuck in largest so far.
And indeed, then
we print it out.
And largest so far is now 74.
We continue on.
We go up more time.
the_nu, points to 15, but
15 is not larger than 74.
And so we skip, we print out 15
and 74, and then we come out.
And at the end, we get
the largest so far.
The name no longer-- I mean,
largest so far at the end
is the largest, but
the variable name.
OK.
Got it?
That's one idiom.
So let's just switch
to another idiom.
Now counting.
How many things are we
going to, how many times
is loop going to execute,
how many things are we
going to find in the loop?
It's all the same notion.
And the pattern
is really simple.
We start some variable, zork.
A better name for
this would be count,
but I want to call it zork.
And then we have a loop.
And then in the loop,
we just add one to zork.
And at the end,
zork-- that should
be light blue right there.
Zork should be the total count.
Now of course, we can look at
it and say it's going to be six.
But assume this loop is
looping through a million lines
in a file, or
something like that.
So it's cheating to look at
it and say, oh, it's six.
Because we want to
actually compute it.
So it's really simple.
Zork starts at zero.
It's going to run,
zork is one now,
and two, three, four,
five, six, and then
we've run out of stuff,
and then we print out six.
So that's the idiom.
Before, during, and after.
We do something before,
we do something during.
And in a sense,
this zork here is
the number we've seen so far.
And at the end, it
becomes the total number.
Summing in the
loop, very similar.
Again, you have to think
of this as, there's
a whole bunch of variables here.
We start a variable at zero.
Each time through the
loop, we add whatever
it is that we're seeing.
Instead of adding one, we're
adding 9, 41, 12, 3, 74, 15.
And zork would be best
thought of as running total.
So zork is the running total.
And so if you look at the
numbers, running total's nine,
numbering total's 50, running
total's 62, 65, 130, and 154.
And then we skip
out, and at the end
the running total
becomes the total.
So that's another
of these patterns
that we do something
at the beginning,
we do something in the middle,
and we have something very nice
for ourselves at the end.
Finding the average of
a sequence of values
is the combination of the
two previous patterns.
This time, I'm going to use
more mnemonic variables.
Other variable called count,
everyone calls this count.
Sum, now, total would maybe
be a better word for this.
The running total.
And then the count and
the sum start out at zero.
And then each time
through the loop,
count equals count plus 1,
so we're adding one to count.
Sum equals sum plus
value, so we're
adding one to sum-- I
mean, adding the value.
Value, of course, being
9, 41, 12, 3, 74, 15.
And then at the very end,
we can print out the number.
We have six things
with a total of 154,
and then we calculate
the average.
Of course, these
are integer numbers.
And so this is a
truncating division.
So 154 over 6 equals 25,
and not 25 point something.
If we were in Python 3000,
Python 3, it'd be better.
So the integer averages of the
numbers we just looked at it
is 25.
So sometimes we're
searching, like for a needle
in a haystack.
Looking for something.
And again, you have to
think of, like, your hand
is some amount of
data, and you've
got to hunt for something.
And there might be
a million things,
and you might only
want five of them.
And you can use
look by hand, or you
can write a loop that's got
an if statement that says
found it.
Maybe I found it at line
seven, or found it wherever.
So this is filtering, or
finding, or searching,
looking for a needle in
a haystack in a loop.
And so the idea basically
is that we have this loop.
It's going to go through all
the values, 9, 41, 12, 3, 74.
But we put in the loop,
we embed an if statement.
If the value we're looking
at is greater than 20,
print I found it.
So when value is nine, this
is going to do nothing.
And just go and
make value be 41.
And then value 41,
oh, yup, there we go.
Print large number,
so off this comes.
Then value becomes
12, nothing happens.
Value becomes three,
nothing happens.
Value becomes 74, oops, this
time it's going to happen.
So out comes large number 74.
Then value becomes
15, nothing happens.
And then value is all done.
And so it comes and finishes.
So this is the searching,
or filtering, or catching,
or whatever.
We can also, if we don't just
want to print everything out,
we want to say, is
something in there?
We'll look through
this million things
and tell me if blah exists.
And in this, we're
going introduce
the notion of Boolean variable.
Boolean is a true/false.
It only has two values,
and we've already
used it in the wild, true.
So that capital True,
that is a constant.
Just like seven, or
42, or 99, or Sam.
And so we're going to make
this variable called found.
Now found is mnemonic variable,
it's just a name I picked.
So found equals False.
This is going to be false until
we find what we're looking for,
and then it's going
to switch to true.
So it starts out
and it's false, then
we're going to run this
bit of code three times.
And if the value that we
are looking at is three,
then we're going to
set found to be true,
and we'll print found
value each time through.
So value's going to take
on 9, 41, 12, 3, 74,
so we get a line of
output for each one.
And the first time
through, it's not
yet found, because
we're looking at a nine.
Second time, we've
not yet found,
we looked at 41, still false.
So it can stay false
for a long time.
Oh, we found a true.
And then that means that this
code's going to run once.
And so you can think of this
found variable as sticky.
It's going to stay false,
and then the rest of the loop
it's going to stay true,
and at the end it is true.
Now the way we usually do
these kinds of things is we
don't bother with
this print statement,
so we wouldn't see
all this stuff.
All we see is before
false, after true.
And after it would just tell
us that, yeah, we found it.
There was a three somewhere
in that long list of numbers.
I'm just adding this print
statement so we can trace it.
But basically, this
loop from here to here
is asking the question, is there
the number three in the list
that we're about to go through?
Now I'll just give you a second
and ask you a quick question.
You can pause if you want.
How could you improve
this loop using the break?
Where might you put a break
to make this loop smarter?
It's OK if it didn't
jump out at you.
So if you think about
it, once you hit true,
there's really little point in
looking at the rest of them.
There just is no point.
So we could put a break right
here, inside this block.
You say, look, I'm
looking for a three.
All I care is whether
I found it or not.
If I find it, I mark it
to true that I found it,
and I get out of the loop.
Why bother?
Why do all these things?
Just get out.
So don't worry about it,
I'm just pointing that out
that that's one of the places
where break could be used.
The loop functions
either way, it just
looks through all the
rest of them as well.
OK.
So here's this largest
value one I've used before.
And away we go.
We have largest so
far, we check to see
if the one we're
looking at is better.
And if it is, we keep
it, and then away we go.
And then we find
the largest is 17.
What if, what would you
have to change in this code
to make this search for the
smallest of all the values?
Point where in the
screen, what would you
have to change to make
this look for the smallest
in the list of values?
What's making this
about being largest?
What would you have to change?
OK.
Pause if you like.
So here is some things
that you might do
to make it work about smallest.
So hey, one thing
we would do, let's
change the name of the variable.
We had a variable
named largest so far,
and now we'll change it to
be called smallest so far.
Changing the variable name
doesn't change the program
at all.
But it makes the program easier
to read if the program works.
So it's like smallest so far.
But that didn't make
it about being small.
The thing that made
about being small
is change this greater
than to a less than.
Because we're
thinking when we're
doing largest so far, if
the number we're looking at
is bigger than largest
so far, we keep it.
If the number looking
at in the smallest
is smaller than the smallest so
far, then we want to keep it.
So this is like keep.
This line here is
the keeping line.
And this is the when
line, when to keep.
We'll keep it if it's smaller.
So that's the key.
And so, yeah, so I name it
smallest so far, whoopdy doo.
That's good.
But the real thing that had this
being about largeness smallness
was whether this is less
than and greater than,
and this was the
repeated code that got
rechecked over and over again.
But this still has a bug in it.
So let's run this visually.
So now we've got a variable
called smallest so far.
We are going to check to
see if a series of numbers
that I'm about to show you
are smaller than the smallest
so far.
So the first number is 9.
Is that's smaller
than negative 1?
No, it's not.
Negative one is smaller.
The second number is 41.
Is that smaller than negative 1?
No, it is not.
The next number's 12.
Is that smaller than negative 1?
No.
Negative 1 is smaller than 12.
Three?
No, not smaller.
74?
15?
Not smaller.
So we're all done, yay,
and the smallest number
we saw in the list
is negative one?
Negative one wasn't
even in the list.
So that's not a
very good program.
So let's take a look at what
went wrong with this program.
So we fixed it, we fixed
it as best we could.
We made it, we changed
the words largest
to smallest, yay, that'll fix.
Just makes it more
readable, doesn't actually
change the program.
And we made this less than.
So now what happens
is it comes in,
if 3 is less than negative 1,
smallest so far, of course,
is negative one.
This just never runs.
This never runs.
And so as we print, smallest
so far stays negative 1.
And oops, that should be
negative one right there.
Sorry, forgot to fix that.
Here, let me magically fix that.
So let's take a look at
what went wrong with this.
So here we have the code.
Smallest so far as negative one.
We have it fixed so
that we're looking
for smaller numbers
rather than larger numbers
by turning this to less than.
But the first time through,
smallest so far is negative 1,
and the_num is three.
Three is not less than
negative 1, so we skip through.
And the printout of the first
line is negative one, three.
And doesn't take long to
realize that it's just
going to keep doing this.
Smallest so far is going to
stay negative one no matter
what we look at on this side.
And then we're going
to come out the end,
and we end up with
negative one as the answer.
Not very good.
So the question is what
should we make this value be?
Negative one, it barely
worked in the largest,
because we were working
with positive numbers.
And so starting
with negative one
as the largest so far was a
reasonable assumption, as long
as the numbers
were all positive.
What would be the
number to choose here?
Think about that for a sec.
Pause if you have to.
Let me clear it.
Let me make it real clear.
What's the right
thing to put here?
So what, a million?
That might work.
Million might work.
But what if all these numbers
were larger than a million?
Then that wouldn't work.
So the problem is,
there's no real good value
unless you could make
this be somehow infinity.
You could make this be infinity.
But there's a way to
do this in Python,
and it's a really kind
of cool technique.
It's a way we signal ourselves.
And that is, we're going
to use a special value.
Not negative 1,
it's not a number.
And the special value
we're going to use is none.
It's a different type.
It's not a number, it's
itself its own type.
So we're going to do is we're
going to mark smallest as none.
And at a high level, what
we're really saying is
we haven't seen anything so far.
The smallest we've
seen so far is none.
We've not seen anything so far.
Now we have to change our
little if inside the loop,
this is this intelligence
in the middle.
First, we say, if smallest
is none, is is an operator.
Part of the Python language.
If smallest is none,
exactly the same as none,
then the smallest we've
seen so far is the value.
Now, this is going to
happen the first time.
Because smallest
starts out none.
And then as soon as we
said smallest to the value,
it's going to be
that first number,
so it's going to be nine.
So smallest is quickly
going to become nine.
Then we print out
the smallest is nine
after we've seen the nine.
Then we go up to the top and
we say, is smallest none?
And the answer is, no it's not,
because smallest is now nine.
Then this else if
is going to ask,
is the value we're
looking at, which is 41,
is the value less than smallest?
Well, no it is not.
Nine is smaller than 41.
And so in a sense, after the
first time this statement
is executed, this is going
to always be false, right?
Because smallest
is no longer none.
And this is going to be the
thing that really is operating.
And then it's going to work.
And smallest will become 9, the
smallest so far is 9, but then
we see the 3 finally.
And the value 3 is less than
9, and so then we take 3,
and you stick it into smallest.
And we end up with this.
And then the loop runs some more
times, and when we're all done
we have 3.
So the trick here is
we put this none in,
and we have a
little more if code
to check to see if we
haven't seen anything so far.
You can think of this
as a way to trigger
on the first iteration.
Special code that's
really going to-- it
looks at it on each
iteration, but it's never
true after the first iteration.
So that's just a technique.
So this is an is not operator.
I think it's a
real elegant thing.
Don't start overusing it.
At a low level, its real
meaning is exactly the same
as in type and value.
There's a is, and
there's an is not.
But don't do things like
saying, if i equal-- oops.
Won't even let myself
type the bad code.
If i is 4, don't say that.
Don't say that.
Don't do if i is 4.
It may work in
certain situations,
it's really best used in
very limited situations
where you're checking for
some of these special values
like none, and false.
The problem is if you
use equality here,
it tries to convert
values, and it may end up
giving you a false yes.
And so is is a stronger
equality than simple equals.
Equals is same
numeric value, where
is is exactly the same thing.
But don't overuse is.
Use double equals
95% of the time,
and use is when you're
checking if it's
one of these special
constants like true or false.
OK?
So this is iterations.
I mean, our loops are going
to get more sophisticated,
and we have more
interesting things to do.
But we talked about
some indefinite loops,
definite loops,
iteration variables.
Some patterns like maximum,
minimum, summing, averaging.
We introduced the
concept of none.
And so this is,
we're getting there.
We've got a couple more
chapters before we really start
hitting the data analysis.
So see you in the next lecture.