Hello.
Welcome to my video on how
to run Python on Windows.
I'm Charles
Severance, and this is
my book Python For
Informatics and I
have a bunch of free courses.
The book is free.
And so I hope you enjoy
learning how to program.
So the first thing
we're going to do
is download some software.
You need a programmer editor.
And so Notepad Plus
Plus is a good one.
It has syntax highlighting
and other things
and it doesn't
mess up your files.
It understands that you
just want a plain text file.
So I'm going to download
and install this.
You want to be an
administrator when you're
doing this in your Windows box.
I'm an administrator on
my particular Windows box.
Going to run it.
And you might get prompted
for a password here,
but I'm just going to say yes
because I am the administrator.
And I'll run through the
installation process here.
So that's all done.
I'm not going to bother
running it right now.
So there we go.
So I've done a Notepad.
The next thing I want to do is
I'm going to download Python.
It's here.
I'm at the Python download page.
For my class, I use Python 2.7.
You could use Python 3.
They're slightly
different languages.
I think it's fine to learn both
languages although we're really
at the point where
increasingly people are
starting to use Python 3.
But there's so many things
that are there for Python 2.
So the question often asked is,
like, which one of these two?
Do I go x86 or the non?
It's pretty safe to do this one.
But-- so if I go Start
and then I type pc info,
this will tell me
something about this PC.
Different versions of Windows
have this in different places.
But basically, I
get to the point
where it says I have a system
type 64-bit operating system.
So I can get a 64-bit
download, which is nice to do.
So I will go back
to Control Panel.
And I'm going to download
my windows 64-bit installer.
And I'm going to run it.
And again, I'm going to
need to be an administrator.
I'm going to install
for all users.
I'm going to leave
it in the directory
that it wants to put
it on my local drive.
Python 2.7-- you can
put it elsewhere,
but then you're going
to have to remember it.
Please don't put spaces in the
path no matter what you do.
And again, I'm the super user.
So I'm going to say yes.
So we're all done.
OK, so now, I'm going to
minimize my web browser.
So the next thing I'm going to
do is I'm going to run Notepad.
And of course, you
could have shortcuts.
But I'm going to use
the Start button.
I'm going to hit Start and I'm
going to type in my keyboard
notepad, N-O-T-E-P-A-D.
And up comes Notepad Plus.
And I will take that.
So here, we have Notepad Plus.
And I'm going to right a
simple Python program--
print "hello world".
OK, and I'm going to save this.
So I'm going to
say File, Save As.
And I'm going to put
this on my desktop.
I could make a folder.
Sure, let's make a folder.
Call this Learn because
I'm Python learning.
So I'm going to the folder.
You'll notice the folder
showed up as soon as I made it.
Now I'm going to make this file.
I'm going to call
it firstprog.py.
Now, you'll notice it
did syntax coloring.
As soon as it realizes
that this is a .py file,
it knows the Python language.
And so it's giving me some help.
And if I go into
Learn, I will see
that there is indeed sitting
in this folder a file called
firstprog.py.
Unfortunately, Windows hides
the .py but shows us this little
Python icon.
You can run it by
clicking on this
but this is not my preferred
way of running it, OK?
So I'm just going
to minimize that.
And I'm going to say start.
And then I'm going to type CMD.
This is the command prompt.
Sometimes you have to do Start
Run CMD on really old versions
of Windows, or just
Start CMD, and then
run the command prompt.
And this will initially
seem, like, why am I using
this old school command prompt?
But after a while,
part of the goal
is to really get to be
good at your computer
and knowing how
the computer works.
So this is the command
prompt and you type commands.
So one of the command
you can type is dir.
You're in your home directory.
That's what
[? user.csv ?] means.
And I'm going to go into
my desktop with the CD,
which stands for Change
Directory-- D-E-S-K-T-O-P.
Now I'm in my desktop.
Move my little cursor there.
And I do a dir and you'll see
a whole series of things there.
And then you'll see this
Learn folder-- L-E-A-R-N.
So I'm going to change into
that directory-- CD Learn--
and do a dir there.
And lo and behold, I see exactly
what I was seeing in here.
So this is really
just a graphical image
of what's in that folder.
I mean, and you can even sort
of see the path if you look here
that it's in MySQL and
[? user/csev/desktop/learn, ?]
which is exactly
where I'm at-- SQL
and
[? user/csev/desktop/learn. ?]
This may see-- when you start
reading and writing files,
it's important that you put
your files in the same folder
here as the program.
So to run the Python program,
you simply type firstprog.py.
It's as if-- whoops,
F-I-R-S-T-P-R-O-G.py.
It's as if you build an
extension of the system.
The little program
you wrote in Python
is sitting there for you to run.
And I can make a change
like something else
and save that file.
And then I can run it again.
Now, here's a trick.
I can hit the up arrow and just
run the same program again.
Syntax error-- PR.
Oh, I put an M in.
Print, Save.
Now I just come back here.
I hit up arrow and run it again.
And so now I have my
old two line program.
And away it goes.
So the only other
thing to know is
to how to start
Python for the command
so you can do interactive
playing with Python.
And this way, you can
type Python commands.
And you can add it to your
path and go look on Google
as to how to add
something your path.
But it's easier just
to say C:/python27
because that's where we--
oops, python27/python.
I cannot type.
And so this is the
chevron prompt, right?
There's the chevron prompt.
So I can type a print
yo or I can type
take me to your Python leader.
Syntax error-- yeah, we've
been through this before.
I hate computers.
OK, so you get out.
But here, you've
got to be careful
because you can't run programs.
And so you can type
quit to get out.
And now you're back
at the command prompt
and you can type dir.
So you can learn
the commands here.
All we really know
is we know dir, CD.
And when in doubt, just
close this window If you get
lost in the wrong
folder or something.
So that's pretty much
all I wanted to do.
Please don't make directory
names or folder names
with spaces in.
It just makes life confusing.
So stick with simple names.
Don't put long spaces
in either folder names
or file names because then it's
harder to do this stuff, OK?
Thanks.