Hello and welcome to
our how to use Notepad
to run Python applications.
This is part of my open
and free textbook Python
for Informatics--
Exploring Information.
At this point, you should
have hopefully by now
installed Python.
If you haven't yet
installed Python,
you can go-- my book is
really any Python version two
is fine-- 2.5, 2.6, 2.7.
The simplest thing to do
is to go down to this link
right here, which is the
Windows x86 mSI installer.
If you're in doubt
as to whether or not
you're a Windows
64 or x-- 32-bit,
just go ahead and
grab the 32-bit.
Download it, run it.
I won't go through that here.
It's straightforward.
It's pretty much the same as
running most install packages.
The other thing that you're
going to want to install
is programmer editor.
I recommend Notepad
for Windows users.
You really don't
want to use Notepad.
It will mess up your
programs and turn them
into various things and not
save them the right way.
So we just want a
programmer editor
that understands programs.
It's going-- it'll
be good for HTML.
It'll be good for CSS,
good for lots of things.
So again, download that.
There's a couple ways.
You can just go
Notepad Plus in Google
and find it and
download and install it.
But I'm going to
assume that you've
done both of those things.
So now what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to show you how to run
the program assuming you've
installed these two things.
So let's go ahead and
start Notepad Plus Plus.
I've already got here.
And there we go.
So now I'm going to write my
first Python program print
"hello world"-- world.
I'm not a very good typer.
OK, so then what
we've got to do is
I've got to save it somewhere.
So we're going to run this.
This is just editing a file.
So I'm going to
save it, Save As.
And I'm going to put
it on to my desktop.
And I'm going to name
the file firstprog.py.
Now, you might want to
put this in a folder.
If you're going to
be using, please
don't put names in
your folders, OK?
I mean spaces in your folders.
So I could put this
in a folder, but I'm
going to put it on my desktop.
So the saving shows
up right here.
It is indeed on my desktop.
Now, to actually run this,
we're going to run it
through the command line.
There are many ways
to do this, but I
prefer running it
through the command line
so you really get
a sense of control
rather than clicking on things.
So this version
of Windows, I have
to start a command prompt
CMD-- so start CMD.
Sometimes, it's start run CMD
depending on your Windows.
But one way or another,
you get this little black
and white beautiful
little screen.
And where I'm at is telling
me the current directory.
I'm in the C drive
user screen caster--
that's my home directory.
And I can go one folder
down to go into my desktop.
And when I'm in my
desktop in this window,
it's the same as here.
So if I do a dur, which is
the command to list the files,
I see firstprog.py sitting in
the exact same place that I am,
OK?
So the way that you run this
is you simply type firstprog.py
at the command line.
We're going to run a
Python program and Python
sort of-- Windows
understands that
files that end with the
suffix PY are Python programs.
And so here is my first program.
But it's saying I've
got a syntax error.
It says something, something,
something, print "hello world".
Let me look at
this more closely.
Print-- oh, oh, oh.
I should have called that print.
Oh, there we go.
We see syntax highlighting.
So now I'm going to save this.
Oops-- File, Save.
Now, here's a little
trick that you can do.
Seeing as how I just
typed firstprog.py
and I want to run the
same command again,
I just hit the up arrow
and it automatically
knows what my
previous command is.
You can scroll
through these things.
Away we go.
Firstprog.py-- OK, that
works a little better.
It says hello world now.
So you just basically will
write second, you know?
You do stuff here in your
Python and you will save it.
Save it and then you'll
hit the up arrow run it.
And there we go.
I'm changing.
So this is the Python program.
It's stored both on your
desktop and here you can run it.
OK, so that is basically
the idea of how this works.
And-- oh, let me show
you one more thing.
Sorry, I was checking my notes.
If you want to run the Python
interpreter interactively,
you have to type its full
path-- C:-- in my case,
I've got Python
2.7 installed here.
Python27/python.exe-- oh,
I didn't do that very well.
But here, I typed the up arrow.
And I type EXE.
And so now I'm at
the chevron prompt.
And so I can say,
like, print yo.
I could say x equals 5 print 5.
Now to get out of
the chevron prompt,
you either type quit with
parentheses or Control-Z.
And I will take
Control-Z to exit.
And that exits the
Python interpreter,
the interactive
mode of Python, OK?
Thanks a lot.
Bye.