So, here we are, talking about integers
and floating points.
These are a concept in programming
languages and in Python called type.
Variables and constants have a type.
We can see that if you say 1, versus 1.0,
they have different, they, it works
different, it functions differently.
And so Python keeps track of both
variables and literals/constants, and
having them have a type.
And we've seen this, right?
Now, the interesting thing is, is Python
is very aware of
the type and can use the same syntax to
accomplish different things.
So if we look at this line here, where we
say dd equals 1.4.
Well it looks at the 1 and looks at the 4
and it says,
oh those are two integers. I will add those
together and give you a 5.
So it gives you an integer, an integer, and an
integer comes back,
Okay?
And then ee equals 'hello ' plus 'there'.
Well these are two strings,
'hello ' and 'there'. And it says hmm, this must
be a concatenation.
Alright? So I'm going to concatenate those
together because
those are strings and I know how to
concatenate strings.
And that's kind of like string addition,
right?
And so we see a "hello there" as a result.
Now the interesting thing is, where
did this space come from?
Let me change colors here.
Oops.
Where did that space come from?
Well, the plus does not add the space.
Here's a space right there, and that's the
space.
So I can concatenate it, hello space plus
there, and that's how I got hello there.
But, the key thing is, is this plus
operator, clear, this plus operator looks
to either side
and says oh,
they're strings.
I think you mean concatenation.
Here it looks either side and says oh,
those are integers, I think you mean
addition.
So Python is very aware of type and type
informs Python what you really mean.
So, it looks like those are kind
of the same, but they're quite different
operations.
So the type can get you into trouble.
Remember Python is looking at the type.
So here we have a little problem, our
first traceback, first of many
tracebacks.
So here we have ee which is hello there
which is
exactly what we did. This is a string and
this is a string.
So ee should be a string. And then we try
to add 1 to it.
And again, Python is saying oh, I see
a plus sign here, so I'm going to look
over here, yeah,
that's a string, and look over here, and
that's an integer.
And it's like, aaah! And this is a traceback.
Now, here's a good time to talk about
tracebacks.
Tracebacks, I color them red.
Because you might think that Python
dislikes you or
thinks that you're, you know, unworthy of
its brilliance.
And certainly the way these things are
worded it sounds like,
you know, the, you're being scolded.
It's like, hey, type error.
You can, cannot concatenate str and int
objects, right?
That's, I'm, I'm scolding you, you bad,
bad programmer.
And it does feel a bit like you're
scolded.
But, if you go back to lecture one, this
is also
the moment where, really, we shouldn't
think of this as like scolding.
We should think of this as Python sort of
asking for help.
It's like,
wow, you gave me this line, and I, Python,
have no idea.
In all your greatness, could you give me
some possible
clue as to what you really
mean for me to do?
Because I'm so lost.
And given that I'm Python and I'm lost and
you are the only
purpose for my existence, I must stop
until you give me better guidance.
So, don't look at tracebacks as scolding.
They sound like scolding.
I'll stop coloring them red after a while.
So, if Python is so obsessed with the type
of things, you
should be able to ask Python what the type
of something is.
So there's a built-in function called
type.
This is part of the Python language.
Type (), and you can put a variable in
here.
What's the type of the variable ee?
And it says, oh yeah, I know what that is,
that would be a string.
And then you can also put a constant in
here.
And say what's the type of quote, hello,
quote, and that's a string too.
And what's the type of the number 1?
Well that would be an integer.
So it's picky about the type, but it will
also share with you what it believes the
type is.
And there's several types of numbers.
As I've already mentioned, there are
integers, which are the whole numbers.
They can be positive and negative and
zero.
And then there are the decimal numbers,
the floating point numbers,
like 98.6 or negative 2.5 or 14.0.
Python knows these as well because it does
division different if it's presented with
two integers, or an integer and a float,
or a float and a float.
And so here we have x is 1, and we'll say
what is it?
It's an integer.
And we say it's 98.6, and we'll say, well,
what's that?
It's a float.
And you can ask for both variables and
constants.
So what's the type of 1? It's an integer.
And what's type of up 1.0?
And it's a float.
You can also convert types.
It has a bunch of type conversion
functions built into it.
So, there's implicit conversion going on
when you're sort of saying, you know,
divide an integer by a floating point.
It says okay I see, I look to
the sides and
I will make the, I will make the
conversion for you.
But you can also be explicit.
So in this case we're going to say,
take this
99 and convert to a floating point
version of itself.
Which is 99.0.
And then do the division.
So Python looks out here and goes oh,
after that, that's
a float, and that's an integer if I look
over here.
And then that means that the
result is a float.
And the division is done as a float.
So we are force converting the 99 integer
into a 99.0 float.
And we can even do this like and just
stick it in the variable.
So we can just put 42 in i and that is an
integer.
Then we can say, hey, convert float that i
into a float and stick it into the
variable f.
And so we can print it.
And now it's 42.0 instead of 42.
Right? They're not the same.
They're both kind of 42, but one is a
floating point 42 and the other is an
integer 42.
And we can ask, and that is a float.
And you can also do the same thing in the
middle of
a calculation, where you have 1 plus 2
times a float of 3.
This float is done quickly.
So the first thing that happens
this is 1 plus 2 times 3.0 over 4
minus 5.
So
the first thing that happens is these
floats
are done because they are parentheses so
they matter.
So this is a built-in function called
float that takes, as its
argument, a non-floating point number and
gives you back a floating point number.
We'll talk more about functions
in Chapter Four.
You can also convert between strings and
numbers, and if you
recall, I, we did the example where we
took a string.
In this case, I'm being a little
confusing, because
I'm making a string with the
characters 1, 2, 3.
Now, this is not the same as 123.
This is a three-character string
with 1, 2, 3 in it.
And I can ask what kind of thing is in
there, and it says,
oh, there's a string in there.
I know about that.
And then I can try to add 1 to it, and
it seems intuitive that quote 123 plus 1
would be somehow 124.
But it's not.
Python takes a look at the plus and says,
oh there's
a string on that side, and an integer on
that side.
I am going to freak out and tell you
that you cannot concatenate
a string and an integer.
Okay?
But there is an int function
that converts various things, including
strings, to an integer.
So we can give as its parameter, its input,
the string value, then it
converts it to an integer, and then we'll
put the result in the variable ival.
We can ask what the type of that is, it's
an i, it's a integer.
And now we can use it in an expression,
print ival plus 1, and
so now Python looks to both sides, sees an
integer, sees an integer, and
gets 124.
Voila.
Now, if I make a new variable and I stick
hello Bob in it, and I
say hey, let's convert hello Bob to an
integer, as you might expect, it blows up.
And it says, invalid literal
for int.
These, these tracebacks again, once you
kind of get used to the kind of harsh
wording of them, because they're not
saying, sorry, comma,
they're trying to tell you what's
going on.
So, cannot concatenate string and integer,
and invalid literal for int.
It's trying to be as helpful as it
possibly can
be to give you a clue as to what to fix.
So, again, not scolded.
Okay, so that's variables and types and
type conversion.
Now we'll talk a little bit about
user input.
And there's a function that's built into
Python called raw_input.
And what happens when raw_input runs is
it, it has as one of
its parameters, a prompt, which is
something that shows up on the screen.
Who are you?
And then,
it waits, tik, tik, tik, tik, tik.
Sits and waits, says, what next?
And then, you type a string,
dot, dot, dot, dot, dot,
and then you hit the Enter key.
The Enter key.
And then whatever you typed here goes
into a variable.
And it is a string.
And, then you,
then you can use it.
So I'm going to print the string Welcome,
comma. So that means I'm printing two
things now.
The comma adds a space between Welcome and
then nam, and so
Welcome is a literal, and then Chuck is
coming from this nam variable.
So this is a two-line program.
I think this is one of your
assignments, actually,
to well, it's one of the exercises
in the book.
To a prompt for a user's name, and
then welcome them, okay?
So raw_input is a function that issues a
prompt, waits, and then takes whatever
string that's entered, and then returns it
and then puts it into that variable.
So, now we're going to create kind of the
first useful program.
It's not a powerful program.
It is a, an interesting problem of the
fact that for some reason there
is a difference in the numbering scheme
of United States elevators and
European elevators.
European elevators, the floor that you
walk out on is the
zero floor.
The floor above that is the
one floor and the
floor below that, the basement,
is the minus one floor.
And so you walk in and you can go either
up the elevator or down the elevator.
Of course, in the United States, the floor
that you walk in is the
one and then there's the two floor above
that and then there's like, the basement.
So this is the
imagination that the Americans
have as to how to number floors, right?
The Europeans go zero, one, minus one.
So, children who go to hotels learn
instantly the notion of zero and the
notion of positive and negative
numbers and
the symmetry between positive and
negative numbers.
I mean, I just wish the United States
hotels would switch to this
to teach young people zero immediately and
negative numbers.
So we somehow think that numbers all in
the United States start at 1
and then there are no
negative numbers, there's the
basement.
I wonder why that is, but whatever.
For people who travel a lot, they may be
confused by this.
They need a way to convert back and
forth between the US and European
numbering system.
So this is a simple program that
demonstrates
a real classic pattern of input processing
and output.
It's just three lines, but it has the
essential things that all programs that
are useful.
They generally read some data,
do some work with
the data, and then produce some
kind of results.
And so, so the first line is a raw_input
that effectively, that puts out a prompt
and then it waits.
It says, please enter your Europe floor.
It sits there.
We type a zero,
then zero goes into inp, but it is a
string.
It's not a number.
It's a string.
So we can't add to it. But we can take
and convert it to an integer with
the int function.
Int of inp, thats a string being
converted to an integer
so now its a real numeric zero.
And we can add 1 to that and we
sum that together.
And we put it into the
variable usf and then we print US floor,
comma, and then
whatever the variable for usf is. And out
comes US floor 1.
So we've written a very simple elevator
floor conversion
from a European floor to a
United States floor.
Don't ask about negative numbers, it's not
really good at that.
But from zero and positive numbers it
works great.
So another thing to think about in any
programming language is comments.
Comments are like commentary, you know,
and basically it's a way for us to
add notations for ourselves and for other
humans interspersed in the code.
And so in Python anything after a pound
sign is ignored.
You can have a pound sign at the beginning
of a line and then the
whole line is ignored.
There are two or three reasons why you
could do this.
One is sort of like paragraph headings,
where you can
say what's going to happen in English or,
or your language.
And you can write documentation says this
code was written by Charles Severence,
December 2010.
And you can also just hide
a line of code to
test and, and turn it on and off without
actually deleting
the line of code.
It's a real common thing in debugging.
So for example, here is a, here is a, the
program that we've been playing with.
This is our word counting program that
we've been talking about
from the beginning.
And here is an example of four comments,
one, two, three, four.
Four comments that basically tell us what
these paragraphs are going to do.
Now, they don't have any effect on the
program whatsoever.
But this one says get the name of the file
and open it.
Kind of helpful, right?
Count the word frequency.
That's what this little bit does.
Find the most common word.
And all done, print this out.
So it's really can be very helpful just to
add a little tiny bit of stuff.
And you don't want to overuse comments.
You don't want to say like x equals 12,
take 12 and put it into x.
Sometimes people teach
you and try to say, oh you need a one
comment every three lines.
I don't believe in any of those rules.
I basically say if its useful to describe
it, then describe it.
So that's comments.
So some operators apply to strings.
We've already talked about plus.
It's kind of silly, although
useful in places.
You can actually multiply strings.
The asterisk looks and
says I've got a string and an integer, and
it prints out the string five times.
Not a lot of use for that.
Now, let's talk a little bit about
choosing variable names.
This is something that is
really confusing.
So I said like, x equals 1, x equals x
plus 1, what does x mean?
And the answer is, it doesn't
mean anything.
I chose it.
I wanted to make a variable,
and so I picked x.
We pick x a lot, probably because
we learned
in algebra in sixth grade that
x was a variable.
So, and it's short, and so,
why not call it x?
But as your programs get larger this gets
kind of frustrating
to have all your variables like x
and y and z.
And so the notion of mnemonic, it means
memory aid.
We choose our variable names wisely, so
they remind us of what the variable's
going to do internally.
And so, as I go through this lecture
in the beginning if I choose a variable
that's too clever
you're going to think that it's
part of the language.
And so I sort of switch back and forth
between well-chosen variable names
and stupid variable names to kind of
reemphasize the notion that I can choose.
Mnemonic is a good practice, okay?
So here we go.
Let's take a look at a bit of code.
So the question is, what is
this code doing?
What will it even print out?
Is it syntactically correct?
Now you could probably cut and paste this
into your brow, into Python and figure
out that it is syntactically correct.
There are three variables.
This one here and this one here match.
This one here and that one there match.
And these two match.
So it's taking these two numbers and
multiplying together, and then printing
out the product
of the two numbers, if you're real careful
and like look at every, every character.
Now, this would be called
non-mnemonic variables.
They're really messy.
Now Python, it's happy, because all it
wants is to say, oh.
Here is then name that
I, the programmer, decided I
wanted to call this
piece of memory and I'll refer to
it down here, okay?
And so Python is happy.
Now if you hand this to another human
being they are going to be really unhappy.
Because they are going to be like, what
are you doing?
So one better way to write it would be to
make the variables very simple.
And then cognitively we humans can figure
out which is which,
because again it's still only
about matching.
The a has to match the a, the b matches
the b, and the c's match.
It's actually the exact same program.
A equals 35.
B equals 12.5.
C equals A times B.
And print C.
It is these.
Python sees these as the same program.
It doesn't care what we name them.
Now, a human will
be much appreciative if you say, here you
can either have this one or this one.
This one will make them a lot happier.
Okay?
So that is certainly cognitively easier,
but it's not really
giving you any sense of what's going on
here, right?
So an even better way to write this exact
same program to do the exact same thing
would be to choose variables
named hours, rate, and pay,
if indeed that is what you're doing.
Now you can look at this and you go,
oh well, shoot,
35 is the number of hours, and 12.5 is the
rate, and the pay is
the number of hours times the rate, and
then we are going to print out the pay.
And that makes a lot of sense.
So this is really a awesome and wonderful
characterization.
And if that's what you're doing
and those are hours,
rate, and pay, it's a great thing
to name the variables.
But, this is where beginning students
get confused.
And so sometimes I'll write it this way
and sometimes I'll write it this way.
Because you'll look at this, until you get
a little
more sophisticated, a little more skilled,
and you'll say like
does Python know something about payroll?
Is hours a reserved word?
Is rate a reserved word and pay
a reserved word?
Are these things that Python knows about?
And the answer is, no.
Python sees these three programs as
exactly the same name.
It's just this person really made a very
bad choice of variable name.
This person made a less bad choice of
variable name,
and this person made a really awesome
choice of variable name.
So the only difference between those two
things is style.
They are the exact same program.
And Python is equivalently happy with
these, but humans
are most happy when the variables are
easy to remember
and they are somewhat descriptive of what
their expected contents will be.
That's mnemonic.
To help you remember what you were meaning
to do when you write the program.
This is still a bit cryptic, having these
really short, one-character variable
names is still
a bit cryptic.
So,
You have a couple of assignments at the
end of the chapter.
One of the assignments is to write a
program to prompt
the user for hours and rate per hour and
compute pay.
So, I won't do this here, but just a
couple of sort of odd things.
You're going to be using raw_input.
But remember that hands a string in so
you're going
to have to use float.
The function to convert it to a floating
point number so you can actually do a
calculation.
And then you're going to have to use
multiplication and print.
So then multiplication, and then print.
So some combination of raw input, float,
multiplication, and print,
constructed to make your program do
exactly this.
So, this is the end of Chapter Two.
We talked about types,
reserved words, variables, the
mnemonic, how you choose variable names.
We'll hit this a couple more times
because choosing variable names is always
problematic.
Operators, operator precedence, which just
means like does multiplication happen
before plus, parentheses.
Integer division is a little weird because
it truncates, oops, right, 9 over 10.
Oops, 9 over 10 equals 0.
That's the integer division truncating.
Conversion, this is like the int()
float().
And then user input, which is raw_input.
And then comments, which are ways for you
to add human-readable text to your
program.
Okay? See you next lecture.