Okay, so we're almost done with
conditionals.
I want to show you one more kind of
conditional.
It's a little bit different.
It's not a bit of code structure
that you make, it is,
it is dealing with the fact that some
things may blow up.
Like, if you read a number from a user and
you try to convert it
to a floating point number, as you may
have already done in some of your
homework,
it can blow up.
You know it's going to blow up, but you
don't exactly want it to kill your program.
So, the concept of try and except are,
hey, this is a dangerous thing.
I know it might blow up.
I know exactly what it might blow up, but
I don't want to die
I don't want to stop my program
when it blows up.
I want to continue.
And that's the purpose of the except
block.
So, here's a little bit of code.
And, you know, it's, we've done
this code before.
This is code that's kind of
similar to, like
your rate and pay homework, where
you read a string
using raw input, you converted it using
float, but
then if you typed in Fred, the
thing blows up.
So we're kind of simulating that
right here.
So here we have a variable astr
called Hello Bob,
and then we try to turn it into an
integer.
And then we're going to print that out,
and then we have
another string called one, and that has
the letters 1, 2, 3.
We convert that to an integer, and then we
print that one out.
The problem is, is that when this runs,
this is going to fail.
It's going to fail with this traceback,
okay?
And the problem is, is when the traceback
happens, the program stops executing.
The traceback is Python's way of asking
you, hey, this
would be bad, I don't know what to do,
I'm stopping.
So that means that the rest of your
program is gone, right?
It,
The fact that we had stuff down here
doesn't matter.
This line died with the traceback.
It stopped.
It doesn't, like, give you a traceback and
then keep going.
It gives you a traceback, and
that's the end.
Now this might be something, instead of
just the string, Hello Bob, which is
insane.
Data might have come from a raw input,
where the user was typing, and you say,
give me a number, and they type something
that's not a number, and this would
blow up.
It's like, hey, I know it's going to
The problem with this is that you don't,
oops, erp, clear the thing.
Oh and now we have to start it on fire again.
Okay, it's on fire.
The problem is, is that in a sense, this
program is you.
If you recall, we have you as the, typing
these commands
into these scripts, feeding the central
processing unit, answering the question
what next?
So you should take it a little personally
when your program gets a traceback.
because that means you, in the form of
your program, have been vaporized.
And you're not present to give any more
instructions.
It stops.
It stops dead in its tracks.
You are gone.
So, we want to make sure we control this
behavior.
We know it might blow up,
and we want to capture the situation where
it does, and execute alternate code.
Okay.
So here it goes.
It's a bit of syntax.
I mentioned that it uses the try and
except keywords.
These are reserved words in Python.
And then it's a little indented block.
So, astr equals Hello Bob, great.
Try means, we're about to do something
dangerous, let's take out some
insurance policy on it.
And that is, we're going to convert this
to an integer.
Take astr, convert it to an integer, put
it in istr.
If that works, great, we'll just continue
on, and ignore this except.
If it blows up, we're going to jump into
the
except block, and then we'll have
alternate substitute code.
In this case, I'm going to set the
variable to negative 1 as an indicator.
Then I'll print it out, and I'll do it
again.
Try this code, and away we go.
So, when this runs, we know exactly how
it's going to run.
It, whoa, woop, come back.
We'll set this string, the try
takes out the insurance,
this blows up, so it runs down to here
and runs this part, and then it'll
print First minus 1.
And it sets the string to 1, 2, 3, not
123, but 1, 2, 3 as a string.
It takes out an insurance policy.
This time it works, and that puts
istr is going to be 123,
so we don't run the accept code, and
so out comes the
second 1, 2, 3, okay?
So the try is, take out insurance on this
little bit of code, and if it fails,
run this alternate code. If not, skip the
alternate code.
So it's kind of conditional.
If you put multiple lines in the block
between
the try and the except, it runs until one
dies.
So it doesn't come back, okay?
It's not taking insurance out on,
separately, on all three statements.
It's like, here's a block of stuff, and if
anything blows up,
stop.
And the things that run do run.
So if, this is really kind of bad code,
because you really don't want
the print in here.
It's actually a good idea on the try
except to have as little in the
try block as you possibly can, so you're
real clear on what's going to fail.
but, so here we come in, shh, it's Bob,
so it's going to fail.
We run this.
That runs successfully.
This blows up, so it quits and jumps into
the except blocks and continues.
The point is, is that this code never
executes, never executes.
The other point is, this code does
execute.
Just because this blew up, this is already
executed,
it might have done something other, more
complex than
print Hello, okay?
So, so there you go.
So, if we look at this kind of in a
picture,
we, we set this through the try block, it
runs, it runs.
And the, the try except kind of has this
escape hatch that says, if there is
a [SOUND] explosion somehow, then
it runs this
alternate code and then it comes out and
finishes, okay?
And, again, this, it doesn't go
back and finish the block, and it doesn't
undo the work that is done by that.
So it doesn't un-execute it.
If it executes and works, it just keeps on
going, then
it blows up, and then sort of flushes its
way out, okay?
So here's an example of how you might do
this in a running program, like the
programs that you're about to be assigned,
where
you're supposed to check for user input
having errors.
So, here is a little conversion of a
number, and
and so we're saying, you know, enter a number,
and we're putting a string into rawstr.
It's a string, and and so, we don't know.
And here's where we're going to convert it
into an integer,
and we're just not sure if it's going to
work or not.
So, we know how int works. It either
converts it or it blows up.
So we know
it's going to do that, we just don't
know what the user's going to type, we
don't know.
So we have to take out insurance on it.
So this runs,
and then we do a try, and then we
try to convert it,
and if it works, it's great, and if
it fails, it runs this and sets it to
negative 1.
And afterwards, we either have the number
or negative 1.
And so, if the person enters 42,
it says Nice work.
Well, let's show you where it runs.
If the person says 42, it runs through
here, gets the string 42, converts that
to an integer, skips here, and then says,
Nice work, and that's how it runs.
If, on the other hand, they type
forty two, the words,
this gets to be the string forty two.
It runs here, this blows up.
So it comes and runs this part here.
And then it says, if ival is greater than
0, which is not true,
so it runs this part and says
Not a number.
So this is our way of compensating for
user input
that might have errors in it, errors that
we're anticipating, right?
You'd, you'd rather at least
put up some kind of a
message, rather than just have a
traceback,
if you're writing code for somebody else.
It just kind of is
not very classy. So,
the classic program to do this is a
time-and-a-half for overtime pay.
So you get some pay rate like
$10 an hour for your first 40 hours,
and then you get 15 hours, for
any hours above it.
So you have to sort of say, oh, okay, if
this ends up being, this ends up being
some kind of a thing, where, let me draw
that picture a little better.
Hours greater than 40, you're going to do
one thing, and
if hours are less than 40, you're going to
do another thing.
So you have two payout calculations.
If the hours are greater than 40, then
you're going to do
a overtime calculation, which is kind of
like, 40 times the regular rate.
And then, the number of excess hours,
like 5 overtime hours
times the reg, rate times
one-and-a-half.
So this is kind of the calculation that
happens if the hours are greater than 40.
And then, if the hours are less than 40,
it's just pay
equals rate times hours.
So it, you're going to do one of two
calculations, depending on how it works.
So that's one of the programming problems
for this chapter.
That's a classic.
It's the classic if, then, else.
You can actually do it with an if, then
if you're tricky.
There's a lot of ways to do this, so pick
a, pick one and do it.
Now the next thing I want you to do is, I
want you to take that
same program, do it again in another,
another assignment, or another problem in
the chapter, and that is have some kind of
a non-numeric input, and have it blow up.
So if they type, you know, something like
nine, put out an error.
Or, if they type something here, put out
an error.
Now, don't write a loop.
No loop.
This is one execution of the program, and
this is another execution of the program.
Later, we can write loops.
We haven't even talked about loops.
So this is running it twice.
All I want you to do is exit.
So take a look in the book as to how to
just get out.
So it, it's, it, I don't want you to try
to say, I'm going to
prompt for these numbers until I get a
good one, we'll do that later.
I just want you to deal with the
fact that
you read a thing, you use the try
to convert it to a float and see if it
works.
And if you don't, you just quit.
Don't, don't, don't try to be tricky and
repeatedly prompt.
So don't repeatedly prompt.
One prompt, and then
quit, okay?
So, this is contintous-,
conditional execution, if, if then else,
and then I added a little bit with
the try and except, as well.
And the try and except is really a
limited kind of a problem.
It really is to compensate for errors that
you anticipate are going to happen, and
you can imagine what you want to do
as a replacement for what those
errors are, okay?
See you next lecture.