Hello.
My name is Charles Severance,
and I'd like to welcome you
to the launch of
online.dr-chuck.com.
I decided to create my
own MOOC environment,
mostly because my personal
research is in technology,
and teaching and learning.
And I absolutely love
teaching in Coursera,
and I love working
with Stanford Class2Go.
But really, for me to
do the kind of research
that I want to do,
I need to create
my own environment,
an environment that I
can do AB testing myself.
I don't want to just be in
someone else's environment.
And I continue to work in
all those environments.
And I want to sort of take
what my core values are.
I'm passionate about open.
I'm passionate
about open source.
about open content.
And now, this MOOC adds the
dimension of open enrollment.
So I'm trying to make it so
that my MOOC, based on Python,
this particular class
I'm going to teach,
which is the first I'll put
into my MOOC environment,
is really as much
for teaching teachers
as it is for teaching students,
being that when you're
done with this class,
you can walk away
with the material in this class.
You can remix this material.
You can teach your own classes.
It's based on this free
book that I've written
called Python for Informatics.
This is an open book you
have to buy the books.
We print them here at the
University of Michigan,
but you can download
a PDF, and HTML,
and you can have the
source code to the book.
It's Creative
Commons Attribution.
And so the course
I'm going to teach
is also a very special course.
It means a lot to me.
I have a passion
about teaching people
to program without
trying to teach
them to be computer scientists.
I think it's wonderful to
be a computer scientist,
but I also think a lot of
people just need to program
and just need to kind of
understand how data works.
And so this class is going to
stay away from mathematics.
It's really going
to focus on data.
The book is called Python
for Informatics Exploring
Information.
So I hope that you'll consider
joining me on this quest
and come join the class.
We'll have two classes, one
would start January 14, 2013,
and the other will be this thing
called the playground, which
you can come and join any time.
I'm not giving any
certificates or badges
or anything like that.
I will have kind of a hall of
fame that if you, you know,
pass the class, you can put
yourself in the hall of fame
if you so choose.
If you don't want to,
you don't have to.
So I thank you for
thinking about joining me
on this expedition.
I hope you, like I said,
that you enroll and play
with some of the
things that I've put up
and give me some feedback.
This whole thing is a beta test.
I'm just one guy, and I'm
like coding this up by myself,
and trying to teach my
classes and write this code
and keep these systems running.
So be a little patient.
And I'm always
looking for feedback.
You know, see me
on Twitter @drchuck
or let me know how you think.
We'll see how the next couple
of months go as I try to make
my own personal MOOC
environment online.dr-chuck.com.