Hello, and welcome to
the Worked Exercises
for Python for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
I'm Charles Severance, and I'm
your guide and guest programmer
for this particular example.
As always, this material is
copyright, Creative Commons
attribution.
So we've been working
through a series of exercises
that are doing time
and a half for overtime
and pay of various kinds, to
look at various if-then else.
Now we're on to functions.
And so we're going
to create a function
called compute pay that takes
two parameters, hour and rate.
And it actually does exactly
the same thing as the other one.
It's just we're doing
it in a different way.
OK?
So we will start by running
TextWrangler and the Terminal
program.
Turn the program smaller
and get to the bottom.
TextWrangler smaller.
And let's go CD desktop,
CD Python for Informatics.
And there we are,
got some files here.
Let's make use of Hours2.py.
So I'm going to open Hours2.py.
Hours3.py was Maya.
Actually, I'll use
Hours3.py because that's
my try accept code.
OK.
So the idea is is we're supposed
to encapsulate this bit of code
in a function
called compute pay.
So one of the things
you do with functions
is you have to define
them before you use them.
So we're going to
put the function up
here and use the Def keyword.
Def, compute pay.
And we're going to
accept some parameters.
I'm going to call
it H and R, just
to emphasize the difference
between the parameters
we use inside the function
and the arguments in the call.
So the code needs to be in this
function is these lines of code
right here.
So we're going to
cut them out of here
and then we're going
to indent them and make
them the body of the function.
OK.
So now the variables
in this function
are not H-- are
not hours and rate.
They're P-- I'm going to just
change them all to this--
and I'm just changing
this to kind of emphasize
the difference between
these variables that
live in the function
and the variables that
live in the calling code.
So in the function, they're
called H and R and P.
And the only one other
thing I'm going to do
is I want to put a return
statement in to return P
as the result of the function.
And so the Python will come in.
It'll see the Def.
It'll read all this stuff.
It won't do it.
Then the first
executables is try.
It still works the same way.
And then change this
to be in the main code.
Rate and hours.
And then I'm going to put
a print statement just
for yucky doodles.
Print in compute pay.
And print out H and R. And then
before I do my return here,
I'm going to say--
I'm going to print out
what I am sending back.
And print out the computed pay.
And then the only
thing I have to do left
is I got the rate and
the hours, and I'm
going to call my function.
So I'm going to say pay
equals compute pay, or invoke
the function and pass in rate
and hours as my arguments.
And then print it out.
So here's the main code.
Oop, well, I'll just
say we are back.
And then print out pay.
So I have a print before and
after the call to compute pay.
And I have a print
once compute pay starts
and when compute pay finishes.
I have to reorganize my
screen a little bit here.
We can see them all.
I got to save this as something
else so I don't ruin ours too.
I'll call this Hours4.py.
And I'm going to save Python.
Hours before .py.
OK.
So I'll type.
So what's happened here is
it's typing in our hours
so it's on this
line here, line 11.
It's already made it all
the way through here.
OK?
I'm going to print
statement in a second here.
So there we go.
It's made it through.
It hasn't done any work
but it remembered this code
and stored it under
the name compute pay.
And it's here.
So now I'll do hours.
40 hours and $10.
So I'm running through
this code right here.
And then I want it here
next, because we're not
going to put bad hours in.
So the next line that
happened is in the main code,
which is here.
Then it called compute
pay right there.
[? Sewed ?] it up here.
And h is 10, and r is 40.
It doesn't quite look right.
But the compute pay,
we're done, and that's 400
and everything is cool.
So it's back, right?
So let's do this.
Let's do another one.
And I'll put in 50
hours and $10 an hour.
That one should have overtime
because we put in 50 hours,
but it's not.
So what is the problem here?
10 and 50 are coming in.
We're getting the numbers right.
We're going into compute
pay and it's 10 and 50.
Then we're coming back.
So we're printing out the
hours, the H and the R variable.
Oh, ooh, I see it.
I see it.
The mistake is right
here and right here.
Can you see it?
We have user parameters.
And these are arguments, these
are the real variables, rate
and hours.
The parameters are H and
R. We got two parameters
but we've got the order wrong.
So here I have rate first.
So H here is rate.
And look, if we look at what we
print out here in compute pay,
the first thing
we print out is H.
But it's really 10, which
is supposed to be rate.
Oops.
So I got to fix this.
That should be R to correspond
to the first parameter.
And that should
be H to correspond
to the second parameter.
And just to keep my sanity, I'm
going to print out R comma H,
so I'll say rate hours,
just to be consistent.
No, no, no.
Since I'm prompting for
hours and rate, h comma r,
I change this to be h comma r.
And then make this
be hours comma rate.
Because I think it makes more
sense for hours to be first.
I don't know why that
makes more sense.
But now we're corresponding
our mnemonic variables inside
of our function, or h and r,
that allude to hours and rate.
But they're not the
same as hours and rate.
So h is an alias to hours
when this is called.
OK?
So now let's run it again
and see if she works.
So I'll do 50 hours.
$10 an hours.
Oh, I'll bet I didn't save it.
50 hours, $10 an hour.
Yay, it works.
It works.
We got ourselves our overtime.
OK.
So let me say, H equals
and then I'm going to add R
equals here, just so
we know which rate
and what H and R are.
Just add some strings there.
Run it again.
If I'd done that
in the first place,
I probably would not
have made that-- I'd have
seen that mistake much faster.
So we've got 50 hours
and $10 per hour.
And so it's working.
So just to continue on here
on this, I could do this.
I could call this
function again.
And I could say, just to show
you I'm reusing this code,
I'm going to make
a variable named Z.
And I'm going to say
12.2 is my parameter.
My second parameter
is $10 an hour.
And so now I'm using constants
instead of variables.
And you'll see that it's
going to call compute pay once
this time and H
and R going to be
hours and rate the first time.
In the second time, they're
going to be called again,
but 12 and 10 are
going to be what
H and R are the second time.
And then print ZZZZ comma z.
That's just a silly message.
OK?
So we're going to--
this stuff is unchanged.
It just prompts and
gets us the rate.
We're going to call compute
pay twice this time.
One time with hours and
rate, and the second time
with 12.2 and 10.0 Let's
take a look at how that runs.
I mean maybe a little longer.
Let's see.
50 hours, $10 an hour.
Oh, yeah, it would
help for me to save.
Help for me to save.
Don't make that mistake.
50 hours, $10 an hour.
OK.
So in the main code,
then it calls compute pay
and does one computation.
And then it's here, it's back
in the main code right there.
And then it calls
compute pay again.
This time the variables
H and R are 12.2 and 10.0
The last time, H and
R were 50 and 10.
OK?
The key is this H and R, the
parameters in the function
are ephemeral.
They come and they go.
Compute pay works with
different values each time,
but it uses H and R
internally as kind
of its scratch area for this.
See if I can get this all
on one screen, yes, I can.
OK.
So this is just showing
that we're running it twice,
once H is 50 and the next
time is 12 because it's simply
the first parameter.
And the first time
the parameter was 50.
The second time is was 12.2.
OK?
So let's just walk
through, scribbling
what's going on here.
We'll just kind of
go through this.
So Python starts
at the beginning.
It sees Def, and it says,
oh, don't run this code.
Remember it.
Name it compute pay.
So H and R don't exist.
They don't exist until
a function is invoked.
Then we get to try.
We've got some insurance
on these four lines.
We read our-- and
convert our input
and I write our
hours and our rate.
Good, so we don't
run the accept.
Then we print in the main code.
OK.
And then we come to this line.
We see compute pay.
And so that goes up here.
And H and R are hours and rate.
And it runs this code.
It returns P, and that P
comes back as the value
here and end being put into pay.
Then we print we are back.
Then we run into this statement.
And we have to call compute pay.
So it goes up again.
This time h and r are 12 and 10.
Run through the code,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
And then returns 122.
And that returns to this
call, not the previous one.
And then that puts 122 into z.
And then the program
continues on.
So again, this does nothing.
And it calls it twice and
has two sets of arguments.
And the parameters represent
different arguments
in the different call.
OK?
So let me just clean
this up one last time
and get rid of a-- oops, get rid
of the debug print statements.
Get rid of that.
Get rid of this.
So you can see what it's
really supposed to look like.
We don't need that.
Well, I'll just comment that
one out to keep in case later.
This is debug print.
So I'll keep that,
get rid of those two.
So now it doesn't
do any printing.
So let's run it one more time.
40, 10, good stuff.
50, 10, good stuff.
So it works.
So there's the ultimate
program and looks pretty good.