Hello and welcome to
Python for Informatics.
I'm Charles Severance.
And I'm the teacher
for the course.
So I always like start,
when I teach a course,
and talk about who
should take the course.
And I have written this book.
And I'm teaching this
course with the notion
that everybody should
know some programming.
Not necessarily that
everyone is supposed
to be a computer scientist
or professional programmer,
but I really believe that
everyone should understand
this world that
we live in, that's
increasingly full of gadgets
that have microprocessors
in them and displays.
And I think it helps
us understand our world
and make sense of it, to
know a little something
about programming.
And most of the jobs that you're
ever going to get these days
are going to have something
to do with technology.
And so just a little
understanding.
You may become curious, and
you may want to learn more.
And you may want to learn
about the web and databases
and all kinds of things.
But right now I just want to
give you a basic understanding
of how things work.
I'd be real happy if
we made you curious.
So I always like to start,
talk a little bit about myself,
so you know who I am.
I am at the University
of Michigan,
and I'm a clinical
associate professor.
And you can follow
me on Twitter.
I generally don't friend
students on Facebook
until long after
they've graduated
and if they're really friends.
So don't do that.
But you can follow
me on Twitter.
I do like Twitter.
I have all kinds of stuff
on Flickr and other places.
And I live my life
pretty openly.
And so you can see
what's going on.
I have a long history
in computer programming.
I was one of the leaders of
the Sakai open source learning
management system that
some of you may have used.
Some of you may have used
Moodle, the other open source
learning management system.
Teaching and learning with
technology is my research area.
And prior to that,
I was a guy that
did high-performance computing.
That was my research
area as well.
And I have hobbies of
off-road motorcycling.
And I play hockey every week.
You can see a little
picture of me there.
And the one year that
we won the playoffs,
and you see that I'm somewhere
in there wearing a cast.
I broke this finger during
the hockey playoffs.
And I didn't want to get
it cast until-- I broke it
in the semi finals--
and I didn't want
to let go until the finals.
So I played the final with
a broken finger, and we won.
And that's the cup
that I'm holding there.
And then I got my finger cast.
Another thing-- like I said,
I've worked on Sakai a lot.
And I have even had
the audacity to write
a book about that experience.
Open source is a very
passion-provoking thing.
And it's really quite wonderful.
And so that's my tattoo.
You see the Sakai tattoo.
It's on the book.
It's a real, live tattoo.
And as a matter of fact,
since I finished as the lead--
I still work on Sakai.
I'm just not in
charge anymore-- I
put a ring of tattoos of
all the different learning
management systems-- Blackboard,
Desire2Learn, Canvas, Moodle--
all the ones that
implement the standard
that I helped promulgate.
IMS Learning Tools
Interoperability.
And it is actually featured
throughout this class.
It's how we plug
things together.
You might see things flashing
by that LTI in the URL.
And that's because
of this standard
that I spent four years of my
life trying to get adopted.
And it has been adopted.
I'm really pretty proud of that.
And then sort of one
last silly thing.
You may have met me already
without even knowing it.
I did a project where I had
students do viral videos.
And I try to do a
viral video myself.
And so I did this iPad
steering wheel mount.
It caused a lot of people to
put a lot of mean comments
about me, about how what
smart-- or not so smart--
guy I really am.
So feel free to
take a look at that.
I have a sense of humor.
I hope that you figured
that out by now.
I didn't set out, when I was
young, to be a programmer.
I'm older than most of you.
Not necessarily all of you,
but older than most of you.
And back when I
was in high school,
the notion of programming
as an avocation
was rather rare thing.
And I was a pretty
smart guy, knew my way
around mathematics and
physics and things like that.
And I went to college in
1975, in the fall of 1975.
And the adviser said, hey,
take this programming class.
We're putting all
the freshmen into it.
And so in I go.
And they put me in this class.
And this class started at
an outrageously early time.
It was 10:30 in the morning.
And I was enjoying myself
greatly and playing
a lot of video games.
That was when you actually went
someone to play video games,
rather than play video
games at your house.
And I was really
enjoying collage.
And I figured out that
you could skip class,
and no one would care.
And so I skipped,
started skipping
lot of these really early
10:30 in the morning classes.
And at one point about halfway
through the semester, I walk in
and they're handing
out pieces of paper
with a midterm exam on it.
And I look at this
piece of paper,
and apparently I
missed a lot of class,
because almost none of the
words made any sense to me.
Somehow, that sort of shocked
me into actually going to class.
And I picked up
quickly after that.
I really learned that
programming was not
so much about trying
to please the computer,
but instead the computer
would do anything I wanted.
If I would just learn
its simple language
and explain to it in its simple
language what I wanted done,
that it would dutifully
go off and do whatever
it is that I wanted.
And so I became a prodigy in
the second half of this class.
And I got all the
programming caught up.
And I did extra assignments
and did all these cool things.
And at the end of the
class, I got a D. I got a D.
But then I changed my
major to computer science.
And I really enjoyed it.
It's been a great
profession for me.
But I understand.
I understand how you may
be a little bit confused
as you're learning this.
And so I really understand
it as I go through this.
And I really built this book
and this course-- this book
and this course--
to address those who
might be a little bit nervous.
I give you lots of
recorded videos, et cetera.
So let's talk a little
bit about the course.
The book that I
just mentioned is
called Python for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
It's a book that I wrote.
I wrote specifically to
be different than most
of the first programming
books that you'll pick up.
A lot of computer scientists
see computer science
and programming as
applied mathematics.
And when you get into
advanced programming,
you certainly have to
have a really strong grasp
of mathematics for
a lot of reasons.
But you don't need so much
mathematics in the beginning.
So this book is actually adapted
from another computer science
book that was a free and
open book that I adapted.
But I took the math out.
I took the math out, and
I put in all about data.
And that's why I call
Exploring Information.
It's free.
You can download as HTML.
You can download it as a PDF.
You can download it on iBooks.
You can download
it on ePub reader.
I've got that version.
You go to www.PythonLearn.com.
And it's all free.
Because of some little
bits of complexity,
I can't sell a paper
copy of this book yet.
At some point, I've got
to rewrite a few more
chapters of it to be
completely belonging to me.
And then I can actually
sell a printed copy.
But for now it's actually
only available to people
who can somehow make it
to Ann Arbor, Michigan,
and buy it from our library.
So one of the theories of
this book and this course
is open content.
My book is free.
My book is remixable.
My lecture slides are
Creative Commons Attribution.
My recorded videos are
sitting there on YouTube.
You can use them
any way you like.
Or use them inside the
context of my class,
inside the context
of your class.
Use them as a study guide.
I really don't care.
The videos are Creative
Commons with attribution.
And all the software
that I'm using
for this class--
both the online code
and the Moodle and the Sakai
that I'm using in the class--
it's all open source as well.
And when I finish the course,
each time I finish it,
I will make a zip
file or a backup file
from Moodle and
Common Cartridge,
to the point where if you
have a Moodle or a Sakai,
you can load this stuff
into-- or even Blackboard
or Desire2Learn-- you
should be able to load
this stuff in and
then remix the course
to your own satisfaction.
And the reason is is that to
me these large scale courses,
everyone's so excited
about how many students are
these large scale
courses, and somehow
that these students are going
to take the course from me.
And I become
well-known, et cetera.
I really believe that in
the long term, for this
to really change education
in the way that many of us
want to see education
changed, we have to teach
and empower teachers.
And so I'm hopeful that
some of you watching this
are actually teachers and
are going to come in here
and figure out how
to make sense of this
and use it in your
own classroom.
I want to empower the
teachers to take this material
and teach with this material
and use me as a supplement
to their own teaching, rather
than me doing all the teaching.
I think that all
these things need
to be localized to
different cultures,
different cultural references,
different examples,
different languages.
Just merely translating
parts of things
into a different language--
just not to me satisfactory.
And so if you're a
teacher, get a hold of me.
In the early days,
I might even want
to have you teach on my
infrastructure to test it out.
Part of this is for me
to build the cool stuff
and see what everyone thinks,
what works, what doesn't work.
So this to me is the
learning activity
in the kind of ways we use
technology to enhance learning,
is a curiosity to me.
And whether you're
a teacher or not,
I'm always curious about how
effective this is working
and how it can be improved.
Because I think we
should all come up
with a way to help each
other teach better.
So the Python that
we're teaching
is-- there's two
versions of Python.
One is Python 3.
It's the newest and the latest.
But it's not completely
widely adopted yet.
And so we still use
the old Python 2.
I don't really
apologize for that,
because most of the industry
is still using Python 2.
And Python 3 is just there.
And people are slowly but
surely converting to it.
But it was designed as
a many-year transition,
where both Python 2 and
Python 3 would continue.
So I mentioned that the
course that we're teaching
is going to use some
pretty cool technology.
And it's all open source.
And if you look at
the URLs, you can
find where the source
to all this stuff is.
Figure all this out.
And it's open source, so
you could adapt it or use it
or install it or do whatever.
So the course starts, of
course, with-- unless you're
taking the course on the
Michigan campus, when you'll
start in our CTools
system-- but if you're not
taking the course
from Michigan campus,
you start on this kind
of enrollment site,
called Dr. Chuck Online.
Dr. Chuck Online is
where you sign in,
where you put your
profile in, you
put your location information.
And then you enroll
in the classes.
And then it tracks your overall
progress towards completion.
The actual course instruction is
not done with Dr. Chuck Online.
I have a copy of Moodle.
And this is Moodle.
Many of you may have used
Moodle at various places
around the world.
I happen to be using
Moodle because it's
got software that allows me
to connect it into Dr. Chuck
Online most effectively.
I'd like to use not just
Moodle in this situation,
but I'd like to be able to
launch multiple learning
management systems.
But you'll go through
Moodle, and you'll
see, for example, that will be
things like a discussion forum,
and then things
you're supposed to do.
An these'll sort of be ordered.
It's kind of like an
outline of the course.
Here's what you're
supposed to do.
You're supposed to read
this, take this lecture,
watch this, do this,
turn in the problem.
This is just kind of
a mock-up right now.
As I put the lectures up,
it'll build quite nicely.
Now one of the
interesting things
here is I've got an autograder.
An autograder makes
it so that you
can get immediate feedback
on whether your programs are
right or wrong.
So when you click on one
of these autograders,
you actually go into
another program.
And so this is the autograder.
And the idea is is that you
are to write a program that
uses raw input to prompt
a user for their name
and welcomes them.
And I'll give you some animated
walk-throughs, so you see this.
The first few I will
show you exactly what
to do, click for click,
so you get used to it.
These first few programs
are just simple.
But it's more to get
used to writing a program
and then running it
through the autograder.
And so the idea
is you've written
the program somewhere on
your laptop or your computer.
And you've debugged it
and you've got it working.
And this particular program only
has two lines of Python in it.
It prompts for a name and
then prints the name out.
But you come and then you would
paste in the working program
right here.
And then you press
this Check Code button.
Press the Check Code button,
and then it does some thinking.
It runs your code and checks
to see if your output matches
what it's supposed to say.
So this is the output
of your program.
And this is the output that the
program is supposed to produce.
And first it checks to see
if there's any mistakes
and gives little notes and
tells you where are mismatching.
And then it finishes.
And you're matched OK.
And that's great.
And then what it does
is it does a few more
checks to see if you're sneaky
or cheating or just whatever.
So it'll give you little notes.
Say, hey, you're supposed
to do this and this.
And you seem to not
use this or that.
Both to catch you and but
also if you miss something,
it might help you.
When it's all said and done,
it'll say, congratulations.
The exercise is complete.
Then you press the
Submit Grade button.
And then the grade-- all
the grades are 0 or 1--
it's submitted back to Moodle.
So let me go back here.
So that means that your
grade will come back
into this Moodle.
And if you go down a
little farther down here,
you will see your grades.
And then you'll be able
to immediately check
to see if your grade
has been updated.
And inside a Moodle, you
will see a bunch of grades.
And then you'll
see your progress
on each of those grades.
Now the other thing that
happens is that the grade then
moves back up.
It takes 15 minutes for the
grade to make it back here.
But this is kind of like
your overall course progress.
And this little
bar moves across.
This one here says it's one.
And that means
I've completed it.
I've got all the points.
Actually that's the
Python playground
that I've got all the points in.
And away you go.
And so that's how it works.
We go from launching
into the course.
We do all our learning in here.
We launch into the autograder.
And then we type our program
in here, hit the Check.
And if it says your
exercise is complete,
then the Submit Grade appears.
And then you send your grade.
And the grades work
their way back up.
And at some point, you
pass the class when
you reach the passing
[? grade. ?] Again,
I'm going to come
back and touch on this
and give you some explicit
instructions on how to do this.
There's also a threaded
discussion called Piazza.
This is a code that I'm using
to help threaded discussion.
You can get help from the
other students in the class,
give help.
It's just a place for us to
meet and to talk to each other.
And when you're all done,
you will end up in a map.
And so this is the map, sort of
early before registration map.
We got 121 students
in the class.
And here you see all where
all the students are at.
They're all over the place.
We already got students from
all over the world in the class.
We have 121.
By the time it starts,
there'll be many more.
You'll be able to see
how many there are.
And these change color.
They start out at green.
And then they move through
sort of pink and yellow.
It's kind of like horse ribbons.
So when you are successful,
you will get a blue ribbon.
Culturally, the ribbon color
is not uniform culturally.
But for most
cultures, blue ribbons
are number one and red
ribbons are number two.
I think yellow are number
three, and pink are number four.
And green is somewhere
in the bottom.
So basically you can see
this as we all start out
as green when we start.
And then as we make progress,
we go to like things
like yellow and pink.
And then when we've totally
achieved everything,
we get a blue.
And so this is the
Python playground,
where people can play.
So it's a lot easier
to get a blue ribbon
in the Python playground.
And so you'll notice I
sort of glossed over this.
There are two classes.
One class is the Python
for Informatics class.
And that is a
structured class where
I will be participating in it
on a daily or weekly basis.
And other students--
and I'm mixing
my off-campus and
on-campus students--
and so it has to
start a certain time,
because I'm using it
both for my off-campus
and on-campus students.
So you'll see another
100 or so students come
in from my on-campus class.
And they'll be going through
it too at the exact same time.
So this is a mixing of
my on-campus students
and my off-campus students.
And I think that's
particularly awesome and cool.
And so if you're going to enroll
in Python for Informatics,
you got to enroll sometime
between January 14 and 28.
I'm not going to give
you forever to catch up.
But if you're watching this
sometime other than January 14
to the 20-- and I'll
give the class again
after that-- but the
Python for Informatics
is when I or someone else is
monitoring the class actively.
But if you just want to
go in and do the problems
by yourself, as I put the
problems into the Python
for Informatics, I will also put
them in the Python playground.
The Python playground, you
can go in any time you like.
Go as long as you like.
Do it all by yourself.
Earn a blue ribbon.
There you go.
You've earned a blue ribbon
in Python playground.
It'll be pretty much the same
as in Python for Informatics.
The difference is
Python for Informatics
is at a given time during
a given time period.
And that's when I'm
going to teach the class.
That's when I'm going
to teach the class.
And I hope to have other
teachers teach the class.
And so they can have
their own version of this.
And they can teach it when
they want on whatever schedule
that they want.
And if I get a lot of
students that want to join up,
I can open another thing.
And if I get enough
students, maybe I'll
teach it in the middle of
the summer or something.
I can do this any
time, but I want
to make it so that there's
a time for me to focus
on the class, to be
in the class with you.
So you can do the
Python playground
anytime starting right now.
And the problems
and the assignments
will be pretty much the same.
You can use the Python
playground to pre-study.
But I don't have it set up yet.
The Python playground will
grow along with the class.
Once I'm done with the
class the first time,
the Python playground will be
the entire and complete class.
And then I might tweak
it each time I teach it.
That's how I
generally do classes.
And Python playground
will always
have been the last time
I taught the class.
But you will stay in
Python playground forever
and ever and ever.
And all your little
blue ribbons and stuff
will stay forever and
ever in Python playground.
Python playground is
set up so that even
if I change the
grading rules, if you
get a blue ribbon in
Python playground,
you can have a blue ribbon
forever and ever and ever.
So welcome to the class.
Bring your friends.
I think we will
have a lot of fun.
It's not as sophisticated as
things like Udacity or Coursera
or edX, because I'm it.
I'm writing software.
I'm the teacher.
I'm the everything.
But with great responsibility
comes great flexibility.
And so I am really enjoying and
looking forward to this class.
I'm looking forward
to hearing from you
and the comments you might have
as we go through the class.