Hello, and welcome
to a Worked Exercise
for Python for Informatics--
Exploring Information.
My name is Dr.
Charles Severance,
and I'm your host for this
particular worked exercise.
This material is copyright
Creative Commons Attribution.
Again, try to work these
exercises yourself.
In the beginning, they're
intended to be easy.
They're intended to
be work from the book
and the other materials,
and this is supposed
to be used as a last resort.
But you're here, so I
assume you know those rules.
I assume that you also
have everything installed--
Python is installed.
You know how to use
your text editor.
your Command Line.
This screencast will not sort
of go through all of those.
Although, it will
review some of them.
Go back to pythonlearn.com,
and go through the software
installation screencast
to get to the point
where your ready
to run programs.
So here's our exercise.
We are going to
write the program.
It's going to enter the
hours and enter the rate
and then compute pay.
It's going to prompt
and read some strings
and convert from floating point
and then do some multiplication
and away we go.
So let's minimize that.
I will start up my TextWrangler.
And this is the last
program I was working on.
And I'll get rid of those
and start up my terminal.
Make it a little bit smaller
and pull it down here.
And break down TextWrangler,
so now I have a new document.
And so I'm going to
do what I always do.
And so the first
thing we've got to do
is we've got to
prompt for some hours.
And so I'm going
to make a variable
called imp, which is just sort
of mnemonic for some input.
It's a string.
Because raw input
always reads a string.
It doesn't read-- even
though they're numbers,
it reads them as a string,
We'll have to convert them.
Raw_input ('Enter Hours: ")
And I'm just going to keep it
simple, and I'm going
to Print imp out.
Now I have to save
this file-- Save As--
and I'll put it in Python here.
And I'm going to
call it hours1.py
because we're going to do a
whole series of these things.
Save that.
Now you'll notice that as
soon as it saves as a .py,
that it does syntax coloring--
thank you very much.
So then I go into my
Command window, CD desktop.
I have everything in this
folder py4infs on my desktop--
right there, that folder-- CD.
And then I do ls.
Again, dir for unix,
and then here we go.
So I say python hours1.py.
Again-- and I use Tab
a lot because I just
don't like typing.
So let's run it.
So I enter some hours-- 1, 2,
3, and it prints out 1, 2, 3.
And just to show you
it's just a string,
I'll just put some
crap in there,
and out comes exactly as
you would expect-- crap.
And let's do this.
Let's just say I
print type(imp)--
just to sort of prove ourselves.
It's a string, right?
It is a string.
It is not an integer.
So how do we convert from a
string to an integer-- float.
We use the built
in function float.
And now I'm going to
call my variable hours
to be quite mnemonic.
And I'll call it the
float conversion.
And then I'll Print hours.
And Print the type of hours.
Now, you might say, hey, Chuck.
You're a pretty smart guy.
This is only like
five lines of code.
How come you're
doing this slowly?
How come it takes so many steps?
That's what we call
iterative development.
So I'm just being
really safe here.
I'll get to the whole
program in a bit.
I mean that's this dot,
dot, dot stuff down here.
There will be more.
But I'm just sort of playing
with it one bit at a time,
and making sure that I
know what's going on.
I'm doing this a little
bit more exaggerated here,
but when I write programs, I
usually start with hello world
and then add to it.
You start with sort of
a nice blank canvas,
and put some basic
stuff on the back of it.
OK, so now I'm going
to read some input
to prove that this is a string.
I'm going to convert the string
to a floating point-- put
in a different number.
Then I'll print out that
thing and the type of it
just to sort of be
sure that it works.
So I print python hours
1.py, and I go 1, 2, 3.
And it turns out that now I've
converted it to 1, 2, 3, 4,
and I've got myself a float.
And, of course, now if
I put junk in there,
it's going to get a trace back
here because it just cannot
convert dskj to float.
We're going to fix
that later, OK?
So now I'm going to start
deleting some of this stuff
because that's pretty
clear that that's working.
OK, so now, I've got
to promp for rate.
Well, good programmers don't
type if they don't have to.
So I'm just going to
Cut and Paste this.
And then I'm going to
change this to rate,
so raw_input("Enter Rate: ")
and then that'll be a string,
of course.
Then I will change
that to float.
And I'm going to
put that into rate.
And just to be sure, I'm going
to Print out rate, hours.
Now at this point, they should
be floating point numbers.
So let's run that.
We'll start with a simple
test-- 40 hours, $10 an hour.
There we go.
They've been converted to
floats-- just peachy fine.
So I'm going to create
a variable called
pay rate times hours.
And I'm going to Print out pay.
And I will just get rid of
this one with a comment.
And notice how I used
a comment, a pound sign
there because I'm
not deleting that.
I keep that in case
something goes wrong.
I don't think it's going
to, but here we go.
Whoa, syntax error-- invalid
syntax, pay rate times hours.
Oh, I forgot the
equal sign-- need
to make that an
assignment statement.
So let's try this again--
python hours 1, 40, 10, 400.
There we go.
And let me go check.
Let's run the data-- 35 and 275.
I'll run my program
again-- 35, $2.75 an hour,
and 6.23 is my sample
example, right?
Yes it is.
So there we go.
So here you have it--
powers and rate equal pay.