Hello.
And welcome to chapter two.
Hope you enjoyed chapter one.
It was the one longer
lectures, trying
to motivate you a little bit.
And now we're going to kind
of go back to the basics.
Chapter one covered sort
of the first four or five
chapters of the book.
So as always, this
video, the slides
are copyright Creative
Commons Attribution as well as
the audio.
And so now we're going
to talk about sort
of the really low
level things that
make up the Python language.
Constants-- some of
this is terminology
just so I can say
the word constant
and you won't freak out.
Constant is as
contrasted with something
that changes, is variable.
We'll talk about variables
in the next slide.
But for now, constants.
Constants are
things that are sort
of natural and instinctive,
things like numbers, 123, 98.6,
or hello world.
And so what I'm
doing here is we're
using the Python interpreter.
And that's how you can
tell the Chevron prompt.
And I'm saying print 123.
And then Python
responds with 123.
Print 98.6, Python responds with
98.6 and print 'hello world.'
So the constants
are the 123, 98.6,
and 'hello world.'
So these are things,
we can use either single
quotes or double quotes to make
strings.
And so programs kind of
work with numbers and work
with strings.
And we have these non-varying
values that we call constants.
So the other side of the
picture is the variable.
And the way I like to
characterize a variable
is it's a place in the
memory of the computer.
We give it a name
as a programmer.
We pick the variable name.
In this, I'm saying x
equals 12.2 and y equals 14.
I am choosing the name.
And I'm choosing
what to put in there.
This is a statement called
an assignment statement.
And the way to think of
the assignment statement
is that it sort of
has a direction.
We're saying, dear Python,
go find some memory.
I will use the label x later
to refer to that memory.
And take the number 12.2
and stick it into x.
This is sequential code.
Then the next thing
I want you to do
is I'd like you to go find
some more memory, call it y.
I will call it y later,
and stick 14 in there.
And so that ends up sort
of with two little areas
of memory, one labeled x.
And here's a little
cell in which
we'd like a draw or something.
And one labeled y,
and we put 12.2.
After these lines run, we
have 12.2 in one and 14
in the other.
Then for example, if there's
another line that's down here,
so there's this third line
after this has happened,
after this has
happened, x equals 100.
Remember, this has kind
of got a direction to it.
Oh, remember that x that I had?
I would like now
to put 100 in that.
So as I'm thinking
this through, I
think of that as
sort of removing
the 12.2 or overriding the 12.2
and putting 100 in its place.
And so at the end here,
x is left with 100.
And y is left with 14.
So these variables can kind
of have one value in them.
And we can look at them, and
we can reuse them and put
different values in if we want.
There's some rules for
naming your variables.
Again, you get to pick
the variable names.
Often, we pick variables
that makes some sense.
We'll talk about
that in a second.
In Python, variables can
start with an underscore.
We tend not to, as normal
programmers, use those.
We let libraries use those.
It has to have letters, numbers,
and underscores and start
with a letter or an underscore.
Case matters, so spam
is good. eggs is good.
spam23 is good, because
the number is not
the first character.
_speed, that's also
perfectly fine,
because it starts with an
underscore or a letter.
23spam starts with a
number, so that's bad.
This starts with something other
than a letter or an underscore.
And you can't use a dot
in the variable name.
It turns out the dot
has meaning to Python
that would confuse it.
And it wouldn't understand
what we really mean there.
So that would be a syntax error.
Because case is
sensitive, that means
that things like
all lowercase spam
is different than a uppercase
S and all uppercase.
These are three distinct
variables that are unique.
Most people don't
choose variables
that might be so confusing.
So to you as you write
it, and as to anybody
that might read it, would
find three variables
named as very confusing.
So it's a bad idea.
Don't do it.
But I'm just showing
you as an example
that case can make a
variable name distinct.
And again, this variable
is a place in memory
that we are going to store
and retrieve information,
whether it be numbers
or strings or whatever.
These are things
that we control.
Now Python also has a
set of reserved words.
And what it really means is you
can't use these for variables.
These words have
very special meaning,
and, four, is, raise, if.
So you can't make
a variable name if.
It'll be like, oh, no.
That is if.
I know what if is.
So these are words that Python
has as its core vocabulary
and forbids you to use
them for other purposes,
like variable names or
later function names.
So that's kind of the
vocabulary, constants,
variables, and reserved words.
Now, we take these and
we start assembling them
into sort of sentences,
statements, Python statements
that do something.
So we've already talked about
an assignment statement.
It has kind of an arrow here.
It says, hey, Python, go
find me a place called x.
Take the number 2 and stick
it in there for later,
then continue on.
Now because there's an
arrow, the right side of this
is done first.
And you can kind of ignore for
the moment the left-hand side.
And it calculates
the right-hand side
by looking at the current value
for x, which happens to be 2.
And it adds these two things
together, and then gets 4.
And then at the point where it
knows that this number is 4,
it will then store
that back into x.
And so then later we print
x, and we will get the 4.
And so again, this is
a sequence of steps.
And the variable x changes
as these steps continue.
And we're saying print
x, that really means
print the current value for x.
So we can do a number
of different operators
and assignment statements.
We calculate this
right-hand side.
This is sort of all
calculated, whatever this is,
based on the
current value for x.
It does this calculation.
And then when it knows
what the answer is,
it assigns that
into the variable
that's on the left-hand side
of the assignment statement.
Again, calculate the right-hand
side completely, and then move
it to the left-hand side.
Some early languages actually
didn't use the equal sign
for the assignment operator.
This assignment
operator, in a way,
it kind of-- some languages,
an early language, actually
used an arrow.
Arrows aren't really
on people's keyboards.
Another language used colon
equals as this assignment
operator.
But we use equals.
Now if you're
familiar with math,
this can be a little confusing,
like x = 1, and then x = 2.
That, as mathematics,
would be bad math.
Because in a proof or a problem,
x can only have one value.
But in programming, if
this was two statements,
that means just x had
value, and then the value
for x changed later.
OK.
So I'll just kind
of go through this.
Because it's working
from the right-hand side
to the left-hand side on
assignment statements,
it is pulling out
these x values.
So x may have 0.6.
It pulls the values
out before sort
of ignoring this
part right here.
And it's just going to try
to resolve this expression.
And it has multiplication
and parentheses and things
like that.
So it basically pulls the
0.6 into the calculation,
does over 1 minus
x, which gives you
0.4, then it multiplies
these three things together,
giving 0.93.
And then what it is all
done with all of that,
it takes that 0.93, and
then puts it back into x.
And so this is just
sort of emphasizing
how the right-hand side is
computed to produce a value,
then it is moved
into the variable.
And that is why you can
have x on both sides.
Because this is like the
old, and this is the new.
The old x participates
in the calculation.
And then when the calculation
is done, it becomes the new x.
I hope that makes sense.
So this on the right-hand side
here is a numeric expression.
So we have a number of
different operators.
Some of them are instinctive,
intuitive, the plus
and the minus.
The reason some of these are
so weird is in really old days,
we didn't have too many
things on the keyboard.
And a lot of programs
are very mathematical.
And so they figured out what was
on the keyboard of the computer
equipment of the
day, and then they
had to fake certain things.
So it turns out that plus and
minus were on the keyboard.
And so plus and minus are
addition and subtraction
respectively.
There was no kind of times
operator for multiplication.
And dot was used
for decimal point.
So they used asterisks
for multiplication.
So in computers, languages,
nearly all of them,
they basically use a
times for multiplication.
Slash is used for division.
So we say like 8/2,
which is 8 divided by 2.
Raising something to the
power, like 4 squared,
that is double asterisk.
And then remainder is if
you do a division that
gives you the remainder
rather than divisor.
So 8 over 2 is 4, remainder 0.
So the remainder is what you get
with this particular operator.
There's a few cool
things that we
can do with remainder that we
won't talk about right away.
But it's there.
And so here's just a couple
of sample expressions.
I
Let's give me green, OK.
So again, I'm using
a Python interpreter.
So this is just the prompt.
The chevrons are the prompt.
Create the variable
xx, and assign it to 2.
Retrieve the old
value in an addition.
Then print it out and put it
back into xx, so xx has 4.
yy, this is a multiplication.
440 times 12 is 5,280.
yy over 1,000, this is
little counterintuitive.
Because yy is an
integer, it then
does it in a truncated division.
So 5,280 divided by 1,000 is 5.
And so that's an
integer division.
We'll see in a second about
floating point division.
Now we take the variable
jj and we set it to 23.
And now we're going to use
the modulo or remainder
operator to say what
is the remainder when
we divide this jj by 5.
And so if you think
about this, we
take old long division, 23
divided by 5, you end up
with 4, and then remainder 3.
The modulo operator, or the
percent, or the remainder
operator, gives us
back this number.
And so that's why kk is 3.
It is the remainder
of 23 when divided
by 5 or the remainder of
the division of 5 and 23.
And the raising to the
power 4 cubed is 4**3.
And so that end up being 64.
So that's just operations.
Now just like in
algebra and mathematics,
we have rules about which
operations happen first.
In general, things
like the power
happens before the
multiplication and division,
and then the addition
and subtraction happen.
So there are some rules when
you're looking at an expression
and trying to calculate
what its value is.
If you don't have parentheses,
it follows these rules.
And so the rule that sort
of trumps all the rules
is that parentheses
are always respected.
So a lot of us just write these
with parentheses in place, even
sometimes, though,
you don't need it.
Then after parentheses
have been handled,
then it does exponentiation.
Then it does multiplication,
division, and remainder.
And then it does
addition and subtraction.
And then, all else being equal,
it just works left to right.
So let's look
through an example.
So here is a calculation
that is 1 plus 2 times 3
divided by 4 over 5.
And the question is what
order does this happen?
OK.
And so let's sort of
take a look at this.
And so we start with are
there any parentheses?
And the answer is no.
There are no parentheses.
So let's go next.
Power.
And so the power says,
OK, let's look across
and find those things that
are raised to a power.
And the 2 cubed, or 2 the
third power, is the power.
So we're going to do that one.
And then the way
I do it when I'm
sort of doing these
slowly is I rewrite it.
So the 2 to the third
power becomes 8.
So it's 1 plus 8 over 4 times 5.
And then now we can say, power?
That's taken care of.
Now we're going to do
multiplication and division.
And we go across.
Now we have both a division
and a multiplication.
And multiplication and division
are done at the same time.
So that means we
do left to right,
which means we do the first
one that we encounter first.
So that will be 8 over 4,
because of the left to right
rule.
And so we find that one.
And that's the one that
gets computed next.
And that turns into two.
And again, I like to rewrite
these expressions just
to keep my brain
really, really clear.
After a while, you just
do it in your head.
But I rewrite them.
When I was first
learning them, at least,
I rewrote it all the time.
And so next, looking at this,
there's a multiplication.
We're not done with
multiplication yet.
So the 2 over 5
is the next thing.
And then we do that calculation,
and that becomes 10.
And again, we rewrite it.
And now we've done
the multiplication.
And we're going to
do addition next.
And that's just 1 over 10.
And that becomes 11.
And so basically,
this big long thing
through a series of
successive steps becomes 11.
And indeed, when we print
it out, that's what we get.
So there's the rules that
are parentheses, power,
multiplication, addition,
and then left to right.
But smart people usually
just put parentheses in.
So here's an example.
Go back, go back.
Here's an exam question.
Now, I wouldn't write
this code this way.
I would put a parenthese here.
And a parenthese there.
It's the same thing.
Because that's exactly-- the
2 times 3 is going to happen.
And the 4 over 5
is going to happen.
And then the plus and minus
will happen left to right.
But why not make it
easier on your readers
and just put the parentheses in?
Because they're redundant.
They're not necessary.
But away you go.
Now if you don't
want it to happen
in that order, of course, then
you have to put parentheses.
If you want the
addition to happen
before the multiplication, then
you have to put parentheses in,
which you can.
But we tend to recommended that
you use more parentheses rather
than less parentheses.
Now Python integer
division in Python 2,
which we are using
Python 2 for this class--
there's a new Python 3
that the world is slowly
transitioning to.
And a lot of people are
using it and teaching,
but it's not as common
sort of in the real world
with libraries and utilities.
And so we'll stick with
Python 2 for a few more years
until Python 3 really
kind of turns the corner.
It's nice to have it there.
But there's so much Python.
And it's so popular,
Python 2, that it's just
kind of hard to get
everybody up to Python 3.
So in Python 2, integer
division truncates.
And you saw that before,
where I did the 5,280 by 1,000
and I got 5.
But we can look at a couple of
examples that make this really
very quite clear.
So 10 divided by 2 is
5, as you would expect.
9 divided by 2 is 4, not
exactly what you'd expect.
You kind of expect that
to be 4.5 instead of four.
But in Python 3, it will be 4.5.
But for now, in Python
2, 9 over 2 is 4.
And 99 over 100 is 0.
Now that seems rather
counterintuitive.
But it is a truncating division.
It's not a rounding division.
It is a truncated division.
Now interestingly, if you
make either of these numbers
have a decimal, make them what
we call floating point numbers,
then the division is
done in floating point.
So 10.0 over 2.0 is 5.0.
Now these are different.
This is an integer number,
and this is a floating point
number.
It's 5.0.
And then 99.0 100.0 is
exactly as you would expect.
And it's a floating
point number.
Now you can also mix integers
and floating point numbers
as you go.
So here we have 99 over 100.
Those are both integers,
integer, integer.
And it comes out with zero,
because it's truncating.
Now if we have an integer
and a floating point number,
99 over other 100.0, then
that comes out as 0.99.
The either one, if
we have 99 over 100,
that's a floating point
and that's an integer,
we still end up with
a floating point.
So this is a floating
point, floating point,
and even in complex
expressions as it evaluates,
when it sees an integer.
So the first thing
you would evaluate
is this would become 6.
So it would be 1 plus
6 over 4.0 minus 5.
Then it would be
doing this 6 over 4.0,
and that would be 1.5.
1 plus 1.5 minus 5.
And so this is an integer,
and that's a floating point.
And the result becomes
a floating point.
And then the rest
of the calculation
is done floating point to the
point where the ultimate is
a floating point negative 2.5.
So you can throw a floating
point into a calculation.
And as soon as the calculation
touches the floating point,
the remainder of the calculation
is done in floating point.
It kind of converts
it to floating point.
But it doesn't want
to convert it back.
Because it considers floating
point sort of the more general
of the representations.
So here we are talking about
integers and floating points.
These are a concept in
programming languages
and in Python called type.
Variables and
constants have a type.
We can see that if
you say 1 versus 1.0,
it works differently, it
functions differently.
And so Python keeps
track of both variables
and literal slash constants
and having them have a type.
And we've seen this, right?
Now, the interesting
thing is Python
is very aware of the type
and can use the same syntax
to accomplish different things.
So if we look at this line
here, where we say dd = 1.4,
well, it looks at the 1 and
it looks at the 4 and says,
oh, those are two integers.
I will add those together
and give you a 5.
So it gives you an
integer and integer,
and an integer comes back.
And then ee = hello plus there.
Well, these are two
strings, hello and there.
And it says, hm, this
must be a concatenation.
So I'm going to
concatenate those together.
Because those are strings.
And I know how to
concatenate strings.
And that's kind of like
string addition, right?
And so we see hello
there as a result.
Now the interesting thing is
where did this space come from?
Let me change colors here.
Oops.
Where did that space come from?
Well, the plus does
not add the space.
There's a space right there.
And that's the space.
So I concatenated
hello space plus there.
And that's how I
got hello there.
But the key thing is is
this plus operator, clear.
This plus operator looks
to either side and says,
oh, they're strings.
I think you mean concatenation.
Here, it looks at
either side and says,
oh, those are integers.
I think you mean addition.
So Python is very aware of type.
And type informs Python
what you really mean.
So it looks like those
are kind of the same.
But they're quite
different operations.
So the type can
get you in trouble.
Remember, Python is
looking at the type.
So here we have a little
problem, our first trace back,
first of many trace backs.
So here we have ee,
which is hello there,
which is exactly what we did.
This is a string.
And this is a string.
So ee should be a string.
And then we try to add 1 to it.
And again, Python is saying
oh, I see a plus sign here.
So I'm going to look over here.
Yeah, that's a string.
And I'm going to look over
here, that's an integer.
It's like, ah.
And this is a trace back.
Now, here's a good time
to talk about trace backs.
Trace backs, I colored them red.
Because you might
think that Python
dislikes you or
thinks that you're
unworthy of its brilliance.
And certainly the
way these things
are worded it sounds like
you're being scolded.
It's like, hey, type error.
You cannot concatenate
stir an int objects.
Right?
I'm scolding you.
You bad, bad programmer.
And it does feel a
bit like your scolded.
But if you go back
to lecture one,
this is also the moment
where really we shouldn't
think of this as like scolding.
We should think of this as
Python sort of asking for help.
It's like, well, you
gave me this line.
And I, Python, have no idea.
In all your greatness,
could you give me
some possible clue as to what
you really mean for me to do?
Because I'm so lost.
And given that I'm
Python, and I am lost,
and you are the only
purpose for my existence,
I must stop until you
give me better guidance.
So don't look at trace
backs as scolding.
They sound like scolding.
I'll stop coloring
them red after a while.
So if Python is so obsessed
with the type of things,
you should able to ask Python
what the type of something is.
So there's a built-in
function called type.
This is part of the Python
language, type parenthese.
And you can put a
variable in here.
What's the type of
the variable ee?
And it says, oh, yeah,
I know what that is.
That would be a string.
And then you could also put
a constant in here and say,
what's the type of 'hello?'
And that's a string, too.
And what's the type
of the number one?
Well, that would be an integer.
So it's picky about the type.
But it'll also share with you
what it believes the type is.
And there's several
types of numbers.
As I've already mentioned,
there are integers,
which are the whole numbers.
They can be positive
and negative and zero.
And then there are the decimal
numbers, the floating point
numbers, like 98.6 or
negative 2.5 or 14.0.
Python knows these as well.
Because it does
division different
if it's presented
with two integers,
or an integer and a float,
or a float and a float.
And so here we have x is 1.
And we say, what is it?
It's an integer.
And we say it's 98.6.
And say, well, what's that?
It's a float.
And you could ask for both
variables and constants.
So what's the type of 1?
It's an integer.
And what's the type of 1.0?
And it's a float.
It can also convert types.
It has a bunch of type
conversion functions
built into it.
So there's an
implicit conversion
going on when you're
sort of saying divide
an integer by a floating point.
It says, OK, I
looked to the sides.
And I will make the
conversion for you.
But you can also be explicit.
So in this case we're
going to say, take this 99
and convert it to a floating
point version of itself, which
is 99.0, and then
do the division.
So Python looks out here and
goes, oh, that's a float.
And that's an integer
if I look over here.
And then that means that
the result is a float.
And the division
is done as a float.
So we are force converting the
99 integer into a 99.0 float.
And we can even do this and
just stick it in the variable.
So we can put 42 in i.
And that is an integer.
Then we can say, hey, convert
float that i into a float
and stick it into
the variable f.
And so we can print it.
And now it's 42.0 instead of 42.
They're not the same.
They're both kind of 42.
But one is a floating point 42,
and the other is an integer 42.
And we can ask, and
that is a float.
And you can also
do the same thing
in the middle of a
calculation where you
have 1 plus 2 times float of 3.
This float is done quickly.
So the first thing that happens,
this is 1 plus 2 times 3.0
point 0 over 4 minus 5.
So the first thing that happens
is these floats are done.
Because they're
parentheses, so they matter.
So this is a built-in
function called
float that takes,
as its argument,
a non-floating point
number and gives you back
a floating point number.
We'll talk more about
functions in chapter four.
You can also convert
between strings and numbers.
And if you recall, we did the
example where we take a string.
In this case, I'm being
a little confusing
because I'm making a string
with the characters 1, 2, 3.
Now, this is not
the same as 123.
This is a three character
string with 1, 2, 3 in it.
And I can ask what kind
of thing is in there.
And it says, oh, there's
a string in there.
I know about that.
And then I can try
to add 1 to it.
And it seems intuitive
that quote 1, 2, 3 plus 1
would be somehow 124.
But it's not.
Python takes a look
at the plus and says,
oh, there's a
string on that side
and an integer on that side.
I am going to freak out and
tell you about you cannot
concatenate a string
and an integer.
But there is an
int function that
converts various
things, including
strings, to an integer.
So we can give as its parameter,
it's input, the string value.
Then it converts
it to an integer.
And then it will put the
result in the variable ival.
We can ask what the
type of that is.
It's an integer.
And now we can use it in an
expression, print ival plus 1.
And so now, Python looks to
both sides, sees an integer,
sees an integer, and gets 124.
Voila.
Now if I make a new variable
and I stick hello Bob in it
and I say, hey, let's convert
hello Bob to an integer,
as you might
expect, it blows up.
And it says invalid
literal for int.
These trace backs,
again, once you kind of
get used to the harsh wording
of them, because they're not
saying, sorry comma.
They're trying to tell
you what's going on.
So cannot concatenate string
and integer and invalid literal
for int.
It's trying to be as helpful as
it possibly can be to give you
a clue as to what to fix.
So again, not scolding.
OK.
So that's variables, and
types, and type conversion.
Now we'll talk a little
bit about user input.
And there's a
function that's built
into Python called raw input.
And what happens when
raw input runs is it
has, as one of its
parameters, a prompt,
which is something that
shows up on the screen.
Who are you?
And then it waits.
It sits and waits.
It says, what next?
And then you type a string.
And then you hit the Enter key.
And then whatever you typed
here goes into a variable.
And it is a string.
And then you can use it.
So I'm going to print
the string welcome comma.
So that means I'm
printing two things now.
The comma adds a
space between welcome.
And then nam.
And so welcome is a literal.
And then Chuck is coming
from this nam variable.
So this is a two-line program.
I think this is one of
your assignments actually.
Well, it's one of the
exercises in the book
to prompt for a user's
name and then welcome them.
So raw input is a function
that issues a prompt,
waits, and then takes
whatever string is entered,
and then returns it, and then
puts it into that variable.
So now we're going
to create kind
of the first useful program.
It's not a powerful program.
It is an interesting problem of
the fact that for some reason
there's a difference
in the numbering
scheme of United
States elevators
and European elevators.
European elevators, the
floor that you walk out on
is the 0 floor.
The floor above
that is the 1 floor.
And the floor below that, the
basement, is the minus 1 floor.
And so you walk in
and you can either
go up the elevator
or down the elevator.
Of course, in the United States,
the floor that you walk in
is the 1.
And then there's the
2 floor above that.
And then there's the basement.
So this is the imagination that
the Americans have as to how
to number floors.
The Europeans go 0, 1, minus 1.
So children who
go to hotels learn
instantly the notion
of zero and the notion
of positive and negative
numbers and the symmetry
between positive and
negative numbers.
I mean, I just wish the
United States hotels
would switch to this I
to teach young people 0
immediately and
negative numbers.
So we somehow think that
numbers in the United States
start at 1, and then there
are no negative numbers.
There's the basement.
I wonder why that
is, but whatever.
For people to travel a lot,
they may be confused by this.
They need a way to convert
back and forth between the US
and European numbering system.
So this is a simple
program that demonstrates
a real classic pattern of
input processing and output.
It's just three lines.
But it has the essential
things that all programs that
are useful-- they
generally read some data,
do some work with the
data, and then produce
some kind of results.
And so the first line is a raw
input that effectively puts out
a prompt.
And the wait.
It says, please enter
your Europe floor.
It sits there.
We type a 0.
Then 0 goes into int.
But it is a string.
It is not a number.
It is a string.
So we can't add to it.
But we can take and convert
it to an integer with the int
function, int of imp.
That's a string being
converted to an integer.
So now it's a real numeric 0.
We can add 1 to that.
And we sum that together.
And we put it into
the variable usf.
And then we print
US Floor comma,
and then whatever the
variable for usf is.
And out come US Floor 1.
So you're written a very
simple elevator floor
conversion from a European
floor to a United States floor.
Don't ask about
negative numbers.
It's not really good at that.
But from 0 and positive
numbers, it works great.
So another thing to think about
in any programming language
is comments.
Comments are like commentary.
And basically, it's a way
for us to add notations
for ourselves or for
other humans interspersed
in the code.
And so in Python, anything
after a pound sign is ignored.
You can have a pound sign at
the beginning of the line,
and then the whole
line is ignored.
There are two or three
reasons why you could do this.
One is sort of like
paragraph headings, where
you can say what's
going to happen
in English or your language.
And you can write
documentation that
says, this code was written
by Charles Severance December,
2010.
And you could also just
hide a line of code
to test and turn it on
and off without actually
deleting the line of code.
It's a real common
thing in debugging.
So for example,
here is the program
that we've been playing with.
This is our word
counting program
that we've been talking
about from the beginning.
And here is the example of
four comments, one, two, three,
four, four comments
that basically tell us
what these paragraphs
are going to do.
Now, they don't have any effect
on the program whatsoever.
But this one says get the
name of the file and open it.
Kind of helpful, right?
Count the word frequency, that's
what this little bit does.
Find the most
common word, that's
what this little bit does.
And all done, print this out.
So it really can be
very helpful just
to add a little
tiny bit of stuff.
You don't want to
over use comments.
You don't want to say like, x =
12, take 12 and put it into x.
Sometimes people
teach you and try
to say, oh, you need one
comment every three lines.
I don't believe in
any of those rules.
I basically say if it's
useful to describe it, then
describe it.
So that's comments.
So some operators
apply the strings.
We've already talked about plus.
It's kind of silly,
although useful in places.
You could actually
multiply string,
where the asterisk
looks and says
I got a string and an integer.
And it prints out the
string five times.
Not a lot of use for that.
Now, let's talk a little bit
about choosing variable names.
This is something that
is really confusing.
So I said, like, x
= 1, x = x plus 1.
What does x mean?
And the answer is it
doesn't mean anything.
I chose it.
I wanted to make a variable.
And so I picked x.
We pick x a lot
probably because we
learned in algebra in sixth
grade that x was a variable.
And it's short.
And so why not call it x?
But as your programs
get larger, this
gets kind of frustrating
to have all your variables
like x and y and z.
And so the notion of
mnemonic, it means memory aid.
We choose our
variable names wisely,
so they remind us of
what the variable is
going to do internally.
And so as I go
through this lecture,
in the beginning if I choose
a variable that's too clever,
you're going to think that
it's part of the language.
And so I sort of
switch back and forth
between well chosen
variable names
and stupid variable
names to kind
re-emphasize the notion
that I can choose.
Mnemonic is a good practice.
OK.
So here we go.
Let's take a look
at the bit of code.
So the question is what
is this code doing?
What will it even print out?
Is it syntactically correct?
Now you can probably cut
and paste this into Python
and figure out that it
is syntactically correct.
There are three variables.
This one here and
this one here match.
that one there match.
And these two match.
So it's taking these two numbers
and multiplying together,
and then printing out the
product of the two numbers
if you're real careful and
look at every character.
Now this would be called
non-mnemonic variables.
They're really messy.
Now Python, it's happy.
Because all it wants
is to say, oh, here's
the name that I, the
programmer, decided I wanted
to call this piece of memory.
And I'll refer to it down here.
OK.
And so Python's happy.
Now, if you hand this
to another human being,
they're going to
be really unhappy.
Because they're going to
be like what are you doing?
So one better way
to write it would
be to make the
variables very simple.
And then cognitively, we humans
can figure out which is which.
Because again, it's still
only about matching.
The a has to match the a.
The b matches the b.
And the cs match.
It's actually the
exact same program.
a = 35, b= 12.5, c equals
a times b, and print c.
Python sees these
as the same program.
It doesn't care
what we name them.
Now a human will be much
appreciative if you say here,
you can either have
this one or this one.
This one will make
them a lot happier.
OK?
So that is certainly
cognitively easier.
But it's not really
giving you any sense
of what's going on here.
So an even better way to
write this exact same program
to do the exact
same thing would be
to choose variables
named hours, rate,
and pay if indeed that
is what you're doing.
Now you can look at this and
you go, oh, well shoot, 35
is the number of hours.
And 12 and 1/2 is the rate.
And the pay is the number
of hours times the rate.
And then we're going
to print out the pay.
That makes a lot of sense.
So this is really an awesome
and wonderful characterization.
And if that's what
you're doing and if those
are hours, rate, pay,
it's a great thing
to name your variables.
But this is where beginning
students get confused.
And so sometimes I'll
write it this way,
and sometimes I'll
write it this way.
Because you'll look
at this until you
get a little more sophisticated
a little more skilled,
and you say, like, does Python
know something about payroll?
Is hours a reserved word?
Is rate a reserved word
and pay a reserved word?
Are these things that
Python knows about?
And the answer is no.
Python sees these three programs
as exactly the same name.
It's just this person really
made a very bad choice
of variable name.
This person made a less bad
choice of a variable name.
And this person made a
really awesome choice
of variable name.
So the difference between
these two things is style.
They are the exact same program.
And Python is equivalently
happy with these.
But humans are most happy
when the variables are
easy to remember and
they are somewhat
descriptive of what they're
expected contents will be.
That's mnemonic to
help you remember
what you were meaning to do
when you write the program.
This is still a bit cryptic
having these really short
one character variable names.
It's still a bit cryptic.
So you have a couple
of assignments
at the end of the chapter.
One of the assignments
is to write a program
to prompt the user for hours and
rate per hour and compute pay.
So I won't do this
here, but just
a couple of sort of odd things.
You're going to be
using raw input.
But remember that
hands a string in.
So you're going to have to use
float to function to convert it
to a floating point
number, so you can actually
do a calculation.
And then you're going to have
to use multiplication and print,
so multiplication
and then print.
So it's some combination of raw
input, float, multiplication,
and print constructed to make
your program do exactly this.
So this is the end
of a chapter two.
We talked about types,
reserved words, variables,
the mnemonic how you choose
variable names-- we'll
hit this a couple more times,
because choosing variable names
is always problematic--
operators, operator
precedence, which just means
like does multiplication happen
before plus, parentheses.
Integer division is a little
weird, because it truncates.
9 over 10 = 0.
That's the integer
division truncating.
Conversion, this is
like the int float.
And then user input,
which is raw input.
And then comments,
which are ways
for you to add human readable
text to your program.
OK.
See you next lecture.