Hello and welcome to chapter
11, regular expressions
from the book Python
for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
As always, these slides are
copyright Creative Commons
attribution as well
as the audio and video
that you're watching or
listening to right now.
So regular expressions
are an interesting thing.
You've seen from the
chapters up til now,
I've had a singular focus
on pulling information out
of data.
Raw data, this mailbox
file that perhaps you're
getting tired of already.
But it's a lot of
fun, because I can
have you go look for
something and pick it out
and you're doing
something that would be
really painful to do by hand.
And while it's not all about
computing, there's games
and there's things like
weather computations
that do calculations,
pulling extracting data out
is a big part of computing.
And so there's actually
a library that's
built specifically do this.
And if you start doing
a few finds and slicing,
it gets long after a while.
Like split, for example,
really saved us a lot of time.
But sometimes, the data
that you're looking for
is a little more
sophisticated than broken
into spaces or colons
or something like that.
And you just want to tell
something to go find,
I see what I want
and I see where
it's embedded in the
string, go get it for me.
And regular expressions are
themselves a programming
language.
They're like a really smart
wild card for searching.
So we've used wild cards in
various things in search.
But they are a really smart
version of a wild card.
And so regular expressions
are quite powerful.
And they're very cryptic.
And as a matter of
fact, you don't even
need to learn them if you
don't feel like it, right?
I've got this little guide.
I need a guide for myself
when I do regular expressions.
It sometimes takes
me a few minutes
to write a regular expression
to do exactly what I want.
So in a way, writing
a regular expression
is like writing a program.
It's highly specialized to
searching and extracting data
from strings, but it's
like writing a program.
And it takes a while
to get it right.
And you have to change this,
what about a slash there.
But they actually are fun.
And they're a great way
to exchange little program
snippets to say, oh yeah,
I'm looking for this.
Oh, here's a little reg
expression you might try.
So they're like
programs themselves.
It is this language
of marker characters.
So when we look for
regular expressions,
some characters like
ABC, have meaning as ABC.
But some characters, like
carrot or dollar sign
mean the beginning of the line
or at the end of the line.
And so we encode, in this
string, a program, basically.
So it's a rather
old school language.
It's from a long time.
It predates Python, which
is over 20 years old.
It also marks you as
a little cool, right?
It's a distinct marking that
makes it so that you know
something other people don't.
So you can know how to program.
But if you know regular
expressions, they'll be like,
whoa, I tried to look at
those and they're tough.
In a way, knowing regular
expressions is like a tattoo.
So it's casual Friday.
And that's why I'm
wearing a t-shirt today
and so I figured I would
come in today in a t-shirt.
But seeing as how
it's the first I'm
wearing a short
sleeved shirt, it's
also first time I can show
you my real tattoo here.
So here's my real tattoo.
And in the middle is the
Sakai, the open source
learning manager system,
always close to my heart.
And then you have
the IMS logo, which
is IMS Learning Tools
and Operability, which
is a standard that
means a lot to me.
Blackboard, OLAT, Learning
Objects, Angel, Moodle,
Instructure, Jenzabar,
and Desire2Learn.
I call this the
ring of compliance.
Because these are all of the
first six or seven learning
management systems that complied
with the IMS Learning Tools
Interoperability Standard
and Specification,
which is something that I spent
a lot of my life making work.
So I figured I'd make
a tattoo and just
a part of my rough, tough image.
And actually,
regular expressions
are indeed part of my
rough, tough image.
Because I'm like, I'm down
with regular expressions.
And people are like, impressed
with my regular expression
knowledge.
But as impressive as I am,
I still need a cheat sheet.
So I'll have a cheat sheet that
you can download, hopefully,
on the Python [INAUDIBLE]
website or whatever.
And it doesn't have to be much.
It's really just a crutch.
And these are the characters
that have special meaning.
Like carrot or dollar sign match
the beginning or end of line,
respectively.
So they're not really
matching a dollar sign,
they match-- they mean something
in our little mini string
like programming language.
So like many things that we
do in Python going forward,
once you want some
sophisticated capability,
it comes with Python, but it
comes in the form of a library.
And so the regular
expression library,
we have to say import RE at
the beginning of our programs
to import to regular
expression library.
Then we call
RE.search to say I'm
looking for search from the
regular expression library.
There's two basic
basic capabilities
inside this library that
we're going to look at.
One is search that
replaces find.
It's like a smart find.
And then find all is a
combination of a smart find
and automatic extraction.
So we'll look at both
of those in turn.
And I'll do it by comparing
them to existing Python
that you already should
know at this point.
So here's some code that's,
say, looking for lines that have
the string from colon in them.
So we're going to
open a file, we're
going to strip the white
space, if we find--
if we hunt within
line for from, if it's
greater than or equal to
zero, then we'll print it.
And so this is just going
to give us a number.
If it's not found,
it's negative 1.
So it's only going to print
the lines that from in them.
Here is the equivalent
using regular expressions.
So these two things
are equivalent.
So we have to import to library,
like I mentioned before.
And all the rest
of it's the same.
The IF test is RE.search that
says, within the library,
RE, called the Search Utility.
And then pass in the
string we're looking for
and the line, the actual
text we're looking in.
So this is like look for from
inside of line and return
me a true or false,
whichever depending on
whether you find it or not.
Now, might say, you
just got done telling me
that it was more dense.
And the answer is, there's
a few more characters here.
But we'll see in a second how
you can quickly add more power
to the regular expression.
Find you have to start adding
more Python lines to make
it more sophisticated where
in the regular expression,
you start changing-- you change
the search string to give more
of the direction of
what you're looking for.
And that's what we'll
be doing pretty much
is changing the search string.
So now, if we want to switch
to, say, wait, wait, wait,
we don't just want the
from anywhere in the line.
We want it to start with from.
So we would change
line.startswith('From').
And that's either going to
be true or false depending on
whether or not the
line starts with from.
Now, we do the same thing
with regular expressions
by changing the search string.
So now we're in
regular expressions.
So this really just
isn't a string.
It's a string plus
characters that
are interpreted as commands by
the regular expression library.
So the caret, which is the first
one on our regular expressions
sheet, matches the
beginning of the line.
It's not actually a caret.
So that says, the first
character, this two character
sequence, caret f means
f but in column one
in the first
character of the line.
So again, this is going
to give us a true or false
if this regular
expression matches.
The beginning of the line from:
and it's the same as this.
It's, does it start with from?
So again, these
two are equivalent.
But you see the
pattern where we're
going to do something to this
string using these characters
that have meaning, OK?
So the next thing
that's most commonly
done other than caret and
dollar sign for the end of line
is the wild card characters.
And so we use cards
possibly in like DOS
where we can use
question mark or star in
like a dir command or
dir dot star dot star
if you're familiar with that
or even a Unix command like ls,
you know, star dot whatever.
This is not how regular
expressions work.
And the problem is
that dot, dot is--
it matches a single character
in regular expressions.
Asterisk means any
number of times.
So if I look at this
and color code this
to make a little
more sense, the caret
is actually kind of part of the
regular expression programming
language.
Says, I'm a virtual character
matching the beginning of line.
The x is a real character.
The dot is part of the
regular programming
language-- any character.
Star is part of the regular
expression programming that
says the immediate previous
character many times s--
0 or more times.
And then colon
matches the colon.
And so if you look
at lines, these
are the kinds of lines that
will give me a true because they
start with an x followed by some
number of characters followed
by colon.
So that's true.
Start with x followed by
some number of characters
followed by colon.
OK, and so that's
basically how this works.
And so this five
character string,
there are-- some of these
things are like instructions
and some of them are the actual
characters were looking for.
So the x and the colon are the
characters we're looking for
and the caret, dot, and
star are programming, right?
They are logic that we're
adding to the string.
OK, so let's say for example
you're-- part of any of these
things and part of the stuff
we've done so far has to assume
that the data is some
level of being clean.
And so the data that
I've been giving you in
boxed up TXT is
not inconsistent.
It doesn't have, like,
too much weirdness in it.
I'm not trying to trick
you and mislead you
although we had situations where
you sort of get a trace back
because you think there's
going to be five words.
You grab a line, you break it,
and there's only two words.
And you get a trace
back because you're
looking at the fifth word
or something like that.
But if your data is less
clean or even if you just
want to be real careful, you
can fine tune your matching.
So here's that same match.
Give me a character x followed
by any number of characters
followed by a colon.
And that's what I'm looking for.
Give me lines that
match that pattern.
So this x starts at any
number of characters.
Colon, great.
That's any number of
characters-- great.
Oh wait, and there's
an email that
says x plane is two weeks
behind schedule colon two weeks.
Well, the regular
expression didn't
know that dash made
sense to you and you just
assumed that everything
that started with a capital
x had a dash after it.
So x is what it starts with--
any number of any character--
and then a colon.
So this becomes true.
This may not make you happy.
It may not be what
you're looking
for because you haven't
been specific enough
in your regular expression.
So we can be more specific
in our regular expression.
So for example, this is a more
specific regular expression.
It still says start with an
x as the first character,
then a dash-- that's
a real character,
not a-- then this next thing,
instead of being a dot,
it's backslash capital
S. It's on the sheet.
Oh, it's not on the sheet.
I lost the sheet.
Come back, sheet.
I can't live without my sheet.
Backslash capital S means
a non-whitespace character.
So that means
spaces won't match.
And then I change
the asterisk zero
or more times thing to a plus.
And that means
one or more times.
Here's a character, a
non-whitespace-- these two
things kind of work together--
a non-whitespace character
at least one time as many
as we like and then a colon.
So if we look here,
it starts with x
dash any number of
non-whitespace characters
and ends in colon--
starts with x dash
any number of caret
characters, ends in a colon.
True, true.
This one starts with an x but
doesn't start with an x dash.
As a matter of fact, these
characters are blanks.
So this becomes a false.
It does have an x
and does have a colon
and matched the previous one.
But this one here
is more specific.
OK, so it's more specific.
And so it matches what you want.
Now, it depends on what
you're looking for.
Maybe you do want this line
and so you're looking for x.
I don't know.
But if you want, you
can be increasingly
sophisticated in
what you're looking
for in a regular expression.
So now let's talk
about extracting data.
So everything we've done so far
is, is it there or is it not?
But it's really common
once you find something
that you want to
break it into pieces.
So we can combine the
searching and the parsing
into one statement.
And instead of
using search, which
returns for us a true false,
we're going to use find all.
So in this example, I'm going
to show you a new syntax.
The square bracket, in
regular expression language,
means a way to list
a set of characters.
So this says-- this is a
single character that says,
I want to match anything in
the range zero through nine.
Plus means one or more of those.
So that says-- so this whole
thing says one or more digits.
That's a regular expression
that says one or more digits.
You can put other
things inside here.
You can put, like-- you could
make a thing that says a, b, c,
d.
And that would say, I'm going to
match a single character that's
a or b or c or d.
Or you could say,
like, 1357 bracket.
That's a single character
that's either a one or a three
or a five or a seven.
So the bracket is a list
of matching characters
in the dash inside the
bracket-- means range.
We'll see in a
second that you can
stick a not inside the bracket.
It's on the sheet.
So again, remember-- in
this little mini language,
we are programming, right?
We are giving instructions
to the regular expression
engine as it were, OK?
So if we do this-- and here
is an expression that says,
I would like to find things
that are one or more digits.
And so it's one or more digits.
And so it's going
to look through here
and it's going to find it
as many times as it can.
So there is one or more digits.
There is one or more digits.
And there is one or more digits.
And so what find all gives
us back is a list of strings.
So it found it.
Where do I match?
Where-- it's looking
the whole time.
And then it says, oh,
I've got it-- 2, 19, 42.
So it actually extracts
the strings that match
and gives you a Python list
of strings-- Python list
of strings.
Kind of like split except
it's like a super smart split,
right?
It's split, but I've
directed it what to look for.
And if-- so here's an example
of-- that's what I just did.
Find me one or more
digits and then
extract them-- so 2, 19, 42.
Here I'm saying using
the same bracket syntax
to look for a single character,
a capital A, E, I, O,
or U, and one or more of those.
And if you look, there are no
uppercase vowels in my string.
So it says I want to
find all the things that
match A, E, I, O, U. So
things like AA would match
and, you know, OU would match.
And so that's what we would
get if they were in the string.
But because there are none,
we get an empty string.
So even if there are none,
you get an empty string.
So it always returns a string.
It may be a zero length string.
And that's what you
have to check, OK?
OK, now, matching has
this notion of greedy
where when you put one of
these pluses or asterisks,
it kind of has this outward
pushing feeling, right?
And so when you say I'm
looking for something
that starts with an F at the
beginning of the line followed
by one or more characters
followed by a colon,
you can think of this
as pushing outward.
So if we look at a line
here that has from colon
using the colon character,
it will try to expand.
So it certainly has to match the
F. And it's looking for a colon
any number of characters.
But it's trying to
make the string that
matches as big as possible.
So it skips over this colon
and goes to that colon.
And so the thing
that we get is here.
And so it ignored this and said,
I will make as large a string
as I can.
So that's the plus
that's doing it.
Dot plus pushes.
It's like, I got a colon, but is
there another colon out there?
So push it.
OK, so that's a greedy matching.
It can get you in some trouble
like being greedy in general.
And both asterisk and plus
sort of behave in a greedy way
because they're zero or more
or one or more characters.
So they can sort
of push outward.
OK, now you can turn this off.
It's a programming language.
We can tweak it, OK?
And so we add a question mark.
So this is a three
character sequence now.
So if you say dot plus question
mark, that says one or more
of any characters
push-- but instead
of being greedy and
pushing as far as you can,
this means stop at the first.
Stop at the first.
Oops-- stop at the first.
I can never draw on
this thing fast enough.
Stop at the first, OK?
And that's it.
Just don't be greedy.
Don't try to make the
string as large as possible.
Go with the smaller one--
the smaller possible one.
We still need to find an F and
we still need to find a colon.
But when you find the
first colon, stop.
And so what this does
is this changes it
so that what we
match is from colon
instead of going all the way.
So the greedy match
pushes as far as it can.
The non greedy
match is satisfied
with the first thing that meets
the criterion of the string.
So this is a little three
character programming
sequence-- any character one
or more times and not greedy.
If, for example, we were trying
to solve the problem of pulling
the email address
out of a string,
we can make good use of
this non blank character.
And so the at sign
is just a character.
And then we can say,
I want at least one
non blank character
before it and at least
one non blank
character after it.
So the way regular
expressions does, it says, OK.
I find my at sign and I push
in a greedy manner outwards
as long as they're
non blank characters.
Push, push, push, push, push,
push, push, whoops, stop.
Push, push, push,
push, push, stop.
OK, so it's some number of non
blank characters, an at sign,
followed by some number
of non blank characters.
So that's using greedy matching.
Its doing that, OK?
And so this is where we
get Stephen Marquard.
And we would know if it wasn't
there by the empty list, right?
And so we get
stephenmarquard@uct.ac.za.
Now, we can also fine tune
what we extract, right?
In the previous
slide, we extracted
whatever matched, right?
Whatever this matched, it
looked across the whole string
and found it.
It found the thing,
shoved it over,
and gave us what it matched.
But it's possible to
make the match larger
than what's extracted to
extract a subset of the match.
And we'll see that on
this next slide OK?
So here's this same
thing, which is an at
and then with non blank
characters as far as the eye
can see in either direction.
But I'm going to add
to it caret from space.
So this has to start with--
the first character is
to be a caret.
It's got to have the word from.
It's got to have one space.
And then immediately, it's
got to find this, right?
It's got to find a series
of non blanks followed
by an and sign followed
by another series of one
or more non blanks.
And then what we
do-- so if we didn't
put these parentheses
in, it would match
and we would get
all of this data.
It would go to here.
But what we can do with the
parentheses-- the parentheses
are part of the regular
expression language-- saying,
OK, I want to match
the whole thing.
The parentheses aren't
part of the string up here.
I want to match the
whole thing but I only
want to extract this
part in parentheses.
So this whole thing is a regular
expression that's matched.
And then the parentheses part
is what's retrieved for you.
And so this makes it
so that the only time
it's going to look for
at signs are on lines
that start with from space.
It is going to want the
immediate next character
to be a non blank, some number
of non-white characters,
followed by an at sign, some
number of non blank characters.
It's going to stop right there.
And it's only going to
extract from here to here.
So we get out Stephen Marquard.
But this is a pretty
narrowly scoped thing
because the first
four characters
have to be from space.
And so that's a way
to combine a stricter
match even though you don't
actually want all the data.
So you can add those things
all over the place, OK?
OK, then we can compare
the different ways
of extracting data.
So if we look at how we
extract the hostname.
Remember how we did
this many chapters ago.
So we did a data dot find which
says, oh, the first at sign
is a 21.
So the first one is a 21.
Then we say, we want to
find the space after that.
So that's the at position.
That's 31.
And then we want to
extract the data that's
one beyond the at up to but
not including the space.
And that is the variable that
we're going to print out host.
And so we extract this
bit of information
and out comes the
host-- quite nice, OK?
We also saw another technique.
And by the way, all
these techniques are OK.
All these techniques are fine.
Another technique we saw once
we sort of played the split
and lists was what I
call the double split
version of this where
the first thing we do
is we split that line.
The first thing we do
is we split the line.
And then we know-- and blanks--
that the second thing, which
is the sub 1, word sub 1,
is the entire email address.
And then this is
the double split.
We take the email address and
we split it by an at sign.
And then we get a list of the
pieces of the email address--
the email name and
the email host--
and then we grab
the sub 1 of that.
And then we have the host
so that's the double split
way of doing this, right?
Now, in this, we still
haven't done the from yet.
But it is the double
split way to do this.
So if we think
about how we would
do this in a regular
expression, we're
going to say look
through the string.
Find all-- we're going
to-- here's the find all.
And the reg
expression exploded up
says, look through
the string for an and.
Do, do, do, do, got an and.
Then, oh, start
extracting and extracting.
And then this is another
form of the sync--
this is one character.
It's a single character.
Match any non blank character
and zero or more of them, OK?
So find an at sign.
Start extracting and extracting.
Match this is one character.
That is a set of
possible matches.
And that's some character.
This means not-- not a blank.
That's a blank right there.
That's a plane
character right there--
not a blank as many
times as you want.
You might want to
turn that into a plus
to guarantee at least one.
That might be better done
as a plus right there.
So this would probably
make more sense
as a plus to say I want at
least-- after the at sign, I
want at least one
non blank character.
And the parentheses simply
say I don't want the at sign.
So the at sign-- I really want
those non blank characters
after the at sign.
So that's what I
want to extract.
So it's like, go
find the at sign.
OK, great, found the at sign.
Start extracting.
Look for non blank
characters and extracting.
So pull that part out
and put it right there.
Now, an even cooler version
of this that you probably
kind of imagined right away
is we say, you know what?
I would like this
first character
to-- the first part
of the line to be
from with a blank followed
by any number of characters
followed by an at sign.
So the at sign is real.
Then start extracting, then any
number of non blank characters
and extracting.
So this is like eight
or nine lines of Python
all rolled into one thing, OK?
so start at the
beginning of the line.
Look for string
from with a space.
Then skip a bunch of characters
looking for an at sign.
Skip characters until
you encounter an at sign.
Then start extracting.
Match any non blank-- a
single non blank character.
So this is kind of like one
non blank character, one non
blank character.
But once you suffix
it with the asterisk,
that changes it to be
many non blank characters.
And then stop extracting, OK?
So it's like, find from
followed by a space-- great.
That's the first part.
Now throw away until
you find an at sign.
Then start extracting.
Keep going with non
blank characters
until you hit the
first blank characters
and pull that part out.
Now, the result is we
get the exact same data.
But with this added
to it, we're much more
narrow in the kind of things
that we're looking for.
And if we get noisy data that
like-- say something like,
you know, meet at Joe's, right?
We don't want that.
That won't match, right?
We want that to be like a false.
And that allows us
to sort of really
fine tune our matching
and extracting.
And this is just the beginning.
They're very, very powerful.
So the last thing
that I will show you
is sort of a program
that is kind of like one
of the programs that we
did in a previous section.
Except now, we're going to use
regular expressions to do it.
So if you remember,
we had this thing
where we're doing spam
confidence where we're
looking for lines and pulling
this number out and then
calculating you the average
or the maximum or whatever.
And so here is a-- we import
the regular expression library.
We open the file.
We're going to do
this with appending
to a list-- we'll put
the numbers in a list
rather than doing the
calculational loop.
We strip the data.
Now, here's the
key thing, right?
We're going to have a
regular expression that
says, look for the
first character
being x followed by a
dash followed by all this.
All this exactly has to match
literally followed by a colon.
And then there's a space.
And then we begin extracting.
And we're looking for the
digits 0 through 9 or a dot.
And we're looking
for one or more.
And then we end extracting.
So that's-- the parentheses are
telling us what to pull out.
So that just means
that we're going
to pull out those numbers, all
the digits and the numbers,
until we get something-- I mean,
all the digits and the period
and we'll get something other
than a digit and a period.
And then we'll be done, OK?
And so this is going to pull
those numbers out and give us
back a list.
Now, the thing
about it is we have
to realize that sometimes
this is not going to match.
Because we're sending
every line-- not just
the ones that start with x.
We're sending every
line through this.
And so we need to know
when we didn't get a match.
And the way we know we didn't
get a match is if the list
the number of items in the
list that we got back is zero,
then we're going to continue.
So this is kind of
our if we're searching
for the needle in the haystack.
But then once we find
what we're looking for,
the actual number that
we're interested in
is already sitting here
in stuff sub 0, OK?
And then we convert to a float.
We append it.
And then when the
loop is all done,
we print out the maximum, OK?
And so this is sort of
encoding a number of things
and ending up with a very
solid and safe matching.
So we're really--
it's hard for this
to find a line that's wrong.
And you could even
improve this a little bit
to make it even a little
tighter where it would
go find a number like 0.999.
You could say, oh, it's--
all the numbers are 0 dot--
so you could make this a little
more so it would even skip
things that-- you can make it
so it looks exactly the way you
want to look.
So I emphasize that this is
kind of a weird language.
And you need some kind of thing.
We talked about all these.
We have the beginning of a line.
We have the end of the line
matching any character,
matching space
characters, matching
non-whitespace characters.
Star is a modifier that
says zero or more times.
Star question mark is a
modifier that says zero or more
times non greedy.
Plus is one or more times.
Plus question mark is one
or more times non greedy.
When you have bracket
syntax, it's a set.
It's a single character
that's in the listed set.
So that's lowercase vowels.
You can also have the first--
if the first character of this
is a caret, that flips it.
So that means everything
except capital X,
capital Y, capital
Z. So it's everything
that's not in the set capital
X, capital Y, capital Z.
And then you can also put
dashes in to represent ranges.
Bracket a through z and 0
through 9 in lowercase letters
and digits will match.
But again, this is
a single character.
Now, you can put a plus
or a star after these guys
to make them happen
more than one time.
And you can even
put them in twice.
So if I wanted a two digit
number, I could say 0-9, 0-9.
Oops, this is one character.
This is one character and
this is the possible things.
So that's, you know, 000 0
would match, 10 would match,
99 would match, et cetera.
And then the parentheses
are the things
that if you are in the middle
of a big long matching string
and you don't want to
extract the whole thing,
you can limit the things you're
extracting to the stuff that's
just in there.
With all these characters
that have all this meaning,
we have to have a way to
match those characters.
So dollar sign is
the end of a line.
But what if we're looking for
something that actually has
a dollar sign in the string?
And that's what the
backslash is for.
So if you put the
backslash in front
of a otherwise
meaningful character,
it becomes the actual character.
So this is saying
match a dollar sign.
Those two character say
And then this says one character
that's 0 through 9 or a dot.
And then we put
the plus modifier
to say at least
one or more times.
And so that sort of is
a greedy, of course.
So that will get us
this and extract it,
including the dollar sign.
So the escape character
is the backslash.
OK, so there we are.
Now we're done.
So this is a little bit cryptic.
It's kind of a puzzle.
It's kind of fun and
it's extremely powerful.
And you don't have to know it.
You don't have to learn it.
But if you do,
you'll find that it's
very useful as we sort
of dig through data
and are trying to write
things that are pretty quick.
And the thing I like
about regular expressions
is that they tend to be,
if you write them well,
they tend to be less
sensitive to bad data.
They tend to ignore data there.
You can put more detail.
I exactly want this.
Or if you're writing
find and extract,
you're making a lot of
assumptions about the data--
that it's clean and you're not
going to miss hit on something.
So OK, well, good luck in your
use of regular expressions
and we'll see you later.