So I hope you enjoyed that
video about Doug Crockford.
He's a pretty funny guy.
He's got sort of an
irascible sense of humor.
You can find some more
of his talks on YouTube.
One of his probably
the funnest things
is this picture that's
wandering around the internet.
Douglas Crockford
wrote a book called
JavaScript, The Good Parts.
And so what we see
here, of course,
is here is the book that
talks about JavaScript,
The Definitive Guide, which is
everything, and then the book
called JavaScript,
The Good Parts
is much smaller than JavaScript,
The Definitive Guide.
Part reason for
that is JavaScript
is a really, really deep
and powerful language.
As you've probably
seen with the video,
if I've shown you the
video of Brendan Eich,
he was very thoughtful when
he designed the language
to seem simple on
the surface but yet
be subtly complex and powerful
just under the surface.
And so that's why
there's a big difference
between doing JavaScript
at the light level
and doing JavaScript
at an awesome level.
And so as Doug mentioned, JSON,
he didn't exactly invent it.
He just came up with a term
to legitimize the notion.
And JSON.org describes it, and
he hasn't changed it barely
at all since he came
up with the idea.
And that, as he said, is
one of the charming things.
So in the debate of XML versus
JSON, XML has its advantages.
JSON has a lot of advantages,
and in many situations,
people would push XML where JSON
would've been more appropriate.
So there's a bit of a
backlash against XML,
but there's still places
where XML is useful.
But when you just
have two applications
and they really just
want to send some lists
and dictionaries
back and forth, JSON
is a much better way to do it.
Both applications know
what they're looking for.
And so JSON represents data as
nested lists and dictionaries.
This is another form of
composite data structures
where before we talked
about data structures,
it would say "a list"
or "a dictionary."
And then we got
to the point where
we had a list of tuples, which
is more of a composite data
structure because it's
a data structure that
within it has data structures.
Well, in JSON,
we'd just go crazy.
It's turtles all the way
down, as the joke says.
And it really has two
basic primitive structures
that are repeated over
and over and over again.
And that is they map exactly
onto Python's dictionaries
and Python's lists.
And this particular bit of JSON
is using just the dictionary
format.
Of course, it's a
triple-quoted string,
but the open brace
and close brace
are the indication
that we are starting
a JavaScript object, which
is a set of key value pairs.
So this is name
matched to Chuck.
It's a dictionary, comma.
And then phone maps to-- but
this is now another dictionary.
Type matched international,
number matched to this string.
And then that's the
end of this thing.
And then email is another
dictionary with only one
key and one value.
So this is a dictionary
that contains
two dictionaries within it.
And so this is a
composite data structure.
And much like what we
had to do with XML,
we load the library
using import--
import the JSON library.
JSON is built into Python
in the more recent versions
that we're using.
And you basically
take the string data
and you do JSON.loads, which
parses this and turns it
into internal Python
data structures.
But the difference
is unlike XML,
which is this tree
structure, it actually
is exactly Python
structures at this point.
So this means that what we get
back in info is a dictionary.
And if we want
the word "chuck"--
if we want the word "chuck,"
we simply say info sub "name."
So info is this outer
dictionary and the key name
and the value is chuck.
So it's like give
me info sub chuck.
No querying, no nothing.
It just is a Python dictionary
when we get it back.
So if we then take
a quick look at how
to get at this value right here,
well, info sub email-- well,
that's this bit right here.
Actually, it's this
bit right here.
Let me start that again.
Info sub email is
this dictionary.
So infor sub email is
itself a dictionary.
Then we say sub hide
to go deeper into it
and then this value is yes.
So you see that
the JSON, there's
no sort of querying or finding
or find all-ing or looking up.
It's just there.
And you'll also notice that
this is not nearly as self
descriptive.
We don't have the
less than person
and all that other stuff that
gives us a clue as to what's
actually going on in here.
But if we know what
we're looking for--
and we're just looking
for the name thing,
and it's always going
to be the name thing--
we just write info sub name.
And so JSON really is a
very direct representation
of lists and dictionaries
as a wire format.
And that's why it's very,
very popular compared to XML
when you really just are
sending data between two
cooperating applications.
Here's an example of a
list of dictionaries.
And so in Python-- well,
Python is the same way.
JSON and Python kind
of look the same.
Here we have square brackets,
just like a Python list.
And the first item in this
list is this dictionary
followed by that comma followed
by the second item in the list
is this diction.
So we have two item list.
So when we parse this whole
thing using JSON.loads,
we get back info is a
list of dictionaries.
Because this is a
In this case, there's only
two of them in the list.
Our dictionary-- I mean our
list contains two dictionaries.
And then each dictionary
has some key value pairs.
And so de-reference
these things.
Actually, I probably should
add a little example.
A simple de-reference would
be info sub zero sub name.
Because info is a list, sub
zero is that one right there.
And then within that,
chuck is sub name.
So again, this is
just Python syntax.
Info is a list.
Sub zero is the first
element of that list.
And the thing that is the
first element of that list
is a dictionary.
So to look up the name
value, we do sub name.
We could also take info, which
is a list-- a list of two
dictionaries.
And now we can have a for
loop for item and info.
So that means that item is going
to be an iteration variable.
It's going to first
look at this and then
it's going to look at that.
Item is going to
be a dictionary.
So we can say item sub name,
which is this bit right here.
We can say item sub ID, which
is this bit right there.
And item sub X, which
is that bit right there.
So you just tear
these things apart.
The curly brace things
turn into dictionaries
and the square brace
things turn into lists.
And again, like I said,
it's not as self-describing,
but if you know what
it's supposed to be,
then your Python code
looks really simple
as you take this stuff apart.
So once we have a
serialization, we
use HTTP to move this
data back and forth.
One application produces
data, and another application
consumes data.
It leads to start
a notion called
a service oriented approach.
And a service oriented
approach is a place
where we break our applications
into multiple pieces
and often run them
in multiple servers.
Take something as
complex as Coursera.
They have lots of servers
that do special purposes.
And your user
interface that you see
is pulling data from many
servers-- different kinds
of servers and
pulling them together.
One might be a server
that tells who's
registered in what courses.
Another might be the
threaded discussion server.
Another might be
the video server.
And so what you is you
break your application
into multiple services
and then you basically
compose those together
to produce what
seems to be an application.
Another good example
of this would
be airline reservation
systems that
try to sell you hotel
rooms and rental cars.
Well, airlines don't
have rental cars
and they don't have hotel rooms.
They just call a rental
car web service--
a rental car service--
and a hotel room service.
And they got their own data.
And so somehow in this thing you
can buy a flight, a rental car,
or a hotel room.
And they book them by making
calls to those services.
So this is called a
service oriented approach
where you don't try to
build on every application
to do every single thing.
It does its thing
and it takes services
from other applications.
And when we are going
to use services,
especially those that
don't belong to us--
like if many airlines want to
talk to the car reservation
system-- they have to come up
with a standard that says, OK,
if you're an airline
company and want
to talk to our car reservation
system, here is a standard.
These things are called APIs or
application program interfaces.
So using these APIs, we can
standardize and make it easier
so that by the time
it's all said and done,
once our airline system talks
to one car company-- car
rental company-- it can talk
to 50 different car rental
companies.
And so the act of
studying these APIs
and standardizing these APIs to
make things simpler to reduce
everybody's cost is an important
part of IT development.
The building of standards
is an important part
of IT development.
As a matter of fact,
it's one of the things
that I do a whole
bunch of my time.
So here's a video
that gives an idea
of the value of this
service oriented approach--
about how we use services
across multiple parts
of an application and
exchange data back and forth
and then apply standards at each
of those service boundaries.