Hello, and welcome
to the reality
show about exercises in Python.
It's not a very
exciting reality show,
but I'm your host,
Charles Severance.
And these exercises
come from Python
for Informatics,
Exploring Information.
And, of course, this material is
a Creative Commons attribution,
as well as the book
and other materials.
So by now, I hope
that you're getting
pretty good at using Python.
Hopefully, the Python
Learn materials
have been helpful to
get things set up.
So the exercise that
we're working on today
is exercise 7.3 from
the Files chapter.
And our goal is simply
to read through a file
and print out the contents
of a file, all in uppercase.
Executing the program will
look like this screen.
Well, we obviously have to
prompt for the file name
because it says
enter the file name
and then we give it a file name.
We're going to get our file
from this URL shown here,
Python for Informatics slash
code mbox short dot txt.
So let's do that.
So let's go ahead and do this.
So the first thing we're
going to do is go to the web.
And here's Python
for Informatics.
By the time you're seeing this,
maybe it'll be even prettier.
And the URL is in
these code samples,
and this is old school
user look and feel.
And I'm going to open this.
And this is the data that
we're going to work with,
the mailbox format data.
And I'm going to save
this as a text file.
And I'm going to put it
in my desktop, folder
Python for Informatics.
I'm going to put this mailbox
file right in the same place
as all my other files.
And I'm going to verify that
that's looking really good now
by opening up a terminal window.
I'm going to go
into that folder.
Find out that point right
there is in my desktop.
Python.
And there we are.
I've got my file.
So I'll open up Text Wrangler.
Make it a little smaller.
Actually, I could open
this file in Text Wrangler
if I wanted to.
Open mbox-short.
And so there it is, I want
to look at it really closely.
But I don't want that.
I only want to make
a new Python program.
And so we will.
Well, first thing
we've got to do
is we've got to
enter a file name.
So let's do that.
I'll call my variable f
name equals raw input.
Enter a file name.
Colon, space.
Oops.
Switch back to single quotes.
You can use double
quotes or single quotes,
but single quotes are cool.
Double quotes make it look like
you're a Java program, that you
can't remember whether it's
single quotes or double quotes.
Python doesn't care about
it, but the cool people
use single quotes.
I mean, if you want to be cool.
I'm trying to be cool.
You can see I sometimes
don't get it all.
I'm not that cool.
So then I'm going
to print file name.
And let's save this.
And then as soon
as you save it, you
will see that Python
for Informatics.
I'm going to call it
program shout dot py.
And as soon as we get it, we
get a nice syntax coloring
which helps us
understand if we've
made a typographical error like
that or something like that.
So we'll save it.
And if I come here,
right now I'll
see shout dot Python, shout.py.
I say Python shout.py.
Enter file name.
Fred.
Looks good.
I didn't do much else.
So the thing we've got to
do, of course, to read a file
is we can't just read it.
We're going to have
to get a file handle.
So we'll call our file handle
fhand variable equals open.
And then fname is the file.
And then, of course, we can
write a for loop for line in.
Now, line is just variable name.
Don't want to enter key words.
Line is just a variable name.
And fhand.
And that's because the file
handle is a type of sequence
that we can iterate
through in a for loop,
and this loop will run for each
successive line in the file.
And so I will just
say print line
to know that my loop is actually
iterating through the file.
So we've got four lines.
And we'll say Fred again.
And son of a gun, if the
open blows up because there
is no Fred.
So we have to run a program
here that's actually
in the directory.
mbox-short.
Now be sure to log one.
The mbox-short is
just a little easier.
It's small.
it's just the first few
lines of the full mbox file.
So here we go.
And there we are.
Ah, I'm going to have to make
that a little bit bigger.
So if we go up here
and we look at this,
one of the things that we see
is it doesn't look like the file
because there is a blank
line after every line.
And you're saying, oh, crap.
Why is that?
Well, you're just going to have
to get used to the idiom that
is trimming lines.
And so I'm going to trim.
I'm only going to trim on
the right side, line.rtrim.
I'm going to trim the
white space on the end.
And the problem is
there's a new line here,
and that print statement
is also adding new lines.
So I'm just going to trim it.
Save that.
Something smaller so we can
see it going at the same time.
I used Command-K on my
Macintosh to clear the screen.
You can actually use CLS
in Windows if you want.
And so I'm going to run
the same program again.
mbox-short.txt.
Oh, oh, oh.
It's not rtrim.
Store object has
no attribute rtrim
because it's rtrim in
some other language,
and I'm forgetting because I'm
switching between languages.
But there's no method.
And you'll notice that the
syntax coloring is not right,
either.
And it's rstrip.
How many people caught that?
Not many, probably.
I didn't even catch it.
Let's try it again.
mbox-short.txt.
So now it's still
ugly and nasty,
but you can see when we
print the file out here,
there's no extra blank lines.
And that's because the new
lines have been stripped off.
We're still getting a new
line from the print statement,
but we only want one new line.
So we're getting pretty close.
In this bit of the loop right
here, we've got the line.
We've taken off the white space.
So now, it's a pretty
simple task to just say
line=line.upper.
And then we're going to convert
the whole thing to uppercase.
And run it again.
mbox-short.txt.
There we go.
It is shouting, shouting,
shouting, because everything
is in uppercase.
So that's pretty
straightforward.
Not too much error checking.
Let me show you one
Python idiom that
allows you to contract this.
So in a sense, this
is a function call
that says give me back a new
string which is a copy of line
with the white space removed.
Well, this is the string.
And we can apply a string
library method to it as well.
So I can actually tack on
the end of this the upper.
And I can take this line out.
And now I can do
it in all one line.
And this code says take
line, strip the white space,
and then take the
resulting white space free
and convert it to uppercase.
And that should
accomplish the same thing.
Let's make sure we
don't have blank lines.
We don't have blank lines,
so everything is fine.
So we can add a few things.
Let's add something to this.
We got their
specifications done.
We're done at the minimum.
But let me show you
something cool here.
Let's just say you got tired
of typing that file name
all the time.
Here's a little trick.
If the length of fname
is less than one--
I'll just say equals zero--
we're going to set the fname,
fname=mbox-short.txt.
So that basically means if
we enter our real file name,
the length of the file name
will be greater than zero.
If we don't, we're
just going to assume
we're going to change
that variable to fname.
And then when we open
it, we'll have it.
So watch this.
Oh, better save that.
So I could type the file name.
But if I hit enter,
it just does that.
Look how convenient that is.
So effectively, we're creating
a default, as it were.
When the user types Enter,
they do their thing.
So that's pretty much
it for the exercise 7.3,
the shouting exercise.