OK, so welcome to our
BerryBoot start-up video.
This is a video that
shows what happens
once you have prepared your SD
card with a BerryBoot image.
And so I'm about
to plug-- I've got
my SD card already plugged in.
And so I'm about to
plug in my Raspberry Pi.
And you will watch it
from the beginning.
So that's a good sign.
And so up we come.
And so the first thing it
asks-- this is BerryBoot now.
And one of the things that's
important to configure
in a Raspberry Pi
is the overscan.
And so it's showing
us some green lines.
And do you see
the green borders?
Now you're actually supposed
to see at the top here,
you're supposed to see a
little black outside the green.
So what we want to
say is we want to say,
do we see the green borders?
We want to say, no, we don't.
OK?
And so that give us a
little more edge here.
So we'll say, no, we don't.
And we're going to have a
wired network connection.
The Raspberry Pi doesn't
come with a Wi-Fi,
and so we have to use the
wired network connection.
OK.
And so up we go.
And we're going to format it.
So now what it's doing is
it's copying the files that we
put on originally
and reformatting
it to be the operating
system that it needs to be.
So this takes a minute.
OK, so now we're in good shape.
It has connected to the
network and found out
a series of distributions
that you could install.
We're going to choose
this first one,
but we'll first scroll
through so we can
take a look at the other ones.
There's various things.
There's things that
are aimed at children.
There's one laptop per child.
There's a special web server.
But really what
we're going to do
is we're going to put
a basic Linux on it,
a basic Debian Linux.
So we're going to
click here and say OK.
Now this is a point where if
your network wasn't working,
you would have to be solving the
problem of getting your network
working.
But our network is working.
So here we go.
And so this download is
going to take a little while.
So I'm going to skip to the very
end because it's 451 megabytes.
It's going to take
about 12 minutes.
So there we go.
We have installed it.
This is the one we want.
We're going to make
it the default.
And then we are going to
exit to reboot the system.
So it's going to reboot
now, flashy, flashy.
And now it's booting
again, starting back up.
And the fact that--
we'll speed it up.
We can go back to this
Edit menu at any time.
This is really nice.
This Edit menu
allows you to make
changes, an important thing.
If you're having
trouble, for example,
there are some advanced
configurations here.
And things like if you've
got your overscan wrong,
there's config.txt.
You might set an
overscan value in here.
But we've already set that.
So we're going to
leave this alone.
And so now we'll just
have to exit this again,
and it'll reboot again.
But you can always
stop the boot.
That's one nice thing
about BerryBoot.
We're rebooting.
There we are.
And so you can always
stop and restart.
And it gives you 10 seconds
to interrupt the process,
to install a new
operating system.
But once I let this expire, it
will actually boot the Linux.
And you'll see the Linux start.
So the Linux is starting.
Now, the overscan has been
fixed because you can actually
see the characters.
If you can't see
the characters, that
means that you didn't set
your overscan correctly.
All this text that you're seeing
is Unix or Linux starting up.
And it doesn't matter too much.
The first time it takes
a little bit longer
to start things up
than other times.
After a while, things
will make sense to you.
You'll get used to it.
It's kind of like in
the movie The Matrix,
after a while, it all
makes sense to you.
But this is just the
operating system starting up.
All operating
systems, whether they
be Windows or Unix or
Macintosh, they all
do something like this.
They just don't show
you all the details.
Part of the goal
of the Raspberry Pi
is to show you the details,
let you see what's going on,
what you learn from this.
For now you can ignore it.
After a while, this might
make more sense to you.
Now, you'll notice
it got an IP address.
That's important.
That means that the network
is properly working.
So I'm going to go
down, and here you
have a config screen that
we'll only show once.
And I'm just going to
make sure that we're going
to start the desktop on boot.
So I'm using my cursor
keys to do this.
I'm going to select
Boot Behavior.
And I want to boot
straight to desktop.
So is says Yes.
So I'm going to say-- I'm going
to hit Enter to store that.
OK?
And now I'm going
to cursor down.
And I'm a cursor to the
right and say Finish.
And this is going
to reboot it again.
Would I like to reboot now?
And I'll hit Enter again.
So it's now restarting.
See the flashing thing?
That flashy really just
means no video signal.
And so up we come this time.
Again, BerryBoot is
starting, giving us
a chance to change
our configuration,
our low level configuration.
If you ever get in
trouble, you can always
unplug and plug your Raspberry
Pi back in and you'll see that.
And you have 10 seconds to go
into the Configuration menu.
So now we're starting up again.
This is Linux starting up again.
OK, so now what's
happening is it's
going to take a moment
while our desktop starts.
It's totally black.
That's normal.
It'll always do this.
Take a moment.
Be patient.
Our cursor shows up and a
Raspberry Pi logo shows up.
So this is all a very good sign.
So now I can move
my mouse around.
It's a familiar
Windows-like environment.
Now, the first
thing I like to do
is I'd like to check
to see the overscan.
So move your cursor
up to the top.
Move your cursor to the left.
If it can't go any
farther that means
that the edge of the screen
and the edge of mouse
is exactly right.
Come down to the bottom.
That's good.
Now, if you go to
the upper right,
you'll notice the mouse
kind of disappears,
but it's just off the screen.
So that's OK.
That's just fine.
So now we're in good shape.
So we have our
overscan set properly.
We're in great shape.
This is like most
operating systems.
It has a Start menu.
OK.
And the question,
of course, is now
what do you do with
your Raspberry Pi?
And since I'm a
Python teacher, I'm
going to write a simple
Python program using IDLE.
So IDLE is an interactive
development environment
for Python.
Now I clicked on it.
It will take a moment.
These things aren't the fastest.
It's OK.
And so here I have IDLE.
Let me make the screen
a little smaller.
Shew.
I'm going to start a new window.
And then this is going
to be where I'm going
to write my Python program.
And I'm going to say the
classic print, "Hello world."
And I'm going to save
this, File, Save As.
I'm going to put it on
my desktop as hello.py.
This is a traditional first
programming assignment,
"Hello world."
And really, it's not
really the computer
saying "Hello world" to you.
It's you inside the computer
saying "Hello world" back
to yourself.
Because the computer really
does nothing except what
you tell it to.
So this is our Python program.
And I'm going to run the
Python program, run the module.
And there we go. "Hello world."
So this "Hello
world" came from you.
I will change this.
I will say, "Hello world-- this
is Chuck inside a Raspberry
Pi."
Oops, I got a typo there.
Let me make my window bigger so
you can see my whole program.
"Hello world-- this is Chuck
inside a Raspberry Pi."
Remember, the
reason we do this is
it's because we're making the
Raspberry Pi do our bidding.
And our first thing to do as
a human inside of a computer
is to tell the world hello
from within the computer.
Run module.
Yes, of course I'll save it.
Here we come.
"Hello world-- this is Chuck
inside a Raspberry Pi."
OK, so, I'll close these.
And you'll notice that
sitting on my desktop
is a new file called hello.py.
And that's my little
program that I
added to my Raspberry Pi, the
first thing that I did it.
So a couple things--
you got a Start menu.
And Log Out is where
you would shut down.
There's other tools, very many
things inside of a Raspberry
Pi.
But what we're
going to do is we're
going to simply shut this down.
It brings up.
Do you want to reboot it,
which you can or shut down.
Shut down will shut it
down and power it off.
And once you shut
it down, you're
going to have to unplug and plug
it back in to start it back up.
So there we go.
Now, as it shuts down, we'll
see a couple of messages again.
It's going to shut down.
Shut down, shut down.
And now it's finishing,
and our video
is going to go away
because we're all done.
And at this point, you might as
well unplug your Raspberry Pi.