Hello and welcome to
www.pythonlearn.com.
On this particular
video, we're going
to show you how to write
a simple program using
a text editor and a terminal
on the Raspberry Pi.
Raspberry Pi is a really cool
system, that runs Unix-- Linux.
And so here we have a desktop.
Once you've got your
Raspberry Pi working,
you should have a desktop.
It as a Start icon
at the bottom.
And we're going to start.
We actually don't have
to install anything.
For the Macintosh
and Windows, we
had to install various things.
But now everything
comes on Linux,
because it's sort of
set up for programmers.
I'll start a simple text editor.
And I'll write a little Python
program in the text editor.
We call these scripts.
And the classic thing to do
is to write a program that
says, "hello world."
And I'm going to do
a save of this file.
And I'm going to
put on my desktop.
And make a new
folder called assn0.
And then in assn0, I'm going to
call my file hello.py and save
it.
I've got my screen
a little small
so you can see a little better.
You'll notice on that desktop
that folder showed up,
and if I click
inside the folder,
there is indeed hello.py.
So now what we're
going to do is we're
going to-- there's a lot
of ways you could run this.
There are things-- there
are tools called IDLE,
and you may have even learn
and used these before.
I prefer showing you
really how stuff works.
The technique I'm going to show
you works pretty much the same
on a Macintosh or
a Windows, where
you actually talk
the operating system
and say, hey, run
my Python for me.
So I'm going to open
up a terminal window,
and a terminal window let's us
type operating system commands.
So for example, the
first command is ls.
That list the directories and
files of wherever you're at.
The pwd stands for
print working directory.
It say where you're at.
And I'm the /home/csev.
That's my account.
And cd says change directory.
And I'm going to change
into the desktop.
And just as a-- I can
type D-E Tab, and as
long as that's unique,
it automatically
goes to the desktop.
And then Enter.
If I type ls.
Well, I see kind of
what's on that desktop.
That desktop has a
folder called assn0.
Assn0.
0.
And then I go into
that folder, assn0.
So you navigate one folder in.
And you'll see it's telling
you, roughly, where you're at.
And if I do an ls here,
in this command line,
it says, oh, you've
got one file.
And it's named hello.py.
And if you look at
this, it's showing you
the exact same information.
So we're really-- this
terminal is a different view.
And I like it, because we can
type commands here, and-- be
smaller-- you can type commands.
I can tell you
exactly what to type.
It's easier to write
documentation, frankly.
So we want to run this program.
We wrote the program
over here, and now we
want to run the
program in this window.
So we type python hello.py.
And that says, go
find Python-- that's
like Microsoft Word or
some other program, that
happens to be the Python
itself that we're running.
And feed it hello.py.
This one file.
So when I type Enter,
it's going to run it.
And so it's going to
interpret these commands.
And I told Python that the
first thing, and last thing,
I wanted to do was to do
a print of "hello world".
That of course is--
they're traditional.
This is a script.
It's a series of commands.
Print "howdy world."
Print "yo world."
I can have all kinds
of things in here.
Print "peace out."
I don't know what to type.
Now there's some
shortcuts that you'll
get used to using pretty fast.
I can keep saying
File Save, but you'll
notice Control-S is a save.
And you'll notice this
little asterisk up here.
Watch when I press Control-S.
That asterisk means the file's
been modified, but not saved.
This will save you a
little bit of insanity.
Make sure you know that.
It's like, oh, it's not saved.
So Control-S. Pressed.
And now it's been saved.
That's how I know it's saved.
And it's been saved over here.
And now I am going to say
python hello.py to run it again.
And now it's yelling at me.
Oops.
I see what I did wrong.
I should have said print.
I should have said, instead of
pring, I should've said print.
You think it would be
smart enough to know that,
like, why isn't this
guy doing print.
So now I have to
save it again, so I
do Control-S. And now
here's another trick,
you cant hit the Up Arrow and
run the previous command again.
So hit the Up Arrow and hit
Enter, and there is my output.
OK.
So not too hard.
Everything's already
pre-installed
on the Raspberry Pi Linux.
Pretty much all Linux are going
to have something like this.
And so away we go,
thanks for listening.